<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akn:akomaNtoso xmlns:akn="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><akn:act><akn:meta><akn:identification source="#cosilico"><akn:FRBRWork><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-44" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-44" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2023-03-01" name="release" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#virginia-general-assembly" /><akn:FRBRcountry value="us-va" /><akn:FRBRnumber value="title-44" /><akn:FRBRname value="act" /></akn:FRBRWork><akn:FRBRExpression><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-44/eng@2023-03-01" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-44/eng@2023-03-01" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2023-03-01" name="publication" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#lexisnexis" /><akn:FRBRlanguage language="eng" /></akn:FRBRExpression><akn:FRBRManifestation><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-44/eng@2023-03-01/main.xml" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-44/eng@2023-03-01/main.xml" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="conversion" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#cosilico" /></akn:FRBRManifestation></akn:identification><akn:references source="#cosilico"><akn:TLCOrganization eId="virginia-general-assembly" href="/ontology/organization/us-va/general-assembly" showAs="Virginia General Assembly" /><akn:TLCOrganization eId="lexisnexis" href="/ontology/organization/lexisnexis" showAs="LexisNexis" /><akn:TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="/ontology/organization/cosilico" showAs="Cosilico" /></akn:references></akn:meta><akn:preface><akn:docTitle>Title 44. </akn:docTitle></akn:preface><akn:body><akn:section eId="sec_44-1"><akn:num>§ 44-1</akn:num><akn:heading>Composition of militia</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The militia of the Commonwealth of Virginia shall consist of all able-bodied residents of the Commonwealth who are citizens of the United States and all other able-bodi ed persons resident in the Commonwealth who have declared their intention to become citizens of the United States, who are at least 16 years of age and, except as hereinafter provided, not more than 55 years of age. The militia shall be divided into thre e classes: the National Guard, which includes the Army National Guard and the Air National Guard; the Virginia Defense Force; and the unorganized militia. History History. 1930, p. 948; 1942, p. 642; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(1); 1944, p. 24; 1958, c. 393; 1970, c. 662; 1973, c. 401; 1976, c. 399; 1979, c. 647; 1984, c. 765; 1989, c. 414; 2011, cc. 572, 586; 2015, c. 221. Annotations The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendments by cc. 572 and 586 are identical, and in the first sentence substituted able-bodied residents of the Commonwealth who are citizens of the United States for able-bodied citizens of this Commonwealth and made minor stylistic changes, and in the last sentence, deleted State preceding Defense Force and made minor stylistic changes. The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendment by c. 221 substituted three classes for four classes and deleted the naval militia following Virginia Defense Force  in the last sentence. Law Review. For essay, Article I, Section 13 of the Virginia Constitution: Of Militias and an Individual Right to Bear Arms, see 48 U. Rich. L. Rev. 215 (2013). CASE NOTES Virginia Nat ional Guard part of the Virginia Militia.  Because the Virginia National Guard is part of the Virginia Militia, of which the Governor of Virginia acts as Commander-in-Chief, and it falls under the Virginia Department of Military Affairs, the Virginia National Guard is part of an agency of the Commonwealth and is entitled to Eleventh Amendment protection. Fauber v. Va. Army Nat'l Guard, No. 5:08-cv-00068, 2009 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 31040 (W.D. Va. Apr. 9, 2009) .</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-2"><akn:num>§ 44-2</akn:num><akn:heading>Composition of National Guard</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. The Nationa l Guard shall consist of the regularly enlisted militia and of commissioned and warrant officers, who shall be residents of the Commonwealth of Virginia and shall fall within the age limits and qualifications as prescribed in existing or subsequently ame nded National Guard regulations (army and air), organized, armed and equipped as hereinafter provided. Upon original enlistment members of the National Guard shall not be less than 17 nor more than 55 years of age, or, in subsequent enlistments not more than 64 years of age. B. Notwithstan ding the above, persons otherwise qualified but residing outside the Commonwealth of Virginia, may enlist or serve as commissioned or warrant officers in the National Guard. History History. 1930, p. 948; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(2); 1958, c. 393; 1976, c. 399; 1979, c. 647; 2011, cc. 572, 586. Annotations The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendments by cc. 572 and 586 are identical, and made minor stylistic changes in the last sentence, and deleted the former last sentence, which read: All enlistments in the National Guard of persons under the age of eighteen years made prior to June 27, 1958, shall be held, and the same are hereby declared valid and effective in all respects, if otherwise valid and effective according to the law t hen in force. § 44-2.1. Repealed by Acts 1989, c. 414. Annotations Cross references. For the Virginia Defense Force, see now § 44-54.4 et seq.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-3"><akn:num>§ 44-3</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 2015, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>221, cl. 2. Annotations Editors note. Former § 44-3, Composition of naval militia, derived from 1930, p. 949; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(3); 1972, c. 823; 1973, c. 401.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-4"><akn:num>§ 44-4</akn:num><akn:heading>Composition of unorganized militia</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The unorganized militia shall consist of all able-bodied persons as set out in § 44-1, except such as may be included in §§ 44-2 and 44-54.6 and except such as may be exempted as hereinafter provided. History History. 1930, p. 949; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(4); 1970, c. 662; 1973, c. 401; 1984, c. 765; 2015, c. 221. Annotations The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendment by c. 221 deleted 44-3 and made related changes.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-5"><akn:num>§ 44-5</akn:num><akn:heading>Exemptions from militia duty</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text In addition to those exempted by the laws of the United States, the following persons shall be exempt from military duty under a state call: 1. The o fficers, judicial and executive, of the governments of the United States and the Commonwealth of Virginia; 2. The members of the General Assembly of the Commonwealth of Virginia and of the Congress of the United States; 3. Persons in the active military or naval services of the United States; 4. Persons employed by the United States in the transmission of the mail; 5. The judges and clerks of courts of record; 6. The mayor and councilmen of incorporated cities and towns; 7. Members of the governing bodies of counties; 8. Sheriffs, United States district attorneys, attorneys for the Commonwealth and city attorneys; 9. Marine pilots; 10. All persons who because of religious belief shall claim exemption from military service, if the conscientious holding of such belief by such person shall be established under such r egulations as the President of the United States shall prescribe, shall be exempted from militia service in any capacity that the President shall declare to be combatant; and 11. Such other persons as may be designated by the Governor in the best interests of the public and of the Commonwealth. History History. 1930, p. 949; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(5); 1958, c. 393; 1976, c. 399; 2011, cc. 572, 586. Annotations The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendments by cc. 572 and 586 are identical, and renumbered subdivisions to remove repealed subdivisions and to delete subdivisions 4 and 11, which read: Customhouse clerks and Lighthouse keepers, respectively; and made minor stylistic changes.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-6"><akn:num>§ 44-6</akn:num><akn:heading>Maintenance of other troops</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text In time of peace the Commonwealth shall maintain only such troops as may be authorized by the President of the United States; but nothing in this chapter shall be const rued as limiting the rights of the Commonwealth in the use of the Virginia National Guard or Virginia Defense Force within or without its borders in time of peace and nothing contained in this chapter shall prevent the organization and maintenance of Sta te Police or constabulary. History History. 1930, p. 949; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(6); 1958, c. 393; 1984, c. 765; 2011, cc. 572, 586. Annotations The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendments by cc. 572 and 586 are identical, and deleted State preceding Defense Force.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-7"><akn:num>§ 44-7</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 2015, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>221, cl. 2. Annotations Editors note. Former § 44-7, Classification of militia, derived from 1930, p. 948; 1942, p. 642; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(1); 1944, p. 24; 1958, c. 393; 1970, c. 662; 197 3, c. 401; 1976, c. 399; 1979, c. 647; 1984, c. 765; 1989, c. 414; 2011, cc. 572, 586. Article 2. General Administrative Officers. -360§ 44-8. Governor as Commander in Chief. -360§ 44-9. Commander in Chief to prescribe regulations. -360§ 44-9.1. Censorship of certain sermons prohibited. -360§ 44-10. Divisions of military staff. -360§ 44-11. Department of Military Affairs; Adjutant General. -360§ 44-11.1. Duties of the Department of Military Affairs. -360§ 44-12. Repealed by Acts 2004, c. 12. -360§ 44-13. Powers of Adjutant General. -360§ 44-13.1. Virginia National Guard Morale, Welfare, and Recreation Program established. -360§ 44-13.2. Administration of the MWR Program. -360§ 44-13.3. Virginia National Guard MWR Fund. -360§ 44-13.4. Risk management. -360§ 44-14. Expenditures for Department. -360§ 44-15. Reports to Secretary of Defense. -360§ 44-16. Records of Adjutant General. -360§ 44-17. Regulations as to reports and care of property. -360§ 44-18. Repealed by Acts 2015, c. 221, cl. 2. -360§ 44-19. Adjutant General to have charge of military property. -360§ 44-20. Deputy Adjutant General (Army and Air) and Assistant Adjutant General (Army); assistants and clerical forces of Adjutant G eneral. -360§ 44-21. Bonds of Adjutant General and fiscal clerks. -360§ 44-22. Auditing accounts of Adjutant General. -360§ 44-23. Repealed by Acts 1984, c. 734. -360§ 44-24. United States Property and Fiscal Officer. -360§ 44-24.1. Repealed by Acts 2015, c. 221, cl. 2.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-8"><akn:num>§ 44-8</akn:num><akn:heading>Governor as Commander in Chief</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Governor shall be Commander in Chief of the armed forces of the Commonwealth, and shall have power to employ such forces to repel invasion, suppress insurrection, a nd enforce the execution of the laws. History History. 1930, p. 950; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(8); R. P. 1948, § 44 -8; 1958, c. 393; 1964, c. 227. Annotations Cross references. For constitutional authority, see Va. Const., Art. V, § 7. CASE NOTES Virginia Nat ional Guard part of the Virginia Militia.  Because the Virginia National Guard is part of the Virginia Militia, of which the Governor of Virginia acts as Commander-in-Chief, and it falls under the Virginia Department of Military Affairs, the Virginia National Guard is part of an agency of the Commonwealth and is entitled to Eleventh Amendment protection. Fauber v. Va. Army Nat'l Guard, No. 5:08-cv-00068, 2009 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 31040 (W.D. Va. Apr. 9, 2009) .</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-9"><akn:num>§ 44-9</akn:num><akn:heading>Commander in Chief to prescribe regulations</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Commander in Chief shall have the power, and it shall be his duty, from time to time, to issue such orders and to prescribe such regulations relating to the organiz ation of the armed forces of the Commonwealth as will cause the same at all times to conform to the federal requirements of the United States government relating thereto. History History. 1930, p. 950; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(9); R. P. 1948, § 44 -9; 1958, c. 393. Annotations OPINIONS OF THE ATTORNEY GENERAL Don t Ask, Dont Tell in the Virginia National Guard.  The Virginia General Assembly may or may not have the authority to mandate that the Virginia National Guard continue the Dont Ask, Dont Tell polic y after its recent repeal by Congress, but the federal regulations governing the repeal have not yet been issued. The United States Constitution expressly reserves to the states the power to appoint officers to the state militias, including the National Guard. The power to determine which state guard officers are eligible for service in the overlapping National Guard of the United States, however, rests with Congress. See opinion of Attorney General to The Honorable Bill Janis, Member, House of Delegate s, 11-001, 2011 Va. AG LEXIS 6 (01/25/11). Congress, through the spending power, can condition the use of federal funds on the States acceptance of the federal repeal of Dont Ask, Dont Tell . Should the General Assembly wish to avoid the conditions likely to be attached to these funds with respect to Dont Ask, Dont Tell and mandate that the policy continue in the Virginia National Guard, it can raise, equip and fund an i ndependent Virginia militia entirely from state revenues. See opinion of Attorney General to The Honorable Bill Janis, Member, House of Delegates, 11-001, 2011 Va. AG LEXIS 6 (01/25/11). § 44-9.1. Censorship of certain sermons prohibited. Text Notwithstanding any contrary provisions of law, the religious content of sermons, homilies, preaching, religious messages, or other speeches within religious services m ade by chaplains of the Virginia National Guard while in Title 32 or State Active Duty status or of the Virginia Defense Force shall not be censored or restricted by any state government official or agency, so long as (i) the religious content offered is not in any way a precursor of, introduction to, or part of any official ceremony, gathering, or formation that is not part of the religious service; (ii) the content does not urge disobedience of lawful orders; and (iii) members of the National Guard or Defense Force are not required to attend the service or event where such content is delivered. History History. 2015, c. 283. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2015, c. 283 was codified as this section at the direction of the Virginia Code Commission.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-10"><akn:num>§ 44-10</akn:num><akn:heading>Divisions of military staff</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The military staff shall be divided into (a) the personal staff of the Governor and (b) the administrative staff. The personal staff of the Governor shall be constituted as now prescribed by law. The administrative staff shall be as is authorized by the Secretary of Defense of the United States and shall perform such duties as the commander in chief may direct. History History. 1930, p. 950; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(10); R. P. 1948, § 4 4-10; 1958, c. 393.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-11"><akn:num>§ 44-11</akn:num><akn:heading>Department of Military Affairs; Adjutant General</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text There is hereby created the Department of Military Affairs to which is transferred all of the functions, powers and duties of the former Division of Military Affairs. The Governor shall appoint an Adjutant General with the rank of brigadier general, major general or lieutenant general as the Governor may prescribe, subject to confirm ation by the General Assembly if in session, and if not in session, then at its next succeeding session. The Adjutant General shall not hold the rank of lieutenant general unless such rank is federally recognized. The Adjutant General shall be in direct charge of the Department of Military Affairs and shall be responsible to the Governor and commander in chief for the proper performance of his duties. All the powers conferred and the duties imposed by law upon the Adjutant General shall be exercised or performed by him under the direction and control of the Governor. The Adjutant General shall serve at the pleasure of the Governor for a term coincident with that of the Governor. No person shall be appointed Adjutant General who shall not have had at le ast ten years commissioned service in the Virginia National Guard in at least field grade. The Adjutant General, while serving as such, may be a member of the Virginia National Guard. The Adjutant General shall receive a salary prescribed by law. History History. 1927, p. 106; 1930, p. 951; Michie Code 1942, §§ 585(62), 2 673(12); 1948, p. 48; R. P. 1948, § 44-11; 1964, c. 227. Annotations CASE NOTES Virginia National Guard part of an agency of the Commonwealth.  Because the Virginia National Guard is part of the Virginia Militia, of which the Governor of Virginia acts as Commander-in-Chief, and it falls under the Virginia Department of Military Affairs, the Virginia National Guard is part of an agency of the Commonwealth and is entitled to Eleventh Amendment protection. Fauber v. Va. Army Nat'l Guard, No. 5:08-cv-00068, 2009 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 31040 (W.D. Va. Apr. 9, 2009) . § 44-11.1. Duties of the Department of Military Affairs. Text A. The Departm ent of Military Affairs shall support the objectives of the Governor and federal authorities by: 1. Admin istering and employing the Virginia Militia, as set forth in § 44-1; 2. Integrating into state operations all supporting Department of Defense capabilities and those forces provided by supporting states in a Title 32 or State Active Duty status; 3. Providing for the safety of citizens of the Commonwealth by maintaining order and public safety and assisting in counter-drug efforts, in cooperation with Virginia State Police and loc al law-enforcement agencies; 4. Preparing and executing contingency plans to provide for a timely and capable response to chemical, biological, radiological, nuclear, or explosive incidents; 5. Preparing and executing contingency plans necessary for the provision of homeland defense; 6. Ensuring the support to families of service members of the Virginia National Guard; 7. Administering a state at-risk program for youth; and 8. Recruiting a force sufficiently manned and trained to accomplish the above duties. B. The Departm ent of Military Affairs shall perform such other duties as may be designated by the Governor. History History. 2007, cc. 127, 728. Annotations CASE NOTES Virginia National Guard part of an agency of the Commonwealth.  Because the Virginia National Guard is part of the Virginia Militia, of which the Governor of Virginia acts as Commander-in-Chief, and it falls under the Virginia Department of Military Affairs, the Virginia National Guard is part of an agency of the Commonwealth and is entitled to Eleventh Amendment protection. Fauber v. Va. Army Nat'l Guard, No. 5:08-cv-00068, 2009 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 31040 (W.D. Va. Apr. 9, 2009) .</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-12"><akn:num>§ 44-12</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 2004, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>12.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-13"><akn:num>§ 44-13</akn:num><akn:heading>Powers of Adjutant General</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text As head of the Department of Military Affairs, the Adjutant General shall have command of all of the militia of the Commonwealth, subject to the orders of the Governor as Commander in Chief, and shall distribute all orders from the Governor pertaining to the military service and shall perform all duties imposed upon him or that Department by this title in the manner prescribed by law. History History. 1927, p. 106; 1930, p. 951; Michie Code 1942, §§ 585(62), 2 673(13); R. P. 1948, § 44-13; 1958, c. 393; 1989, c. 414. § 44-13.1. Virginia National Guard Morale, Welfare, and Recreation Program established. Text The Adjutant General is authorized to establish a Virginia National Guard Morale, Welfare, and Recreation Program (the MWR Program) to provide leisure, recreation, and lodging opportunities for Virginia National Guard members and their families, Virginia Defense Force members and their families, employees of the Department of Military Affairs and their families, and other users of Department facilities as authorized by the Adjutant General. History History. 2016, c. 622. § 44-13.2. Administration of the MWR Program. Text The Adjutant General may authorize the MWR Program to (i) contract for goods and services; (ii) hire employees; and (iii) receive funds from patrons in exchange for goo ds or services provided within the MWR Program. The Adjutant General is authorized to establish MWR Program facilities throughout the Commonwealth that, in the Adjutant Generals judgment, are necessary for military purposes. The Adjutant General shal l promulgate regulations to govern the operation of the MWR Program. The Adjutant General may appoint a director for the MWR Program. The Adjutant General shall establish a system of bookkeeping, accounting, and auditing procedures for the proper handlin g of funds derived from the MWR Programs operations. History History. 2016, c. 622. § 44-13.3. Virginia National Guard MWR Fund. Text There is created within the state treasury a special nonreverting fund to be known as the Virginia National Guard MWR Fund, referred to in this section as the Fund.  The Fund shall be established on the books of the Comptroller. All (i) proceeds collected under the MWR Program and (ii) donations made to the Virginia National Guard MWR Program shall be paid into the state treasury and credited to the Fund. Intere st earned on moneys in the Fund shall remain in the Fund and be credited to it. Any moneys remaining in the Fund, including interest thereon, at the end of each fiscal year shall not revert to the general fund but shall remain in the Fund. Moneys from th e Fund shall be used for the enhancement of morale, welfare, and recreation and the administration of the MWR Program, including paying the costs of (a) salaries of MWR Program employees; (b) public liability insurance, when needed; (c) infrastructure im provements on military property used in support of the MWR Program; and (d) any other expenses considered necessary in furtherance of the MWR Program by the Adjutant General. Expenditures and disbursements from the Fund shall be made by the State Treasur er on warrants issued by the Comptroller upon written request signed by the Adjutant General. History History. 2016, c. 622. § 44-13.4. Risk management. Text The MWR Program shall be eligible to participate in the state risk management pool. The MWR Program shall procure separate insurance policies to cover liability associa ted with activities and operations not otherwise covered in the state risk management pool or by the Division of Risk Management. History History. 2016, c. 622.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-14"><akn:num>§ 44-14</akn:num><akn:heading>Expenditures for Department</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text All payments and disbursements payable out of the appropriation to the Department of Military Affairs shall be made by the State Treasurer upon warrants of the Comptrol ler issued upon vouchers signed by the Adjutant General or such person as the Adjutant General may designate for such purpose. Expenditures not specifically provided for but manifestly for the benefit of the military service may be made by the Adjutant G eneral with the written approval of the Governor. History History. 1930, p. 950; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(11); 1944, p. 24; R. P. 1948, § 44-13; 2004, c. 12. Annotations The 2004 amendments. The 2004 amendment by c. 12 deleted concurrence of the Board of Military Affairs and the preceding written approval in the last sentence.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-15"><akn:num>§ 44-15</akn:num><akn:heading>Reports to Secretary of Defense</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Adjutant General shall make such returns and reports to the Secretary of Defense, or to such officers as he may designate, at such times and in such form as may fro m time to time be prescribed. History History. 1930, p. 951; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(13); R. P. 1948, § 4 4-14; 1958, c. 393.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-16"><akn:num>§ 44-16</akn:num><akn:heading>Records of Adjutant General</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Adjutant General shall keep a record of all officers and enlisted personnel, and shall also keep all records and papers required by law or regulations to be filed t herein. History History. 1930, p. 951; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(13); R. P. 1948, § 4 4-15; 1970, c. 662; 2011, cc. 572, 586. Annotations The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendments by cc. 572 and 586 are identical, and deleted in his office following shall also keep.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-17"><akn:num>§ 44-17</akn:num><akn:heading>Regulations as to reports and care of property</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Adjutant General is empowered to make such regulations pertaining to the preparation and rendering of reports and returns and to the care and preservation of public property as in his opinion the conditions demand, such regulations to be operative and in force when promulgated in the form of general orders, circulars, circular letters, or other regulations and documents. History History. 1930, p. 951; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(13); R. P. 1948, § 4 4-17; 1964, c. 227.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-18"><akn:num>§ 44-18</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 2015, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>221, cl. 2. Annotations Editors note. Former § 44-18, Seal of Adjutant General, derived from 1930, p. 951; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(13); R. P. 1948, § 44-18.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-19"><akn:num>§ 44-19</akn:num><akn:heading>Adjutant General to have charge of military property</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Adjutant General shall have charge and care of all state military property and all United States military property issued to the Commonwealth of Virginia, and shall cause to be kept an accurate and careful account of all receipts and issues of the same. He shall require to be kept careful memoranda of all public military property on hand in the state arsenal or storehouses, and in the possession of the several orga nizations of the Virginia National Guard or issued to the Virginia Defense Force, and shall guard such property against injury and loss to the extent of his ability. He shall require every accountable and responsible officer of the National Guard to acco unt for every deficiency in public military property in his possession immediately after such deficiency is discovered. The Adjutant General shall have the care and control of the state military reservation near Virginia Beach, and of such other real est ate as the Commonwealth may acquire for military purposes, and it shall be the duty of the Adjutant General to provide for the proper care of such property and buildings thereon. For the maintenance, upkeep and improvement of the military reservation or reservations, the Adjutant General may expend from the appropriation to the Department of Military Affairs such amounts as may be necessary. History History. 1930, pp. 950, 952; Michie Code 1942, §§ 2673(11), 2673(13) ; 1944, p. 24; R. P. 1948, § 44-19; 1958, c. 393; 1989, c. 414; 2011, cc. 572, 586. Annotations The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendments by cc. 572 and 586 are identical, and deleted State preceding Defense Force.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-20"><akn:num>§ 44-20</akn:num><akn:heading>Deputy Adjutant General (Army and Air) and Assistant Adjutant General (Army); assistants and clerical forces of Adjutant General</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Adjutant General shall have a Deputy Adjutant General (Air), a Deputy Adjutant General (Army) and an Assistant Adjutant General (Army) whose grades shall not exceed that of brigadier general and he shall have other assistants and such clerical forces as may be necessary who shall serve at the pleasure of the Adjutant General, subject to the provisions of general law, and shall perform such duties as he may assign t hem. The Adjutant General shall have such other clerks and employees as may be necessary for the administration of his office. History History. 1930, p. 952; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(13); R.P. 1948, § 44 -20; 1964, c. 227; 1979, c. 504; 1983, c. 74.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-21"><akn:num>§ 44-21</akn:num><akn:heading>Bonds of Adjutant General and fiscal clerks</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Adjutant General and his fiscal clerks shall be bonded in accordance with § 2.2-1840. History History. 1930, p. 952; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(13); R. P. 1948, § 4 4-21; 1964, c. 227; 2011, cc. 572, 586; 2021, Sp. Sess. I, c. 152. Annotations The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendments by cc. 572 and 586 are identical, and deleted the last sentence, which read: The penalties of the bond shall be as follows: of the Adjutan t General, $10,000, of each of his fiscal clerks, $3,000. The 2021 Sp. Sess. I amendments. The 2021 amendment by Sp. Sess. I, c. 152, effective July 1, 2021, substituted be bonded in accordance with § 2.2-1840 for each give bond, with suf ficient sureties, to be approved by the Governor, as provided by law for other state officers.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-22"><akn:num>§ 44-22</akn:num><akn:heading>Auditing accounts of Adjutant General</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The office and accounts of the Adjutant General pertaining to the Commonwealth of Virginia shall be audited by the direction of the Governor in the same manner as the o ffice and accounts of other state officers are audited, as provided by law. History History. 1930, p. 952; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(13); R. P. 1948, § 4 4-22.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-23"><akn:num>§ 44-23</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1984, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>734.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-24"><akn:num>§ 44-24</akn:num><akn:heading>United States Property and Fiscal Officer</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Governor shall appoint, designate or detail, subject to the approval of the Secretary of Defense, an officer of the National Guard of the Commonwealth to serve as a United States Property and Fiscal Officer. Any officer of the National Guard who has been so appointed and is serving as United States Property and Fiscal Officer, may be removed for just cause by the Governor with the approval of the Secretary of Defen se. The Adjutant General is hereby declared ineligible to serve as United States Property and Fiscal Officer. The duties and remuneration of said United States Property and Fiscal Officer shall be such as are prescribed by existing or subsequently amende d regulations of the armed forces of the United States. History History. 1930, p. 952; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(14); R. P. 1948, § 4 4-24; 1958, c. 393. § 44-24.1. Repealed by Acts 2015, c. 221, cl. 2. Annotations Editors note. Former § 44-24.1, Adjutant General may provide group health and hospitalization insurance for employees of Department, derived from 1966, c. 402. Article 3. National Guard in General. -360§ 44-25. Organization; composition of units. -360§ 44-26. Location of units and headquarters. -360§ 44-27. Appointment and promotion of officers. -360§ 44-28. Qualifications of commanding or staff officers. -360§ 44-29. Qualifications of National Guard officers. -360§ 44-30. Tests as to fitness for officers; examining board. -360§ 44-31. Relative rank of officers. -360§ 44-32. Oath of National Guard officers. -360§ 44-32.1. Administration of oaths of office and enlistment. -360§ 44-33. Elimination and disposition of officers. -360§ 44-34. Repealed by Acts 1958, c. 393. -360§ 44-35. Enlistments in National Guard. -360§ 44-36. Enlistment contract and oath. -360§ 44-37. Discharge of enlisted persons. -360§ 44-38. Membership continued in National Guard after termination of federal service. -360§ 44-39. Uniforms, arms and equipment. -360§ 44-39.1. Possession of handguns by members at National Guard facilities. -360§ 44-40. Discipline and training. -360§ 44-40.01. Nonjudicial disciplinary proceedings. -360§ 44-40.1. Persons subject to the Virginia military laws. -360§ 44-40.2. Administration of oaths and taking of sworn statements by commissioned officers. -360§ 44-41. Armory drills, inactive training, annual active duty training, etc. -360§ 44-41.1. Failure to report; etc. -360§ 44-41.2. Sharing of information with Virginia Employment Commission upon separation.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-25"><akn:num>§ 44-25</akn:num><akn:heading>Organization; composition of units</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Except as otherwise specifically provided by the laws of the United States, the organization of the National Guard, including the composition of all units thereof, shal l be the same as that prescribed for the active army, air force and navy, subject in time of peace to such general exceptions as may be authorized by the Secretary of Defense. History History. 1930, p. 952; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(15); 1958, c. 393; 1964 , c. 227.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-26"><akn:num>§ 44-26</akn:num><akn:heading>Location of units and headquarters</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Governor shall determine and fix the location of the units and headquarters of the National Guard within the Commonwealth. History History. 1930, p. 953; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(16); 1958, c. 393.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-27"><akn:num>§ 44-27</akn:num><akn:heading>Appointment and promotion of officers</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text All officers of the National Guard shall be appointed and commissioned by the Governor, through the Adjutant General. Within the organization, insofar as practicable, all appointments and promotions shall be based on professional qualifications, efficiency, length of service in grade, length of commissioned service, and demonstrated command and staff ability at the appropriate level, and will be effected only when an appropriate vacancy exists in the applicable table of organization and equipment or table of organization or distributi on. History History. 1930, p. 953; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(17); 1958, c. 393; 1964 , c. 227; 1970, c. 662; 2011, cc. 572, 586. Annotations The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendments by cc. 572 and 586 are identical, and substituted through the Adjutant General for as follows in the first paragraph; deleted subdivisions (1) through (3), which concerned appointments of second lieutenants, forwarding of names of best qualified persons to the Adjutant Generals office for gubernatorial consideration, and appointments made upon the recommendation of the Adju tant General, respectively; and deleted the subdivision (4) designation.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-28"><akn:num>§ 44-28</akn:num><akn:heading>Qualifications of commanding or staff officers</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text No person shall be appointed a commanding or staff officer unless such person shall have had federally recognized commissioned military service, nor shall any officer b e appointed who fails to qualify as to fitness for military service under such regulations as the Secretary of Defense shall prescribe. Such officers may hold their positions until they have reached the age or length of service as prescribed in existing or subsequently amended National Guard regulations, unless separated from the service prior to that time by reason of resignation, disability, withdrawal or termination of federal recognition or commission, or upon finding of a legally convened court-mar tial. History History. 1930, p. 953; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(18); 1958, c. 393; 1970 , c. 662.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-29"><akn:num>§ 44-29</akn:num><akn:heading>Qualifications of National Guard officers</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The qualifications of National Guard officers shall be as prescribed in current and subsequently amended National Guard regulations. History History. 1930, p. 953; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(19); 1958, c. 393.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-30"><akn:num>§ 44-30</akn:num><akn:heading>Tests as to fitness for officers; examining board</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text No person shall hereafter be appointed an officer of the National Guard unless such person first shall have successfully passed such tests as to physical, moral, and pr ofessional fitness as the President shall prescribe. The examination to determine such qualifications for commission shall be conducted by a board of three commissioned officers appointed by the Secretary of Defense from the active army or the National G uard, or both. History History. 1930, p. 954; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(20); 1958, c. 393; 1964 , c. 227; 1970, c. 662.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-31"><akn:num>§ 44-31</akn:num><akn:heading>Relative rank of officers</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Relative rank among officers of the same grade shall be determined according to current and subsequently amended Department of Defense and National Guard regulations. History History. 1930, p. 954; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(21); 1964, c. 227.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-32"><akn:num>§ 44-32</akn:num><akn:heading>Oath of National Guard officers</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Commissioned officers of the National Guard shall take and subscribe to the following oath of office: I do solemnly swear that I will support and defend the Constitution of the United States and the Constitution of the Commonwealth of Virginia, against all enemies, foreign and domestic; that I will bear true faith and allegiance to the same; that I will obey the orders of the President of the United States and of the Governor of the Commonwealth of Virginia; that I make this obligation freely, without mental reservation or purpose of evasion, and that I will well and faithfully discharge the duties of the office of in the National Guard of the United States and of the Commonwealth of Virginia, upon which I am about to enter; so help me God. Click to view History History. 1930, p. 954; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(22); 1958, c. 393. § 44-32.1. Administration of oaths of office and enlistment. Text Any duly commissioned officer or warrant officer of the Virginia National Guard or any commissioned officer of any of the armed services of the United States may admini ster the oaths of office and enlistment to prospective officers and enlisted personnel desirous of becoming members of the Virginia National Guard and the National Guard of the United States. Any duly commissioned officer of the Virginia Defense Force, w hen called into service by the Governor, may administer oaths to prospective officers and enlisted personnel desirous of becoming members of the Virginia Defense Force. History History. 1947, p. 143; Michie Suppl. 1948, § 2673(22a); 1958, c. 393; 1 979, c. 647; 2011, cc. 572, 586. Annotations The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendments by cc. 572 and 586 are identical, and in the last sentence, substituted Virginia Defense Force for Virginia State Guard and state guard of Virginia, respectively.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-33"><akn:num>§ 44-33</akn:num><akn:heading>Elimination and disposition of officers</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text At any time the moral character, capacity, and general fitness for the service of any National Guard officer may be determined by an efficiency board of three commissio ned officers senior in rank to the officer whose fitness for service shall be under investigation, said board to be appointed by the Adjutant General and convened on his order. If the findings of such board be unfavorable to such officer and be approved by the Adjutant General, such officer shall be discharged. Commissions of officers of the National Guard may be vacated upon resignation, if approved by the Adjutant General, absence without leave for three months, upon the recommendation of an efficienc y board, pursuant to sentence of a court-martial, upon physical disqualification, when convicted of a felony in a civil court, when appointed or inducted into the armed forces of the United States, when federal recognition is withdrawn from such officer or from the unit to which assigned, upon reaching maximum age limitation, and when it has been determined that an officer is subversive or disloyal. Officers of the Virginia National Guard rendered surplus by the disbandment of their organization shall b e placed in another unit, providing an appropriate vacancy exists, otherwise such officers shall be separated from the Virginia National Guard and automatically revert to the reserve. History History. 1930, p. 954; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(23); 1958, c. 393; 1964 , c. 227; 1970, c. 662.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-34"><akn:num>§ 44-34</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1958, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>393.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-35"><akn:num>§ 44-35</akn:num><akn:heading>Enlistments in National Guard</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Enlistments in the National Guard shall be as prescribed in existing or subsequently amended National Guard regulations. History History. 1930, p. 954; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(25); 1958, c. 393.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-36"><akn:num>§ 44-36</akn:num><akn:heading>Enlistment contract and oath</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Enlisted persons shall not be recognized as members of the National Guard until they shall have signed an enlistment contract and taken and subscribed to the oath of en listment prescribed by present or subsequently amended National Guard regulations; or such oath of enlistment as shall be prescribed by the Governor of Virginia for members of the Virginia Defense Force. History History. 1930, p. 955; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(26); 1958, c. 393; 2011 , cc. 572, 586. Annotations The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendments by cc. 572 and 586 are identical, and deleted State preceding Defense Force.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-37"><akn:num>§ 44-37</akn:num><akn:heading>Discharge of enlisted persons</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text An enlisted person discharged from service in the Virginia National Guard shall receive a discharge in writing. The form and classification of such discharge shall be a s prescribed by existing or subsequently amended National Guard regulations. History History. 1930, p. 955; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(27); 1958, c. 393.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-38"><akn:num>§ 44-38</akn:num><akn:heading>Membership continued in National Guard after termination of federal service</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text When inducted into the active military service of the United States and thereafter discharged or separated from the armed forces, all persons so inducted and thereafter discharged or separated shall resume their membership in the Virginia National Guard and shall continue to serve therein as though their service had not been so interrupted. History History. 1930, p. 955; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(28); 1958, c. 393. Annotations CASE NOTES Federal service regarded as temporar y.  This section shows that the service of members of the National Guard in the army of the United States is regarded as temporary. City of Lynchburg v. Suttenfield, 177 Va. 212, 13 S.E.2d 323, 1941 Va. LEXIS 208 (1941).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-39"><akn:num>§ 44-39</akn:num><akn:heading>Uniforms, arms and equipment</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The National Guard shall, as far as practicable, be uniformed, armed, and equipped with the same type of uniform, arms, and equipment as are or shall be provided for th e armed forces of the United States. History History. 1930, p. 955; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(29); 1958, c. 393. § 44-39.1. Possession of handguns by members at National Guard facilities. Text To the extent permitted by federal law and by the terms of any contract between the Virginia National Guard and a privately owned facility, any member of the Virginia N ational Guard who possesses a valid concealed handgun permit issued pursuant to Article 6.1 (§ 18.2-307.1 et seq.) of Chapter 7 of Title 18.2 shall be permitted to possess a concealed handgun owned by such member at all facilities of the Virginia Nati onal Guard and at all privately owned facilities under contract with the Virginia National Guard. Nothing herein precludes the commanding officer of any member from prohibiting such member from possessing a concealed handgun while such member is particip ating in any training or other exercises where the commanding officer determines that (i) such possession would interfere with the conduct of such training or other exercises, (ii) such possession may result in mission impairment, or (iii) the member is unfit to carry a handgun. History History. 2016, c. 740.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-40"><akn:num>§ 44-40</akn:num><akn:heading>Discipline and training</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The discipline and training of the Virginia National Guard shall conform to that of the Armed Forces of the United States, and to that end, the Manual for Courts-Martia l, United States, including but not limited to the Uniform Code of Military Justice as now existing or subsequently amended, is hereby incorporated as a part of the military laws of Virginia except where in conflict with other provisions of this chapter. Officers and soldiers of the National Guard shall have such powers in the performance of their duty under this title as officers and soldiers of the active armed services have in the performance of like duty under the Uniform Code of Military Justice an d Manual for Courts-Martial, United States. However, should a person commit an offense punishable under the criminal laws of Virginia, then prosecution under the criminal laws shall bar prosecution under this chapter. The Adjutant General shall by regula tion adapt to state usage the provisions and terminology of the Manual for Courts-Martial, United States, including but not limited to the Uniform Code of Military Justice. History History. 1930, p. 955; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(30); 1958, c. 393; 1976 , c. 399; 1984, c. 7; 1987, c. 32. § 44-40.01. Nonjudicial disciplinary proceedings. Text Service members of the Virginia National Guard, not in federal service, are subject to nonjudicial punishment pursuant to Part V of the Manual for Courts-Martial, Unite d States. A commanders authority to impose nonjudicial punishment shall not include the authority to impose correctional custody, arrest in quarters, restriction, or extra duties. Reduction in rank shall not be imposed if the service member has more than 10 years of military service and is in the rank of E-5 or above. When nonjudicial punishment is to be imposed by a commanding officer of the rank of major or above, a service member shall not be allowed to demand trial by court-martial in lieu of no njudicial punishment. Service members shall retain all appeal rights available under the Manual for Courts-Martial, and the appeal shall include a review for abuse of discretion and legal sufficiency of the evidence. History History. 2015, c. 194. § 44-40.1. Persons subject to the Virginia military laws. Text All members of the Virginia National Guard are subject to the military laws of Virginia when under orders to be present for duty under Title 32 of the United States Cod e or while in a state active duty status. History History. 1976, c. 399; 2011, cc. 572, 586. Annotations The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendments by cc. 572 and 586 are identical, and substituted under Title 32 of the United States Code or while in a state active duty status for not in federal service. § 44-40.2. Administration of oaths and taking of sworn statements by commissioned officers. Text In addition to those powers set forth in § 44-40, commissioned officers in the Virginia National Guard may administer oaths and take sworn statements in connection w ith any investigation required by law or regulation pertaining to the Virginia National Guard in the performance of their duties. History History. 1987, c. 32.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-41"><akn:num>§ 44-41</akn:num><akn:heading>Armory drills, inactive training, annual active duty training, etc</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Training, including inactive training, armory drills, annual active duty for training, active duty training and other exercises, shall be conducted in accordance with e xisting or subsequently amended National Guard regulations. History History. 1930, p. 955; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(31); 1958, c. 393; 1964 , c. 227. § 44-41.1. Failure to report; etc. Text If any person, being an active member of the Virginia National Guard, in violation of valid orders, fails to initially report to his appointed place of duty at the appo inted time of duty under Title 32 of the United States Code or for state active duty, or having initially reported absents himself without leave, he shall be guilty of a Class 4 misdemeanor. A warrant for such offense may be sworn by any officer of the u nit to which the soldier or airman who failed to report, or absented himself, is assigned. Any such warrant shall be withdrawn upon the written request of the soldier or airmans commanding officer. History History. 1977, c. 315; 1978, c. 342; 1983, c. 65; 1984, c. 206; 2011, cc. 72, 108. Annotations Cross references. As to punishment for Class 4 misdemeanors, see § 18.2-11. The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendments by cc. 72 and 108 are identical, and rewrote the section. § 44-41.2. Sharing of information with Virginia Employment Commission upon separation. Text The Adjutant General shall, in consultation with the Commissioner of the Virginia Employment Commission, establish a program under which the Department of Military Affa irs shall, upon request of a member of the Virginia National Guard, provide information on the member to the Virginia Employment Commission, including (i) the individuals name; (ii) the date, or anticipated date, of the individuals discharge, sep aration, or release from the Virginia National Guard; (iii) the characterization, or anticipated characterization, of the individuals discharge from the Virginia National Guard; (iv) the individuals level of education; (v) contact information for the individual; (vi) the individuals military job classification and list of military training and certifications; (vii) the individuals civilian skills, training, and certification, as self-selected by the individual; and (viii) the industry, e mployment sector, profession, or other career classification, as self-identified by the individual, in which the individual will seek employment. Nothing in this section shall be construed to limit the collection and maintenance of information for records required to be kept by the Virginia Employment Commission pursuant to 16 VAC 5-32-10 or pursuant to any other regulation adopted in accordance with § 60.2-111. History History. 2014, cc. 42, 302. Article 4. National Guard Courts-Martial. -360§ 44-42. Kinds of courts-martial; how constituted and powers. -360§ 44-43. Repealed by Acts 2011, cc. 572 and 586, cl. 2. -360§ 44-44. Special courts-martial. -360§ 44-45. Summary courts-martial. -360§ 44-46. Repealed by Acts 1977, c. 74. -360§ 44-46.1. Military judges. -360§ 44-47. Process and procedure. -360§ 44-48. Review of judgments of courts-martial; procedure. -360§ 44-49. Where sentences executed. -360§ 44-50. How process and sentence executed. -360§ 44-51. Certificates. -360§ 44-52. Repealed by Acts 2011, cc. 572 and 586, cl. 2. -360§ 44-53. Collection of fines. -360§ 44-54. Disposition of fines. Annotations Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 12B M.J. Military, § 11.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-42"><akn:num>§ 44-42</akn:num><akn:heading>Kinds of courts-martial; how constituted and powers</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text In the National Guard not in federal service, there shall be special and summary courts-martial, constituted like similar courts of the army and the air force. They sha ll have the jurisdiction and powers, except as to punishments, and shall follow the forms and procedures provided for such courts as are enumerated in the Manual for Courts-Martial United States. History History. 1930, p. 956; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(32); 1976, c. 399; 2011 , cc. 572, 586. Annotations The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendments by cc. 572 and 586 are identical, and deleted general following there shall be and made a minor stylistic change.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-43"><akn:num>§ 44-43</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 2011, cc</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>572 and 586, cl. 2. Annotations Editors note. Former § 44-43, pertaining to general courts-martial and penalties, was derived from Acts 1930, p. 956; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(33); 1958, c. 393; 1964, c. 227; 1976, c. 399; 1977, c. 74.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-44"><akn:num>§ 44-44</akn:num><akn:heading>Special courts-martial</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. In the Nati onal Guard for servicemembers on orders for duty under Title 32 of the United States Code or state active duty, the first commanding officer in the rank of colonel or above may convene special courts-martial. B. A special c ourt-martial may not try a commissioned officer. C. A special c ourt-martial shall have the authority to impose any of the following fines and penalties: 1. A fin e of not more than $1,000; 2. Forfeiture of two-thirds pay per month for six months; 3. A reprimand; 4. Bad Conduct discharge; 5. Restriction to limits; 6. Imposition of extra duty; 7. Confinement for not more than three months; 8. Reduction of enlisted persons one or more pay grades; or 9. Any combination of these punishments. History History. 1930, p. 956; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(34); 1958, c. 393; 1964 , c. 227; 1976, c. 399; 1977, c. 74; 2011, cc. 572, 586. Annotations The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendments by cc. 572 and 586 are identical, and rewrote subsection A, which read: In the National Guard, not in federal service, the commanding offi cer of each garrison, fort, post, camp, air base, auxiliary air base, or other place, where troops are on duty, or brigade, regiment, wing, group, detached battalion, separate squadron, or other detached command, may convene special courts-martial. Speci al courts-martial may also be convened by superior authority; and rewrote subsection C, which read: A special court-martial shall have the same powers of punishment as a general court-martial, except that of dismissal or dishonorable discharge. A ny fine imposed by a special court-martial shall not exceed $100 nor shall any period of confinement exceed 10 days. A special court-martial may award a bad conduct discharge.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-45"><akn:num>§ 44-45</akn:num><akn:heading>Summary courts-martial</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. In the Nati onal Guard for servicemembers on orders for duty under Title 32 of the United States Code or active state duty, the first commanding officer in the rank of lieutenant colonel or above may convene a summary court-martial, consisting of one commissioned of ficer. Proceedings conducted under the provisions of this section shall be informal. B. A summary c ourt-martial shall have the authority to impose fines of not more than $500, to impose forfeitures of two-thirds pay for one month, to restrict to limits, to impose extra duty, to require confinement for not more than seven days, and to reduce enlisted p ersons one or more pay grades. History History. 1930, p. 956; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(35); 1958, c. 393; 1964 , c. 227; 1976, c. 399; 1977, c. 74; 2011, cc. 572, 586. Annotations The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendments by cc. 572 and 586 are identical, and rewrote subsection A, which read: In the National Guard, not in federal service, the commanding offi cer of each garrison, fort, post, camp, air base, auxiliary air base, or other place where troops are on duty, or division, brigade, regiment, wing, group, squadron, battalion or detached company, or other detachment, may convene a summary court-martial, consisting of one commissioned officer. Proceedings conducted under the provisions of this section shall be informal; and in subsection B, substituted $500 for twenty-five dollars, forfeitures of two-thirds pay for one month for forfeitures of pay and allowances and seven days for 2 1/2 days.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-46"><akn:num>§ 44-46</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1977, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>74. Annotations Cross references. For present provisions as to confinement by courts-martial, see §§ 44-44, 44-45 and 44-53. § 44-46.1. Military judges. Text A military judge shall be a commissioned officer of the National Guard, shall be so assigned as a legal officer, shall be admitted to the practice of law, and shall be certified for such duty by the Adjutant General. The Adjutant General shall designate a military judge on a case-by-case basis to preside over courts-martial of the Virginia National Guard. History History. 1976, c. 399; 2011, cc. 572, 586. Annotations The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendments by cc. 572 and 586 are identical, and substituted Virginia National Guard for National Guard not in federal service in the las t paragraph.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-47"><akn:num>§ 44-47</akn:num><akn:heading>Process and procedure</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text In the Virginia National Guard military judges whenever they sit on a military court, and otherwise presidents of courts-martial and summary court officers, shall have power to issue warrants to arrest accused persons and to bring them before the court for trial whenever such persons shall have disobeyed an order in writing from the convening authority to appear before such court, a copy of the charge or charges having been delivered to the accused with such order, and to issue commitments in carrying out sentences of confinement, and to issue subpoenas and subpoenas duces tecum, and to enforce by attachment attendance of witnesses and the production of books and pape rs, and to sentence for a refusal to be sworn or to answer as provided in actions before civil courts. They shall also have power to punish for contempt occurring in the presence of the court. History History. 1930, p. 957; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(37); 1976, c. 399; 2011 , cc. 572, 586. Annotations The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendments by cc. 572 and 586 are identical, and substituted In the Virginia National Guard for In the National Guard, not in federal service  at the beginning.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-48"><akn:num>§ 44-48</akn:num><akn:heading>Review of judgments of courts-martial; procedure</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Judgments of special and summary courts-martial shall be subject to review by the Adjutant General only, except that sentences of Bad Conduct discharge shall also be su bject to review by the Governor; and such judgments may be affirmed, set aside or modified; provided, however, no higher or greater sentence, punishment, penalty, fine or forfeiture than that imposed by the court-martial shall be approved; otherwise tria ls and proceedings, including nonjudicial punishment, pretrial proceedings, post-trial proceedings, search and seizure proceedings and proceedings by all courts and boards, including review proceedings, shall be in accordance with the Manual for Courts-M artial United States, as now existing or subsequently amended, procedure for courts of inquiry, and retiring boards, and other procedures under military law, as may from time to time be prescribed by the appropriate secretary of the respective services. History History. 1930, p. 957; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(38); 1964, c. 227; 1976 , c. 399; 2011, cc. 572, 586. Annotations The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendments by cc. 572 and 586 are identical, and deleted general following Judgments of and substituted sentences of Bad Conduct disc harge for sentences of dismissal from the service or dishonorable discharge.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-49"><akn:num>§ 44-49</akn:num><akn:heading>Where sentences executed</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text All sentences to confinement imposed by any military court of this Commonwealth shall be executed in such penal institutions of the Commonwealth as may be appropriate f or similar terms of confinement sentenced for violations of criminal laws of the Commonwealth. History History. 1930, p. 957; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(39); 1958, c. 393; 1964 , c. 227; 1976, c. 399.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-50"><akn:num>§ 44-50</akn:num><akn:heading>How process and sentence executed</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text All processes and sentences of any of the military courts of this Commonwealth shall be executed by any sheriff, deputy sheriff, sergeant, or police officer into whose hands the same may be placed for service or execution, and such officer shall make return thereof to the officer issuing or imposing the same. Such service or execution of process or sentence shall be made by such officer without tender or advancement of fee therefor, but all costs in such cases shall be paid from funds appropriated for military purposes. The actual necessary expenses of conveying a prisoner from one county or city in the Commonwealth to another, when the same is authorized and directed by the Adjutant General of the Commonwealth, shall be paid from the military fund of the Commonwealth upon a warrant approved by the Adjutant General. History History. 1930, p. 957; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(40); 1958, c. 393; 1976 , c. 399.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-51"><akn:num>§ 44-51</akn:num><akn:heading>Certificates</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Where any sentence to fine or imprisonment shall be imposed by any military court of this Commonwealth, it shall be the duty of the military judge whenever one sits on such court, and otherwise the president of the court or summary court officer, upon the approval of the findings and sentence of such court, to make out and sign a certificate entitling the case, giving the name of the accused, the date and place of tria l, the date of approval of sentence, the amount of fine, or manner, place, and duration of confinement, and deliver such certificate to the sheriff, or deputy sheriff, sergeant or police officer of the county, city or town wherein the sentence is to be e xecuted; and it shall thereupon be the duty of such officer to carry such sentence into execution in the manner prescribed by law for the collection of fines or commitments to service of terms of imprisonment in criminal cases determined in the courts of this Commonwealth. History History. 1930, p. 957; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(41); 1958, c. 393; 1976 , c. 399.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-52"><akn:num>§ 44-52</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 2011, cc</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>572 and 586, cl. 2. Annotations Editors note. Former § 44-52, pertaining to dismissal or dishonorable discharge, was derived from Acts 1930, p. 958; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(42); 1976, c. 399.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-53"><akn:num>§ 44-53</akn:num><akn:heading>Collection of fines</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text For the purpose of collecting any fines or penalties imposed by a court-martial, the military judge whenever one sits on such court, and otherwise the president of the court, or the summary court officer, shall, within fifteen days after the fines or penalties have been imposed and approved, make a list of all the persons fined, describing them distinctly, and showing the sums imposed as fines or penalties on each pers on, and shall draw his warrant, under his official signature, directed to any marshal of the court, or to the sheriff, sergeant, or any policeman of any city or county, as the case may be, thereby commanding him to levy such fines or penalties, together with the costs, on the goods and chattels of such delinquent, and the warrant shall thereupon have the force and effect of fieri facias, but such delinquent shall not be entitled to the benefit of any exemption law of this Commonwealth, as against such w arrant and the lien thereof. In default of sufficient personal property to satisfy the same, the officer executing the same shall make report accordingly to the drawing authority of the warrant which may then require the fined person to show whether or n ot he possesses sufficient property to satisfy the fine and if such property is found to exist and the fined person fails to deliver it over the executing officer shall be ordered to take the body of the delinquent and convey him to the jail of the city or county in which he may be found, whose jailer shall closely confine him without bail until the fine or penalty and jailers fees be paid. No such imprisonment shall extend beyond the period of ten days. History History. 1930, p. 958; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(44); 1976, c. 399; 1977 , c. 74.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-54"><akn:num>§ 44-54</akn:num><akn:heading>Disposition of fines</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text All fines imposed by courts-martial or other military courts, whether collected by such courts or by the civil authorities, shall be turned over by the courts or by the civil officer collecting the same to the Adjutant General, who shall keep an accurate account of the same. The Adjutant General, after deducting the costs of holding the courts and the collection of the fines, shall annually turn the balance in to the t reasury of the Commonwealth, to be placed to the credit of the Literary Fund. History History. 1930, p. 958; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(43); 1958, c. 393. Article 4.1. National Guard Mutual Assistance Compact. -360§ 44-54.1. Compact enacted into law; terms. -360§ 44-54.2. Payment of liability of State pursuant to Article III (f) of compact. -360§ 44-54.3. Members of National Guard deemed to be in state service when engaged pursuant to compact. § 44-54.1. Compact enacted into law; terms. Text The National Guard Mutual Assistance Compact is hereby enacted into law and entered into by the Commonwealth of Virginia with all other states legally joining therein, in the form substantially as follows: NATIONAL GUARD MUTUAL ASSISTANCE COMPACT Article I. Purposes. The purposes of this compact are to: 1. Provi de for mutual aid among the party states in the utilization of the national guard to cope with emergencies. 2. Permit and encourage a high degree of flexibility in the deployment of national guard forces in the interest of efficiency. 3. Maximize the effectiveness of the national guard in those situations which call for its utilization under this compact. 4. Provide protection for the rights of national guard personnel when serving in other states on emergency duty. Article II. Entry into Force and Withdrawal. (a) This compa ct shall enter into force when enacted into law by any two states. Thereafter, this compact shall become effective as to any other state upon its enactment thereof. (b) Any party state may withdraw from this compact by enacting a statute repealing the same, but no such withdrawal shall take effect until one year after the governor of the withdrawing state has given notice in writing of such withdrawal to the governors of all othe r party states. Article III. Mutual Aid. (a) As used in this article: 1. Emergency means an occurrence or condition, temporary in nature, in which police and other public safe ty officials and locally available national guard forces are, or may reasonably be expected to be, unable to cope with substantial and imminent danger to the public safety. 2. Requesting state means the state whose governor requests assistance in coping with an emergency. 3. Responding state means the state furnishing aid, or requested to furnish aid. (b) Upon reque st of the governor of a party state for assistance in an emergency, the governor of a responding state shall have authority under this compact to send without the borders of his state and place under the temporary command of the appropriate national guar d or other military authorities of the requesting state all or any part of the national guard forces of his state as he may deem necessary, and the exercise of his discretion in this regard shall be conclusive. (c) The govern or of a party state may withhold the national guard forces of his state from such use and recall any forces or part or member thereof previously deployed in a requesting state. (d) Whenever n ational guard forces of any party state are engaged in another state in carrying out the purposes of this compact, the members thereof so engaged shall have the same powers, duties, rights, privileges and immunities as members of national guard forces in such other state. The requesting state shall save members of the national guard forces of responding states harmless from civil liability for acts or omissions in good faith which occur in the performance of their duty while engaged in carrying out the purposes of this compact, whether the responding forces are serving the requesting state within its borders or are in transit to or from such service. (e) Subject to the provisions of paragraphs (f), (g) and (h) of this article, all liability that may arise under the laws of the requesting state, the responding state, or a third state on account of or in connection with a request for aid, shall be assumed and borne by the requesting state. (f) Any respon ding state rendering aid pursuant to this compact shall be reimbursed by the requesting state for any loss or damage to, or expense incurred in the operation of any equipment answering a request for aid, and for the cost of the materials, transportation and maintenance of national guard personnel and equipment incurred in connection with such request: Provided, that nothing herein contained shall prevent any responding state from assuming such loss, damage, expense or other cost. (g) Each party state shall provide, in the same amounts and manner as if they were on duty within their state, for the pay and allowances of the personnel of its national guard units while engaged without the state pursuant to this compact and while going to and retur ning from such duty pursuant to this compact. Such pay and allowances shall be deemed items of expense reimbursable under paragraph (f) by the requesting state. (h) Each party state providing for the payment of compensation and death benefits to injured members and the representatives of deceased members of its national guard forces in case such members sustain injuries or are killed within their own state, shall provide for the payment of compensation and death benefits in the same manner and on the same terms in case such members sustain injury or are killed while rendering aid pursuant to this compact. Such compensation and death benefits shall be deemed items of expense reimbursable pursuant to paragraph (f) of this article. Article IV. Delegation. Nothing in this compact shall be construed to prevent the governor of a party state from delegating any of his responsibilities or authority respecting the national gua rd, provided that such delegation is otherwise in accordance with law. For purposes of this compact, however, the governor shall not delegate the power to request assistance from another state. Article V. Limitations. Nothing in this compact shall: 1. Expan d or add to the functions of the national guard, except with respect to the jurisdictions within which such functions may be performed. 2. Authorize or permit national guard units to be placed under the field command of any person not having the military or national guard rank or status required by law for the field comma nd position in question. Article VI. Construction and Severability. This compact shall be liberally construed so as to effectuate the purposes thereof. The provisions of this compact shall be severable and if any phrase, clause, sentenc e or provision of this compact is declared to be contrary to the constitution of any state or of the United States or the applicability thereof to any government, agency, person or circumstance is held invalid, the validity of the remainder of this compa ct and the applicability thereof to any government, agency, person or circumstance shall not be affected thereby. If this compact shall be held contrary to the constitution of any state participating herein, the compact shall remain in full force and eff ect as to the remaining party states and in full force and effect as to the state affected as to all severable matters. History History. 1968, c. 36. Annotations The numbers of §§ 44-54.1 through 44-54.3 were assigned by the Virginia Code Commission, the 1968 act having assigned no numbers. § 44-54.2. Payment of liability of State pursuant to Article III (f) of compact. Text Upon presentation of a claim therefor by an appropriate authority of a state whose national guard forces have aided this State pursuant to the compact, any liability of this State pursuant to Article III (f) of the compact shall be paid out of funds appropriated to the Department of Military Affairs. History History. 1968, c. 36; 1980, c. 221. § 44-54.3. Members of National Guard deemed to be in state service when engaged pursuant to compact. Text In accordance with Article III (h) of the compact, members of the National Guard forces of this Commonwealth shall be deemed to be in state service at all times when en gaged pursuant to this compact, and shall be entitled to all rights and benefits provided pursuant to this title as amended. History History. 1968, c. 36. Article 4.2. Virginia Defense Force. -360§ 44-54.4. Organization; definitions. -360§ 44-54.5. Composition of units. -360§ 44-54.6. Members, appointment and enlistment. -360§ 44-54.7. Regulations. -360§ 44-54.8. Administration of oaths. -360§ 44-54.9. Uniform; rank in precedence; command. -360§ 44-54.10. Discipline. -360§ 44-54.11. Discharge; dismissal. -360§ 44-54.12. Arms, equipment and facilities. § 44-54.4. Organization; definitions. Text The Virginia Defense Force with a targeted membership of at least 1,200 shall be organized within and subject to the control of the Department of Military Affairs. When called to state active duty, the mission of the Virginia Defense Force shall be to (i) provide for an adequately trained organized reserve militia to assume contro l of Virginia National Guard facilities and to secure any federal and state property left in place in the event of the mobilization of the Virginia National Guard, (ii) assist in the mobilization of the Virginia National Guard, (iii) support the Virginia National Guard in providing family assistance to military dependents within the Commonwealth in the event of the mobilization of the Virginia National Guard, and (iv) provide a military force to respond to the call of the Governor in those circumstances described in § 44-75.1. Nothing in this article shall be construed as authorizing the Virginia Defense Force or any part thereof to be called, ordered...</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-55"><akn:num>§ 44-55</akn:num><akn:heading>44-55 through 44-66</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Repealed by Acts 2015, c. 221, cl. 2. Annotations Editors note. Former §§ 44-55 through 44-66, Naval Militia in General, derived from 1930, pp. 958961; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(45)(50), (58)(60); 1973, c. 401; 1998, c. 52. Article 6. Naval Militia Courts-Martial. -360§§ 44-67 through 44-74. Repealed by Acts 2015, c. 221, cl. 2.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-67"><akn:num>§ 44-67</akn:num><akn:heading>44-67 through 44-74</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Repealed by Acts 2015, c. 221, cl. 2. Annotations Editors note. Former §§ 44-67 through 44-74, Naval Militia Courts-Martial, derived from 1930, pp. 960, 961; Michie Code 1942, § 2673 (51)(57); 1973, c. 401. Article 7. Regulations as to Active Service. -360§ 44-75. Repealed by Acts 1988, c. 352. -360§ 44-75.1. Militia state active duty. -360§ 44-75.1:1. Compact enacted into law; terms. -360§ 44-75.2. Militia training duty. -360§ 44-76. Transportation, equipment and support of militia. -360§ 44-77. Orders to officers and appointment of rendezvous. -360§ 44-78. Repealed by Acts 1988, c. 352. -360§ 44-78.1. Request for assistance by localities. -360§ 44-79. Repealed by Acts 1988, c. 352. -360§ 44-80. Order in which classes of militia called into service. -360§ 44-81. Length of service when called out. -360§ 44-82. How troops paid while in service; transportation to be furnished; movement of troops and supplies not to be delayed. -360§ 44-83. Pay and allowance of members. -360§ 44-84. Regulations enforced on actual service. Annotations Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 12B M.J. Military, § 14.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-75"><akn:num>§ 44-75</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1988, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>352. § 44-75.1. Militia state active duty. Text A. The Governo r or his designee may call forth the militia or any part thereof to state active duty for service in any of the following circumstances: 1. In th e event of invasion or insurrection or imminent threat of either; 2. When any combination of persons becomes so powerful as to obstruct the execution of laws in any part of this Commonwealth; 3. When the Governor determines that a state agency or agencies having law-enforcement responsibilities are in need of assistance to perform particular law-enforcement functions, which fu nctions he shall specify in his call to the militia; 4. In the event of flood, hurricane, fire or other forms of natural or man-made disaster wherein human life, public or private property, or the environment is imperiled; 5. In emergencies of lesser magnitude than those described in subdivision 4, including but not limited to the disruption of vital public services, wherein the use of militia personnel or equipment would be of assistance to one or more departments, agencies, institutions, or political subdivisions of the Commonwealth; 6. When the Governor determines that the National Guard and its assets would be of valuable assistance to state, local or federal agencies having a drug law-enforcement function to combat the flow of or use of illegal drugs in the Commonwealth, he may provide for the National Guard or any part thereof to support drug interdiction, counterdrug and demand reduction activities within the Commonwealth, or outside the Commonwealth under the N ational Guard Mutual Assistance Counterdrug Activities Compact. In calling forth the National Guard under this section, the Governor shall specify the type of support that the National Guard shall undertake with state, local or federal law-enforcement ag encies. Once called forth by the Governor, the National Guard is also specifically authorized to enter into mutual assistance and support agreements with any law-enforcement agencies, state or federal, operating within or outside this Commonwealth so lon g as those activities are consistent with the Governors call. All activities undertaken by the National Guard in the areas of drug interdiction, counterdrug and drug demand reduction shall be reported by the Adjutant Generals office to the Govern or and reviewed by the Governor no less frequently than every three months; and 7. When the Governor or his designee, in consultation with the Adjutant General, determines that the militia or any part thereof is in need of specific training to be prepared for being c alled forth for any of the circumstances expressed in subdivisions 1 through 6 above. Such training may be conducted with a state or federal agency or agencies having the capability or responsibility to coordinate or assist with any of the circumstances set forth in subdivisions 1 through 6 above. B. The Virgini a National Guard shall be designated as a state law-enforcement agency for the sole purpose of receiving property and revenues pursuant to 18 U.S.C. § 981(e) (2), 19 U.S.C. § 1616a, and 21 U.S.C. § 881(e) (1) (A). History History. 1988, c. 352; 1993, c. 932; 1995, c. 49; 1996, cc. 71, 805. Annotations Cross references. As to the rule that no state, county or municipal officer or employee shall forfeit his title to office or position or vacate the same by reason of military servi ce, see § 2.2-2802. As to workers compensation coverage for members of Virginia National Guard, Virginia Defense Force and naval militia during response to orders, see § 65.2- 103. § 44-75.1:1. Compact enacted into law; terms. Text The National Guard Mutual Assistance Counterdrug Activities Compact is hereby enacted into law and entered into by the Commonwealth of Virginia with all other states le gally joining therein, in the form substantially as follows: INTERSTATE COMPACT ON NATIONAL GUARD COUNTERDRUG OPERATIONS ARTICLE I. PURPOSE. The purposes of this compact are to: 1. Provi de for mutual assistance and support among the party states in the utilization of the National Guard in drug interdiction, counterdrug and demand reduction activities. 2. Permit the National Guard of this Commonwealth to enter into mutual assistance and support agreements, on the basis of need, with one or more law-enforcement agencies operating within this Commonwealth, for activities within this Commonwealth, or with a National Guard of one or more other states, whether said activities are within or without this Commonwealth in order to facilitate and coordinate efficient, cooperative enforcement eff orts directed toward drug interdiction, counterdrug activities, and demand reduction. 3. Permit the National Guard of this Commonwealth to act as a requesting or a responding state as defined within this compact and to ensure the prompt and effective delivery of National G uard personnel, assets, and services to agencies or areas that are in need of increased support and presence. 4. Permit and encourage a high degree of flexibility in the deployment of National Guard forces in the interest of efficiency. 5. Maximize the effectiveness of the National Guard in those situations which call for its utilization under this compact. 6. Provide protection for the rights of National Guard personnel when performing duty in other states in counterdrug activities. 7. Ensure uniformity of state laws in the area of National Guard involvement in interstate counterdrug activities by incorporating said uniform laws within the compact. ARTICLE II. ENTRY INTO FORCE AND WITHDRAWAL. A. This compact shall enter into force when enacted by any two states. Thereafter, this compact shall become effective as to any other state upon its enactment thereof. B. Any party state may withdraw from this compact by enacting a statute repealing the same, but no such withdrawal shall take effect until one year after the governor of the withdrawing s tate has given notice in writing of such withdrawal to the governors of all other party states. ARTICLE III. MUTUAL ASSISTANCE AND SUPPORT. A. As used in this article:Demand reduction means providing available National Guard personnel, equipment, support and coordination to federal, state, local and civic organizations, institutions, and agencies for the purposes of the prevention of drug abuse and the reduction in the demand for illegal drugs.Drug interdiction and counterdrug activities means the use of National Guard personnel, while not in federal service, in any law-enforcement support activities that are intended to reduce the supply or use of illegal drugs in the United States. These activities include, but are not limited to: 1. Providing information obtained, during either the normal course of military training or operations or during counterdrug activities, to federal, state or local law-enforcement officials that may be relevant to a violation of any federal or state law with in the jurisdiction of such officials; 2. Making available any equipment, including associated supplies or spare parts, base facilities, or research facilities of the National Guard to any federal, state or local civilian law-enforcement official for law-enforcement purposes, in accordance with other applicable laws or regulations; 3. Providing available National Guard personnel to train federal, state or local civilian law-enforcement personnel in the operation and maintenance of equipment, including equipment made available above, in accordance with other applicable laws; 4. Providing available National Guard personnel to operate and maintain equipment provided to federal, state or local law-enforcement officials pursuant to activities defined and ref erred to in this compact; 5. Operating and maintaining equipment and facilities of the National Guard or other law-enforcement agencies used for the purposes of drug interdiction and counterdrug activities; 6. Providing available National Guard personnel to operate equipment for the detection, monitoring and communication of the movement of air, land and sea traffic; to facilitate commu nications in connection with law-enforcement programs; to provide transportation for civilian law-enforcement personnel; and to operate bases of operations for civilian law-enforcement personnel; 7. Providing available National Guard personnel, equipment and support for administrative, interpretive, analytic or other purposes; and 8. Providing available National Guard personnel and equipment to aid federal, state and local officials and agencies otherwise involved in the prosecution or incarceration of individ uals processed within the criminal justice system who have been arrested for criminal acts involving the use, distribution or transportation of controlled substances as defined in 21 U.S.C. § 801 et seq. or otherwise by law, in accordance with other a pplicable law.Law-enforcement agency means a lawfully established federal, state, or local public agency that is responsible for the prevention and detection of crime and the enforcement of penal, traffic, regulatory, game, immigration, postal, customs or controlled substances laws. Mutual assistance and support agreement or agreement means an agreement between the National Guard of this Commonwealth and one or more law-enforcement agencies or between the National Guard of this Commonwealth and the National Guard of one or more other states, consistent with the purposes of this compact.Official means the appointed, elected, desi gnated or otherwise duly selected representative of an agency, institution or organization authorized to conduct those activities for which support is requested.Party state refers to a state that has lawfully enacted this compact.Requesting state means the party state whose governor requested assistance in the area of counterdrug activities.Responding state means the party state furnishing assistance, or requested to furnish assistance, in the area of counterdrug activities. State mea...</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-76"><akn:num>§ 44-76</akn:num><akn:heading>Transportation, equipment and support of militia</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Whenever the Governor shall call forth the militia, whether by virtue of the Constitution or of § 44-75.1, he shall issue such orders and take such measures for proc uring and transporting the elements thereof as to him shall seem best; and for their accommodation, equipment and support, he shall appoint such a staff as to him shall seem proper. History History. 1930, p. 962; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(62); 1958, c. 393.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-77"><akn:num>§ 44-77</akn:num><akn:heading>Orders to officers and appointment of rendezvous</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Such orders shall be sent to such officers and in such manner as the Governor may deem expedient, with a notification of the place of rendezvous; and the officers to wh om the orders are sent shall proceed immediately to execute the same. History History. 1930, p. 962; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(63).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-78"><akn:num>§ 44-78</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1988, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>352. § 44-78.1. Request for assistance by localities. Text In the event of the circumstances described in subdivision A 2, 4 or 5 of § 44-75.1 arise within a county, city or town of the Commonwealth, either the governing bod y or the chief law-enforcement officer of the county, city or town may call upon the Governor for assistance from the militia. The Governor may call forth the militia or any part thereof to provide such assistance as he may deem proper in responding to s uch circumstances, but in all instances the militia shall remain subject to military command and not to civilian authorities of the county, city or town receiving assistance. History History. 1988, c. 352. Annotations Cross references. As to workers compensation coverage for members of Virginia National Guard, Virginia Defense Force and naval militia during response to orders, see § 65.2- 103.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-79"><akn:num>§ 44-79</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1988, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>352.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-80"><akn:num>§ 44-80</akn:num><akn:heading>Order in which classes of militia called into service</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The National Guard, the Virginia Defense Force, and the unorganized militia or any part thereof may be ordered into service by the Governor in such order as he determin es. History History. 1930, p. 963; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(66); 1964, c. 227; 1989 , c. 414; 2011, cc. 572, 586; 2015, c. 221. Annotations The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendments by cc. 572 and 586 are identical, and deleted State preceding Defense Force. The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendment by c. 221 deleted the naval militia following Virginia Defense Force.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-81"><akn:num>§ 44-81</akn:num><akn:heading>Length of service when called out</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The National Guard, the Virginia Defense Force, or the unorganized militia, when called into service by the Governor, shall serve for such time as, in the Governors judgment, may be necessary. History History. 1930, p. 963; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(67); 1958, c. 393; 1989 , c. 414; 1993, c. 112; 2011, cc. 572, 586; 2015, c. 221. Annotations The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendments by cc. 572 and 586 are identical, and rewrote the section, which read: The National Guard, the Virginia State Defense Force, the naval mil itia or the unorganized militia, when called into service by the Governor, shall serve for sixty days after their arrival at the place of rendezvous, unless sooner discharged. But the Governor shall, at all times, have power to retain them in service for such time as, in his judgment, may be necessary; however, except when the whole National Guard or the whole Virginia State Defense Force is not required, no individual shall be retained for a longer period than sixty days except in instances where an in dividual soldier or airman of the National Guard voluntarily consents to service beyond sixty days. The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendment by c. 221 deleted the naval militia following Virginia Defense Force.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-82"><akn:num>§ 44-82</akn:num><akn:heading>How troops paid while in service; transportation to be furnished; movement of troops and supplies not to be delayed</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text All officers and enlisted personnel of the National Guard or Virginia Defense Force, whenever called out in aid of the civil authorities, shall receive the compensation herein provided, and such compensation, and the necessary expenses incurred in furnishing supplies, subsistence, quartering, and transporting troops, shall be paid no later than 10 work days after the receipt of required payroll documentation by the Pay roll Services Bureau of the Department of Accounts by the State Treasurer. Such payments shall be made on warrants to be drawn by the Comptroller, on the State Treasurer, upon certificates of the officer in actual command of the troops, and upon payrolls prepared according to such forms as the state regulations shall prescribe. Such payrolls and certificates are to be transmitted to the Adjutant General through the regular military channels, and he shall approve them before such warrants shall be drawn. The Comptroller and the State Treasurer are hereby authorized and directed to draw the warrants and make the payments herein provided for in accordance with current or subsequently amended pay and allowances of United States armed forces. The several transportation companies in this Commonwealth shall furnish transportation for troops so called out, stores, munitions and equipments, upon application of t he officer in actual command, accompanied by a certificate from him of the number of personnel to be carried and their destination, and a copy of the order calling them out. For such transportation the transportation company shall be entitled to receive compensation from the Commonwealth. Transportation of troops and military supplies shall be as speedy as possible and have the right-of-way over all passenger and freight traffic on transportation lines w ithin the Commonwealth, and failure to furnish transportation when called upon, or unnecessary delay in transporting such troops and supplies, shall be punishable by a fine of not less than $1,000 or more than $10,000. History History. 1930, p. 963; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(68); 1958, c. 393; 1973 , c. 401; 2011, cc. 572, 586; 2015, c. 221. Annotations The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendments by cc. 572 and 586 are identical, and in the first sentence in the first paragraph, inserted Virginia Defense Force and substituted shall be paid no later than 10 work days after the receipt of required payroll documentation by the Payroll Services Bureau of the Department of Accounts by the State Treasurer for shall be paid monthly by the State Treasurer out of the milit ary contingent fund, and out of any moneys not otherwise appropriated; and in the second paragraph, deleted the last sentence, which read: And it shall be the duty of the Adjutant General to contract annually with the various transportation compa nies of the Commonwealth, for rates of transportation, should there be occasion for it, provided, that such rates shall not exceed any maximum fixed by law. The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendment by c. 221 substituted National Guard or Virginia Defense Force for National Guard, Virginia Defense Force, or naval militia in the first sentence.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-83"><akn:num>§ 44-83</akn:num><akn:heading>Pay and allowance of members</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Notwithstanding any other provision of law, when called into state active duty, not in the service of the United States, members of the National Guard and members of th e Virginia Defense Force shall receive pay and allowances equal to their rank and years of service, as determined by the Department of Military Affairs. The Adjutant General may increase state active duty pay on an annual basis by a rate not to exceed th e most recent percentage increase in basic pay for members of the Armed Forces. History History. 1930, p. 964; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(69); 1958, c. 393; 1988 , c. 352; 2011, cc. 572, 586; 2016, c. 341; 2020, c. 832. Annotations The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendments by cc. 572 and 586 are identical, and added the next-to-last sentence. The 2016 amendments. The 2016 amendment by c. 341 substituted state active duty for active state duty and members for officers in the first sentence, s ubstituted members for enlisted persons and and allowances as if they were on a day of Annual Training for rations, and allowances as enlisted persons of like grade of the United States armed forces in the second sentence , deleted rations following pay and substituted National Guard for a day of Annual Training, capped at 25 years of service for United States Armed Forces in the third sentence, and deleted the former final sentence, which read: When rations are not issued, the value of the same shall be commuted and paid by the Adjutant General. The 2020 amendments. The 2020 amendment by c. 832, rewrote the section, which read: When called into state active duty, not in the service of the United States, officers of the Na tional Guard shall receive the same pay and allowances as prescribed for members of like rank in the United States Armed Forces. For each day of such service, members of the National Guard shall receive the same pay and allowances as if they were on a da y of Annual Training. For each day of service, members of the Virginia Defense Force called to state active duty shall receive the same pay and allowances as persons of like grade in the National Guard for a day of Annual Training, capped at 25 years of service.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-84"><akn:num>§ 44-84</akn:num><akn:heading>Regulations enforced on actual service</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Whenever any portion of the militia shall be called into service to execute the law, suppress riot or insurrection, or to repel invasion, the military justice opinions as set forth in Article 4 (§ 44-42 et seq.) of this chapter, and the regulations prescribed for the National Guard of the United States, and the regulations issued thereunder, shall be enforced and regarded as a part of this chapter until such forces shall be duly relieved from such duty. History History. 1930, p. 964; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(70); 1958, c. 393. Article 8. Unorganized Militia. -360§ 44-85. Regulations and penalties. -360§ 44-86. When ordered out for service. -360§ 44-87. Manner of ordering out for service. -360§ 44-88. Incorporation into the Virginia Defense Force. -360§ 44-89. Draft of unorganized militia. -360§ 44-90. Punishment for failure to appear.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-85"><akn:num>§ 44-85</akn:num><akn:heading>Regulations and penalties</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Whenever any part of the unorganized militia is ordered out, it shall be governed by the same rules and regulations and be subject to the same penalties as the National Guard. History History. 1930, p. 965; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(71); 2015, c. 221. Annotations The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendment by c. 221 deleted or naval militia at the end of the section.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-86"><akn:num>§ 44-86</akn:num><akn:heading>When ordered out for service</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The commander in chief may at any time, in order to execute the law, suppress riots or insurrections, or repel invasion, or aid in any form of disaster wherein the live s or property of citizens are imperiled or may be imperiled, order out the National Guard and the inactive National Guard or any parts thereof, or the whole or any part of the unorganized militia. When the militia of this Commonwealth, or a part thereof, is called forth under the Constitution and laws of the United States, the Governor shall order out for service the National Guard, or such part thereof as may be necessary; and he may likewise order out such a part of the unorganized militia as he may d eem necessary. During the absence of organizations of the National Guard in the service of the United States, their state designations shall not be given to new organizations. History History. 1930, p. 965; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(72); 1958, c. 393.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-87"><akn:num>§ 44-87</akn:num><akn:heading>Manner of ordering out for service</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Governor shall, when ordering out the unorganized militia, designate the number to be so called. He may order them out either by calling for volunteers or by draft. History History. 1930, p. 965; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(73); 1944, p. 25; 1958, c. 393; 1984, c. 765.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-88"><akn:num>§ 44-88</akn:num><akn:heading>Incorporation into the Virginia Defense Force</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Whenever the Governor orders out the unorganized militia or any part thereof, it shall be incorporated into the Virginia Defense Force until relieved from service. History History. 1944, p. 25; Michie Suppl. 1946, § 2673(73); 1984, c. 765; 201 1, cc. 572, 586. Annotations The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendments by cc. 572 and 586 are identical, and deleted State preceding Defense Force.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-89"><akn:num>§ 44-89</akn:num><akn:heading>Draft of unorganized militia</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text If the unorganized militia is ordered out by draft, the Governor shall designate the persons in each county and city to make the draft, and prescribe rules and regulati ons for conducting the same. History History. 1930, p. 965; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(74).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-90"><akn:num>§ 44-90</akn:num><akn:heading>Punishment for failure to appear</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Every member of the militia ordered out for duty, or who shall volunteer or be drafted, who does not appear at the time and place ordered, shall be liable to such punis hment as a court-martial may direct. History History. 1930, p. 965; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(75); 1958, c. 393. Article 9. Pay of Militia. -360§§ 44-91, 44-92. Repealed by Acts 1958, c. 393.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-91"><akn:num>§ 44-91</akn:num><akn:heading>44-91, 44-92</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Repealed by Acts 1958, c. 393. Article 10. Privileges of United States Reserve, National Guard, and Naval Militia. -360§ 44-93. Leaves of absence for employees of Commonwealth or political subdivisions. -360§ 44-93.1. Supplement of military pay and additional life insurance benefits for employees of Commonwealth or political subdivision s. -360§ 44-93.2. Leaves of absence from nongovernmental employment. -360§ 44-93.3. Reemployment rights. -360§ 44-93.4. Discrimination against persons who serve in the Virginia National Guard, Virginia Defense Force, or National Guard of an other state and acts of reprisal prohibited. -360§ 44-93.5. Penalties for denial. -360§ 44-94. Exemption from jury duty. -360§ 44-95. Repealed by Acts 1958, c. 393. -360§ 44-96. Military property exempt from levy and sale. -360§ 44-97. Exemption from arrest. -360§ 44-97.1. Continuance or time for filing pleading, etc., where party or attorney is on active duty. -360§ 44-98. Interference with employment of members of Virginia National Guard or Virginia Defense Force. -360§ 44-99. Organizations may own property; suits. -360§ 44-100. No action allowed on account of military duties; counsel for members sued or prosecuted. -360§ 44-101. Repealed by Acts 1958, c. 544. -360§ 44-102. Commission not to vacate civil office. -360§ 44-102.1. Rights, benefits and protections upon call to active duty; contract termination. -360§ 44-102.1:1. Benefits upon call to active duty under a state of emergency; health care premiums. -360§ 44-102.2. Virginia Military Family Relief Fund established.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-93"><akn:num>§ 44-93</akn:num><akn:heading>Leaves of absence for employees of Commonwealth or political subdivisions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. All officer s and employees of the Commonwealth or of any political subdivision of the Commonwealth who are former members of the armed services or members of the organized reserve forces of any of the armed services of the United States or National Guard shall be e ntitled to leaves of absence from their respective duties, without loss of seniority, accrued leave, or efficiency rating, on all days during which they are engaged in federally funded military duty, to include training duty, or when called forth by the Governor pursuant to the provisions of § 44-75.1 or § 44-78.1.There shall be no loss of regular employer pay during such leaves of absence, except that paid leaves of absence for federally funded military duty, to include training duty, shall not e xceed 21 workdays per federal fiscal year, and except that no officers or employees shall receive paid leave for more than 21 workdays per federally funded tour of active military duty.When relieved from such duty, they shall be restored to positions hel d by them when ordered to duty. If the office or position has been abolished or otherwise has ceased to exist during such leave of absence, they shall be reinstated in a position of like seniority, status and pay, if the position exists, or in a comparab le vacant position for which they are qualified, unless to do so would be unreasonable.For the purposes of this section, with respect to employees of the Commonwealth or its political subdivisions who do not normally work approximately equal workdays on five or more days of each calendar week, the term workday shall mean 1/260 of the total working hours such employee would be scheduled to work during an entire federal fiscal year, not taking into account any state holidays, annual leave, militar y leave, or other absences. Where such employee returns from federally funded military duty and the eight-hour rest period required by the Uniformed Services Employment and Reemployment Rights Act (38 U.S.C. § 4301 et seq.) overlaps such employees scheduled work shift, the employee shall receive paid military leave to the extent of such overlap. B. In addition to the provisions of subsection A, any local government may pay such employee when activated for federally funded military duty all or any portion of the difference between his regular pay and the military pay received during all or any part of the term of active federally funded duty. History History. 1930, p. 966; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(78); 1958, c. 393; 1964 , c. 227; 1966, c. 295; 1968, c. 503; 1983, c. 590; 1984, c. 540; 1985, c. 103; 1986, c. 611; 1989, cc. 414, 474; 1991, c. 653; 2002, cc. 212, 354; 2006, c. 621; 2015, c. 221; 2022, c. 430. Annotations Cross references. As to duty of Department of Human Resource Management as to development of personnel policies, see § 2.2-1201. The 2002 amendments. The 2002 amendment by c. 212 inserted the subsection A designation at the beginning of the first paragraph and added subsection B. The 2002 amendment by c. 354 inserted regular employer in the beginning of the second sentence of present subsection A, and inserted the present fourth se ntence of that subsection. The 2006 amendments. The 2006 amendment by c. 621 added the last sentence in the fourth paragraph of subsection A. The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendment by c. 221 substituted United States or National Guard for United States, National Guard, or the naval militia in the first sent ence of subsection A. The 2022 amendments. The 2022 amendment by c. 430 in the second paragraph, substituted 21 for fifteen twice. Law Review. For article surveying developments in labor and employment law in Virginia, see 37 U. Rich. L. Rev. 241 (2002). OPINIONS OF THE ATTORNEY GENERAL Compensation of county treasurer while on active military duty.  A county treasurer may continue to receive compensation as treasurer while involuntarily recalled to active military duty as long as the treasurer is actually per forming the duties of his office, whether such duties are performed via use of the Internet or during the evening hours and weekends. See opinion of Attorney General to Ms. Phyllis C. Katz, County Attorney for New Kent County, 02-003, 2002 Va. AG LEXIS 1 5 (1/31/02). § 44-93.1. Supplement of military pay and additional life insurance benefits for employees of Commonwealth or political subdivisions. Text A. In addition to the paid military leave provisions of § 44-93, the Commonwealth or any political subdivision of the Commonwealth may supplement the military pay of its officers and employees who are reservists or national guard members called to federally funded military duty in an amount necessary to bring their total salary, inclusive of their base military pay, to the level earned at the time they were called to federally funded military duty. The employer may also, in its discretion, continue to provide any health insurance and other existing benefits to such officers and employees. B. In addition to any other benefit provided by law, if an employee of the Commonwealth or of any political subdivision has been called to federal active duty services under Title 10 of the United States Code, the Commonwealth shall provide an additional death benefit in the amount of $20,000 to be paid if the employee is killed in action in any armed conflict while serving with any reserve component of the Army, Navy, Marine Corps, Air Force, or Coast Guard or with any unit of these respective services of the United States. History History. 2002, c. 354; 2005, cc. 907, 910. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2005, cc. 907 and 910, cl. 3 provides: That the provisions of subsection B of § 44-93.1 shall be applicable to the employees described therein killed in action in any armed conflict on or after October 7, 2001, the start of United States armed conflict in Afghanistan. The 2005 amendments. The 2005 amendment by cc. 907 and 910 are identical, and added the subsection A designator and subsection B. § 44-93.2. Leaves of absence from nongovernmental employment. Text A member of the Virginia National Guard or Virginia Defense Force, or a person who is a member of the National Guard of another state and who is otherwise employed in t he Commonwealth, called to state active duty or military duty pursuant to Title 32 of the United States Code shall have the right to take leave without pay from his nongovernmental employment. No member of the National Guard or Virginia Defense Force, or person who is a member of the National Guard of another state, shall be forced to use or exhaust his vacation or other accrued leaves from his nongovernmental employment for a period of active service. The choice of leave shall be solely within the disc retion of the member. History History. 2002, c. 354; 2007, cc. 167, 214; 2011, cc. 572, 586; 2015, c. 22 1; 2016, c. 327; 2018, c. 216. Annotations The 2007 amendments. The 2007 amendments by cc. 167 and 214 are identical, and substituted active duty or military duty pursuant to Title 32 of the United States Code for  active duty pursuant to the provisions of § 44-75.1 or § 44-78.1 by the Governor in the first sentence. The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendments by cc. 572 and 586 are identical, and twice deleted State preceding Defense Force. The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendment by c. 221 substituted National Guard or Virginia Defense Force for National Guard, Virginia Defense Force, or naval militia in the first and second sentences. The 2016 amendments. The 2016 amendment by c. 327 inserted or a resident of the Commonwealth who is a member of the National Guard of another state in the first sentence and a substantially similar phrase in the second sentence. The 2018 amendments. The 2018 amendment by c. 216 substituted person for resident of the Commonwealth twice; and inserted and who is otherwise employed in the Comm onwealth. Law Review. For 2007 annual survey article, Labor and Employment Law, see 42 U. Rich. L. Rev. 489 (2007). For article, Employment Law, see 54 U. Rich. L. Rev. 103 (2019). § 44-93.3. Reemployment rights. Text Upon honorable release from state active duty or military duty pursuant to Title 32 of the United States Code, a member of the Virginia National Guard or Virginia Defen se Force, or a person who is a member of the National Guard of another state and who was previously employed in the Commonwealth, shall make written application to his previous employer for reemployment within (i) 14 days of his release from duty or from hospitalization following release if the length of the members absence by reason of service in the uniformed services does not exceed 180 days or (ii) 90 days of his release from duty or from hospitalization following release if the length of the me mbers absence by reason of service in the uniformed services exceeds 180 days. When released from such duty, they shall be restored to positions held by them when ordered to duty. If the office or position has been abolished or otherwise has ceased t o exist during such leave of absence, they shall be reinstated in a position of like seniority, status and pay if the position exists, or to a comparable vacant position for which they are qualified, unless to do so would be unreasonable. This section sh all not apply when the cumulative length of the absence and of all previous absences from a position of employment with that employer by reason of service in the uniformed services exceeds five years. History History. 2002, c. 354; 2007, cc. 167, 214; 2010, c. 253; 2011, cc. 572, 58 6; 2015, c. 221; 2016, c. 327; 2018, c. 216. Annotations The 2007 amendments. The 2007 amendments by cc. 167 and 214 are identical, and inserted or military duty pursuant to Title 32 of the United States Code; substituted 14 day s for five days in the first sentence, and added the last sentence. The 2010 amendments. The 2010 amendment by c. 253 in the first sentence inserted the clau...</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-94"><akn:num>§ 44-94</akn:num><akn:heading>Exemption from jury duty</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The active officers and members of the National Guard shall be exempt from serving on juries in civil and criminal cases upon presentation to the clerk of the court of a certificate of such membership signed by the commanding officer of the unit of which the person summoned for jury service is a member. History History. 1930, p. 966; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(79); 2015, c. 221. Annotations The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendment by c. 221 deleted and naval militia following National Guard. Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 11B M.J. Jury, § 16.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-95"><akn:num>§ 44-95</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1958, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>393.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-96"><akn:num>§ 44-96</akn:num><akn:heading>Military property exempt from levy and sale</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The uniforms, arms, and equipment required by law or regulations of every commissioned and warrant officer and every enlisted person of the Virginia National Guard and Virginia Defense Force shall be exempt from sale under any execution, distress, or other process for debt and taxes. History History. 1930, p. 966; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(81); 1958, c. 393; 1984 , c. 765; 2011, cc. 572, 586; 2015, c. 221. Annotations The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendments by cc. 572 and 586 are identical, and deleted State preceding Defense Force. The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendment by c. 221 substituted Virginia National Guard and Virginia Defense Force for Virginia National Guard, Virginia Defense Force, and n aval militia. Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 8A M.J. Exemptions from Execution and Attachment, § 23.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-97"><akn:num>§ 44-97</akn:num><akn:heading>Exemption from arrest</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text No person belonging to the Virginia National Guard or Virginia Defense Force shall be arrested on any process issued by or from any civil officer or court, except in ca ses of felony or breach of the peace, while going to, remaining at or returning from any place at which he may be required to attend for military duty; nor in any case whatsoever while actually engaged in the performance of his military duties, except wi th the consent of his commanding officer. History History. 1930, p. 966; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(82); 1984, c. 765; 2015 , c. 221. Annotations Cross references. As to privilege from arrest under civil process, see § 8.01-327.2. The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendment by c. 221 substituted Virginia National Guard or Virginia Defense Force for Virginia National Guard, Virginia State Defense Force o r the naval militia. Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 2A M.J. Arrest, § 2. § 44-97.1. Continuance or time for filing pleading, etc., where party or attorney is on active duty. Text Any party to or attorney in an action or proceeding in any court, including the Supreme Court of Virginia, commission, or other tribunal having judicial or quasi-judici al powers or jurisdiction who has been ordered to participate in state active duty, annual active duty for training, or temporary active duty in the reserve forces of any of the armed services of the United States or National Guard shall be entitled to a continuance, not to exceed three weeks, as a matter of right during the period of such duty, provided the continuance is requested at least four days prior to the first day for which the continuance is sought. The period required by any statute or rule for the filing of any pleading or the performance of any act relating thereto shall be extended for seven days after such active duty, provided a request is made four days prior to the date the pleading or act is due. The failure of any court, commission , or other tribunal to allow such continuance when requested to do so or the returning of such filing or act during the period hereinabove specified shall constitute reversible error. This section shall not prevent the granting of temporary injunctive re lief or the dissolution or extension of a temporary injunction, but the right to such relief shall remain in the sound discretion of the court or other such tribunal. History History. 1981, c. 288; 1990, c. 790; 2011, cc. 572, 586; 2015, c. 221. Annotations The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendments by cc. 572 and 586 are identical, and inserted state active duty in the first sentence. The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendment by c. 221 substituted United States or National Guard for United States, National Guard, or naval militia in the first sentence . Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 4A M.J. Continuances, §§ 3, 14, 15.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-98"><akn:num>§ 44-98</akn:num><akn:heading>Interference with employment of members of Virginia National Guard or Virginia Defense Force</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A person who, either by himself or with another, deprives a member of the Virginia National Guard or Virginia Defense Force of his employment, or prevents, by himself o r another, such member being employed, or obstructs or annoys such member or his employer at his trade, business, or employment, because such member of such organization is such member, or dissuades any person from enlistment in the Virginia National Gua rd or Virginia Defense Force by threat or injury to him in his trade, business, or employment in case he shall so enlist, shall be guilty of a misdemeanor and on conviction thereof shall be fined in a sum not exceeding $500, or imprisonment in jail not m ore than 30 days, or shall suffer both fine and imprisonment. History History. 1930, p. 967; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(83); 1958, c. 393; 1984 , c. 765; 2011, cc. 572, 586; 2015, c. 221. Annotations The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendments by cc. 572 and 586 are identical, and twice deleted State preceding Defense Force. The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendment by c. 221 twice substituted Virginia National Guard or Virginia Defense Force for Virginia National Guard, Virginia Defense Force o r naval militia, substituted his trade, business, or employment for his employment, trade or business and made minor stylistic changes.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-99"><akn:num>§ 44-99</akn:num><akn:heading>Organizations may own property; suits</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Companies or other organizations of the Virginia National Guard and Virginia Defense Force shall have the right to own and keep real and personal property necessary for their use, which shall belong to and be under control of the active members of the unit; and the commanding officer of any unit shall have the right and power to maintain any suit, in his own name, to recover for the use of the unit any debts or effects belonging to the unit, or damages for the injury thereof; and no suit pending in his name shall be abated by his ceasing to be the commanding officer of the unit; but upon motion of the commander succeeding him, such commander shall be admitted to prose cute the suit in like manner and with like effect as if it had been originally instituted by him. Armories owned by such units shall be exempt from all state, county and municipal taxation. History History. 1930, p. 967; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(84); 1958, c. 393; 1984 , c. 765; 2011, cc. 572, 586; 2015, c. 221. Annotations The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendments by cc. 572 and 586 are identical, and deleted State preceding Defense Force. The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendment by c. 221 substituted Virginia National Guard and Virginia Defense Force for Virginia National Guard, Virginia Defense Force and na val militia.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-100"><akn:num>§ 44-100</akn:num><akn:heading>No action allowed on account of military duties; counsel for members sued or prosecuted</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text No action or proceeding shall be prosecuted or maintained against a member of a military court, or officer or person acting under its authority or reviewing its proceed ings, on account of the approval or imposition or execution of any sentence, or the imposition or collection of fine or penalty, or the execution of any warrant, writ, execution, process, or mandate of a military court, nor shall any member of the Virgin ia National Guard or Virginia Defense Force be liable to civil action or suit or criminal prosecution for any act done while in the discharge of his military duty. If any member of the Virginia National Guard or Virginia Defense Force is sued civilly or arrested, indicted, or otherwise prosecuted for any act committed in the disch arge of his official duty while on state duty, the Adjutant General may employ special counsel approved by the Attorney General to defend such member. The compensation for special counsel employed pursuant to this section shall, subject to the approval b y the Attorney General, be paid out of the funds appropriated for the administration of the Department of Military Affairs. History History. 1930, p. 967; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(85); 1972, c. 416; 1973 , c. 401; 1984, c. 765; 2011, cc. 572, 586; 2015, c. 221. Annotations The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendments by cc. 572 and 586 are identical, and twice deleted State preceding Defense Force. The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendment by c. 221 substituted Virginia National Guard or Virginia Defense Force for Virginia National Guard, Virginia Defense Force, or nav al militia in the first and second paragraphs.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-101"><akn:num>§ 44-101</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1958, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>544.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-102"><akn:num>§ 44-102</akn:num><akn:heading>Commission not to vacate civil office</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Any citizen of the Commonwealth may accept and hold a commission in the Virginia National Guard and receive pay therefrom or a commission in the Virginia Defense Force or armed forces reserve of the United States, without thereby vacating any civil office or position or commission held by him; and the acceptance or holding of any such commission, and receiving pay therefrom shall not constitute such holding of an offic e of trust and profit under the government of the Commonwealth and of the United States as shall be incompatible with the holding of any civil office, legislative or judicial, or position or commission under the government of the Commonwealth. History History. 1930, p. 968; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(87); 1958, c. 393; 1984 , c. 765; 2011, cc. 572, 586. Annotations The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendments by cc. 572 and 586 are identical, and deleted State preceding Defense Force and made minor stylistic changes. § 44-102.1. Rights, benefits and protections upon call to active duty; contract termination. Text A. Any right, benefit, or protection that may accrue to a member of the Virginia National Guard under the federal Servicemembers Civil Relief Act (50 U.S.C. § 3901 et seq.), as a result of a call to federal active duty service under Title 10 of the United States Co de shall be extended to a member of the Virginia National Guard called to active duty service under Title 32 of the United States Code, or to state active duty by the Governor, if the active duty orders are for a period of 30 consecutive days or more. In addition, if a member of the Virginia National Guard is called to state active duty by the Governor, the employer shall ensure that the member has the option of continuing, at the members expense, his health care coverage, life insurance, or long-te rm care insurance. B. Any member of the United States Armed Forces or Virginia National Guard who receives permanent change of station orders or has received temporary duty orders in excess of three months duration, his spouse, or his dependent may, at any time prior to the conclusi on of his period of service, terminate without penalty a contract for the following services: 1. Telec ommunications services; 2. Internet services; 3. Television services; 4. Athletic club or gym memberships; 5. Satellite radio services; or 6. Service for an alarm system as defined in § 15.2-911.It shall be a violation of the Virginia Consumer Protection Act (§ 59.1-196 et seq.) for a service provider to fail to comply with the provisions of this subsection. History History. 2003, c. 769; 2010, cc. 811, 861; 2011, cc. 572, 586; 2017, c. 29 3. Annotations Editors note. At the direction of the Virginia Code Commission, 50 U.S.C. § 3901 et seq. was substituted for 50 U.S.C. App. § 501 et seq. to conform to t he reclassification of Title 50 U.S.C. App. The 2010 amendments. The 2010 amendments by cc. 811 and 861 are identical, and added the last sentence. The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendments by cc. 572 and 586 are identical, and substituted the federal Servicemembers Civil Relief Act for the Federal Soldiers and Sai lors Civil Relief Act. The 2017 amendments. The 2017 amendment by c. 293 inserted the subsection A designation and added subsection B. § 44-102.1:1. Benefits upon call to active duty under a state of emergency; health care premiums. Text A. As used in this section: Department means the Department of Military Affairs. Service member means a member of the Virginia National Guard or the Virginia Defense F orce. State of emergency has the same meaning as provided in § 44-146.16. B. If the Gove rnor has declared a state of emergency that activated the Virginia National Guard or the Virginia Defense Force, then the Department is authorized to pay, for any service member who has served under such activation for a period of at least 14 consecutive days, the portion of the premium for such service members health care coverage previously paid by the service members employer, provided that the service member provides satisfactory evidence to the Department demonstrating that (i) immediately prior to being called to state active duty, the service member was employed and received health care coverage through his employer, (ii) the employer paid a premium to maintain the service members health care coverage, and (iii) as a result of the se rvice members state active duty status, the employer is no longer paying such premium. C. Any payment made by the Department pursuant to this section shall cover only the portion of the premium previously paid by the service members employer from day 15 of the service members state active duty until the date the service member is discharged from state active duty. Such payments may also cover dependents of the service member. D. The Departm ent may use the sum sufficient identified in the relevant state of emergency declaration for any payment authorized by this section. E. The Departm ent shall establish policies, procedures, and protocols to implement and record any payment authorized by this section. F. On or befor e November 1, 2022, and annually thereafter, the Department shall report to the Secretary of Veterans and Defense Affairs all payments made pursuant to this section. G. Nothing in this section shall create a legal cause of action against the Commonwealth or the Department. History History. 2022, cc. 373, 372. § 44-102.2. Virginia Military Family Relief Fund established. Text A. There is he reby created in the state treasury a special nonreverting fund to be known as the Virginia Military Family Relief Fund (the Fund). The Fund shall be established on the books of the Comptroller and administered by the Office of the Adjutant General for th e purposes set forth herein. All moneys as may be appropriated by the General Assembly, private gifts, grants, or donations contributed to the Fund, and revenues received by the Commonwealth for the Fund pursuant to § 58.1-344.3 shall be paid into the state treasury and credited to the Fund. Interest earned on moneys in the Fund shall remain in the Fund and be credited to it. Any moneys remaining in the Fund, including interest thereon, at the end of each fiscal year shall not revert to the general f und but shall remain in the Fund. Moneys in the Fund shall be used solely for the purposes of assisting members of the Virginia National Guard and Virginia residents who are members of the reserves of the armed forces of the United States who have been c alled to extended federal active duty for periods in excess of 90 days and missions in support of Virginia civil authorities, including state active duty and federal defense support to civil authority missions, for periods in excess of 30 days, and their families, with living expenses including, but not limited to food, housing, utilities, and medical services. Assistance may be provided from the Fund from the date of entry into active duty until 180 days after release from active duty. Expenditures and disbursements from the Fund shall be made by the State Treasurer on warrants issued by the Comptroller upon written request signed by the Adjutant General. B. The Adjutan t General shall submit an annual report to the Governor and the chairmen of the House Committee on Appropriations and the Senate Committee on Finance and Appropriations of the General Assembly. The report shall detail: 1. The e xpenditures of the Fund, including the amount of awards provided from the Fund to each branch of service, the amount of individual and family assistance provided, the qualifications of the recipients, and the balance available in the Fund for future disb ursements; and 2. The name, address, rank, branch of service, deployment location, and amount of financial assistance provided to each recipient. The information provided under this subdivision that ide ntifies a recipient or members of the recipients family or the deployment location of any member of the Virginia National Guard or the reserves of the armed forces of the United States shall be confidential and shall not be subject to public disclosu re. History History. 2006, cc. 103, 479; 2007, cc. 73, 911; 2015, c. 320. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2010, cc. 287 and 391 provide: § 1. That it shall be the policy of the Commonwealth to exclude from taxation all benefits paid in accordance with the provisions of the Virginia Military Family Relief Fund, as established in § 44-102.2 of the Code of Virginia, to the extent included in federal adjusted gross income. The Virginia Code Commission authorized the substitution of the House Committee on Appropriations and the Senate Committee on Finance and Appropriations f or House Appropriations Committee and the Senate Committee on Finance. March 10, 2021. The 2007 amendments. The 2007 amendments by cc. 73 and 911 are identical, and added the eighth sentence in subsection A. Chapter 911 became effective April 4, 2007, by emergency enact ment clause. The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendment by c. 320 in subsection A, inserted federal preceding active duty and and missions in support of Virginia civil authorities , including state active duty and federal defense support to civil authority missions, for periods in excess of 30 days in the sixth sentence. Law Review. For 2007 annual survey article, Family and Juvenile Law, see 42 U. Rich. L. Rev. 417 (2007). Article 11. Care of Military Property. -360§ 44-103. Deposit in armories or headquarters for safekeeping. -360§ 44-104. Care required and liability of officers. -360§ 44-105. Repealed by Acts 1958, c. 393. -360§ 44-106. Upon disbandment of organization, or call into active federal service, commanding officer to return certain property to A djutant General. -360§ 44-107. Use for private purposes forbidden. -360§ 44-108. Officers and enlisted persons personally liable for military property. -360§ 44-109. Punishment for injuries to military property...</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-103"><akn:num>§ 44-103</akn:num><akn:heading>Deposit in armories or headquarters for safekeeping</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text All arms, equipment and ordnance stores, which shall be furnished to the several commands under the provisions of this chapter, shall be deposited in the armories or he adquarters of such commands for safekeeping. History History. 1930, p. 968; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(88).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-104"><akn:num>§ 44-104</akn:num><akn:heading>Care required and liability of officers</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text All commissioned officers of the Virginia National Guard and Virginia Defense Force shall exercise the strictest care and vigilance for the preservation of the uniforms , arms, supplies, equipment and military property furnished to their several commands under the provisions of this chapter. Any officer receiving public property for military use shall be responsible for the articles so received by him; and he shall not transfer such property, or any portion thereof, to another, either as a loan or permanently, without the authority of the Adjutant General, or his duly authorized representative. History History. 1930, p. 968; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(89); 1958, c. 393; 1984 , c. 765; 2011, cc. 572, 586; 2015, c. 221. Annotations The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendments by cc. 572 and 586 are identical, and deleted State preceding Defense Force. The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendment by c. 221 substituted Virginia National Guard and Virginia Defense Force for Virginia National Guard, Virginia Defense Force and na val militia.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-105"><akn:num>§ 44-105</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1958, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>393.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-106"><akn:num>§ 44-106</akn:num><akn:heading>Upon disbandment of organization, or call into active federal service, commanding officer to return certain property to Adjutant General</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Upon the disbandment of any organization, or call into active federal service of such organization, which has received arms, supplies or equipment from the Adjutant Gen eral, in accordance with the provisions of this chapter, the commanding officer of such organization shall be responsible for the safe return to the custody of the Adjutant General of all such public property in possession of the organization, except for such federally owned property that may be required by federal law to be retained by such organization in the federal service. History History. 1930, p. 968; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(91); 1958, c. 393.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-107"><akn:num>§ 44-107</akn:num><akn:heading>Use for private purposes forbidden</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text No officer or enlisted person shall use, except upon military duty any article of military property belonging to the United States or to the Commonwealth. History History. 1930, p. 969; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(92); 1958, c. 393.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-108"><akn:num>§ 44-108</akn:num><akn:heading>Officers and enlisted persons personally liable for military property</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Every officer and enlisted person to whom any article of military property is delivered in pursuance of the provisions of this chapter shall be held personally responsi ble for its care, safekeeping, and return. He shall use the same for military purposes only, and upon receiving a discharge, or otherwise leaving the military service, or upon demand of his commanding officer or the Adjutant General, shall forthwith surr ender and deliver such property in as good order and condition as the same was at the time he received it, reasonable fair wear and tear excepted. As insurance for compliance with the provisions of this chapter, the Adjutant General may require the bondi ng of any or all such officers or enlisted persons in an amount that he may deem appropriate, commensurate with the responsibilities of such officers or enlisted persons. The cost of such bonds shall be borne from funds appropriated for the operation of the Department of Military Affairs, and shall be without cost to the individual officer and/or enlisted person bonded. History History. 1930, p. 969; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(93); 1958, c. 393.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-109"><akn:num>§ 44-109</akn:num><akn:heading>Punishment for injuries to military property</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Whoever shall willfully or maliciously destroy, injure, or deface any arms or articles of military property belonging to the United States or to the Commonwealth, or re ceive any property in violation of the preceding sections of this chapter, shall be deemed guilty of a misdemeanor and be fined not exceeding double the amount of the value of the property so injured or defaced, or, in the discretion of the jury, be impr isoned in jail not less than two weeks nor more than two months. History History. 1930, p. 969; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(94).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-110"><akn:num>§ 44-110</akn:num><akn:heading>Punishment for sale, etc</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>, of military property. Text Whoever shall secrete, sell, dispose of, offer for sale, or in any manner pawn or pledge, or receive in pawn or pledge, buy, or intentionally fail to return after havin g been legally discharged from the National Guard any of the arms, uniforms, or equipments, being the property of the United States or of the Commonwealth, knowing or having reason to believe the same to be the property of the United States or the Common wealth, shall be deemed guilty of a misdemeanor, and shall, on conviction thereof, be imprisoned in jail for not less than six months nor more than one year, or in the discretion of the jury or judge, be fined not less than $50 nor more than $1,000. History History. 1930, p. 969; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(95); 2011, cc. 572, 586 . Annotations The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendments by cc. 572 and 586 are identical, and inserted or intentionally fail to return after having been legally discharged from the National Guar d and or judge, and made a related change, substituted $1,000 for $100 and made minor stylistic changes.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-111"><akn:num>§ 44-111</akn:num><akn:heading>Replacement of lost or damaged property</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Whenever any military property issued to the militia of the Commonwealth shall have been lost, damaged, or destroyed, and upon report of a disinterested survey officer of the armed forces or militia it shall appear that the loss, damage or destruction of property was due to carelessness or neglect, or that its loss, damage or destruction could have been avoided by the exercise of reasonable care, the money value of suc h property shall be charged against the bond of the officer or enlisted person, if bonded. If such officer or enlisted person is not bonded, the value of such property shall be charged to such officer or enlisted person, and the pay of such officer or en listed person from both federal and state funds at any time accruing may be stopped and applied to the payment of any such indebtedness until the same is discharged. In addition thereto, any officer accountable or responsible for military property shall be liable on his bond to the Commonwealth and the United States Property and Fiscal Officer as accounting, accountable and responsible officer for any lost, damaged, or destroyed property for which he is accountable or responsible. History History. 1930, p. 969; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(96); 1958, c. 393. Article 12. Support of Militia. -360§ 44-112. Requisition for federal funds. -360§ 44-113. County, city and town appropriations. -360§ 44-114. Allowances made to organizations from state appropriations.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-112"><akn:num>§ 44-112</akn:num><akn:heading>Requisition for federal funds</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Governor or such other state officer as may be authorized by law, shall make requisition upon the Secretary of Defense, through the National Guard Bureau, for such state allotment from federal funds as may be necessary for the support of the militia and as may be authorized by the laws and regulations of the United States. History History. 1930, p. 970; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(97); R. P. 1948, § 4 4-112; 1958, c. 393.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-113"><akn:num>§ 44-113</akn:num><akn:heading>County, city and town appropriations</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Counties, cities, and towns may appropriate such sums of money and real and personal property as they may deem proper to the various organizations of the National Guard or the Virginia Defense Force, when such organizations are maintained within the limits of the counties, cities, and towns respectively; and counties may appropriate such sums of money and real and personal property as they may deem proper to the variou s organizations of the National Guard if such organizations are maintained in any incorporated town or city of the second class located within the geographical limits of such counties respectively. History History. 1930, p. 970; 1940, p. 54; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(98); R. P. 1948, § 44-113; 1958, c. 393; 2014, cc. 30, 547; 2015, c. 221. Annotations The 2014 amendments. The 2014 amendments by cc. 30 and 547 are identical, and inserted the Virginia Defense Force and made minor stylistic changes. The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendment by c. 221 substituted National Guard or the Virginia Defense Force for National Guard, the Virginia Defense Force, or naval militia .</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-114"><akn:num>§ 44-114</akn:num><akn:heading>Allowances made to organizations from state appropriations</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text For the necessary expenses of the maintenance of the National Guard and the Virginia Defense Force, to include the providing of one flag of the Commonwealth of Virginia to the next of kin of any individual, upon his death, who was serving in, or honorably served for a period of 20 years in and retired from, the Virginia National Guard, the Virginia Defense Force, or a combination of both, the Adjutant General shall ann ually allot to each organization or unit such amounts as may in his judgment be advisable, and as may be available from the appropriation to the Department of Military Affairs, such allotment to be based upon such scheme of distribution as may appear equ itable to the Adjutant General and best suited to the needs of the military forces of the Commonwealth. History History. 1930, p. 970; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(99); R. P. 1948, § 4 4-114; 1999, c. 667; 2004, c. 12; 2013, cc. 150, 198; 2015, c. 221. Annotations The 1999 amendment inserted to include the providing of one flag of the Commonwealth of Virginia to the next of kin of any individual, upon his death, who was serving in or honorably served for a period of twenty years in and retired from the Virginia Nati onal Guard near the beginning of the section. The 2004 amendments. The 2004 amendment by c. 12 substituted 20 for twenty, deleted with the advice and approval of the Board of Military Affairs following the first occurrence of the Adjutant General and and the Board of Military Affairs following the second occurrence of the Adjutant General. The 2013 amendments. The 2013 amendments by cc. 150 and 198 are identical, and inserted and the Virginia State Defense Force following naval militia and Virginia S tate Defense Force, or a combination of both, the preceding Adjutant General and made a related change. The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendment by c. 221 substituted the National Guard and for the National Guard, the naval militia and and twice substituted Virginia D efense Force for Virginia State Defense Force. Article 12.1. Orders Inducting State Militia Into Federal Service. -360§ 44-114.1. Orders transmitted to and through the Governor. -360§ 44-114.2. Governor to be notified of receipt of order; no action taken until his instructions complied with. -360§ 44-114.3. Orders void if transmitted to militia before Governor notified. -360§ 44-114.4. Governor not prevented from drafting into state military service. § 44-114.1. Orders transmitted to and through the Governor. Text All orders from the federal government or any of its officers, agencies, or departments to the state militia of Virginia, including the National Guard and the unorganiz ed militia, that relate to the call, induction, or drafting of Virginia state troops of any type or description into the federal service for active duty or otherwise and withdrawing them from the control of the Governor of Virginia shall be first transmi tted to and through the Governor of Virginia. The Governor, as commander in chief of the state militia, shall not approve, consent to, or concur in any such order that has not been transmitted as herein required. History History. 1958, c. 540, § 1; 2015, c. 221. Annotations The numbers of §§ 44-114.1 through 44-114.4 were assigned by the Virginia Code Commission, the 1958 act having assigned no numbers. The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendment by c. 221 substituted that for which throughout the section, substituted National Guard and for National Guard, the naval militia, and in the first sentence, inserted or preceding drafting of Virginia troops. § 44-114.2. Governor to be notified of receipt of order; no action taken until his instructions complied with. Text If the Adjutant General of Virginia, or during his absence, any of his assistants, or anyone else in the Department of Military Affairs of the Commonwealth of Virginia, either in a civilian or military status, shall receive an order of the nature required in § 44-114.1 to be transmitted to the Governor, he shall immediately notify the Governor of Virginia of such receipt and the contents of this order by the most ex peditious means, and no action shall be taken by anyone towards notifying the individuals of organizations of the Virginia militia of the contents of such orders or directions received from the federal government on this subject by any of its agencies or representatives until the Governor has been first advised and instructions from him have been complied with fully. History History. 1958, c. 540, § 2. § 44-114.3. Orders void if transmitted to militia before Governor notified. Text If the Adjutant General or anyone else in the Department of Military Affairs should receive such a message of the kind referred to in § 44-114.1 and fail to notify t he Governor immediately, and subsequently transmits such orders, for the purpose of having such orders executed, to any personnel of the state militia, or to any person other than the Governor, then such order or orders shall be illegal, null and void. History History. 1958, c. 540, § 3. § 44-114.4. Governor not prevented from drafting into state military service. Text Nothing in this article shall prevent the Governor from drafting all citizens into the state military service if he may so desire in accordance with the military laws o f Virginia. History History. 1958, c. 540, § 4; 1973, c. 401. Article 13. General Provisions. -360§ 44-115. Custom and usage of United States army, air force and navy; applicability of §§ 44-40, 44-40.01 and Article 4 (§ 44-42 et seq.). -360§ 44-116. Repealed by Acts 2011, cc. 572 and 586, cl. 2. -360§ 44-117. Officers of Virginia Military Institute, the Virginia Womens Institute for Leadership at Mary Baldwin College, the Fi shburne Military School, the Massanutten Military Academy, and Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University to be officers of militia. -360§§ 44-117.1, 44-118. Repealed by Acts 1958, c. 393. -360§ 44-119. Retired list of officers, warrant officers and enlisted persons. -360§ 44-120. Protection of the uniform. -360§ 44-120.1. Manufacture of Virginia military medals and decorations in United States. -360§ 44-120.2. Commonwealths Twenty marksmanship award. -360§ 44-121. Repealed by Acts 2009, c. 108, cl. 1. -360§ 44-122. Citation of chapter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-115"><akn:num>§ 44-115</akn:num><akn:heading>Custom and usage of United States army, air force and navy; applicability of §§ 44-40, 44-40</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>01 and Article 4 (§ 44-42 et seq.). Text All matters relating to the organization, discipline and government of the Virginia National Guard, not otherwise provided for by law or by regulations, shall be decide d by the custom and usage of the United States army, air force or navy, as appropriate. In addition, all members of the Virginia Defense Force and the unorganized militia on training duty or state active duty shall be subject to military discipline. Infr actions of military discipline for the Virginia National Guard shall be punishable under the provisions of §§ 44-40 and 44-40.01 and Article 4 (§ 44-42 et seq.). Infractions of military discipline for the Virginia Defense Force and unorganized m ilitia shall be punishable under the provisions of §§ 44-40 and 44-40.01. History History. 1930, p. 970; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(100); 1964, c. 227; 198 4, c. 765; 1989, c. 414; 2011, cc. 572, 586; 2015, c. 221; 2016, c. 339. Annotations The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendments by cc. 572 and 586 are identical, and deleted State preceding Defense Force. The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendment by c. 221 substituted Virginia Defense Force and for Virginia Defense Force, the naval militia, and and deleted of this cha pter at the end in the second sentence. The 2016 amendments. The 2016 amendment by c. 339 inserted training duty or in the second sentence, inserted for the Virginia National Guard and and 44-40.01 i n the third sentence, and added the last sentence.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-116"><akn:num>§ 44-116</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 2011, cc</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>572 and 586, cl. 2. Annotations Editors note. Former § 44-116, pertaining to printing or purchase and distribution of military laws and Uniform Code of Military Justice, was derived from Acts 1930, p. 970; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(101); 1958, c. 393.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-117"><akn:num>§ 44-117</akn:num><akn:heading>44-117</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Officers of Virginia Military Institute, the Virginia Womens Institute for Leadership at Mary Baldwin College, the Fishburne Military School, the Mas sanutten Military Academy, and Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University to be officers of militia. Text The officers of the Virginia Military Institute, the Virginia Womens Institute for Leadership at Mary Baldwin College, the Fishburne Military School, the Massanutte n Military Academy, and the Commandant of Cadets and Assistant Commandants of Cadets of the Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University shall be commissioned officers of the Virginia militia, unorganized, and subject to the orders of the Governor and the same rules and regulations as to discipline provided for other commissioned officers of the military organizations of the Commonwealth. The Governor is authorized and directed to issue commissions to the professors, assistant professors and othe r officers of the Virginia Military Institute, the Fishburne Military School, the Massanutten Military Academy, and the Virginia Womens Institute for Leadership at Mary Baldwin College, according to the rank prescribed by those institutions; and to t he Commandant of Cadets and Assistant Commandants of Cadets of the Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. Such persons shall be eligible to receive and to continue to hold such commissions, regardless of age, for so long as they continue to be officers, professors or assistant professors of the Virginia Military Institute, the Virginia Womens Institute for Leadership at Mary Baldwin College, the Fishburne Military School, the Massanutten Military Academy, or the Commandant of Cadets or Assistant Commandants of Cadets of Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. The governing boards of each institution shall recommend to the Governor the rank to which such eligible persons shall be commissioned, but the following determinati on of such rank shall be made by the Governor. Commissions in such militia issued such persons by the Governor shall not entitle any person holding the same to any pay or emolument by reason thereof unless he be assigned to duty by order of the Governor with the Virginia National Guard; and in such event, the rank of such officer shall be relatively inferior to that of all other officers of the same grade in the Virginia National Guard. History History. 1930, p. 970; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(102); 1958, c. 393; 197 8, c. 384; 2001, c. 77; 2006, c. 123; 2007, c. 818. Annotations The 2001 amendments. The 2001 amendment by c. 77 inserted the Virginia Womens Institute for Leadership at Mary Baldwin College, in the first, second and third sentences, i nserted and following Virginia Military Institute in the second sentence, and substituted those institutions for it in that sentence. The 2006 amendments. The 2006 amendment by c. 123 inserted the Fishburne Military School in the first through third sentences. The 2007 amendments. The 2007 amendment by c. 818 inserted the Massanutten Military Academy, following The Fishburne Military School, in the section catchline and thro ughout the section. CASE NOTES Single-sex education.  See United States v. Virginia, 518 U.S. 515, 116 S. Ct. 2264, 135 L. Ed. 2d 735, 1996 U.S. LEXIS 4259 (1996). §§ 44-117.1, 44-118. Repealed by Acts 1958, c. 393.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-119"><akn:num>§ 44-119</akn:num><akn:heading>Retired list of officers, warrant officers and enlisted persons</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text There shall be a retired list of officers, warrant officers and enlisted persons of the Virginia National Guard. The following persons, upon their written applications through regular military channels to the Adjutant General, may be placed on the retired list of the Virginia Nati onal Guard: 1. Forme r Adjutant Generals who have resigned or been relieved; 2. Officers or enlisted persons in the guard who have been honorably discharged and have served for at least ten years in active service of the guard, or ten years computing the period se rved in the Virginia National Guard and the period of active service in the United States armed forces.Officers who have served honorably and efficiently in the Virginia National Guard or the Virginia militia shall be commissioned on the retired list of the Virginia militia, unorganized, in their respective grade, or the highest grade held by them in the military service of the Commonwealth, except that officers who have to their credit fifteen years or more of exemplary service may, at the discretion o f the Adjutant General, be retired with commission of the next higher grade to the highest grade held by them in the military service of the Commonwealth of Virginia.Warrant officers and noncommissioned officers shall be placed on the retired list with t he highest rank held by them in the Virginia National Guard.Reentry into the active military service of the Commonwealth or of the United States shall discharge officers, warrant officers and enlisted persons from the retired list, and for any future ret irement new application shall be made. History History. 1930, p. 971; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(104); 1958, c. 393; 198 3, c. 157; 2015, c. 221. Annotations The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendment by c. 221 deleted the last paragraph, which read: All officers, warrant officers and enlisted personnel heretofore placed on the retired li st by virtue of the provisions of an act approved March 3, 1892, as amended, shall be transferred to and borne upon the retired list of the Virginia militia, unorganized.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-120"><akn:num>§ 44-120</akn:num><akn:heading>Protection of the uniform</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text It shall be unlawful for any person, not an officer, warrant officer or enlisted person in the armed forces of the United States, to wear the duly prescribed uniform th ereof, or any distinctive part of such uniform, or a uniform any part of which is similar to a distinctive part of the duly prescribed uniform of the armed forces of the United States. The foregoing provision shall not be construed so as to prevent officers, warrant officers or enlisted persons of the National Guard, nor to prevent members of the orga nization known as the Boy Scouts of America, or such other organizations as the Secretary of Defense may designate, from wearing their prescribed uniforms; nor to prevent persons who in time of war have served honorably as officers of the armed forces of the United States and whose most recent service was terminated by an honorable discharge, muster out, or resignation, from wearing, upon occasions of ceremony, the uniform of the highest grade they have held in such service; nor to prevent any person wh o has been honorably discharged from the armed forces of the United States from wearing his uniform from the place of his discharge to his home, within three months after his discharge; nor to prevent the members of military societies composed entirely o f honorably discharged officers and enlisted persons, or both, of the armed forces of the United States from wearing, upon occasions of ceremony, the uniform duly prescribed by such societies to be worn by members thereof; nor to prevent the instructors and members of the duly organized cadet corps of any educational institution offering a regular course in military instruction from wearing the uniform duly prescribed by appropriate respective authority to be worn by instructors and members of such cade t corps; nor to prevent the instructors and members of such duly organized cadet corps of such institution of learning offering a regular course in military instruction and at which an officer, warrant officer or enlisted person of the armed forces of th e United States is lawfully detailed for duty as instructor in military science and tactics, from wearing the uniform duly prescribed by appropriate authority to be worn by instructors and members of such cadet corps; nor to prevent civilians attending a course of military instruction authorized and conducted by the military authorities of the United States from wearing while attending such a course the uniform authorized and prescribed by such military authorities to be worn during such course of instr uction; nor to prevent any person from wearing the uniform of the armed forces of the United States, in any playhouse or theater or in motion picture films or television while actually engaged in representing therein a military character not tending to b ring discredit or reproach upon the armed forces of the United States. The uniform worn by members of military societies, or the instructors and members of the cadet corps referred to in the preceding paragraph, shall include some distinct ive mark or insignia approved by the Secretary of Defense, to distinguish such uniforms from the uniform of the armed forces of the United States. The members of the military societies and the instructors and members of the cadet corps hereinbefore menti oned shall not wear the insignia of rank prescribed to be worn by the officers of the armed forces of the United States, or any insignia of rank similar thereto, unless otherwise authorized. Any person who offends against the provisions of this section shall, on conviction, be punished by a fine not exceeding $100, or by imprisonment not exceeding 30 days, or by both such fine and imprisonment. History History. 1930, p. 971; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(105); 1958, c. 393; 201 1, cc. 572, 586. Annotations The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendments by cc. 572 and 586 are identical, and deleted officers, warrant officers or enlisted persons of the National Guard, or by following The uniform worn by in the third paragraph. § 44-120.1. Manufacture of Virginia military medals and decorations in United States. Text Virginia military medals and decorations shall be made in the United States. Existing stocks of Virginia military medals and decorations which are of foreign origin may be consumed without violating the provisions of this act. All Virginia military medals and decorations shall have the words Made in the USA stamped on the reverse side. This act shall not limit the country of origin of United States military med als and decorations that are presented to members of the Virginia National Guard. History History. 1999, c. 22. Annotations The number of this section was assigned by the Virginia Code Commission, the 1999 act having assigned no section number. § 44-120.2. Commonwealths Twenty marksmanship award. Text There is hereby established the Commonwealths Twenty marksmanship award to recognize the top 20 marksmen in Virginia. These top 20 marksmen shall be chosen from the Virginia state residents who compete at the annual Virginia State Championship matches sanctioned by the Virginia Shooting Sports Association (the Association). The award shall be administered by the Association and shall consist of (i) an enamel metal tab pin with gray background and white lettering, similar in style, shape, and size to the Presidents Hundred pin awarded by the United States Army; (ii) a fabric patch with hook and loop backing with a green background and black letters, sim ilar in style, shape, and size to the Presidents Hundred patch awarded by the United States Army; and (iii) a certificate. History History. 2015, c. 747; 2017, c. 224. Annotations The 2017 amendments. The 2017 amendment by c. 224 rewrote the first sentence which formerly read: There is hereby established the Commonwealths Twenty marksmanship award to re cognize the top 20 competitors in each of the rifle and pistol Excellence-in-Competition matches at the annual Virginia State Championships conducted by the Virginia Shooting Sports Association (the Association); and added the second sentence.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-121"><akn:num>§ 44-121</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 2009, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>108, cl. 1.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-122"><akn:num>§ 44-122</akn:num><akn:heading>Citation of chapter</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text This chapter may be cited as the Military Laws of Virginia. History History. 1930, p. 973; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(107). Chapter 2. Armories, Buildings and Grounds. -360§ 44-123. Repealed by Acts 2015, c. 221, cl. 2. -360§ 44-123.1. Armory defined. -360§ 44-123.2. Fort Pickett Reservation created; venue. -360§ 44-123.3. Fort Pickett Police; powers; duties; functions. -360§ 44-124. Repealed by Acts 1976, c. 266. -360§ 44-124.1. Power of Adjutant General to acquire and maintain property. -360§§ 44-125 through 44-128. Repealed by Acts 1976, c. 266. -360§ 44-129. Joint use of public buildings for armories. -360§ 44-130. Public grounds for armory building purposes. -360§ 44-131. Military property exempt from taxation. -360§ 44-132. Power of condemnation. -360§ 44-133. Repealed by Acts 2015, c. 221, cl. 2. -360§ 44-134. Management and care of armories and training areas. -360§ 44-134.1. Repealed by Acts 1981, c. 219. -360§ 44-135. Repealed by Acts 1976, c. 266. -360§ 44-135.1. Armory control board for each armory; temporary renting. -360§ 44-136. Sale or lease of armories. -360§ 44-137. City and county aid. -360§ 44-138. Maintenance funds. -360§ 44-139. Reversions of donations. -360§ 44-140. Liberal construction.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-123"><akn:num>§ 44-123</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 2015, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>221, cl. 2. Annotations Editors note. Former § 44-123, Armories, Buildings and Grounds, derived from 1932, p. 758; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(109); R. P. 1948, § 44-123. § 44-123.1. Armory defined. Text As used in this chapter, unless otherwise provided, the meaning of armory shall include training or logistical support facilities, such as, but not limited to, maintenance facilities, training areas, facilities at the State Military Reservation, Virginia Beach, Vir ginia, and the Fort Pickett Maneuver Training Center. History History. 1976, c. 266; 2000, c. 296. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2000, c. 296, cl. 2 provides: That the Virginia Department of Military Affairs and the Virginia Department of State Police may promulgate such regulation s as are necessary to carry out this enactment. The 2000 amendments. The 2000 amendment by c. 296 deleted and following training areas, and added and the Fort Pickett Maneuver Training Center. § 44-123.2. Fort Pickett Reservation created; venue. Text A. All those l ands and improvements thereon constituting the special maritime and territorial jurisdiction of the United States formerly known as Fort Pickett, Virginia, shall specifically include but not be limited to those lands licensed by the Department of the Arm y to the Virginia Army National Guard on October 1, 1997, approximating 41,000 acres known as the Fort Pickett Maneuver Training Center, as well as those lands designated for transfer to the Nottoway County Local Reuse Authority by the United States Base Realignment and Closure Commission of 1996 approximating 4,100 acres, are hereby designated as the Fort Pickett Reservation. B. Venue for a ll civil, criminal and traffic matters occurring on the Fort Pickett Reservation shall lie in Nottoway County. History History. 2000, c. 296. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2000, c. 296, cl. 2 provides: That the Virginia Department of Military Affairs and the Virginia Department of State Police may promulgate such regulation s as are necessary to carry out this enactment. § 44-123.3. Fort Pickett Police; powers; duties; functions. Text There is hereby established within the Department of Military Affairs the Fort Pickett Police Department. The Fort Pickett Police may exercise within the limits of the Fort Pickett Reservation and, when assigned to any other property owned or controlled by the Commonwealth or any agency, department, institution or commission thereof, all the powers, duties and functions that are exercised by the police of the city, or the police or sheriff of the county within which said property is located. The jurisdiction of the Fort Pickett Police shall further extend 300 feet beyond the boundary of any property they are required to protect, such jurisdiction to be concurrent with that of other law-enforcement officers of the locality in which such property is located. The Fort Pickett Police shall refer any complaint which alleges a felony violation to the Virginia State Police or the sheriff of the appropriate jurisdiction who, in cooperation with the Fort Pickett Police, shall conduct an investigation if an investigation is warranted. All members of the Fort Pickett Police shall be subject to the provisions of § 2.2-1202.1 and Chapter 5 (§ 9.1-500 et seq.) of Title 9.1. The Fort Pickett Police Department shall be under the supervision of the Adjutant General, or his designee. The pay structure for the officers and supervisors of the Fort Pickett Police Department shall be the same as that set by the Compensation Board for sheriffs offices. History History. 2000, c. 296; 2012, cc. 803, 835. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2000, c. 296, cl. 2 provides: That the Virginia Department of Military Affairs and the Virginia Department of State Police may promulgate such regulation s as are necessary to carry out this enactment. The 2012 amendments. The 2012 amendments by cc. 803 and 835, cl. 8, are identical, and substituted § 2.2-1202.1 for Chapters 10 (§ 2.2-1000 et seq.) of Title 2.2 in the fifth sentence.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-124"><akn:num>§ 44-124</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1976, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>266. Annotations Cross references. As to the power of the Adjutant General to acquire and maintain property, see § 44-124.1. § 44-124.1. Power of Adjutant General to acquire and maintain property. Text The Adjutant General may acquire for and in the name of the Commonwealth, by gift, grant, appropriation, purchase such real or personal property as is necessary for the maintenance of, the training and administration of, the logistical support of, and the safeguarding of property in the care, custody or control of the Department of Military Affairs when such real or personal property is reasonably necessary to carry ou t and perform the duties required by this chapter and the duties of the office of the Adjutant General. The Adjutant General may make such acquisitions in cooperation with counties, cities, or incorporated towns, private corporations, voluntary incorpora ted or unincorporated associations or individuals, the United States or other states or commonwealths of the United States. The Adjutant General may provide for the day-to-day operation and maintenance of said facilities to include but not limited to hea t, water, light, telephone service, sewer and other costs of operation, including insurance, and may in a like manner make additions, alterations and improvements to said facilities. History History. 1976, c. 266.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-125"><akn:num>§ 44-125</akn:num><akn:heading>44-125 through 44-128</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Repealed by Acts 1976, c. 266. Annotations Cross references. As to the power of the Adjutant General to acquire and maintain property, see § 44-124.1.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-129"><akn:num>§ 44-129</akn:num><akn:heading>Joint use of public buildings for armories</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The governing body of any county, city or incorporated town, wherein a unit or units of the Virginia National Guard have been, or may hereafter be established, may eith er severally, or acting jointly with each other, or with the Adjutant General, construct or acquire by purchase, contract, lease, gift, donation or condemnation, grounds and/or buildings which shall be suitable for public assemblages, conventions, exhibi tions and entertainments; provided, that such buildings, or the plans and specifications therefor, are first approved by the Adjutant General as suitable for use as armories by such National Guard units; provided further, that such governing bodies or ei ther of them, shall have contracted with the Adjutant General for the use of such buildings as an armory by such National Guard unit or units upon terms not inconsistent with this chapter. History History. 1932, p. 759; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(112); R. P. 1948, § 44-129; 2015, c. 221. Annotations The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendment by c. 221 substituted Virginia National Guard for National Guard and naval militia of Virginia.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-130"><akn:num>§ 44-130</akn:num><akn:heading>Public grounds for armory building purposes</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Any municipality or county owning lands on which no permanent building has been actually constructed whether such lands constitute part of a park or site for some publi c structure, is authorized to convey the same to the Commonwealth for use as a site for an armory for the Virginia National Guard; provided, that such conveyance will not prevent the reasonable use of any such structure for the purpose for which it was c onstructed. History History. 1932, p. 760; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(113); R. P. 1948, § 44-130.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-131"><akn:num>§ 44-131</akn:num><akn:heading>Military property exempt from taxation</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text All property actually used for armory and military training purposes, as hereinabove defined, shall be exempt from all taxation, impost or assessment. History History. 1932, p. 760; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(114); R. P. 1948, § 44-131.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-132"><akn:num>§ 44-132</akn:num><akn:heading>Power of condemnation</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The power of condemnation herein granted to the Adjutant General and to counties, cities and incorporated towns, shall be exercised in the manner prescribed in the Code of Virginia. History History. 1932, p. 760; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(115); R. P. 1948, § 44-132.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-133"><akn:num>§ 44-133</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 2015, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>221, cl. 2. Annotations Editors note. Former § 44-133, Use of armories for meetings of veterans associations and other organizations, derived from 1932, p. 760; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(116) ; R. P. 1948, § 44-133.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-134"><akn:num>§ 44-134</akn:num><akn:heading>Management and care of armories and training areas</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Adjutant General shall be responsible for the general management and care of armories and drill and training areas, and shall have the power to adopt and prescribe such rules and regulations for the management and government and for the guidance of the organizations occupying them as may be necessary and desirable; but such rules are not to conflict with the provisions of this chapter. History History. 1932, p. 760; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(117); R. P. 1948, § 44-134. § 44-134.1. Repealed by Acts 1981, c. 219. Annotations Cross references. For provisions concerning the management, harvesting, and sale of timber on state-owned land, see § 10.1-1122.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-135"><akn:num>§ 44-135</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1976, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>266. Annotations Cross references. For present provisions covering the subject matter of the repealed section, see § 44-135.1. § 44-135.1. Armory control board for each armory; temporary renting. Text Each armory erected or provided by the Commonwealth under the provisions of this chapter, excepting those armories or logistical support facilities provided for by lice nse agreement with the United States, shall have an armory control board appointed by the Adjutant General to consist of one or more officers of the organization or organizations quartered therein, and any other persons deemed necessary by the Adjutant G eneral. Such board of control may rent the armory and any temporary quarters or billeting facilities thereon for temporary purposes, subject to any regulations or conditions that may be prescribed by the Adjutant General or such board of control. The mon ey derived from the rental shall be placed in a special revenue interest-earning fund, and properly accounted for. Any nonappropriated funds and interest earned from such funds shall be used to defray the cost of operating, improving, and maintaining suc h armory and its facilities. Any money remaining in the fund at the end of the fiscal year shall not revert to the general fund but shall remain in the fund. History History. 1976, c. 266; 1996, cc. 137, 802.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-136"><akn:num>§ 44-136</akn:num><akn:heading>Sale or lease of armories</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text When the Adjutant General shall receive information from the Governor of the disbandment of an organization of the National Guard occupying or using an armory provided by the Commonwealth under the direction of the Adjutant General, he shall determine whether such armory shall be sold or not, and if it is determined that such armory be sold after due publication as prescribed by the laws of the Commonwealth for the sal e of real estate under a deed of trust, it shall be sold at public auction for the highest price to be paid for same, and upon such terms and conditions as may seem best to the Adjutant General. The proceeds of such sale shall be divided between the Comm onwealth, county, city or individual, as their interest may appear. In case an armory becomes vacant by any reason mentioned in this section, the Adjutant General may lease such armory for a period not to exceed one year, or, when duly authorized by the Governor, may lease the same for a period of years, the proceeds due the Commonwealth therefrom in either case to be turned into the state treasury to be credited to the Armory Fund. Should there be other owner or owners than the Common wealth then the balance of the proceeds shall be equitably turned over to them as their interest may appear. During the time that the troops quartered in an armory are absent from their home station, in federal service, the armory may be leased as above provided, but not sold. History History. 1932, p. 761; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(118); R. P. 1948, § 44-136; 2015, c. 221. Annotations The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendment by c. 221 deleted or naval militia following National Guard in the first sentence.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-137"><akn:num>§ 44-137</akn:num><akn:heading>City and county aid</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Every city and county in the Commonwealth having an active National Guard or Virginia Defense Force organization or organizations is authorized to render such financial assistance as it may deem wise and patriotic to such organization or organizations, either by donating land or buildings, or donating the use of land or buildings, or by contributing to their equipment and maintenance. History History. 1932, p. 761; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(119); R. P. 1948, § 44-137; 1976, c. 266; 2014, cc. 30, 547; 2015, c. 221. Annotations The 2014 amendments. The 2014 amendments by cc. 30 and 547 are identical, and inserted the Virginia Defense Force. The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendment by c. 221 substituted National Guard or Virginia Defense Force for National Guard, Virginia Defense Force, or naval militia.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-138"><akn:num>§ 44-138</akn:num><akn:heading>Maintenance funds</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text In order that there shall be provided maintenance funds for armories and other buildings erected, and areas provided for drill and training and other military purposes under the provisions of this chapter, the Adjutant General is authorized to draw a voucher for such funds, to be paid from any appropriation provided. History History. 1932, p. 761; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(120); R. P. 1948, § 44-138.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-139"><akn:num>§ 44-139</akn:num><akn:heading>Reversions of donations</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text In the event that any real property is donated, deeded, or otherwise conveyed for a nominal sum to the Commonwealth, Department of Military Affairs, Virginia National G uard, Virginia Army or Air National Guard, Virginia Defense Force, or a subordinate element of any such entity under the provisions of this chapter for the purpose of supporting Virginia National Guard or Virginia Defense Force operations, and the organi zation shall fail to accept such property, or shall, after accepting it, upon determination by the Adjutant General, no longer require the property to support the organizations mission, the title to the property thus donated, deeded, or otherwise con veyed may, at the discretion of the Adjutant General, revert to the person, county, or municipality donating such property as their interest may appear. If the Adjutant General chooses not to allow the reversion or if the person, county, or municipality declines to reacquire such property, it shall be declared excess. History History. 1932, p. 761; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(121); R. P. 1948, § 44-139; 2015, c. 221; 2018, c. 647. Annotations The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendment by c. 221 deleted or naval militia following National Guard. The 2018 amendments. The 2018 amendment by c. 647 rewrote the section, which formerly read In the event that any real property is donated to a National Guard organization under th e provisions of this chapter, and the organization shall fail to accept such property, or shall, after accepting it, be disbanded, the title to the property thus donated shall revert to the person, county or municipality donating the same as their intere st may appear.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-140"><akn:num>§ 44-140</akn:num><akn:heading>Liberal construction</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text This chapter shall be liberally construed in favor of its purposes. History History. 1932, p. 762; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(123); R. P. 1948, § 44-140. Chapter 3. Civil Defense. -360§§ 44-141 through 44-146.1.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-141"><akn:num>§ 44-141</akn:num><akn:heading>44-141 through 44-146</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>1. Text Repealed by Acts 1973, c. 260. Chapter 3.1. Post-Attack Resource Management Act. -360§§ 44-146.2 through 44-146.12. §§ 44-146.2 through 44-146.12. Text Repealed by Acts 1975, c. 11. Chapter 3.2. Emergency Services and Disaster Law. -360§ 44-146.13. Short title. -360§ 44-146.14. Findings of General Assembly. -360§ 44-146.15. Construction of chapter. -360§ 44-146.16. Definitions. -360§ 44-146.17. (Effective until July 1, 2023) Powers and duties of Governor. -360§ 44-146.17. (Effective July 1, 2023) Powers and duties of Governor. -360§ 44-146.17:1. Transmittal to General Assembly of rules, regulations, and orders. -360§ 44-146.17:1.1. Certain emergency orders; additional requirements. -360§ 44-146.17:2. Annual statewide drill. -360§ 44-146.18. Department of Emergency Management; administration and operational control; coordinator and other personnel; powers an d duties. -360§ 44-146.18:1. Virginia Disaster Response Funds disbursements; reimbursements. -360§ 44-146.18:2. Authority of Coordinator of Emergency Management in undeclared emergency. -360§ 44-146.18:3. First informer broadcasters; coordination with Department of Emergency Management. -360§ 44-146.18:4. State Coordinator of Emergency Management responsible for annual Virginia Comprehensive Emergency Management Report. -360§ 44-146.18:5. Division of Public Safety Communications established; appointment of Virginia Public Safety Communications Coordinat or; duties of Division. -360§ 44-146.18:6. Geographic Information Network Division established; powers and duties; Division Coordinator. -360§ 44-146.18:7. GIS Fund created. -360§ 44-146.18:8. Additional powers and duties of the State Coordinator of Emergency Management. -360§ 44-146.18:9. Nonstock corporation to assist in the development of GIS data. -360§ 44-146.19. Powers and duties of political subdivisions. -360§ 44-146.20. Joint action by political subdivisions. -360§ 44-146.21. Declaration of local emergency. -360§ 44-146.22. Development of measures to prevent or reduce harmful consequences of disasters; disclosure of information. -360§ 44-146.23. Immunity from liability. -360§ 44-146.24. Cooperation of public agencies. -360§ 44-146.25. Repealed by Acts 2015, c. 221, cl. 2. -360§ 44-146.26. Duties of emergency management organizations. -360§ 44-146.27. Supplementing federal funds; assistance of federal agencies; acceptance of gifts and services; appropriations by local governing bodies. -360§ 44-146.28. Authority of Governor and agencies under his control in declared state of emergency. -360§ 44-146.28:1. Compact enacted into law; terms. -360§ 44-146.28:2. Disaster relief assistance by out-of-state businesses and employees. -360§ 44-146.29. Expired. -360§§ 44-146.29:1, 44-146.29:2 -360§ 44-146.29:3. Emergency Shelters Upgrade Assistance Grant Fund. § 44-146.13. Short title. Text This chapter may be cited as the Commonwealth of Virginia Emergency Services and Disaster Law of 2000. History History. 1973, c. 260; 2000, c. 309. Annotations Cross references. As to postponement of certain elections during state of emergency, see § 24.2-603.1. As to emergency situations at polling locations, see § 24.2-604.2. As to emergency authority of the Secretary of the State Board of Elections, see § 24.2-713. As to extension to file reports required under the Campaign Finance Disclosure Act, § 24.2-945 et seq., in emergency situations, see § 24.2-946.4. As to authority of State Health Commissioner to issue order of quarantine or order of isolation, see §§ 32.1-48.09, 32.1-48.012, respectively. As to waiver of requirements by Board of Pharmacy during disaster or state of emergency, see § 54.1-3307.3. The 2000 amendments. The 2000 amendment by c. 309 substituted 2000 for 1973. Law Review. For survey of Virginia administrative law for the year 1974-1975, see 61 Va. L. Rev. 1632 (1975). Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 12B M.J. Military, § 2. CASE NOTES Effect of amendments to chapter.  The amendments to this chapter were changes of form, which merely interpreted the 1973 act and made it more detailed and specific. They were not changes of substa nce, which add rights to, or withdraw existing rights from, an original act. Boyd v. Commonwealth, 216 Va. 16, 215 S.E.2d 915, 1975 Va. LEXIS 242 (1975). Acute motor vehicle fuel shortage of 1973 was a disaster within the meaning of t his chapter. Boyd v. Commonwealth, 216 Va. 16, 215 S.E.2d 915, 1975 Va. LEXIS 242 (1975). OPINIONS OF THE ATTORNEY GENERAL Electronic meetings during declared emergency.  Section 44-146.21 does not authorize local governing bodies to hold meetings solely by electronic communication during the pendency of the emergency, but § 15. 2-1413 provides additional authority for localities to ensure continuity of government during the declared emergency. See opinion of Attorney General to The Honorable Richard C. (Rip) Sullivan, Jr., Member, Virginia House of Delegates, 20-011, (3/20/20) . § 44-146.14. Findings of General Assembly. Text (a) Because of the ever present possibility of the occurrence of disasters of unprecedented size and destructiveness resulting from enemy attack, sabotage or other hostile action, resource shortage, or from fire, flood, earthquake, or other natural causes, and in orde r to insure that preparations of the Commonwealth and its political subdivisions will be adequate to deal with such emergencies, and generally to provide for the common defense and to protect the public peace, health, and safety, and to preserve the live s and property and economic well-being of the people of the Commonwealth, it is hereby found and declared to be necessary and to be the purpose of this chapter: (1) To c reate a State Department of Emergency Management, and to authorize the creation of local organizations for emergency management in the political subdivisions of the Commonwealth; (2) To confer upon the Governor and upon the executive heads or governing bodies of the political subdivisions of the Commonwealth emergency powers provided herein; and (3) To provide for rendering of mutual aid among the political subdivisions of the Commonwealth and with other states and to cooperate with the federal government with respect to the ca rrying out of emergency service functions. (b) It is furt her declared to be the purpose of this chapter and the policy of the Commonwealth that all emergency service functions of the Commonwealth be coordinated to the maximum extent possible with the comparable functions of the federal government, other states , and private agencies of every type, and that the Governor shall be empowered to provide for enforcement by the Commonwealth of national emergency services programs, to the end that the most effective preparation and use may be made of the nations r esources and facilities for dealing with any disaster that may occur. History History. 1973, c. 260; 1974, c. 4; 1975, c. 11; 2000, c. 309. Annotations The 2000 amendments. The 2000 amendment by c. 309, in subdivision (a)(1), substituted Emergency Management for Emergency Services twice; and added and at the e nd of subdivision (a)(2). CASE NOTES Importance of adequate supply of motor vehicle fuel.  The health, safety and welfare of the people of Virginia depend upon an adequate supply of motor vehicle fuel. Boyd v. Commonwealth, 216 Va. 16, 215 S.E.2d 915, 1 975 Va. LEXIS 242 (1975). CIRCUIT COURT OPINIONS Executive order requiring face masks.  Winery was not entitled to a temporary injunction from enforcement of an executive order requiring face coverings to be worn by individuals in certain settings, b ecause the Governor of Virginia and the Virginia State Health Commissioner validly enacted the order to limit the spread of COVID-19 and expressly waived the application of the criminal prohibition on the wearing of a mask to conceal ones identity. T he winery could not demonstrate a likely success as to the merits, irreparable harm, the balance of equities, and the public interest. Strother v. Northam, 105 Va. Cir. 233, 2020 Va. Cir. LEXIS 106 (Fauquier County June 29, 2020). Plaintiffs motion for declaratory judgment and injunctive relief to declare Executive Order No. 63 (EO 63), requiring face coverings in response to COVID-19, null and void was denied as EO 63 was appropriately issued because it addressed exceptional circumstances that existed concerning a communicable disease of public health threat that was issued by the State Health Commissioner; the law provided broad disc retion and relied on the Governors judgment to determine how to resolve the emergency; the Governors Executive Orders were consistent with the state constitution; and plaintiff failed to establish that he was likely to suffer irreparable harm in the absence of preliminary relief. Schilling v. Northam, 105 Va. Cir. 343, 2020 Va. Cir. LEXIS 120 (Albemarle County July 20, 2020). OPINIONS OF THE ATTORNEY GENERAL Emergency powers of Governor.  Virginia Governor may not unilaterally alter taxes without the approval of the General Assembly. See opinion of Attorney General to the Honorable Janet D. Howell, Member, Senate of Virginia, 21-087, 2021 Va. AG LEXIS 33 (11/18/21). § 44-146.15. Construction of chapter. Text Nothing in this chapter is to be construed to: (1) Limi t, modify, or abridge the authority of the Governor to exercise any powers vested in him under other laws of this Commonwealth independent of, or in conjunction with, any provisions of this chapter; (2) Interfere with dissemination of news or comment on public affairs; but any communications facility or organization, including, but not limited to, radio and television stations, wir e services, and newspapers, may be required to transmit or print public service messages furnishing information or instructions in connection with actual or pending disaster; (3) Empower the Governor, any political subdivision, or any other governmental authority to in any way limit or prohibit the right...</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-147"><akn:num>§ 44-147</akn:num><akn:heading>44-147 through 44-151</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Repealed by Acts 2015, c. 221, cl. 2. Annotations Editors note. Former §§ 44-147 through 44-151, Air Raid Precautions, derived from 1942, pp. 368, 369; Michie Code 1942, §§ 2673(132)(136); 1952, c. 359; 1977, c . 326. Chapter 5. Mobilization of Fire Fighters. -360§ 44-152. Outside service by fire departments. -360§ 44-153. Powers, duties, rights, privileges and immunities. -360§ 44-154. Loss, damages, expense or cost. -360§ 44-155. Liability for acts or omissions. -360§ 44-156. Reimbursement for salaries and expenses. -360§ 44-157. Temporary substitute fire-fighting forces. -360§ 44-158. Rules and regulations. -360§ 44-159. When chapter in effect.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-152"><akn:num>§ 44-152</akn:num><akn:heading>Outside service by fire departments</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Whenever a state of war exists between the United States and any foreign country and at the request of the chief executive of any county, city or town in this Commonwea lth the head of any other fire department may, or if so ordered by the Governor shall, detail, assign and make available for duty and use in such county, town or city any part of the officers, fire fighters, forces, fire-fighting apparatus or other equip ment under his command or control. History History. 1942, p. 369; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(137); 1977, c. 326.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-153"><akn:num>§ 44-153</akn:num><akn:heading>Powers, duties, rights, privileges and immunities</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Whenever all or any part of the regular fire-fighting forces of any county, town or city in this Commonwealth are engaged in rendering services pursuant to this chapter , the officers and members of such fire-fighting forces shall have the same powers, duties, rights, privileges and immunities as if they were performing their duties in the political subdivision in which they are normally employed. History History. 1942, p. 369; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(138).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-154"><akn:num>§ 44-154</akn:num><akn:heading>Loss, damages, expense or cost</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The county, town or city in which any equipment is used pursuant to this chapter shall be liable for any loss or damage thereto and to the supplies therefor and shall p ay any expenses incurred in the operation and maintenance thereof, including the cost of all materials and supplies therefor. No claim for any such loss, damage, expense or cost shall be allowed unless, within sixty days after the same has been sustained or incurred, a written notice of such claim, under oath and itemizing the same, is served by mail or otherwise upon the treasurer of such county, town or city where such equipment was so used. History History. 1942, p. 369; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(139).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-155"><akn:num>§ 44-155</akn:num><akn:heading>Liability for acts or omissions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Neither the Commonwealth nor the political subdivision of the Commonwealth whose fire-fighting forces are engaged pursuant to this chapter shall be liable or accountabl e in any way for or on account of any act or omission on the part of an officer or member of such forces while engaged pursuant to this chapter or for or on account of the operation, maintenance or use of any apparatus, equipment or supplies in connectio n therewith, nor shall any fire commissioner, fire chief or other superior officer or head of a fire department, fire company or other fire-fighting forces, acting pursuant to this chapter, be held liable or accountable in any way for or on account of an y act or omission on the part of any of his subordinates without the political subdivision of their appointment while such subordinates are under the command of an officer other than himself. History History. 1942, p. 369; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(140).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-156"><akn:num>§ 44-156</akn:num><akn:heading>Reimbursement for salaries and expenses</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The political subdivision in which aid or assistance is given pursuant to this chapter shall reimburse the political subdivision furnishing such aid and assistance for any moneys paid for the salaries or other compensation of employees furnished under this chapter during the time they shall not be performing their duties in the political subdivision by which they are employed or act and shall defray the actual travelin g and maintenance expenses of such employees while they are rendering such aid and assistance. The provisions of this section and the term employee as used herein shall mean and apply with equal effect to paid and volunteer fire fighters. History History. 1942, p. 370; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(141); 1977, c. 326.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-157"><akn:num>§ 44-157</akn:num><akn:heading>Temporary substitute fire-fighting forces</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Whenever all or any part of the regular fire-fighting forces of any county, city or town in the Commonwealth are engaged in rendering aid and assistance, pursuant to th is chapter, substitute fire fighters, not exceeding the number of regular fire fighters engaged in rendering such aid and assistance, may be appointed in the same manner as provided by law for the appointment of such regular fire fighters. Except in the case of a volunteer fire company, the compensation of such substitute fire fighters shall be fixed at a sum not greater than the lowest rate of pay for a regular fire fighter in such fire department, company or fire-fighting force. Each person appointed under this section shall be vested with the same powers and charged with the same duties as if he were a regular member of such fire department, company or fire-fighting force. No appointment under this section shall continue for more than two days after the regular fire fighters for whom they are substituting have returned to duty. The compensation of any substitute fire fighter appointed pursuant to this section and any allowable expense actually and necessarily incurred by him in the performance of h is duties shall be charged against the county, city or town in and for which he was appointed and shall be audited and allowed in the same manner as other charges against the county, city or town are audited and allowed. History History. 1942, p. 370; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(142); 1977, c. 326.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-158"><akn:num>§ 44-158</akn:num><akn:heading>Rules and regulations</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Governor is hereby authorized and empowered to prescribe all necessary and reasonable rules and regulations in order to carry out the provisions of this chapter. History History. 1942, p. 370; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(143).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-159"><akn:num>§ 44-159</akn:num><akn:heading>When chapter in effect</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text This chapter shall be in effect only during the time a state of war exists between the United States and any foreign country. History History. 1942, p. 370; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(144). Chapter 6. Emergency Fair Rent Act. -360§§ 44-160 through 44-203.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-160"><akn:num>§ 44-160</akn:num><akn:heading>44-160 through 44-203</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Repealed by Acts 1950, p. 188. Chapter 7. Miscellaneous Laws. -360§ 44-204. Leaves of absence for employees of Commonwealth or political subdivisions. -360§§ 44-205 through 44-207. Repealed by Acts 2015, c. 221, cl. 2. -360§ 44-208. Securing site of structural failure, fire, explosion, or industrial or transportation accident. -360§ 44-209. Closure of United States government; civil relief for furloughed employees and contractors.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-204"><akn:num>§ 44-204</akn:num><akn:heading>Leaves of absence for employees of Commonwealth or political subdivisions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text All officers and employees of the Commonwealth, or of any political subdivision of the Commonwealth who are members of the Virginia Defense Force or National Defense Ex ecutive Reserve shall be entitled to leaves of absence from their respective duties without loss of pay, seniority, accrued leave or efficiency rating on all days during which they shall be engaged in training approved by the Governor or his designee, no t to exceed 21 workdays per federal fiscal year. When relieved from such duty, they shall be restored to positions held by them when ordered to duty. History History. 1938, p. 573; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(124); 1964, c. 227; 198 6, c. 611; 2022, c. 430. Annotations The 2022 amendments. The 2022 amendment by c. 430 substituted Virginia Defense Force for Virginia State Defense Force and 21 for fifteen.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-205"><akn:num>§ 44-205</akn:num><akn:heading>44-205 through 44-207</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Repealed by Acts 2015, c. 221, cl. 2. Annotations Editors note. Former §§ 44-205 through 44-207, Traffic regulations; Issuing agents for sale of obligations of United States; Laws continued in effect, derived from 1942, pp. 367, 394; Michie Code 1942, § 2673(180), 2673(181).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-208"><akn:num>§ 44-208</akn:num><akn:heading>Securing site of structural failure, fire, explosion, or industrial or transportation accident</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The official in charge of the investigation of any structural failure, fire, explosion, or industrial or transportation accident which results in the loss of human life , except when caused by a natural disaster or war, may secure for no more than twelve hours so much of the site where it occurred as, in his opinion, may be necessary to gather evidence regarding the cause of the occurrence. No owner or lessee of the sit e may be denied entrance except to prevent the destruction of evidence. In cases of fire from any cause, the chief or other authorized officer of any fire department or fire company in command at the fire shall have the rights and authority granted to him and his subordinates upon his order or direction by § 27-17.1. Nothing in this section shall limit or otherwise affect the authority of, or be construed to deny access to such site by, any person charged by law with the responsibility of investigating any such accident. History History. 1982, c. 213.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_44-209"><akn:num>§ 44-209</akn:num><akn:heading>Closure of United States government; civil relief for furloughed employees and contractors</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. As used in this section:Closure of the United States government means a closure of the United States federal government for a period of 14 consecutive days or longer as a result of a lapse of appropriation that leads to (i) the curtailment of federal agency activities and services, (ii) a shutdown of nonessential operations, (iii) nonessential workers being fu rloughed, and (iv) only essential employees in departments covering the safety of human life or protection of property being retained.Written proof means (i) a paystub issued by a federal government agency showing zero dollars in earnings for a pay period within the period of any closure of the United States government, (ii) a copy of a furlough no tification letter or essential employee status letter indicating the employees status as nonessential, or (iii) a letter from a company under contract with the United States government issued and signed by an officer or owner of the company or by the companys human resources director stating that the employees not receiving payment from the contractor is directly attributable to a closure of the United States government. B. Notwithstan ding any provision of law to the contrary, any tenant as defined in § 55.1-1200 who is a defendant in an unlawful detainer for nonpayment of rent pursuant to § 55.1-1245 for rent due after the commencement of a closure of the United States governme nt seeking a judgment for the payment of money or possession of the premises shall be granted a 60-day continuance of such unlawful detainer action from the initial court date if the tenant appears on such court date and provides written proof that he wa s furloughed or otherwise was or is not currently receiving wages or payments as a result of a closure of the United States government, and is (i) an employee of the United States government, (ii) an independent contractor for the United States governmen t, or (iii) an employee of a company under contract with the United States government. The provisions of this subsection shall not apply if the landlord has filed a material noncompliance notice for a non-rent violation of the rental agreement or of the Code of Virginia. C. Notwithstan ding any provision of law to the contrary, any homeowner who, after the commencement of a closure of the United States government, defaults on a note that is secured by a one-family to four-family residential property located in the Commonwealth and is s ubject to a foreclosure proceeding on any mortgage or to the execution of or sale under any deed of trust shall be granted a 30-day stay of such proceeding if the homeowner, within 90 days of such closure or 90 days following the end of a closure of the United States government, whichever is later, requests a stay and provides written proof to his lender that he was furloughed or otherwise was or is not currently receiving wages or payments as a result of a closure of the United States government, and i s (i) an employee of the United States government, (ii) an independent contractor for the United States government, or (iii) an employee of a company under contract with the United States government. D. Notwithstan ding any provision of law to the contrary, any owner who rents a one-family to four-family residential dwelling unit located in the Commonwealth to a tenant as defined in § 55.1-1200 and who, after the commencement of a closure of the United States go vernment, defaults on a note that is secured by such dwelling unit and is subject to a foreclosure proceeding on any mortgage or to the execution of or sale under any deed of trust shall be granted a 30-day stay of such proceeding if the owner, within 90 days of such closure or 90 days following the end of a closure of the United States government, whichever is later, requests a stay and provides written proof to his lender that his tenant was furloughed or otherwise was or is not currently receiving wa ges or payments as a result of a closure of the United States government, and is (i) an employee of the United States government, (ii) an independent contractor for the United States government, or (iii) an employee of a company under contract with the U nited States government. E. The provisi ons of this section shall not (i) apply in an instance where a separate, signed legal agreement exists between a landlord and tenant or homeowner and mortgage holder to stay legal action or defer the filing of an unlawful detainer motion for nonpayment o f rent or foreclosure proceeding on any mortgage or to the execution of or sale under any deed of trust for a term of 30 days or greater or (ii) affect any other terms of a valid rental agreement or note secured by a one-family to four-family residential property, mortgage, or deed of trust unrelated to nonpayment of rent or default of a mortgage caused by a closure of the United States government. History History. 2020, c. 1202. Annotations Cross references. As to civil relief for furloughed employees and contractors in the event of closure of United States government, see § 44-209. Editors note. Acts 2020, c. 1202, cl. 2 provides: § 1. That the provisions of subsections B, C, and D of § 44-209, as created by this act, with respect to a continuan ce or stay of (i) an unlawful detainer action or (ii) a foreclosure proceeding on a mortgage or an execution of or sale under any deed of trust shall also be applicable to any tenant, homeowner, or owner, respectively, affected by the novel coronavirus ( COVID-19) pandemic public health crisis during the period for which the Governor has declared a state of emergency (the Emergency). The provisions of subsection D of § 44-209, as created by this act, shall be expanded during the Emergency to include a ny owner who (a) rents a residential dwelling unit, regardless of its size or capacity, located in the Commonwealth, and (b) is affected by the Emergency. § 2. Homeowners and owners shall be excluded from the provisions of this enactment if they are subject to protection from foreclosure under the provisions of a federal, state, or local law, regulation, or action enacted in response to the COVID-19 pandemic or the Emergency. § 3. Any continuance or stay period provided by this enactment shall be tolled during the period of any judicial emergency declared pursuant to § 17.1-3 30 of the Code of Virginia due to the Emergency. § 4. The 60-day continuance provided by this enactment shall run concurrently with any period of eviction protection provided by any other state or federal law. § 5. For purposes of this enactment:  Affected by means to experience a loss of income from a public or private source due to the Emergency, such that the affected party must request a st ay or continuance, as applicable, by providing written proof to a court or lender, as applicable, stating that he is not currently receiving wages or payments from a public or private source as a result of the Emergency.  Written proof means (i) a paystub showing zero dollars in earnings for a pay period within the period for which the Governor has declared a state of emergency (the Emergency) in response to the novel coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic public health crisis, (ii) a copy of a furlough notification letter or essential employee status letter indicating the employees status as nonessential due to the Emer gency, or (iii) any other documentation deemed appropriate by a court or lender. Acts 2020, c. 1202, cl. 4 provides: That the provisions of the second enactment of this act shall expire 90 days following the end of a state of emergency dec lared by the Governor in response to the novel coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic public health crisis. Effective date. Acts 2020, c. 1202 became effective April 22, 2020, by emergency clause. OPINIONS OF THE ATTORNEY GENERAL Construction.  In construing the temporary moratorium on eviction filings under the federal Coronavirus Aid, Relief, and Economic Security (CARES) Act and the protections for fu rloughed employees under § 44-209; it was decided that tenants may receive both the CARES Act protections and the protections of the 60-day continuance. See opinion of Attorney General to Hon. Marcia S. Cia Price, Hon. Lashrecse Aird, Hon. Jei on A. Ward, Hon. Patrick A. Hope, Hon. Marcus B. Simon, Hon. Paul E. Krizek, Hon. Kelly K. Convirs-Fowler, Hon. Jeffrey M. Bourne, Hon. Kathy K.L. Tran, Hon. Alex Q. Askew, Hon. Chris L. Hurst, and Hon. Lee J. Carter, Members, House of Delegates, 20-033, (7/15/20).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section></akn:body></akn:act></akn:akomaNtoso>