<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akn:akomaNtoso xmlns:akn="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><akn:act><akn:meta><akn:identification source="#cosilico"><akn:FRBRWork><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-66" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-66" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2023-03-01" name="release" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#virginia-general-assembly" /><akn:FRBRcountry value="us-va" /><akn:FRBRnumber value="title-66" /><akn:FRBRname value="act" /></akn:FRBRWork><akn:FRBRExpression><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-66/eng@2023-03-01" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-66/eng@2023-03-01" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2023-03-01" name="publication" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#lexisnexis" /><akn:FRBRlanguage language="eng" /></akn:FRBRExpression><akn:FRBRManifestation><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-66/eng@2023-03-01/main.xml" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-66/eng@2023-03-01/main.xml" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="conversion" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#cosilico" /></akn:FRBRManifestation></akn:identification><akn:references source="#cosilico"><akn:TLCOrganization eId="virginia-general-assembly" href="/ontology/organization/us-va/general-assembly" showAs="Virginia General Assembly" /><akn:TLCOrganization eId="lexisnexis" href="/ontology/organization/lexisnexis" showAs="LexisNexis" /><akn:TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="/ontology/organization/cosilico" showAs="Cosilico" /></akn:references></akn:meta><akn:preface><akn:docTitle>Title 66. </akn:docTitle></akn:preface><akn:body><akn:section eId="sec_66-1"><akn:num>§ 66-1</akn:num><akn:heading>Creation of Department of Juvenile Justice</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text There is hereby created within the executive branch, responsible to the Governor, a Department of Juvenile Justice. The Department shall be under the immediate supervis ion of a Director who shall be appointed by the Governor, subject to confirmation by the General Assembly. The Director shall serve at the pleasure of the Governor or until his successor shall be appointed and qualified. Vacancies shall be filled in the same manner as original appointments. History History. 1989, c. 733; 1990, c. 350; 1996, c. 503. Annotations Law Review. For survey on legal issues involving children in Virginia for 1989, see 23 U. Rich. L. Rev. 705 (1989). For a book review, Random Violence and the Transformation of the Juvenile Justice Debate, see 86 Va. L. Rev. 1095 (2000).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_66-2"><akn:num>§ 66-2</akn:num><akn:heading>Supervision of the Department</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Director of the Department of Juvenile Justice shall, under the direction of the Governor, be responsible for the supervision of the Department and shall exercise s uch other powers and perform such other duties as may be conferred or imposed by law upon him. He shall perform such other duties as may be required of him by the Governor and the Secretary of Public Safety and Homeland Security. History History. 1989, c. 733; 1990, cc. 1, 317; 2014, cc. 115, 490. Annotations The 2014 amendments. The 2014 amendments by c. 115, effective March 3, 2014, and c. 490, effective April 2, 2014, are identical and inserted and Homeland Security at the end o f the section.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_66-3"><akn:num>§ 66-3</akn:num><akn:heading>Powers of the Director</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. The Directo r of the Department shall have the following general powers: 1. To em ploy such personnel as may be required to carry out the purposes of this title. 2. To make and enter into all contracts and agreements necessary or incidental to the performance of his duties and the execution of his powers under this title, including, but not limite d to, contracts and agreements with the United States, other states, and agencies and governmental subdivisions of the Commonwealth. 3. With the prior approval of the Governor, to enter into agreements with a public or private entity to operate a work program for children committed to the Department. 4. With the prior approval of the Governor, to acquire real property, by purchase or gift, needed for new or existing state juvenile correctional facilities and for administrative and oth er facilities necessary to the operations of the Department, pursuant to regulations promulgated by the Board to ensure adequate public notice and local hearing. 5. To establish and maintain schools of the appropriate grades, levels, and types in the institutions for persons committed to juvenile correctional centers. 6. To enter into such agreements with private entities, nonprofit civic organizations, school divisions, and public and private two-year and four-year institutions of higher education as it may deem necessary to provide age-appropriate educational programs and training, including career and technical education; career development opportunities; public service projects; restricted Internet access to online courses of institutions of highe r education and approved or accredited online secondary education or adult education and literacy programs leading to a diploma or achieving a passing score on a high school equivalency examination approved by the Board of Education; access to postsecond ary education that includes college credit, certification through an accredited vocational training program, or other accredited continuing education program using videoconferencing technology; and other learning experiences in the furtherance of its dut ies and responsibilities under this chapter for persons committed to the institutions comprising the Department. 7. To designate employees of the Department with internal investigations authority to have the same power as a sheriff or a law-enforcement officer in the investigation of allegations of criminal behavior affecting the operations of the Department. Such employees shall be subject to any minimum training standards established by the Department of Criminal Justice Services under § 9.1-102 for law-enforcement officers prior to exercising any law-enforcement power granted under this subdivision. Nothing in this section shall be construed to grant the Department any authority over the operation and security of detention homes not specified in any other provision of law. The Department sha ll investigate allegations of criminal behavior in accordance with a written agreement entered into with the Department of State Police. The Department shall not investigate any action falling within the authority vested in the Office of the State Inspec tor General pursuant to Chapter 3.2 (§ 2.2-307 et seq.) of Title 2.2 unless specifically authorized by the Office of the State Inspector General. 8. To do all acts necessary or convenient to carry out the purposes of this title. B. The Directo r shall comply with and require all school facilities within the Department to comply with applicable regulations and statutes, both state and federal. History History. 1989, c. 733; 1993, cc. 460, 487; 1995, c. 701; 2012, cc. 803, 83 5; 2013, cc. 143, 214; 2014, c. 84. Annotations The 2012 amendments. The 2012 amendments by cc. 803 and 835, cl. 99, are identical, and inserted the A designation at the beginning of the introductory language; inserted subdivisions A 5 and A 6; redesingated former subdivision A 5 as subdivision A 7; and added subsection B. The 2013 amendments. The 2013 amendments by cc. 143 and 214 are identical, and added subdivision A 7 and redesignated former subdivision A 7 as subdivision A 8. The 2014 amendments. The 2014 amendment by c. 84, in subdivision A 6, substituted achieving a passing score on a high school equivalency examination approved by the Board of Educa tion for the General Education Development (GED) program and testing. § 66-3.1. Repealed by Acts 2011, cc. 798 and 871, cl. 2, effective July 1, 2012. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2011, cc. 798 and 871, cl. 3 provides: That, effective July 1, 2012, the Office of the State Inspector General created by this act shall be deemed the su ccessor in interest to the (i) Office of the Inspector General for Behavioral Health and Developmental Services, (ii) Inspector General for the Department of Corrections, (iii) Inspector General of the Department of Juvenile Justice, (iv) Inspector Gener al of the Department of Transportation, and (v) Department of the State Internal Auditor, to the extent that this act transfers powers and duties. All rights, title, and interest in and to any real or tangible personal property vested in the Inspector Ge neral for Behavioral Health and Developmental Services, the Inspector General for the Department of Corrections, the Inspector General of the Department of Juvenile Justice, the Inspector General of the Department of Transportation, and the Department of the State Internal Auditor to the extent that this act transfers powers and duties as of July 1, 2012, shall be transferred to and taken as standing in the name of the Office of the State Inspector General created by this act. Former § 66-3.1, pertaining to police powers of internal investigators and training, derived from Acts 1997, c. 38. § 66-3.2. Additional duties of the Director. Text A. The Directo r shall coordinate with the Department of Corrections the development and submission of requests for compensation from the United States Department of Justice State Criminal Alien Assistance Program for costs associated with incarcerating undocumented al iens. B. The Directo r shall forward to the Commonwealths Attorneys Services Council, updated on a monthly basis, a list of all juveniles, 14 years of age or older, that (i) have been committed to the Department, (ii) have been found guilty of a felony offense define d as a predicate criminal act under § 18.2-46.1, or have been adjudicated delinquent on the basis of an act that would be a felony and a predicate criminal act under § 18.2-46.1 if committed by an adult, and (iii) have been identified as belonging to a criminal gang. The list shall contain identifying information for each gang member, as well as the offense, court, and date of conviction or adjudication. History History. 2004, c. 126; 2006, cc. 431, 500. Annotations Cross references. As to confidentiality of Department of Juvenile Justice records, see § 16.1-300. Editors note. Acts 2006, cc. 431 and 500, in cl. 2 provide: That the information forwarded by the Department of Corrections and the Department of Juvenile Justice to the Co mmonwealths Attorneys Services Council shall be in a form mutually agreeable to all parties. The 2006 amendments. The 2006 amendments by cc. 431 and 500 are identical, and inserted the A designation at the beginning of the first paragraph and added subsection B.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_66-4"><akn:num>§ 66-4</akn:num><akn:heading>State Board of Juvenile Justice</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text There shall be a State Board of Juvenile Justice, consisting of nine members appointed by the Governor, two of whom shall be experienced educators. In making appointmen ts, the Governor shall endeavor to select appointees of such qualifications and experience that the membership of the Board shall include persons suitably qualified to consider and act upon the various problems that may come before the Board. The appoint ments shall be subject to confirmation by the General Assembly if in session and, if not, then at its next succeeding session. History History. 1989, c. 733; 1996, c. 503; 2013, cc. 37, 232. Annotations The 2013 amendments. The 2013 amendments by cc. 37 and 232 are identical, and substitued nine for seven and inserted two of whom shall be experienced educators in the first sentence; and substituted that may for which may in the second sentence.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_66-5"><akn:num>§ 66-5</akn:num><akn:heading>Term of office of members; suspension or removal</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The members of the Board shall be appointed initially as follows: three members for a term of two years each and four members for a term of four years each. Thereafter , the appointment of such members or their successors shall be for terms of four years, except that an appointment to fill a vacancy shall be for the unexpired term. No person shall be eligible to serve for or during more than two successive four-year t erms. However, any person appointed to fill a vacancy may be eligible for two additional successive terms after the term of the vacancy for which he was appointed has expired. Members of the Board may be suspended or removed by the Governor at his plea sure. History History. 1989, c. 733.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_66-6"><akn:num>§ 66-6</akn:num><akn:heading>Chairman, vice-chairman and secretary</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Board shall select a chairman from its membership, and under rules adopted by itself may elect one of its members as vice-chairman. It shall elect one of its membe rs as secretary. History History. 1989, c. 733.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_66-7"><akn:num>§ 66-7</akn:num><akn:heading>Compensation and expenses</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The members of the Board shall receive no salaries. They shall be paid their necessary traveling and other expenses incurred in attendance at meetings, or while otherw ise engaged in the discharge of their duties, and the sum of fifty dollars a day for each day or portion thereof in which they are engaged in the performance of their duties. History History. 1989, c. 733.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_66-8"><akn:num>§ 66-8</akn:num><akn:heading>Meetings</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Board shall meet at such times as it deems appropriate and on call of the chairman when in his opinion meetings are expedient or necessary. However, the Board shal l meet at least four times each calendar year. History History. 1989, c. 733.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_66-9"><akn:num>§ 66-9</akn:num><akn:heading>Quorum</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A majority of the current membership of the Board shall constitute a quorum for all purposes. History History. 1989, c. 733.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_66-10"><akn:num>§ 66-10</akn:num><akn:heading>Powers and duties of Board</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Board shall have the following powers and duties: 1. To es tablish and monitor policies for the programs and facilities for which the Department is responsible under this law. 2. To ensure the development of a long-range youth services policy. 3. To monitor the activities of the Department and its effectiveness in implementing the policies developed by the Board. 4. To advise the Governor and Director on matters relating to youth services. 5. To promulgate such regulations as may be necessary to carry out the provisions of this title and other laws of the Commonwealth. 6. To ensure the development of programs to educate citizens and elicit public support for the activities of the Department. 7. To establish length-of-stay guidelines for juveniles indeterminately committed to the Department and to make such guidelines available for public comment. 8. To adopt all necessary regulations for the management and operation of the schools in the Department except that the regulations adopted hereunder shall not conflict with regulations r elating to security of the institutions in which the juveniles are committed. 9. To establish compulsory minimum entry-level, in-service, and advanced training standards, as well as the time required for completion of such training, for persons employed as juvenile correctional officers employed at a juvenile correctional facility as defined in § 66-25.3. For such juvenile correctional officers who may have contact with pregnant inmates, such standards shall include training on the general care of pregnant wome n, the impact of restraints on pregnant inmates and fetuses, the impact of being placed in restrictive housing or solitary confinement on pregnant inmates, and the impact of body cavity searches on pregnant inmates. History History. 1989, c. 733; 1990, c. 679; 1996, cc. 755, 914; 2012, cc. 164, 45 6, 803, 835; 2019, c. 366; 2020, c. 526. Annotations Editors note. Acts 1996, cc. 755 and 914, cls. 7 provide: [t]hat the provisions of this act shall apply to offenses committed and to records created and proceedings held wi th respect to those offenses on or after July 1, 1996. The 2012 amendments. The 2012 amendments by cc. 164 and 456 are identical, and rewrote the section. The 2012 amendments by cc. 803 and 835, cl. 99, are identical, and added subdivision 9, which was subsequently redesignated as subdivision 8 at the direction of t he Virginia Code Commission. The 2019 amendments. The 2019 amendment by c. 366 added subdivision 9. The 2020 amendments. The 2020 amendment by c. 526 added the last sentence of subdivision 9. § 66-10.01. Certified mail; subsequent mail or notices may be sent by regular mail. Text Whenever in this title the Board or the Department is required to send any mail or notice by certified mail and such mail or notice is sent certified mail, return recei pt requested, then any subsequent, identical mail or notice that is sent by the Board or the Department may be sent by regular mail. History History. 2011, c. 566. § 66-10.1. Board to establish regulations regarding human research. Text The Board shall promulgate regulations pursuant to the Administrative Process Act (§ 2.2-4000 et seq.) to effectuate the provisions of Chapter 5.1 (§ 32.1-162.16 et seq.) of Title 32.1 for human research, as defined in § 32.1-162.16, to be conducted or authorized by the Department. The regulations shall require the human research committee to submit to the Governor, the General Assembly, and the Director or hi s designee at least annually a report on human research projects reviewed and approved by the committee and shall require the committee to report any significant deviations from the proposals as approved. History History. 1992, c. 603. § 66-10.2. Board to establish regulations regarding youth detained in juvenile correctional facilities pursuant to contracts with the federal government. Text The Board, in collaboration with the Department of Behavioral Health and Developmental Services, shall promulgate regulations governing the housing of youth who are det ained in a juvenile correctional facility pursuant to a contract with the federal government and not committed to such juvenile correctional facility by a court of the Commonwealth. Such regulations shall establish: 1. Stand ards that (i) govern the use of physical force, mechanical restraints, and spit guards and (ii) avoid the use of isolation; 2. Staff training requirements regarding cognitive behavioral interventions, trauma-informed care, cultural background implications, de-escalation techniques, and the use of physical and mechanical restraints; 3. Requirements for an appropriate number of bilingual staff and culturally relevant programs; 4. Methods to ensure that such youth detained understand their rights and responsibilities; 5. Standards to ensure the provision of necessary physical and mental health care; 6. A requirement that any contract entered into by a juvenile correctional facility with the federal government to house youth provide staff of the Department with the same level of acces s to such youth that the Department would ordinarily have regarding any other youth committed to such facility; and 7. Standards for recordkeeping, including extended recordkeeping requirements for records and video footage related to reported incidents. History History. 2020, c. 599. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2020, c. 599 was codified as this section at the direction of the Virginia Code Commission. § 66-10.3. Guidelines and policies and procedures for sharing information derived from juvenile records. Text A. The Departm ent shall develop and biennially update a model memorandum of understanding setting forth the respective roles and responsibilities of the Department, the Department of Behavioral Health and Developmental Services, the Department of Social Services, the court service units, the local departments of social services, and the community services boards or behavioral health authorities regarding the sharing of information derived from juvenile records for purposes of identifying and serving juveniles who may be receiving or who have received treatment, services, or care from the local agencies, the Department, or the Department of Behavioral Health and Developmental Services. B. In developi ng and updating the model memorandum of understanding, the Department shall consult with the Department of Behavioral Health and Developmental Services, the Department of Criminal Justice Services, the Department of Social Services, the Office of Childre ns Services, and representatives selected by the Department from the court service units, local departments of social services, community services boards or behavioral health authorities, youth and family organizations, and such other stakeholders as the Department shall deem appropriate from across the Commonwealth. C. The model m emorandum of understanding shall contain provisions regarding the manner in which a juvenile who may be receiving or who has received treatment, services, or care from such agency or department is identified by the agency or department and how such ident ification is shared among the agencies and departments, including the point at which a juvenile is identified by the agencies or departments that are providing or have provided treatment, services, or care to such juvenile; the manner in which past agenc y or department involvement is identified and shared, including when informed consent from a juvenile or guardian is appropriate and necessary; and the person at each agency or department responsible for identifying any potential juvenile and serving as a contact for information-sharing requests. D. The Departm ent shall distribute the model memorandum of understanding to each court services unit, community services board or behavioral health authority, and local department of social services. History History. 2022, cc. 64, 63.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_66-11"><akn:num>§ 66-11</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 2012, cc</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>164 and 456, cl. 2. Annotations Editors note. Former § 66-11, pertaining to properties formerly held by the Board or Department of Corrections, derived from Acts 1989, c. 733; 1994, c. 672.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_66-12"><akn:num>§ 66-12</akn:num><akn:heading>Definitions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Unless a different meaning clearly appears from the context, as used in this title: Board or State Board means the Board of Juvenile Justice; Child means any natural person under eighteen years of age; Department means the Department of Juvenile Justice; Director means the Director of Juvenile Justice. History History. 1989, c. 733. Chapter 2. Care of Children Committed to Department. -360§ 66-13. Authority of Department as to juveniles committed to it; establishment of facilities; arrangements for temporary care. -360§ 66-13.1. Division of Education; employment of Superintendent; powers and duties. -360§ 66-14. Allowance for maintenance of children placed by Commonwealth in private homes, etc. -360§ 66-15. Schedules of per diem cost of maintenance in detention homes; reimbursements of cities and counties. -360§ 66-16. Acceptance and expenditure of certain funds for children committed to Department. -360§ 66-17. Disposition of property left by child. -360§ 66-18. Examination and placing of such children. -360§ 66-19. Behavioral services unit; director and personnel; examination of children. -360§ 66-20. Observation and treatment of children with mental illness or developmental disabilities. -360§ 66-21. Superintendents and agents of facilities to have powers of sheriff. -360§ 66-22. Daily and additional allowance to children. -360§ 66-22.1. Establishment of stores in juvenile correctional facilities. -360§ 66-23. Authority of superintendents with regard to application for operators licenses and employment certificates. -360§ 66-24. Community group homes and other residential facilities for certain juveniles; licensure; personnel; summary suspension und er certain circumstances; penalty. -360§ 66-25. Collection of information concerning religious preferences by correctional facilities. -360§ 66-25.1. Work programs. -360§ 66-25.1:1. Juvenile academic and career training. -360§ 66-25.1:2. Career training and technical education programs. -360§ 66-25.1:3. Extending limits of confinement of state wards for work and educational programs; disposition of wages; penalties for violations. -360§ 66-25.1:4. Work release furlough. -360§ 66-25.2. Notice to be given prior to release of serious offenders. -360§ 66-25.2:1. Director; notice to school superintendent prior to release of certain offenders.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_66-13"><akn:num>§ 66-13</akn:num><akn:heading>Authority of Department as to juveniles committed to it; establishment of facilities; arrangements for temporary care</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. The Departm ent is authorized and empowered to receive juveniles committed to it by the courts of the Commonwealth. The Department shall establish, staff and maintain facilities for the rehabilitation, education, training and confinement of such juveniles. The Depar tment may make arrangements with satisfactory persons, institutions or agencies, or with cities or counties maintaining places of detention for juveniles, for the temporary care of such juveniles. B. The Departm ent may by mutual agreement with a locality or localities and, pursuant to standards promulgated pursuant to § 16.1-309.9, establish detention homes for use by a locality or localities for pre-trial and post-dispositional detention pursuant to § § 16.1-248.1 and 16.1-284.1. The Department may collect by mutual agreement with a locality or localities and from any locality of this Commonwealth from which a juvenile is placed in such a detention home, the reasonable cost of maintaining such juve nile in such facility and a portion of the cost of construction of such facility. Such agreements shall be subject to approval by the General Assembly in the general appropriation act. C. The Departm ent shall collect data pertaining to the demographic characteristics of juveniles incarcerated in state juvenile correctional institutions, including, but not limited to, the race or ethnicity, age, and gender of such persons, and the types of and extent to which health-related problems are prevalent among such persons. Beginning July 1, 1997, such data shall be collected, tabulated quarterly, and reported by the Director to the Governor and the General Assembly at each regular session of the General As sembly thereafter. History History. Code 1950, §§ 53-324, 53-330, 63-291, 63-366, 63-367, 63-36 8, 63-369, 63.1-239, 63.1-245; 1950, p. 33; 1954, c. 262; 1956, cc. 127, 287; 1962, c. 437; 1968, c. 578; 1974, cc. 44, 45; 1975, c. 178; 1981, c. 487; 1982, c. 636, § 53.1-237; 1989, c. 733; 1991, c. 534; 1996, cc. 755, 914; 1997, c. 894; 2012, cc. 8 03, 835; 2022, cc. 414, 415. Annotations Cross references. As to delinquent juveniles generally, see § 16.1-278.8. Editors note. Acts 1996, cc. 755 and 914, cls. 6, provide: [t]hat no later than October 1, 1996, the Board of Juvenile Justice Services shall establish length-of-stay gui delines for juveniles indeterminately committed to the Department. By November 1, 1996, and annually thereafter, the Department shall provide copies of the guidelines and the estimated impact on juvenile correctional facility bed space needs to the Gener al Assembly. The 2012 amendments. The 2012 amendments by cc. 803 and 835, cl. 99, are identical, and in subsection A, in the second sentence, added education; and in subsection B, in the f irst sentence, deleted of this title following (§ 66-25.3 et seq.), and in the last sentence, substituted The Department of Juvenile Justices Division of Education for The Department of Correctional Education and § 66-13 for Chapter 18 (§ 22.1-339 et seq.) of Title 22.1. The 2022 amendments. The 2022 amendments by cc. 414 and 415 are identical, and deleted former subsection B, which read: In accordance with the Juvenile Corrections Private Managem ent Act, Chapter 2.1 (§ 66-25.3 et seq.), the Department may establish, or contract with private entities, political subdivisions or commissions to establish, juvenile boot camps. The Board shall prescribe standards for the development, implementation and operation of the boot camps with highly structured components including, but not limited to, military style drill and ceremony, physical labor, education and rigid discipline and no less than six months of intensive aftercare. The Department of Juve nile Justices Division of Education shall establish, staff, and maintain educational programs for such juveniles in accordance with § 66-13. A contract to expend state funds to establish a facility for a juvenile boot camp shall not be executed by the Department unless an appropriation has been expressly approved as is otherwise provided by law; and redesignated accordingly. Research References. Virginia Forms (Matthew Bender). No. 9-2603 Assessment Order  Juvenile Boot Camp. Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 9B M.J. Infants, § 81. § 66-13.1. Division of Education; employment of Superintendent; powers and duties. Text A. To assist i n the performance of the duties imposed by § 66-13 the Department shall develop and maintain a Division of Education (Division), which shall be composed of all the educational facilities of all institutions operated by the Department. The Division sha ll be designated as a local education agency (LEA) but shall not be eligible to receive state funds appropriated for direct aid to public education. B. The Departm ent shall employ a Superintendent of the Division, who shall meet the minimum standards for division superintendents set by the Board of Education. The Superintendent shall supervise the administration of the Division. The Department shall employ teacher s and place them in appropriate schools. Other powers and duties of the Superintendent shall be fixed by the Board of Education in accordance with law. C. When the De partment employs a teacher licensed by the Board of Education to provide instruction in the schools of the juvenile correctional centers, the Department of Human Resource Management shall establish salary schedules for the teachers which endeavor to be c ompetitive with those in effect for the school division in which the correctional center is located. History History. 2012, cc. 803, 835. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2012, cc. 803 and 835, cl. 99, enacted this section.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_66-14"><akn:num>§ 66-14</akn:num><akn:heading>Allowance for maintenance of children placed by Commonwealth in private homes, etc</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text For the maintenance of each child committed to the custody of the Department pursuant to subdivision A 14 of § 16.1-278.8 and placed in a private home or in a facili ty other than one operated by the Commonwealth, there shall be paid a per diem allowance which shall be established by the Department from funds appropriated to the Department for this purpose. The cost of such care shall not exceed that amount which wou ld be incurred if the services required by the child were provided in a juvenile facility operated by the Department. No child shall be placed outside the Commonwealth without first complying with the appropriate provisions of Chapters 10 (§ 63.2-1000 et seq.) and 11 (§ 63.2-1100 et seq.) of Title 63.2 or with regulations of the State Board of Social Services relating to resident children placed out of the Commonwealth. History History. Code 1950, §§ 53-325, 63-293, 63.1-240; 1952, c. 644; 1962, c. 437; 1968, c. 578; 1970, c. 326; 1974, cc. 44, 45, 476; 1978, c. 309; 1981, c. 487; 1982, c. 636, § 53.1-239; 1989, c. 733; 1992, cc. 837, 880; 1993, cc. 232, 283; 1996, cc. 587, 597. Annotations Cross references. As to the establishment of a state pool of funds to be allocated to community policy and management teams under the Childrens Services Act, see § 2.2-5211.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_66-15"><akn:num>§ 66-15</akn:num><akn:heading>Schedules of per diem cost of maintenance in detention homes; reimbursements of cities and counties</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Department shall establish schedules setting forth the per diem cost to each locality for maintaining a child in a detention home. In accordance with the schedule, the Department, in addition to all other reimbursements on account of such detention homes, shall reimburse each city or county for the cost of maintaining in such homes any children committed to the Department. The Department shall review annually and adjust, if justified, the per diem it pays to localities for the care of state wards. History History. Code 1950, §§ 53-326, 63.1-241, 63-293.1; 1954, c. 582; 196 8, c. 578; 1974, cc. 44, 45; 1981, c. 487; 1982, c. 636, § 53.1-240; 1989, cc. 683, 733.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_66-16"><akn:num>§ 66-16</akn:num><akn:heading>Acceptance and expenditure of certain funds for children committed to Department</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Department is authorized to accept and expend for the benefit of any child committed to it, or for reimbursement purposes, any funds made available from any source, solely for the current maintenance and support of any such child, whether such funds be provided by the childs parents, or other person, or by the U.S. Department of Veterans Affairs, the Railroad Retirement Act, the old age and survivors insura nce provisions of the federal Social Security Act, as amended, or from any other source. In no event shall the sums so accepted exceed an amount in excess of the cost to the Department of supporting the child. History History. Code 1950, §§ 53-327, 63.1-242, 63-293.2; 1956, c. 400; 196 8, c. 578; 1974, cc. 44, 45; 1981, c. 487; 1982, c. 636, § 53.1-241; 1989, c. 733. Annotations Editors note. At the direction of the Virginia Code Commission, U.S. Department of Veterans Affairs was substituted for Veterans Administration.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_66-17"><akn:num>§ 66-17</akn:num><akn:heading>Disposition of property left by child</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text If any child, having been in the custody of the Department by virtue of § 16.1-278.8, upon being released or having escaped therefrom leaves any personal property va lued at less than $100 in the custody of the Department for six months after his release or escape, the Director may sell such personal property at public sale or otherwise dispose of the property. The proceeds of such sale shall be kept for one year fro m the date of the childs attaining the age of majority. Thereafter, any unclaimed proceeds shall be paid into the state treasury and credited to the Literary Fund. History History. Code 1950, §§ 16.1-178.1, 53-327.1; 1956, c. 555; 1974, cc. 44, 45; 1977, c. 559; 1981, c. 487; 1982, c. 636, § 53.1-242; 1989, c. 733; 1991, c. 534.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_66-18"><akn:num>§ 66-18</akn:num><akn:heading>Examination and placing of such children</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Department shall make a careful physical and mental examination of every child committed to it by the courts, investigate the personal and family history of the chi ld and his environment, and place such children at such facilities as are available. Any children committed to the Department and afterwards found to be eligible for commitment by proper proceedings to any state hospital or admission to a training center for individuals with intellectual disability shall take precedence as to admission over all others and shall in all cases be received into the state hospital or training center within 45 days. History History. Code 1950, §§ 53-328, 63-292, 63.1-243; 1956, c. 127; 1968, c. 578; 1974, cc. 44, 45; 1981, c. 487; 1982, c. 636, § 53.1-243; 1989, c. 733; 2012, cc. 476, 507. Annotations The 2012 amendments. The 2012 amendments by cc. 476 and 507 are identical, and substituted individuals with intellectual disability for the mentally retarded and 4 5 for forty-five in the second sentence.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_66-19"><akn:num>§ 66-19</akn:num><akn:heading>Behavioral services unit; director and personnel; examination of children</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text To assist in the performance of the duties imposed by § 66-18, the Department shall maintain a behavioral services unit and employ as director thereof a clinically c ompetent person. The Department shall also employ such other medical, technical and clinical personnel skilled in the diagnosis and treatment of physical diseases or mental illnesses of children as may be desirable for the operation of such unit. The per sonnel of the unit, when visiting the various facilities maintained by the Department for the care of children committed to the Department, shall conduct a thorough examination of each child at such facilities not theretofore examined by the unit, and ot her children at the facilities for whom such examination is indicated. Such examination shall be for the purpose of determining, diagnosing and treating physical and learning ailments or impairments and mental illnesses with a view to improving the gener al functioning of such children and hastening their rehabilitation. History History. Code 1950, §§ 53-329, 63.1-244, 63-381, 63-384; 1954, c. 68 1; 1966, c. 354; 1968, c. 578; 1974, cc. 44, 45; 1981, c. 487; 1982, c. 636, § 53.1-244; 1989, c. 733; 2012, cc. 476, 507. Annotations The 2012 amendments. The 2012 amendments by cc. 476 and 507 are identical, and substituted physical diseases or mental illnesses for physical and mental diseases in th e second sentence and physical and learning ailments or impairments and mental illnesses for physical, mental and learning ailments or impairments in the fourth sentence.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_66-20"><akn:num>§ 66-20</akn:num><akn:heading>Observation and treatment of children with mental illness or developmental disabilities</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text After commitment of any child to the Department, if the Department finds, as a result of psychiatric examinations and case study, that such child has mental illness or a developmental disability, it shall be the duty of the Department to obtain treatment for the childs mental condition. If the Department determines that transfer to a state hospital, training center, or other appropriate treatment facility is requir ed to further diagnose or treat the childs mental condition, the proceedings shall be in accordance with the provisions of § 37.2-806 or §§ 16.1-341 through 16.1-345, except that provisions requiring consent of the childs parent or guard ian for treatment shall not apply in such cases. No child transferred to a state hospital pursuant to this section or the provisions of Title 37.2 shall, however, be held or cared for in any maximum security unit where adults determined to be criminally insane reside and such child shall be kept separate and apart from such adults. History History. Code 1950, § 53-329.1; 1977, c. 559; 1978, c. 739; 1981, c. 48 7; 1982, c. 636, § 53.1-245; 1989, c. 733; 1990, c. 975; 2012, cc. 476, 507; 2017, c. 458. Annotations The 2012 amendments. The 2012 amendments by cc. 476 and 507 are identical, and substituted has mental illness or intellectual disability for is mentally ill or mentally re tarded in the first sentence. The 2017 amendments. The 2017 amendment by c. 458 substituted a developmental disability for intellectual disability in the first sentence.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_66-21"><akn:num>§ 66-21</akn:num><akn:heading>Superintendents and agents of facilities to have powers of sheriff</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The superintendents of the facilities established by the Department pursuant to § 66-13 and their authorized agents shall have the powers of a sheriff for the purpos e of preserving order at their facilities and for the conveyance of children committed to their care to and from such facilities. History History. Code 1950, §§ 53-332, 63-371, 63.1-247; 1968, c. 578; 1974, cc. 44, 45; 1981, c. 487; 1982, c. 636, § 53.1-246; 1989, c. 733.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_66-22"><akn:num>§ 66-22</akn:num><akn:heading>Daily and additional allowance to children</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Director may allow every child in any facility established by the Department a daily allowance in an amount established by the Board. Additional allowance may be ma de by the Director to provide necessary funds for incidental needs for required activities in schools, foster care and other special placements for other special activities that such children would normally be engaged in resulting from their placement. T he allowance so made may be drawn upon by the child for such purposes as may be authorized by the regulations of the Board. History History. Code 1950, §§ 53-333, 63.1-248, 63-369.1; 1958, c. 366; 196 0, c. 395; 1968, c. 578; 1970, c. 327; 1974, cc. 44, 45; 1975, c. 638; 1981, c. 487; 1982, c. 636, § 53.1-247; 1989, c. 733. § 66-22.1. Establishment of stores in juvenile correctional facilities. Text The Director is hereby authorized to provide for the establishment and operation of stores or commissaries in state juvenile correctional facilities to deal in such art icles as he deems proper. The profits from the operation of such stores shall be used for educational, recreational, or other purposes beneficial to the juveniles committed to the Department as may be prescribed by the Director. History History. 1997, c. 195.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_66-23"><akn:num>§ 66-23</akn:num><akn:heading>Authority of superintendents with regard to application for operators licenses and employment certificates</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The superintendents of facilities established by the Department shall have the authority, commensurate with that of a parent in like cases, to give consent for those ch ildren placed in their respective facilities to (i) application for a motor vehicle operators license and (ii) issuance of an employment certificate. History History. Code 1950, § 53-334; 1977, c. 643; 1981, c. 487; 1982, c. 636, § 53.1-248; 1989, c. 733; 2012, cc. 164, 456. Annotations The 2012 amendments. The 2012 amendments by cc. 164 and 456 are identical, and deleted the former second sentence, which read: Such authority shall be exercised in accordance with regulations established by the Board.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_66-24"><akn:num>§ 66-24</akn:num><akn:heading>Community group homes and other residential facilities for certain juveniles; licensure; personnel; summary suspension under certain circumstances; penalty</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. The Departm ent of Juvenile Justice shall cooperate with other state departments in fulfilling their respective licensing and certification responsibilities of childrens residential facilities. The Board shall promulgate regulations that shall allow the Departme nt to so assist and cooperate with other state departments. The Boards regulations shall establish the Department as the single licensing agency, with the exception of educational programs licensed by the Department of Education, for group homes or r esidential facilities providing care of juveniles in direct state care. B. The Departm ent is authorized to establish and maintain such a system of community group homes or other residential care facilities as the Department may from time to time acquire, construct, contract for or rent for the care of juveniles in direct state care, pendi ng development of more permanent placement plans. Any community group home or other residential care facility that the Department may contract for or rent for the care of juveniles in direct state care shall be licensed or certified in accordance with th e regulations of the Board.Any more permanent placement plans shall consider adequate care and treatment, and suitable education, training and employment for such juveniles, as is appropriate. C. The Departm ent is further authorized to employ necessary personnel for community group homes or other residential care facilities or to contract with private entities for their operation. The Department shall conduct background checks of any individual who (i) acce pts a position of employment at a community group home or other residential care facility, (ii) volunteers at a community group home or other residential care facility on a regular basis and will be alone with a juvenile in the performance of his duties, or (iii) provides contractual services directly to a juvenile in a community group home or other residential care facility on a regular basis and will be alone with a juvenile in the performance of his duties, pursuant to § 63.2-1726. D. The Board s hall promulgate regulations for licensure or certification of community group homes or other residential care facilities that contract with or are rented for the care of juveniles in direct state care pursuant to subsection B.The Boards regulations s hall address the services required to be provided in such facilities as it may deem appropriate to ensure the welfare and safety of the juveniles. In addition, the Boards regulations shall include, but need not be limited to (i) specifications for th e structure and accommodations of such facilities according to the needs of the juveniles to be placed in the home or facility; (ii) rules concerning allowable activities, local government- and group home- or residential care facility-imposed curfews, an d study, recreational, and bedtime hours; and (iii) a requirement that each home or facility have a community liaison who shall be responsible for facilitating cooperative relationships with the neighbors, the school system, local law enforcement, local government officials, and the community at large. E. Pursuant to the procedures set forth in subsection F and in addition to any other legally authorized disciplinary actions, the Director may issue a summary order of suspension of the license or certificate of any group home or residential facility so regulated by t he Department, in conjunction with any proceeding for revocation, denial, or other action, when conditions or practices exist in the home or facility that pose an immediate and substantial threat to the health, safety, and welfare of the juveniles who ar e residents and the Director believes the operation of the home or facility should be suspended during the pendency of such proceeding. F. The summary order of suspension shall take effect upon its issuance and shall be served on the licensee or certificate holder or its designee as soon as practicable thereafter by personal service and certified mail, return receipt requested, to the address of recor d of the licensee or certificate holder. The order shall state the time, date, and location of a hearing to determine whether the suspension is appropriate. Such hearing shall be held no later than three business days after the issuance of the summary or der of suspension and shall be convened by the Director or his designee.After such hearing, the Director may issue a final order of summary suspension or may find that such summary suspension is not warranted by the facts and circumstances presented. A f inal order of summary suspension shall include notice that the licensee or certificate holder may appeal the Directors decision to the appropriate circuit court no later than 10 days following issuance of the order. The sole issue before the court sh all be whether the Director had reasonable grounds to require the licensee to cease operations during the pendency of the concurrent revocation, denial, or other proceeding. The concurrent revocation, denial, or other proceeding shall not be affected by the outcome of any hearing on the appropriateness of the summary suspension.The willful and material failure to comply with the summary order of suspension or final order of summary suspension shall be punishable as a Class 2 misdemeanor. The Director ma y require the cooperation of any other agency or subdivision of the Commonwealth in the relocation of the juveniles who are residents of a home or facility whose license or certificate has been summarily suspended pursuant to this section and in any othe r actions necessary to reduce the risk of further harm to such residents. G. In addition to the requirements set forth above, the Boards regulations shall require, as a condition of initial licensure or, if appropriate, license renewal, that the applicant shall: (i) be personally interviewed by Department personnel to determine the qual ifications of the owner or operator before granting an initial license; (ii) provide evidence of having relevant prior experience before any initial license is granted; (iii) provide, as a condition of initial license or renewal licensure, evidence of st aff participation in training on appropriate siting of the residential facilities for children, good neighbor policies, and community relations; and (iv) be required to screen residents prior to admission to exclude individuals with behavioral issues, su ch as histories of violence, that cannot be managed in the relevant residential facility. H. In addition , the Department shall: 1. Notif y relevant local governments and placing and funding agencies, including the Office of Childrens Services, of multiple health and safety or human rights violations in residential facilities licensed by the Department when such violations result in th e lowering of the licensure or certification status of the facility to provisional; 2. Post on the Departments website information concerning the application for initial licensure or certification of or renewal, denial, or provisional licensure or certification of an y residential facility for children located in the locality; 3. Require all licensees or certificate holders to self-report lawsuits against or settlements with residential facility operators relating to the health and safety or human rights of res idents and any criminal charges that may have been made relating to the health and safety or human rights of residents; 4. Require proof of contractual agreements or staff expertise to provide educational services, counseling services, psychological services, medical services, or any other services needed to serve the residents in accordance with the facilitys operational plan; 5. Modify the term of the license or certificate at any time during the term of the license or certificate based on a change in compliance; and 6. Disseminate to local governments, or post on the Departments website, an accurate (updated weekly or monthly as necessary) list of licensed and operating group homes and other resi dential facilities for children by locality with information on services and identification of the lead licensure agency. History History. Code 1950, §§ 53-331, 63.1-246, 63-291.1; 1966, c. 491; 196 8, c. 578; 1974, cc. 44, 45; 1975, c. 637; 1981, c. 487; 1982, c. 636, § 53.1-249; 1989, c. 733; 1996, cc. 755, 914; 2005, cc. 358, 471; 2006, cc. 168, 781; 2008, c. 873; 2015, c. 366. Annotations Cross references. As to punishment for Class 2 misdemeanors, see § 18.2-11. Editors note. Acts 2006, c. 168, cl. 2, provides: That the Board of Education, the Board of Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services [now the Board of Behavioral Health and Developmental Services], the State Board of Juvenile Justice, and the Board of Social Services shall promulgate regulations to implement the provisions of this act to be effective within 280 days of its enactment. Acts 2006, c. 781, cl. 2, provides: That the Board of Education, Board of Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services [now the Board of Beh avioral Health and Developmental Services], Board of Social Services, and the State Board of Juvenile Justice shall promulgate regulations to implement the provisions of this act to be effective within 280 days of its enactment. Acts 2006, c. 781, cl. 3, provides: That the Board of Education, Board of Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services, Board of Social Serv ices [now the Board of Behavioral Health and Developmental Services], and the State Board of Juvenile Justice shall also include in the emergency regulations required by the second enactment clause provisions to implement the requirements enacted by HB 2 461 (2005) and SB 1304 (2005) [Acts 2005, cc. 358, 471]. Acts 2008, c. 873, cl. 2, provides: That the Board of Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services [now the Board of Behavioral Health and D evelopmental Serv...</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_66-25"><akn:num>§ 66-25</akn:num><akn:heading>Collection of information concerning religious preferences by correctional facilities</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. Notwithstan ding any provision of law to the contrary, any correctional facility established pursuant to this chapter or Chapter 11 (§ 16.1-226 et seq.) of Title 16.1 may collect and disseminate information concerning the religious preferences and affiliations of persons committed to its custody. No person shall be required to indicate his religious preference or affiliation, and no dissemination of the information shall be made except to categories of persons designated by the person who has given his consent t o such dissemination. B. No consent given pursuant to this section shall be construed to allow any correctional facility established pursuant to this chapter or Chapter 11 (§ 16.1-226 et seq.) of Title 16.1 to disseminate to federal government authorities information concerning the reli gious preferences and affiliations of persons committed to its custody for the purpose of compiling a list, registry, or database of individuals based on religious affiliation, national origin, or ethnicity, unless such dissemination is specifically requ ired by state or federal law. History History. Code 1950, § 53-19.15:1; 1977, c. 506; 1982, c. 636, § 53.1 -250; 1989, c. 733; 2019, c. 774. Annotations The 2019 amendments. The 2019 amendment by c. 774 designated the existing provisions as subsection A and added subsection B. § 66-25.1. Work programs. Text A. The Directo r or his designee may enter into an agreement with a public or private entity for the operation of a work program for juveniles committed to the Department. B. The primary purpose of such work program shall be the training of such juveniles, not the production of goods or the rendering of service by juveniles committed to the Department. Such work programs also shall not interfere with or impact a juveniles education program where the goal is achieving a high school diploma or its equivalent. The Board shall promulgate regulations governing the form and review process for proposed agreements. C. Articles pr oduced or manufactured and services provided by juveniles participating in such a work program may be purchased by any county, by any district of any county, city, or town and by any nonprofit organization, including volunteer emergency medical services agencies, fire departments, sheltered workshops and community service organizations. Such articles and services may also be bought, sold or acquired by exchange on the open market through the participating public or private entity. D. Revenues re ceived from the sale of articles, as provided in subsection C, shall be deposited into a special fund established in the state treasury. Such funds shall be expended to support work programs for juveniles committed to the Department. History History. 1993, cc. 460, 487; 1997, c. 639; 2011, c. 551; 2012, cc. 803, 83 5; 2015, cc. 502, 503. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2011, c. 551, cl. 2, provides: That the committee described in subsection A of § 66-25.1 of the Code of Virginia shall develop and submit to the Depar tment of Juvenile Justice a plan to establish a network of businesses willing to employ juveniles released from the Departments commitment. Acts 2011, c. 551, cl. 3, provides: That the provisions of this act shall become effective on July 1, 2012. The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendment by c. 551, effective July 1, 2012, in subsection A, substituted the language beginning a business that employs through to the end for the Office of the Secretary of Commerce and Trade, and the Office of the Secretary of Public Safety. The 2012 amendments. The 2012 amendments by cc. 803 and 835, cl. 101, are identical, and rewrote subsection A. Acts 2012 cc. 803 and 835, cl. 99, also purported to amend subsection A by substituting Department of Juvenile Justices Division of Education for Department of Correctional Education, but the section was deleted by cl. 101. The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendments by cc. 502 and 503 are identical, and in subsection C, inserted by any preceding district and substituted emergency medica l services agencies for lifesaving or first aid crews, rescue squads following volunteer. § 66-25.1:1. Juvenile academic and career training. Text The Director or his designee shall assess, in accordance with criteria established pursuant to § 66-25.1:3, whether a juvenile committed to the Department is an appr opriate candidate for participation in a work release program, apprenticeship program, job enterprise program, or any other work experience opportunity located at or through the juvenile correctional center where the juvenile is placed. History History. 2005, c. 648. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2005, c. 648, cl. 2, provides: That the Board of Juvenile Justice is authorized to operate a pilot program in conformity with this act beginning July 1, 2005, and ending July 1, 2006, at one juvenile correctional center site. Acts 2005, c. 648, cl. 3, provides: That the Department of Juvenile Justice shall submit a report on the implementation of the pilot program and this act to t he House Committee on Militia, Police and Public Safety, and the Senate Committee on Rehabilitation and Social Services by November 15, 2005. The report shall provide an assessment on the implementation of the pilot program permitting a work and educatio nal release program involving the temporary release of juveniles into the community in preparation for their transition from the Department of Juvenile Justices direct care to their home community. Acts 2005, c. 648, cl. 4, provides: That the Board of Juvenile Justice shall promulgate regulations to implement the provisions of this act to be effective wi thin 280 days of its enactment. The regulations shall establish criteria for assessing a juveniles suitability for such programs as authorized by this act. Such criteria shall include a review of the juveniles offense history and behavior during commitment; the completion of an objective risk assessment of the juveniles likelihood to re-offend; and an assessment of the juveniles suitability for the particular community release program. Acts 2005, c. 648, cl. 5, provides: That the second, third, and fourth enactments are effective on July 1, 2005, and the first enactment is effective July 1, 2006. § 66-25.1:2. Career training and technical education programs. Text A. With such f unds as are made available for this purpose, the Department shall provide juveniles committed to the Department with opportunities to work and to participate in career training or technical education programs operated by the Department. B. The Departm ent may develop appropriate interagency linkages with state and local agencies, public and private institutions of education and of higher education, labor and industry councils, the business community, rehabilitative services providers, and employment a nd guidance services to assist juveniles in acquiring necessary work habits, developing marketable skills, and identifying career goals through a broad range of career opportunities and mentoring and apprenticeship programs. In providing career-related p rograms, training, and services, the Department may consult and cooperate with the Virginia Employment Commission and the Department of Labor and Industry. Work training opportunities may include business, industrial, agricultural, highway maintenance an d construction, and work release programs as hereafter specified in this article. In addition, juveniles may be employed to improve, repair, work on, or cultivate public property or buildings. History History. 2005, c. 648; 2012, cc. 803, 835. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2005, c. 648, cl. 2, provides: That the Board of Juvenile Justice is authorized to operate a pilot program in conformity with this act beginning July 1, 2005, and ending July 1, 2006, at one juvenile correctional center site. Acts 2005, c. 648, cl. 3, provides: That the Department of Juvenile Justice shall submit a report on the implementation of the pilot program and this act to t he House Committee on Militia, Police and Public Safety, and the Senate Committee on Rehabilitation and Social Services by November 15, 2005. The report shall provide an assessment on the implementation of the pilot program permitting a work and educatio nal release program involving the temporary release of juveniles into the community in preparation for their transition from the Department of Juvenile Justices direct care to their home community. Acts 2005, c. 648, cl. 4, provides: That the Board of Juvenile Justice shall promulgate regulations to implement the provisions of this act to be effective wi thin 280 days of its enactment. The regulations shall establish criteria for assessing a juveniles suitability for such programs as authorized by this act. Such criteria shall include a review of the juveniles offense history and behavior during commitment; the completion of an objective risk assessment of the juveniles likelihood to re-offend; and an assessment of the juveniles suitability for the particular community release program. Acts 2005, c. 648, cl. 5, provides: That the second, third, and fourth enactments are effective on July 1, 2005, and the first enactment is effective July 1, 2006. The 2012 amendments. The 2012 amendments by cc. 803 and 835, cl. 99, are identical, and deleted or by the Department of Correctional Education in accordance with § 22.1-339 et seq. following operated by the Department in subsection A; and deleted in conjunction with the Department of Correctional Education preceding may consult in the second sentence of subsection B. § 66-25.1:3. Extending limits of confinement of state wards for work and educational programs; disposition of wages; penalties for violations. Text A. The Directo r is authorized to establish work release programs, subject to such rules and regulations as the Board may prescribe, whereby (i) a juvenile who is proficient in a...</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_66-26"><akn:num>§ 66-26</akn:num><akn:heading>Delinquency prevention and youth development programs; agents</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Director shall develop and supervise delinquency prevention and youth development programs in order that better services and coordination of services are provided t o children. The Director shall have the authority to appoint necessary agents for the carrying out of these programs as may be needed. To this end the Director shall cooperate with state and local authorities in establishing and maintaining suitable de linquency prevention and youth development programs. History History. Code 1950, § 53-19.22:1; 1974, c. 496; 1979, c. 700; 1982, c. 636, § 53.1-251; 1989, c. 733. Annotations Cross references. As to establishment of a community-based system of services for juvenile offenders, see § 16.1-309.3. Law Review. For 2000 survey of Virginia law regarding children, see 34 U. Rich. L. Rev. 939 (2000).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_66-27"><akn:num>§ 66-27</akn:num><akn:heading>Authority of Director to make grants to localities</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Director is authorized to make grants to counties and cities pursuant to the provisions of this chapter to promote efficiency and economy in the delivery of youth s ervices and to provide support to localities seeking to respond positively to the growing rate of juvenile delinquency. History History. Code 1950, § 53-335; 1979, c. 698; 1982, c. 636, § 53.1-252 ; 1989, c. 733.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_66-28"><akn:num>§ 66-28</akn:num><akn:heading>Policies</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Board shall prescribe policies governing applications for grants pursuant to this chapter and standards for the operation of programs developed and implemented unde r the grants. The Department shall cooperate with and seek the assistance of representatives of county and city governing bodies, private nonprofit youth service agencies, and private citizens having expertise in the development and any subsequent revisi ons of the standards required by this section. The Department shall establish and make available to localities a list of best practice program models that are likely to qualify for grants pursuant to this chapter, such as programs offering (i) mentorship s, (ii) community service opportunities, (iii) trauma-informed behavioral and mental health services, (iv) career planning and training, (v) employment opportunities, (vi) non-academic supports in a public or private school, or (vii) after-school or summ er programs. History History. Code 1950, § 53-336; 1979, c. 698; 1982, c. 636, § 53.1-253 ; 1989, c. 733; 2000, c. 277; 2022, c. 522. Annotations The 2000 amendments. The 2000 amendment by c. 277 inserted and any subsequent revisions near the end of the second sentence. The 2022 amendments. The 2022 amendment by c. 522, added the third sentence.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_66-29"><akn:num>§ 66-29</akn:num><akn:heading>Ordinances to be enacted by participating localities; applications by localities for grants</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Prior to applying to the Director for a grant pursuant to this chapter, each governing body of a county or city which is to participate in the grant shall enact an appr opriate ordinance or resolution which provides for the creation of a youth services citizen board pursuant to § 66-34. Any county or city or combination thereof may apply to the Director for a grant pursuant to this chapter. The Director shall provide consultation and technical assistan ce, if requested, to localities in the development of applications for such grants. The Director shall approve or disapprove applicants for grants. History History. Code 1950, § 53-337; 1979, c. 698; 1982, c. 636, § 53.1-254 ; 1989, c. 733; 2000, c. 277. Annotations The 2000 amendments. The 2000 amendment by c. 277 deleted hereof, annual preparation of a comprehensive plan based on an objective assessment of the communitys needs and resou rces for developing, coordinating and evaluating youth services and fund of the local share of the grant at the end of the first paragraph.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_66-30"><akn:num>§ 66-30</akn:num><akn:heading>Renewal of grants; suspension for failure to comply with standards; notice and hearing</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Grants approved by the Director pursuant to § 66-29 shall be renewed subject to approval by the Director of an annual plan update for youth services submitted by the participating counties or cities. If the Director determines that a program operating under an approved grant is not in compliance with minimum standards promulgated by the Board, he may suspend all or any portion of the grant until the required standards of operation are met. History History. Code 1950, § 53-338; 1979, c. 698; 1982, c. 636, § 53.1-255 ; 1989, c. 733; 1990, c. 679; 2000, c. 277. Annotations The 2000 amendments. The 2000 amendment by c. 277 an annual plan update for the comprehensive plan in the first paragraph, substituted determines for shall determine in the second paragraph, and deleted after thirty days notice to each participating county and city and after a hearing is held on the matter at the end of the second paragraph.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_66-31"><akn:num>§ 66-31</akn:num><akn:heading>Funding; records to be kept by localities; use of funds</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. Grants made to a county or city or combination thereof pursuant to this chapter shall be of an amount up to seventy-five percent of the total program budget for the proposed program for salaries and all other operating expenses including the lease of facilities, su bject to funds provided by the General Assembly. B. Each county and city receiving moneys under this chapter shall keep records of receipts and disbursements thereof which records shall be open for audit and evaluation by the appropriate state authorities. C. Participati ng counties and cities may not use funds provided under this chapter to decrease those funds allocated by the governing body for existing citizen boards as provided for in § 66-34 hereof with the exception of those programs being funded by federal gra nt moneys. History History. Code 1950, § 53-339; 1979, c. 698; 1982, c. 636, § 53.1-256 ; 1989, c. 733.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_66-32"><akn:num>§ 66-32</akn:num><akn:heading>Withdrawal from program</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Any participating county or city may, at the beginning of any calendar quarter, by ordinance or resolution of its governing authority, notify the Director of its intent ion to withdraw from the grant program. Such withdrawal shall be effective the last day of the quarter in which such notice is given. History History. Code 1950, § 53-340; 1979, c. 698; 1982, c. 636, § 53.1-257 ; 1989, c. 733.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_66-33"><akn:num>§ 66-33</akn:num><akn:heading>Unexpended funds</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text In any case in which any portion of state funds obtained through a grant authorized pursuant to this chapter remains unencumbered or unexpended at the end of the fiscal year, such funds shall be returned by the locality to the State Treasurer, who shall deposit such moneys in the state general fund. History History. Code 1950, § 53-341; 1979, c. 698; 1982, c. 636, § 53.1-258 ; 1989, c. 733.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_66-34"><akn:num>§ 66-34</akn:num><akn:heading>Youth services citizen boards; appointment and qualifications of members</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. Each county and city participating in a program funded by an approved grant shall be represented on a youth services citizen board (the board). The board shall be appointed by the county or city governing body or combination thereof. The board may be composed of (i ) representative elected officials, representatives of public and private agencies serving youths, representatives of local law enforcement, and citizens not employed by government or service agencies, including one representative of the faith community and one representative of the business community, or (ii) the community policy and management team established pursuant to § 2.2-5204 or a similar entity, as approved by the Department, provided that such board or entity (a) includes, for the purposes of this section, at least one representative of the faith community who is not employed by a government or service agency, one representative of the business community who is not employed by a government or service agency, and one representative of loca l law enforcement and (b) complies with any other requirements imposed by the Department. No board member may have an interest in any organization or program that receives grant funds pursuant to this chapter. B. The board s hall actively participate with community representatives in the formulation of a comprehensive plan for the development, coordination, and evaluation of the youth services program and shall make formal recommendations to the governing authority or author ities at least annually concerning the comprehensive plan and its implementation during the ensuing year. C. The board m ay establish a youth advisory team for the purposes of consultation and advice regarding the youth services program. If the board establishes a youth advisory team, the board (i) shall consult with and consider the recommendations of the youth advisory t eam prior to making recommendations to the local governing body pursuant to subsection B and (ii) may apply to the Department for additional funding to support the youth advisory team. History History. Code 1950, § 53-342; 1979, c. 698; 1982, c. 636, § 53.1-259 ; 1989, c. 733; 2000, c. 277; 2022, c. 522. Annotations The 2000 amendments. The 2000 amendment by c. 277 added the last sentence. The 2022 amendments. The 2022 amendment by c. 522, added the subsection designations; in subsection A, added (the board) in the first sentence, rewrote the second and third se ntences, which read: The board shall be appointed by the county or city governing body or combination thereof and may include in its membership representative elected officials, representatives of public and private agencies serving youths, citizens not employed by government or service agencies and at least one member who is below the age of eighteen years. A majority of the board shall be citizens who are not employed by government or service agencies and who are not elected governmental officials .; and added subsection C.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_66-35"><akn:num>§ 66-35</akn:num><akn:heading>Responsibilities of local programs</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text It shall be the responsibility of the local programs to: 1. Prepa re and update pursuant to Department guidelines a comprehensive plan based on an objective assessment of the communitys youth development and delinquency prevention needs and resources; 2. Assist the locality in establishing and modifying programs and services to youth pursuant to § 16.1-309.3 on the basis of an objective assessment of the communitys needs and res ources; 3. Collaborate with public and private entities to identify gaps in program services and identify potential funding sources to assist in developing programs to respond to identified gaps; and 4. Provide assistance to other community agencies and organizations, including the community policy and management team established pursuant to § 2.2-5204, in establishing and modifyin g programs and services to youth. History History. Code 1950, § 53-343; 1979, c. 698; 1982, c. 636, § 53.1-260 ; 1989, c. 733; 1992, cc. 837, 880; 1993, cc. 232, 283; 2000, c. 277; 2022, c. 522. Annotations The 2000 amendments. The 2000 amendment by c. 277 rewrote the section. The 2022 amendments. The 2022 amendment by c. 522, substituted Prepare and update pursuant to Department guidelines a comprehensive plan for Prepare and annually update a comprehensive plan in subdivision 1; deleted former subdivision 3, which read: Collaborate with public and private entities to maintain and disseminate an annual inventory of youth and parenting related services and programs available in the loca lity; and redesignated former subdivision 4 as subdivision 3 and redesignated accordingly.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section></akn:body></akn:act></akn:akomaNtoso>