<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akn:akomaNtoso xmlns:akn="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><akn:act><akn:meta><akn:identification source="#cosilico"><akn:FRBRWork><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-35.1" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-35.1" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2023-03-01" name="release" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#virginia-general-assembly" /><akn:FRBRcountry value="us-va" /><akn:FRBRnumber value="title-35.1" /><akn:FRBRname value="act" /></akn:FRBRWork><akn:FRBRExpression><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-35.1/eng@2023-03-01" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-35.1/eng@2023-03-01" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2023-03-01" name="publication" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#lexisnexis" /><akn:FRBRlanguage language="eng" /></akn:FRBRExpression><akn:FRBRManifestation><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-35.1/eng@2023-03-01/main.xml" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-35.1/eng@2023-03-01/main.xml" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="conversion" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#cosilico" /></akn:FRBRManifestation></akn:identification><akn:references source="#cosilico"><akn:TLCOrganization eId="virginia-general-assembly" href="/ontology/organization/us-va/general-assembly" showAs="Virginia General Assembly" /><akn:TLCOrganization eId="lexisnexis" href="/ontology/organization/lexisnexis" showAs="LexisNexis" /><akn:TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="/ontology/organization/cosilico" showAs="Cosilico" /></akn:references></akn:meta><akn:preface><akn:docTitle>Title 35.1. </akn:docTitle></akn:preface><akn:body><akn:section eId="sec_35.1-1"><akn:num>§ 35.1-1</akn:num><akn:heading>Definitions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text As used in this title, unless the context requires a different meaning: Bed-and-breakfast operation means a residential-type establishment that provides (i) t wo or more rental accommodations for transient guests and food service to a maximum of 18 transient guests on any single day for five or more days in any calendar year or (ii) at least one rental accommodation for transient guests and food service to a m aximum of 18 transient guests on any single day for 30 or more days in any calendar year. Board or State Board means the State Board of Health. Campground means any area, place, parcel, or tract of land, by whatever name called, o n which three or more campsites are occupied or intended for occupancy, or facilities are established or maintained, wholly or in part, for the accommodation of camping units for periods of overnight or longer, whether the use of the campsites and facili ties is granted gratuitously, or by rental fee, lease, or conditional sale, or by covenants, restrictions, and easements, including any travel trailer camp, recreation camp, family campground, camping resort, or camping community. Campground does not mean a summer camp, migrant labor camp, or park for manufactured homes as defined in this section and in §§ 32.1-203 and 36-85.3, or a construction camp, storage area for unoccupied camping units, or property upon which the individual owner ma y choose to camp and not be prohibited or encumbered by covenants, restrictions, and conditions from providing his sanitary facilities within his property lines. Camping unit means any device or vehicular type structure for use as temporary living quarters or shelter during periods of recreation, vacation, leisure time, or travel, including any tent, tent trailer, travel trailer, camping trailer, pickup camper, or motor home. Campsite means any plot of ground within a campground used or intended for occupation by the camping unit. Certified food protection manager means a person who has demonstrated proficiency in f ood safety issues, regulations, and techniques in maintaining a safe-food environment by passing a test and receiving a certification as part of a program that is accredited by the Board. Commissioner means the State Health Commissioner. Department means the State Department of Health. Hotel means any place offering to the public for compensation transitory lodging or sl eeping accommodations, overnight or otherwise, including facilities known by varying nomenclatures or designations as hotels, motels, travel lodges, tourist homes, or hostels. Person means an individual, corporation, partnership, association, or any other legal entity. Restaurant means: 1. Any p lace where food is prepared for service to the public on or off the premises, or any place where food is served, including lunchrooms, short order places, cafeterias, coffee shops, cafes, taverns, delicatessens, dining accommodations of public or private clubs, kitchen facilities of hospitals and nursing homes, dining accommodations of public and private schools and institutions of higher education, and kitchen areas of local correctional facilities subject to standards adopted under § 53.1-68. 2. Any place or operation that prepares or stores food for distribution to persons of the same business operation or of a related business operation for service to the public, including o perations preparing or storing food for catering services, push cart operations, hotdog stands, and other mobile points of service. 3. Mobile points of service to which food is distributed by a place or operation described in subdivision 2 unless the point of service and of consumption is in a private residence.Re staurant does not include any place manufacturing packaged or canned foods that are distributed to grocery stores or other similar retailers for sale to the public.Summer c amp means any building, tent, or vehicle, or group of buildings, tents, or vehicles, if operated as one place or establishment, or any other place or establishment, public or private, together with the land and waters adjacent thereto, that is operated or used in this Commonwealth for the entertainment, education, recreation, religious instruction or activities, physical education, or health of persons under 18 years of age w ho are not related to the operator of such place or establishment by blood or marriage within the third degree of consanguinity or affinity, if 12 or more such persons at any one time are accommodated, gratuitously or for compensation, overnight and duri ng any portion of more than two consecutive days. History History. Code 1950, §§ 35-1, 35-25, 35-43, 35-54; 1960, c. 186; 1964 , c. 327; 1981, c. 468; 1995, c. 797; 2018, c. 450; 2019, c. 275. Annotations Transition provisions. In response to a resolution of the State Board of Health to the Virginia Code Commission, the 1979 General Assembly enacted House Joint Resolution 198, requesting the Code Commission to study and recodify Title 35 of the Code. In January of 1981, the Commission sent to the Governor and General Assembly its report containing a proposed provision of Title 35, Hotels, Restaurants and Camps, of the Code. This report, which was published as House Document No. 11 of the 1981 session, contains revisers notes and other explanatory matter which, while valuable, are too lengthy for inclusion here. The Commissions draft of the revision of Title 35, as amended by th e General Assembly, became c. 468 of the Acts of 1981. Effective October 1, 1981, it repeals Title 35 of the Code and enacts in lieu thereof a new Title 35.1. Acts 1981, c. 468, cls. 5 and 6 provide: 5. That wherever any of the conditions, requirements, provisions, or contents of any section, article, or chapter of Title 35, or any other title of this Code as such titles existed prior to October one, nineteen hundred eighty-one, are transferred in the same or in modified form to a new section, article, or chapter of this title or any other title of this Code and whenever any such former section, article, or chapter is given a new number in this or any other title, all references to any such former section, article, or chapter of Title 35 or other title appearing in this Code shall be construed to apply to the new or renumbered section, article, or chapte r containing such conditions, requirements, provisions, or contents or portion thereof. 6. That the regulations of the State Board of Health in effect on the effective date of this act [Oct. 1, 1981] shall continue in effect to the extent that th ey are not in conflict with this act and shall be deemed to be regulations promulgated under this act. Cross references. As to the applicability of subdivision ordinances to mobile homes, see § 15.2-2247. For provisions as to membership camping, see § 59.1-311 et seq. As to loans to local governments for living shorelines, see § 62.1-229.5. Editors note. At the direction of the Virginia Code Commission, the following changes were made to conform to Acts 2016, c. 588: in subdivision 9 a, substituted institution s of higher education for colleges; and made minor stylistic changes. The 1995 amendment, in subdivision 9 a, in the second sentence, deleted and following nursing homes and inserted and kitchen areas of local correctional facilities subject to standards adopted under § 53.1-68. The 2018 amendments. The 2018 amendment by c. 450 rewrote the section making stylistic changes related to definition sections and adding the definition of Bed-and-breakfast operat ion. The 2019 amendments. The 2019 amendment by c. 275 inserted the definition for Certified food protection manager. Research References. Virginia Forms (Matthew Bender). No. 16-201 Lease Exempt from Virginia Residential Landlord and Tenant Act. Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 9B M.J. Hotels, Inns and Restaurants, §§ 1, 2. OPINIONS OF THE ATTORNEY GENERAL Occasional use.  Infrequent use of a farm building or structure to host concerts, dances or other social gatherings does not constitute a change in occupancy classificatio n and, therefore, does not require the owner to obtain an occupancy permit for the new uses. See opinion of Attorney General to Kevin J. Burke, Esquire, Fauquier County Attorney, 10-071, 2010 Va. AG LEXIS 49 (8/23/10). Food pre pared in home or church for charitable purposes.  A private kitchen in a home or church is not subject to food preparation and service requirements of the State Health Commissioner when the kitchen is used to pre pare food to donate to a charitable organization, where the charitable organization is engaged in a food distribution program for the needy. However, the Board of Health may issue advisory guidelines, which reasonably should be considered by those prepar ing the food. See opinion of Attorney General to The Honorable Mark D. Sickles, Member, Virginia House of Delegates, 15-063, 2016 Va. AG LEXIS 11 (7/22/16). § 35.1-1.1. Certified mail; subsequent mail or notices may be sent by regular mail. Text Whenever in this title the Board, the Commissioner, or the Department is required to send any mail or notice by certified mail and such mail or notice is sent certified mail, return receipt requested, then any subsequent, identical mail or notice that is sent by the Board, the Commissioner, or the Department may be sent by regular mail. History History. 2011, c. 566.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_35.1-2"><akn:num>§ 35.1-2</akn:num><akn:heading>Enforcement</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text This title shall be enforced by the State Board of Health and the State Health Commissioner as executive officer of the Board, acting through duly designated officers. History History. Code 1950, §§ 35-5, 35-17, 35-28; 1981, c. 468.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_35.1-3"><akn:num>§ 35.1-3</akn:num><akn:heading>Commissioner vested with Boards authority</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Commissioner shall be vested with all the authority of the Board pursuant to this title when it is not in session, subject to such rules and regulations as may be p rescribed by the Board. History History. 1981, c. 468.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_35.1-4"><akn:num>§ 35.1-4</akn:num><akn:heading>Applicability of Administrative Process Act</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Administrative Process Act (§ 2.2-4000 et seq.) shall govern the procedures for rendering all case decisions, as defined in § 2.2-4001, and for issuing all or ders and regulations promulgated pursuant to the authority of this title. History History. Code 1950, §§ 35-24, 35-42, 35-52; 1970, c. 273; 1981, c. 4 68. Annotations Editors note. At the direction of the Virginia Code Commission, 2.2-4000 et seq. was substituted for § 2.2-4000 and § 2.2-4001 was substituted for § 2.2-400.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_35.1-5"><akn:num>§ 35.1-5</akn:num><akn:heading>Right of entry to inspect, etc</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>; warrants. Text Upon presentation of appropriate credentials and upon consent of the owner or custodian, the Commissioner or his designee shall have the right to enter at any reasonabl e time onto the premises of any hotel, restaurant, summer camp, or campground to inspect, investigate, evaluate, conduct tests, or take samples for testing as he reasonably deems necessary in order to determine whether any provision of this title, any re gulation of the Board, any order of the Board or Commissioner, or any condition in a license issued by the Board or Commissioner pursuant to this title is being violated. If the Commissioner or his designee is denied entry, he may apply to an appropriate circuit court for an inspection warrant authorizing such investigation, evaluation, inspection, testing, or taking of samples for testing as provided in Chapter 24 (§ 19.2-393 et seq.) of Title 19.2. History History. Code 1950, §§ 35-4, 35-20, 35-27, 35-30; 1981, c. 468.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_35.1-6"><akn:num>§ 35.1-6</akn:num><akn:heading>Orders</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Board is authorized to issue orders to require any person to comply with the provisions of this title or any regulations promulgated by the Board, or to comply with any case decision, as defined in § 2.2-4001, of the Board or Commissioner. Any such order shall be issued only after a hearing with at least thirty days notice to the affected person of the time, place, and purpose thereof. Such order shall become ef fective not less than fifteen days after mailing a copy thereof by certified mail to the last known address of such person. The provisions of this section shall not affect the authority of the Board to issue separate orders and regulations to meet any em ergency as provided in § 35.1-12. History History. 1981, c. 468.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_35.1-7"><akn:num>§ 35.1-7</akn:num><akn:heading>Penalties, injunctions, civil penalties and charges for violations</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. Any person willfully violating, or refusing, failing, or neglecting to comply with any regulation or order of the Board or Commissioner, or any provision of this title, shall be guilty of a Class 3 misdemeanor unless a different penalty is specified. Each day of vi olation shall constitute a separate offense. B. Any person violating, or failing, neglecting, or refusing to obey any lawful regulation or order of the Board or Commissioner, or any provision of this title, may be compelled in a proceeding instituted in an appropriate court by the Board or Commissioner to obey a nd comply with such regulation, order, or provision of this title. The proceeding may be by injunction, mandamus, or other appropriate remedy. C. Without lim iting the remedies which may be obtained pursuant to subsection B, any person violating or failing, neglecting, or refusing to obey any injunction, mandamus, or other remedy obtained pursuant to subsection B shall be subject, in the discretion of the cou rt, to a civil penalty not to exceed $10,000 for each violation. Each day of violation shall constitute a separate offense. D. With the co nsent of any person who has violated or failed, neglected, or refused to obey any regulation or order of the Board or Commissioner or any provision of this title, the Board may provide, in an order issued by the Board against such person, for the payment of civil charges for past violations in specific sums not to exceed the limit set forth in subsection C. Such civil charges shall be in place of any appropriate civil penalty which could be imposed under subsection C. History History. Code 1950, §§ 35-7, 35-21, 35-41, 35-53; 1981, c. 468. Annotations Cross references. As to punishment for Class 3 misdemeanors, see § 18.2-11.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_35.1-8"><akn:num>§ 35.1-8</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1989, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>258.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_35.1-9"><akn:num>§ 35.1-9</akn:num><akn:heading>Local ordinance superseded; exceptions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text This title and the regulations of the Board shall supersede all local ordinances regulating hotels, restaurants, summer camps, and campgrounds other than those adopted pursuant to the provisions of § 35.1-26, except that any locality may adopt ordinances regarding (i) the sale, preparation, and handling of food; (ii) swimming pools, saunas and other similar facilities; (iii) the keeping of guest registers by hotels; and (iv) the display of signs alongside or in plain view of any public roadway to preclude false or misleading advertising thereon to the extent prohibited by § 18.2-217, provided such ordinances are equivalent to or more stringent than the provision s of this title or Title 18.2 in the case of the display of signs alongside or in plain view of any public roadway to preclude false or misleading advertising thereon to the extent prohibited by § 18.2-217, and the regulations of the Board. Nothing in this section shall be construed to limit or affect in any way the powers given to localities under Title 15.2, or under any city charter, or under any other general or special act. History History. 1981, c. 468; 1983, c. 242.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_35.1-10"><akn:num>§ 35.1-10</akn:num><akn:heading>Measures to prevent transmission of disease</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Nothing in this title applicable to restaurants shall prevent the Commissioner from taking whatever action he deems necessary to control the spread of preventable disea ses as set forth in Title 32.1, including but not limited to the exclusion of employees, the medical examination of any employee, the immediate closing of a hotel, restaurant, summer camp, or campground, and the taking of samples for testing. History History. Code 1950, §§ 35-31, 35-40; 1971, Ex. Sess., c. 155; 1981, c. 468; 1993, c. 336. Chapter 2. Regulations. -360§ 35.1-11. Regulations generally. -360§ 35.1-12. Emergency orders and regulations; Commissioner vested with authority of Board. -360§ 35.1-13. Regulations governing hotels. -360§ 35.1-14. Regulations governing restaurants; advisory standards for exempt entities. -360§ 35.1-14.1. Certain uses of sulfiting agents prohibited. -360§ 35.1-14.2. Donations of food to charitable organizations. -360§ 35.1-15. Training materials. -360§ 35.1-15.1. Required human trafficking training. -360§ 35.1-16. Regulations governing summer camps. -360§ 35.1-17. Regulations governing campgrounds.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_35.1-11"><akn:num>§ 35.1-11</akn:num><akn:heading>Regulations generally</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Board shall make, adopt, promulgate, and enforce regulations necessary to carry out the provisions of this title and to protect the public health and safety. In pro mulgating regulations, the Board shall consider the accepted standards of health including the use of precautions to prevent the transmission of communicable diseases, hygiene, sanitation, safety, and physical plant management. History History. 1981, c. 468; 1993, c. 336.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_35.1-12"><akn:num>§ 35.1-12</akn:num><akn:heading>Emergency orders and regulations; Commissioner vested with authority of Board</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Board may make separate orders and regulations to meet any emergency not provided for by general regulations for the purpose of suppressing conditions dangerous to the public health and communicable, contagious, and infectious diseases. History History. 1981, c. 468.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_35.1-13"><akn:num>§ 35.1-13</akn:num><akn:heading>Regulations governing hotels</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Regulations of the Board governing hotels shall provide minimum standards for, but shall not be limited to: (i) food preparation and handling; (ii) physical plant sanit ation; (iii) the provision, storage, and cleansing of linens and towels; (iv) general housekeeping and maintenance practices; (v) requirements for approved water supply and sewage disposal systems; (vi) vector and pest control; (vii) swimming pools, saun as, and other similar facilities, including personnel standards for the operation thereof; (viii) ice machines and dispensers of perishable food items; and (ix) a procedure for obtaining a license. History History. Code 1950, §§ 35-8, 35-9, 35-16, 35-16.1, 35-18; 1956, c. 3 94; 1964, c. 499; 1970, c. 435; 1981, c. 468. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2020, c. 1289, as amended by Acts 2021, Sp. Sess. I, c. 552, Item 302 B, and Acts 2022, Sp. Sess. I, c. 2, Item 294 C, effective for the biennium ending Ju ne 30, 2023, provides: The State Health Commissioner is authorized to develop, in consultation with the regulated entities, a hotel, campground, and summer camp plan and specification review fee, not to exceed $40.00, a restaurant plan and specificat ion review fee, not to exceed $40.00, an annual hotel, campground, and summer camp permit renewal fee, not to exceed $40.00, and an annual restaurant permit renewal fee, not to exceed $40.00 to be collected from all establishments, except K-12 public sch ools, that are subject to inspection by the Department of Health pursuant to §§ 35.1-13, 35.1-14, 35.1-16, and 35.1-17, Code of Virginia. However, any such establishment that is subject to any health permit fee, application fee, inspection fee, risk assessment fee or similar fee imposed by any locality as of January 1, 2002, shall be subject to this annual permit renewal fee only to the extent that the Department of Health fee and the locally imposed fee, when combined, do not exceed the fee a mount listed in this paragraph. This fee structure shall be subject to the approval of the Secretary of Health and Human Resources. Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 9B M.J. Hotels, Inns and Restaurants, § 6.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_35.1-14"><akn:num>§ 35.1-14</akn:num><akn:heading>Regulations governing restaurants; advisory standards for exempt entities</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. Regulations of the Board governing restaurants shall include but not be limited to the following subjects: (i) a procedure for obtaining a license; (ii) the safe and sanitary maintenance, storage, operation, and use of equipment; (iii) the sanitary maintenance and use of a restaurants physical plant; (iv) the safe preparation, handling, protection, and preservation of food, including necessary refrigeration or heating methods; (v) procedures for vector and pest control; (vi) requirements for toilet and cleansi ng facilities for employees and customers; (vii) requirements for appropriate lighting and ventilation not otherwise provided for in the Uniform Statewide Building Code; (viii) requirements for an approved water supply and sewage disposal system; (ix) pe rsonal hygiene standards for employees, particularly those engaged in food handling; (x) the appropriate use of precautions to prevent the transmission of communicable diseases; and (xi) training standards that address food safety and food allergy awaren ess and safety. B. In its regu lations, the Board may classify restaurants by type and specify different requirements for each classification. C. The Board m ay adopt any edition of the Food and Drug Administrations Food Code, or supplement thereto, or any portion thereof, as regulations, with any amendments as it deems appropriate. In addition, the Board may repeal or amend any regulation adopted pursuan t to this subsection. No regulations adopted or amended by the Board pursuant to this subsection, however, shall establish requirements for any license, permit, or inspection unless such license, permit, or inspection is otherwise provided for in this ti tle. The provisions of the Food and Drug Administrations Food Code shall not apply to farmers selling their own farm-produced products directly to consumers for their personal use, whether such sales occur on such farmers farm or at a farmers market, unless such provisions are adopted in accordance with the Administrative Process Act (§ 2.2-4000 et seq.). D. The Board m ay issue advisory standards for the safe preparation, handling, protection, and preservation of food by entities exempt from the provisions of this title pursuant to § 35.1-25 or 35.1-26. E. The provisi ons of the Administrative Process Act (§ 2.2-4000 et seq.) shall not apply to the adoption of any regulation pursuant to subsection C if the Board of Agriculture and Consumer Services adopts the same edition of the Food Code, or the same portions ther eof, pursuant to subsection B of § 3.2-5121 and the regulations adopted by the Board and the Board of Agriculture and Consumer Services have the same effective date. In the event that the Board of Agriculture and Consumer Services adopts regulations p ursuant to § 2.2-4012.1, the effective date of the Boards regulations may be any date on or after the effective date of the regulations adopted by the Board of Agriculture and Consumer Services. Notwithstanding any exemption to the contrary, a regulation promulgated pursuant to subsection C shall be subject to the requirements set out in §§ 2.2-4007.03, 2 .2-4007.04, and 2.2-4007.05, and shall be published in the Virginia Register of Regulations. After the close of the 60-day comment period, the Board may adopt a final regulation, with or without changes. Such regulation shall become effective 15 days aft er publication in the Virginia Register, unless the Board has withdrawn or suspended the regulation, or a later date has been set by the Board. The Board shall also hold at least one public hearing on the proposed regulation during the 60-day comment per iod. The notice for such public hearing shall include the date, time and place of the hearing. F. The Board s hall adopt regulations pursuant to subsection C that allow the receipt for sale or service of rabbits that are slaughtered or processed in a facility that complies with regulations adopted by the Board of Agriculture and Consumer Services pursuant to the provisions of subsection H of § 3.2-5121. G. Regulations adopted by the Board pursuant to this section shall not require an establishment that sells only prepared foods to have a certified food protection manager, as defined in § 35.1-1, on site during all hours of operation. History History. Code 1950, §§ 35-28, 35-32, 35-33, 35-34, 35-35, 35-36, 35- 37; 1981, c. 468; 1993, c. 336; 2003, c. 695; 2004, c. 802; 2007, cc. 873, 916; 2015, cc. 356, 528; 2018, c. 674; 2022, c. 393. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2004, c. 802, cl. 2 provides: That the Rules and Regulations Pertaining to the Sanitary and Operating Procedures in Retail Food Stores adopted by the Bo ard of Agriculture and Consumer Services in effect as of July 1, 2004, shall remain in effect until the effective date of new regulations that have been adopted by the Board of Agriculture and Consumer Services pursuant to subsection B of § 3.1-398.  Effective October 1, 2008, in subsection E, the reference to subsection B of § 3.1-398 was changed to subsection B of § 3.2-5121 at the di rection of the Code Commission to reflect the recodification of Title 3.1. Acts 2020, c. 1289, as amended by Acts 2021, Sp. Sess. I, c. 552, Item 302 B, and Acts 2022, Sp. Sess. I, c. 2, Item 294 C, effective for the biennium ending Ju ne 30, 2023, provides: The State Health Commissioner is authorized to develop, in consultation with the regulated entities, a hotel, campground, and summer camp plan and specification review fee, not to exceed $40.00, a restaurant plan and specificat ion review fee, not to exceed $40.00, an annual hotel, campground, and summer camp permit renewal fee, not to exceed $40.00, and an annual restaurant permit renewal fee, not to exceed $40.00 to be collected from all establishments, except K-12 public sch ools, that are subject to inspection by the Department of Health pursuant to §§ 35.1-13, 35.1-14, 35.1-16, and 35.1-17, Code of Virginia. However, any such establishment that is subject to any health permit fee, application fee, inspection fee, risk assessment fee or similar fee imposed by any locality as of January 1, 2002, shall be subject to this annual permit renewal fee only to the extent that the Department of Health fee and the locally imposed fee, when combined, do not exceed the fee a mount listed in this paragraph. This fee structure shall be subject to the approval of the Secretary of Health and Human Resources. The 2003 amendments. The 2003 amendment by c. 695 redesignated former subsection C as present subsection D and added present subsections C and E. The 2004 amendments. The 2004 amendment by c. 802 in subsection C, substituted The Board may adopt any edition of the Food and Drug Administrations Food Code, or supplement t hereto, or any portion thereof, as regulations, with any amendments as it deems appropriate, for The Board may adopt the Food and Drug Administrations Food Code, or portions thereof, amending or modifying it as necessary, within 280 days of the release of the most current Food Code, or any amendments thereto, issued by the Food and Drug Administration, added the second sentence and inserted or amended in the third sentence; and in subsection E, deleted within the same 280-da y period in the first sentence, added the language beginning and the regulations adopted at the end of the first paragraph. The 2007 amendments. The 2007 amendments by cc. 873 and 916 are identical, substituted §§ 2.2-4007.03, 2.2-4007.04, and 2.2-4007.05 for subsections F, H, and I of § 2.2-4007 in the final paragraph and made a minor stylistic change. The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendments by cc. 356 and 528 are identical, and added clause (xi) of subdivision A and made related changes. The 2018 amendments. The 2018 amendment by c. 674 added subsection F. The 2022 amendments. The 2022 amendment by c. 393 added subsection G. § 35.1-14.1. Certain uses of sulfiting agents prohibited. Text The use of sulfiting agents as preservatives on raw fruits and vegetables is prohibited. No restaurant licensed under this title shall direct or allow its employees or agents to apply sulfiting agents on raw fruits and vegetables prepared for or served to the public. History History. 1986, c. 200. § 35.1-14.2. Donations of food to charitable organizations. Text A. Any restaur ant, licensed by the Department of Health pursuant to this title and any processor, distributor, wholesaler or retailer of food, including, but not limited to, a grocery, convenience, or other store selling food or food products, may donate unserved exce ss foods to any charity organization that is exempt from taxation under. § 501(c)(3) of the Internal Revenue Code, and to political subdivisions for distribution to needy persons. Charitable organizations engaged in food distribution programs for need y persons shall notify the local political subdivision of their programs. Upon the notification of such food distribution programs by such charitable organizations, the local political subdivision shall provide a list of such charitable organizations wit hin its jurisdiction to those restaurants and other food suppliers who request such information. Organizations engaged in such food distribution programs shall be exempt from civil liability as provided in § 3.2-5144 for the donors of the food. B. Charitable organizations engaged in food distribution programs for needy persons shall be deemed exempt from state and local regulations and local ordinances that govern food service and preparation. In addition to accepting donations of food as provided in subsect ion A, such organizations may accept food prepared by their employees or volunteers in private homes or in facilities not otherwise licensed as provided in this chapter. For the purposes of this subsection, charitable organizations shall include nonprofit homeless shelters and hunger prevention programs. C. No food don or or food organization, as defined in § 3.2-5144, ...</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_35.1-15"><akn:num>§ 35.1-15</akn:num><akn:heading>Training materials</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Commissioner shall cause to be written materials designed to provide information on training for the prevention of disease transmission, symptoms of communicable di sease, personal hygiene practices, hazards in food preparation, food safety and food allergy awareness and safety, and any other matter deemed appropriate by the Commissioner for the training of restaurant personnel. The Commissioner may, if he desires, provide personnel for the training of employees of restaurants in the handling of food. History History. 1981, c. 468; 2015, cc. 356, 528. Annotations The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendments by cc. 356 and 528 are identical, and inserted food safety and food allergy awareness and safety in the first sentence. § 35.1-15.1. Required human trafficking training. Text A. As used in this section: Employee means any person employed by a hotel that (i) has frequent or regular interac tions with guests, such as front desk staff, hotel porters, hotel concierge, restaurant waiting and bartending staff, or room service staff; (ii) is in a management position; or (iii) has access to the guests room, including housekeeping staff. Hotel does not include a short-term rental property as defined in § 58.1-3510.4. B. Every hotel proprietor shall require its employees to complete a training course on recognizing and reporting instances of suspected human trafficking. Such training course shall be an online course provided by the Department of Criminal Justice Services at no cost to the hotel proprietor and its employees pursuant to § 9.1-102 or an alternative online or in-person training course approved by the Department of Criminal Justice Services. The Department of Criminal Justice Services shall approve or disapprove of the use of any alternative online or in-person training course within 60 days of the submission of such training course for approval. C. Each hotel employee shall complete the required training course described in subsection B within six months of being employed by a hotel and thereafter at least once during each consecutive period of two calendar years commencing with the date on which he last comp leted the required training course, for as long as he is employed by a hotel. History History. 2022, c. 751. Annotations Editor's note. Acts 2022, c. 751, cl. 3 provides: That, notwithstanding subsection C of § 35.1-15.1 of the Code of Virginia, as created by this act, any individual empl oyed by a hotel as of January 1, 2023, shall complete the required training course on recognizing and reporting instances of suspected human trafficking no later than June 30, 2023. Acts 2022, c. 751, cl. 4 provides: That the provisions of this act shall become effective on January 1, 2023.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_35.1-16"><akn:num>§ 35.1-16</akn:num><akn:heading>Regulations governing summer camps</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The regulations of the Board governing summer camps shall include, but not be limited to: (i) an approved drinking water supply; (ii) an approved sewage disposal system ; (iii) an approved solid waste disposal system; (iv) the adequate and sanitary preparation, handling, protection and preservation of food; (v) the proper maintenance of buildings, grounds, and equipment; (vi) vector and pest control; (vii) toilet, swimm ing, and bathing facilities, including shower facilities; (viii) a procedure for obtaining a license. History History. Code 1950, §§ 35-45, 35-46, 35-47, 35-48, 35-49; 1981, c. 4 68. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2020, c. 1289, as amended by Acts 2021, Sp. Sess. I, c. 552, Item 302 B, and Acts 2022, Sp. Sess. I, c. 2, Item 294 C, effective for the biennium ending Ju ne 30, 2023: The State Health Commissioner is authorized to develop, in consultation with the regulated entities, a hotel, campground, and summer camp plan and specification review fee, not to exceed $40.00, a restaurant plan and specification review fee, not to exceed $40.00, an annual hotel, campground, and summer camp permit renewal fee, not to exceed $40.00, and an annual restaurant permit renewal fee, not to exceed $40.00 to be collected from all establishments, except K-12 public schools, that are subject to inspection by the Department of Health pursuant to §§ 35.1-13, 35.1-14, 35.1-16, and 35.1-17, Code of Virginia. However, any such establishment that is subject to any health permit fee, application fee, inspection fee, risk asse ssment fee or similar fee imposed by any locality as of January 1, 2002, shall be subject to this annual permit renewal fee only to the extent that the Department of Health fee and the locally imposed fee, when combined, do not exceed the fee amount list ed in this paragraph. This fee structure shall be subject to the approval of the Secretary of Health and Human Resources.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_35.1-17"><akn:num>§ 35.1-17</akn:num><akn:heading>Regulations governing campgrounds</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. The regulat ions of the Board governing campgrounds shall include minimum standards for (i) an approved drinking water supply; (ii) an approved sewage disposal system; (iii) an approved solid waste disposal system; (iv) the proper maintenance of buildings, grounds, and equipment; (v) vector and pest control; (vi) toilet, swimming, and bathing facilities, including shower facilities; (vii) effective measures for the control of animals and pets; (viii) appropriate procedures and safeguards for hazardous situations, i ncluding specifically the maintenance and sale of propane gas or other explosives and combustibles; and (ix) a procedure for obtaining a license. B. The Board m ay in its sole discretion prescribe regulations for classes of campgrounds and different requirements for each class. History History. Code 1950, § 35-55; 1981, c. 468. Annotations Cross references. For provisions as to membership camping, see § 59.1-311 et seq. Editors note. Acts 2020, c. 1289, as amended by Acts 2021, Sp. Sess. I, c. 552, Item 302 B, and Acts 2022, Sp. Sess. I, c. 2, Item 294 C, effective for the biennium ending Ju ne 30, 2023, provides: The State Health Commissioner is authorized to develop, in consultation with the regulated entities, a hotel, campground, and summer camp plan and specification review fee, not to exceed $40.00, a restaurant plan and specificat ion review fee, not to exceed $40.00, an annual hotel, campground, and summer camp permit renewal fee, not to exceed $40.00, and an annual restaurant permit renewal fee, not to exceed $40.00 to be collected from all establishments, except K-12 public sch ools, that are subject to inspection by the Department of Health pursuant to §§ 35.1-13, 35.1-14, 35.1-16, and 35.1-17, Code of Virginia. However, any such establishment that is subject to any health permit fee, application fee, inspection fee, risk assessment fee or similar fee imposed by any locality as of January 1, 2002, shall be subject to this annual permit renewal fee only to the extent that the Department of Health fee and the locally imposed fee, when combined, do not exceed the fee a mount listed in this paragraph. This fee structure shall be subject to the approval of the Secretary of Health and Human Resources. Chapter 3. Licenses; Inspections. -360§ 35.1-18. License required; name in which issued; not assignable or transferable. -360§ 35.1-19. Person deemed responsible for campground. -360§ 35.1-20. Issuance and denial of licenses. -360§ 35.1-21. Display of hotel, restaurant, summer camp, and campground licenses. -360§ 35.1-22. Periodic inspections. -360§ 35.1-23. State institutions with dining accommodations to request inspections. -360§ 35.1-24. Advice and assistance to applicants for hotel and restaurant licenses.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_35.1-18"><akn:num>§ 35.1-18</akn:num><akn:heading>License required; name in which issued; not assignable or transferable</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text No person shall own, establish, conduct, maintain, manage, or operate any hotel, restaurant, summer camp, or campground in this Commonwealth unless the hotel, restauran t, summer camp, or campground is licensed as provided in this chapter. The license shall be in the name of the owner or lessee. No license issued hereunder shall be assignable or transferable. The Board shall not issue a license to the owner or lessee of any hotel, summer camp or campground in this Commonwealth that maintains, or conducts as any part of its activities, a nudist camp for juveniles. A nudist camp for juveniles is defined to be a hotel, summer camp or campground that is attended by openly nude juveniles whose parent, grandparent, or legal guardian is not also registered for and present with the juvenile at the same camp. History History. Code 1950, §§ 35-22, 35-26, 35-44; 1981, c. 468; 2004, c. 9 87. Annotations Cross references. As to the applicability of subdivision ordinances to mobile homes, see § 15.2-2247. As to dual licenses for certain day centers which also meet the requirements for a license as a summer camp under § 35.1-18, see § 63.2-1810. Editors note. Acts 1995, c. 639, cl. 1 provides: § 2. Exemptions to licensure requirements of restaurants. Notwithstanding the provisions of Chapters 3 (§ 35.1-18 et seq.) and 4 (§ 35.1-25 et seq.) of Title 35.1, the requirements for the licensure of restaura nts shall not apply to community centers when holding occasional dinners and bazaars of one or two days duration, at which food prepared in the homes of members or in the kitchen of the community center is offered for sale to the public. The 2004 amendments. The 2004 amendment by c. 987 added the last two sentences. Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 9B M.J. Hotels, Inns and Restaurants, § 3. CASE NOTES Section does not authorize state officials to control management of restaurant.  This section is obviously designed to protect the health of the community but it does not authorize state officials to control the management of the business or t o dictate what persons shall be served. Williams v. Howard Johnson's Restaurant, 268 F.2d 845, 1959 U.S. App. LEXIS 3494 (4th Cir. 1959) (decided under former § 35-26).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_35.1-19"><akn:num>§ 35.1-19</akn:num><akn:heading>Person deemed responsible for campground</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text In the event that the Commissioner or his designee cannot establish which person is responsible for a campground, the owner of the parcel of land upon which the campgro und lies shall be deemed to be the person responsible for obtaining a license and meeting the requirements of this title and the applicable rules and regulations for retaining a license. History History. 1981, c. 468.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_35.1-20"><akn:num>§ 35.1-20</akn:num><akn:heading>Issuance and denial of licenses</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Commissioner shall issue a license for each hotel, restaurant, summer camp, and campground which, after inspection, is found to be in compliance with all applicable regulations and provisions of this title. The Commissioner shall notify by certified mail any applicant denied a license of the reasons for such denial. History History. 1981, c. 468.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_35.1-21"><akn:num>§ 35.1-21</akn:num><akn:heading>Display of hotel, restaurant, summer camp, and campground licenses</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. As used in this section, mobile food unit means a restaurant that is mounted on wheels and readily moveable from place to place at all times during operation. B. The license of each hotel, restaurant, summer camp, and campground issued pursuant to this chapter shall be prominently displayed. C. The Departm ent shall issue a license in the form of a sticker to a restaurant that is a mobile food unit that meets the requirements of this chapter, which license shall be prominently displayed on the mobile food unit. History History. Code 1950, § 35-26; 1981, c. 468; 2017, c. 281. Annotations Cross references. As to license requirements for mobile food units, see § 58.1-3715.1. The 2017 amendments. The 2017 amendment by c. 281 designated the existing language as subsection B, and added subsections A and C.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_35.1-22"><akn:num>§ 35.1-22</akn:num><akn:heading>Periodic inspections</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Commissioner shall cause each restaurant, summer camp, and campground in the Commonwealth to be inspected at least annually, with no more than 12 months elapsing be tween each such inspection, in accordance with applicable provisions of this title and the regulations of the Board. However, no restaurant, summer camp, or campground shall receive additional inspections until all other restaurants, summer camps, or cam pgrounds in that locality, as defined in § 15.2-102, respectively, have also been inspected, unless the additional inspections are (i) necessary to follow up on a preoperational inspection or one or more violations; (ii) required by a uniformly applie d risk-based schedule established by the Department; (iii) necessary to investigate a complaint regarding the restaurant, summer camp, or campground; or (iv) otherwise deemed necessary by the Commissioner or his designee to protect the health and safety of the public. The Commissioner, as he deems appropriate, shall cause each hotel in the Commonwealth to be inspected in accordance with applicable provisions of this title and the reg ulations of the Board. However, no hotel shall receive additional inspections until all other hotels in that locality, as defined in § 15.2-102, have also been inspected, unless the additional inspections are (a) necessary to follow up on a preoperati onal inspection or one or more violations, (b) required by a uniformly applied risk-based schedule established by the Department, (c) necessary to investigate a complaint regarding the hotel, or (d) otherwise deemed necessary by the Commissioner or his d esignee to protect the health and safety of the public. If at any time the Commissioner finds that a hotel, restaurant, summer camp, or campground is not in compliance with applicable provisions of this title or regulations of the Board, he may revoke or suspend the license of that hotel, restaurant, summer camp, or campground. History History. Code 1950, §§ 35-4, 35-6, 35-7, 35-15, 35-23, 35-46, 35-47, 35-51, 35-56; 1981, c. 468; 1996, cc. 200, 834; 2016, c. 581; 2017, c. 465. Annotations The 1996 amendments. The 1996 amendments by cc. 200 and 834 are identical, and deleted hotel preceding restaurant in the first sentence and added the present second se ntence. The 2016 amendments. The 2016 amendment by c. 581 substituted at least annually, with no more than 12 months elapsing between each such inspection for periodically, but no t less often than annually in the first sentence. The 2017 amendments. The 2017 amendment by c. 465 added the second sentence in the first and second paragraphs. OPINIONS OF THE ATTORNEY GENERAL Food pre pared in home or church for charitable purposes.  A private kitchen in a home or church is not subject to food preparation and service requirements of the State Health Commissioner when the kitchen is used to pre pare food to donate to a charitable organization, where the charitable organization is engaged in a food distribution program for the needy. However, the Board of Health may issue advisory guidelines, which reasonably should be considered by those prepar ing the food. See opinion of Attorney General to The Honorable Mark D. Sickles, Member, Virginia House of Delegates, 15-063, 2016 Va. AG LEXIS 11 (7/22/16).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_35.1-23"><akn:num>§ 35.1-23</akn:num><akn:heading>State institutions with dining accommodations to request inspections</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The head of every state institution with dining accommodations shall request the Commissioner to inspect such dining accommodations not less often than annually. Upon r eceipt of any such request, the Commissioner shall cause the dining accommodations to be so inspected and a report to be filed with the institution. History History. 1981, c. 468.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_35.1-24"><akn:num>§ 35.1-24</akn:num><akn:heading>Advice and assistance to applicants for hotel and restaurant licenses</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Commissioner may provide for consultative advice and assistance, within such limitations and restrictions as he deems proper, to any person who applies for a licens e provided for in this chapter. History History. 1981, c. 468. Chapter 4. Exemptions. -360§ 35.1-25. Exemptions. -360§ 35.1-26. Cities, counties, and towns may by ordinance exempt certain fairs.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_35.1-25"><akn:num>§ 35.1-25</akn:num><akn:heading>Exemptions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. The provisi ons of this title applicable to restaurants shall not apply to: 1. Board inghouses that do not accommodate transients; 2. Cafeterias operated by industrial plants for employees only; 3. Churches; fraternal or school organizations; organizations that are exempt from taxation under § 501(c)(3) of the Internal Revenue Code; and volunteer fire departments and volunteer emergency medical services agencies that hold occasional dinners, bazaars, and other fund-raisers of one or two days duration, at which food (i) prepared in the homes of members; (ii) prepared in the kitchen of the church, school, or organization; o r (iii) purchased or donated from a restaurant licensed pursuant to Chapter 3 (§ 35.1-18 et seq.) is offered for sale to the public. Restaurants licensed pursuant to Chapter 3 that donate or sell food to the entities identified in this subdivision sha ll not be required to apply for any additional permits from, or pay any additional permit application fees to, the Department for the proposed occasional dinner, bazaar, or other fundraiser; 4. Grocery stores, including the delicatessen portion that is a part of a grocery store selling exclusively for off-premises consumption, and places manufacturing or selling packaged or c anned goods; 5. Churches that serve meals consisting of food prepared in the homes of members or in the kitchen of the church or purchased or donated from a restaurant licensed pursuant to Chapter 3 ( § 35.1-18 et seq.) for their members or their invited guests; 6. Convenience stores or gas stations that are subject to the Department of Agriculture and Consumer Services Retail Food Establishment Regulations or any regulations subsequently ado pted and that (i) have 15 or fewer seats at which food is served to the public on the premises of the convenience store or gas station and (ii) are not associated with a national or regional restaurant chain. Notwithstanding this exemption, such convenie nce stores or gas stations shall remain responsible for collecting any applicable local meals tax; 7. Concession stands at youth athletic activities, if such stands are promoted or sponsored by a youth athletic association or by any charitable nonprofit organization or group thereof th at has been recognized as being a part of the recreational program of the political subdivision where the association or organization is located by an ordinance or resolution of such political subdivision; or 8. Any bed-and-breakfast operation that prepares food for and offers food to guests, regardless of the time the food is prepared and offered, if (i) the premises of the bed-and-breakfast operation is a home that is owner occupied or owner-agent occupied, (ii) the bed-and-breakfast operation prepares food for and offers food to transient guests of the bed and breakfast only, (iii) the number of guests served by the bed-and-breakfast opera tion does not exceed 18 on any single day, and (iv) guests for whom food is prepared and to whom food is offered are informed in a manner established by the Board in regulations that the food is prepared in a kitchen that is not licensed as a restaurant and is not subject to regulations governing restaurants. B. No regulati on issued by the Board shall require any restaurant that is operated by (i) a nonprofit civic service organization, (ii) a volunteer fire department, or (iii) a volunteer emergency medical services agency to employ a certified food protection manager. History History. Code 1950, § 35-38; 1962, c. 629; 1972, c. 493; 1981, c. 468; 1982, c. 51; 1993, c. 201; 2004, c. 227; 2010, cc. 86, 594; 2013, cc. 188, 317, 512; 2015, cc. 502, 503; 2018, c. 450; 2019, c. 275. Annotations Editors note. Acts 1995, c. 639, cl. 1 provides: § 2. Exemptions to licensure requirements of restaurants. Notwithstanding the provisions of Chapters 3 (§ 35.1-18 et seq.) and 4 (§ 35.1-25 et seq.) of Title 35.1, the requirements for the licensure of restaura nts shall not apply to community centers when holding occasional dinners and bazaars of one or two days duration, at which food prepared in the homes of members or in the kitchen of the community center is offered for sale to the public. The 2004 amendments. The 2004 amendment by c. 227 added subdivision 6; and made a minor stylistic change. The 2010 amendments. The 2010 amendments by cc. 86 and 594 are identical, and in subdivision 5, inserted consisting of food prepared in the homes of members or in the kitchen of t he church and substituted or their invited guests for as a regular part of their religious observances. The 2013 amendments. The 2013 amendments by cc. 188 and 317 are identical, and substituted that for which in subdivisions 3 through 5; substituted fund-raisers for fund raisers in subdivision 3; added subdivision 7; and made related changes. The 2013 amendment by c. 512 rewrote subdivision 3 which read: Churches, fraternal, school and social organizations, and volunteer fire departments and rescue squads which hold occasional dinners, bazaars, and other fund raisers of one or two days duration, at which food prepared in the homes of members or in the kitchen of the church, school or organization is offered for sale to the public; substitu ted that for which in subdivisions 4 and 5; inserted or purchased or donated from a restaurant licensed pursuant to Chapter 3 (§ 35.1-18 et seq.) in subdivision 5; in subdivision 6, deleted Rules and Regulations Pertaining to the Sanitary and Operating Procedures in following Consumer Services and substituted Establishment Regulations for Stores. The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendments by cc. 502 and 503 are identical, and substituted volunteer emergency medical services agencies for rescue squads in subdivisi on 3. The 2018 amendments. The 2018 amendment by c. 450 added subdivision 8 and made related changes. The 2019 amendments. The 2019 amendment by c. 275 designated the existing provisions as subsection A and added subsection B.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_35.1-26"><akn:num>§ 35.1-26</akn:num><akn:heading>Cities, counties, and towns may by ordinance exempt certain fairs</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The governing body of any county, city, or town may provide by ordinance that this title shall not apply to: 1. Food booths at fairs, if such booths are promoted or sponsored by any political subdivision of the Commonwealth or by any charitable nonprofit organization or group thereof. The ordinance shall provide that the health officer of the county, city, or town in which the fair or activity is held, or a qualified person designated by him, shall e xercise such supervision of the sale of food as the ordinance may prescribe. History History. Code 1950, § 35-38.1; 1964, c. 462; 1981, c. 468; 1983, c. 251 ; 2011, c. 465; 2013, cc. 188, 317, 512. Annotations The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendment by c. 465 added subdivision 3. The 2013 amendments. The 2013 amendments by cc. 188 and 317 are identical, and deleted former subdivision 2, which read: Concession stands at youth athletic activities, if such st ands are promoted or sponsored by either a youth athletic association or by any charitable nonprofit organization or group thereof which has been recognized as being a part of the recreational program of the political subdivision where the association or organization is located by an ordinance or resolution of such political subdivision; and redesignated former subdivision 3 as subdivision 2. The 2013 amendment by c. 512 deleted former subdivision 3, which read: Organizations that are exempt from taxation under § 501(c)(3) of the Internal Revenu e Code that hold occasional fund-raisers for the duration of the event at which food is prepared by such organization and is offered for sale to the public. Chapter 5. Posting Hotel Rates; Hotel Liability. -360§ 35.1-27. Posting of rates. -360§ 35.1-28. Liability.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_35.1-27"><akn:num>§ 35.1-27</akn:num><akn:heading>Posting of rates</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Every hotel shall post in a conspicuous place in its office a list of the ranges of the charges for its rooms and shall post in each guests room the maximum charge for that room. If the hotel is operated on the American or modified American plan, the notice shall contain the maximum charge for the room and the number of meals provided. History History. Code 1950, § 35-2; 1981, c. 468.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_35.1-28"><akn:num>§ 35.1-28</akn:num><akn:heading>Liability</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. It shall be the duty of any person owning or operating a hotel to exercise due care and diligence in providing honest and competent employees and to take reasonable precautions to protect the persons and property of the guests of the hotel. No hotel shall be held l iable in a sum greater than $300 for the loss of any wearing apparel, baggage, or other property not hereinafter mentioned belonging to a guest when such loss takes place from the room or rooms occupied by the guest. Unless the loss shall take place from the office of the hotel after the valuables are deposited there, no hotel shall be liable for any loss by any guest of jewelry, money, or other valuables of like nature belonging to any guest if the hotel shall have posted in the room or rooms of the gu est in a conspicuous place, and in the office of the hotel, a notice stating that jewelry, money, and other valuables of like nature must be deposited in the office of the hotel. The hotel shall not be obligated to receive from any one guest for deposit in such office any property hereinbefore described exceeding a total value of $500. B. Each guest s room shall have suitable locks on its doors and windows unless permanently secured. If a guest fails to lock the doors or windows of his room, the hotel shall not be liable for any property taken from the room in consequence of such failure on the part of the guest. The burden of proof shall be upon the operator of the hotel to show that he complied with the provisions of this section and that the guest failed to comply with these requirements. C. In the case of loss by fire or overwhelming disaster, a hotel shall exercise ordinary and reasonable care in the custody of the baggage or other property of its guests, but in no case shall the hotels liability exceed $250 to any one guest unless the negligence of the hotel was the cause of the fire or overwhelming disaster. D. No liabilit y shall attach to any hotel for the baggage, hats, umbrellas, coats, or other wearing apparel of a guest until the same is placed by the guest in the actual custody of an employee of the hotel. The mere depositing of such baggage, hats, umbrellas, coats, or other wearing apparel inside the hotel shall not be construed as putting in actual custody until taken in charge by the hotel or its employee, or properly placed in a room or rooms assigned to the guest. E. Nothing con tained in this section shall be construed so as to change or alter the principles of law concerning a hotels liability to a guest or other person for personal injury, nor to exempt in anywise the owner or operator of a hotel from being liable for the value of any property of guests taken or stolen from any room therein by any employee or agent of the hotel. F. A notice of the provisions of this section shall be posted conspicuously in each guests room. History History. Code 1950, §§ 35-10, 35-11, 35-12, 35-13; 1981, c. 468. Annotations Research References. Virginia Forms (Matthew Bender). No. 1-209 Complaint against Hotel  Injury to Guest. Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 9B M.J. Hotels, Inns and Restaurants, §§ 7, 8. CASE NOTES Editors note. Many of the cases cited in the notes under this section were decided under former § 35-10. Statutes such as this section are enacted for the benefit of the innkeeper and, in order to bring himself within the limitation of liability, he must comply with the statute. Sagman v. Richmond Hotels, Inc., 138 F. Supp. 407, 1956 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 3772 (D. Va. 1956). Compliance with the statutory requirement results in protection of the innkeeper against liability beyond the statutory provisions. Sagman v. Richmond Hotels, Inc., 138 F. Supp. 407, 1956 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 3772 (D. Va. 1956). Classification of hotel owners -operators.  Hotel owner-operator who operates a bar or restaurant for the accommodation of its guests and the general public may be an innkeeper as to some of the patrons, an d a business invitor as to the others. Wise v. United States, 8 F. Supp. 2d 535, 1998 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 8737 (E.D. Va. 1998). Duty of hotel owners and operators.  Subsection A does not impose duty on hotel owners and operators to protect guests against unforeseeable, intentional criminal acts of third persons. Rather, subse ction A serves as a means of protecting guests from negligent acts by the hotel and maybe even criminal acts by hotel employees. Wise v. United States, 8 F. Supp. 2d 535, 1998 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 8737 (E.D. Va. 1998). No liability for cri minal assault by third party.  In a suit brought by a guest to recover for personal injuries he sustained when he was shot multiple times on an innkeepers property, the trial court properly sustained the innkeepers demurrer to the guests claim, because the duty of care owed by an innkeeper with respect to protecting a guest from criminal assault by a third party is not governed by § 35.1-28 but remains governed by the common law . Taboada v. Daly Seven, Inc., 271 Va. 313, 626 S.E.2d 428, 2006 Va. LEXIS 30 (2006) (reversing Taboada v. Daly Seven, Inc., 2004 Va. Cir. LEXIS 209, 65 Va. Cir. 336 (Roanoke 2004)). Liability of innkeeper under implied warranty.  Although there may be no liability for an innkeeper under this section, a guest may be entitled to succeed in Virginia on an implied warranty, negligence aside. I t is but a fair placement of the innkeepers responsibility to a guest under his roof. Schnitzer v. Nixon, 439 F.2d 940, 1971 U.S. App. LEXIS 11251 (4th Cir. 1971). But see Ely v. Blevins, 706 F.2d 479, 1983 U.S. App. LEXIS 28292 (4th Cir. 1983). Guest injured while using unlighted hallway.  In the absence of request for and refusal of lights in the hallway of a hotel, or of some condition absolving a guest from making such request, or justifying the use of the hall while it is in utter darkness, the hotelkeeper is not liable for injuries received by a guest through falling down steps while groping his way through a dark and unlighted passageway in the hotel, and a declaration stating such a case is bad on demurrer, as it shows such contributory negligence on the part of the plaintiff as bars a recovery. Baker v. Butterworth, 119 Va. 402, 89 S.E. 849, 1916 Va. LEXIS 115 (1916). Inquiry as to value of property re ceived.  The duty is upon the innkeeper to make inquiry concerning the value of property received for safekeeping from a guest. He may, at his option, decline to accept re sponsibility under this section or he may require, as a condition, permission to examine it and satisfy himself as to value. Should he fail to make such inquiry, he does so at his own risk and is liable for resulting loss, depending upon proper proof, an d his liability is not limited to $500. Sagman v. Richmond Hotels, Inc., 138 F. Supp. 407, 1956 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 3772 (D. Va. 1956).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section></akn:body></akn:act></akn:akomaNtoso>