<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akn:akomaNtoso xmlns:akn="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><akn:act><akn:meta><akn:identification source="#cosilico"><akn:FRBRWork><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-40.1" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-40.1" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2023-03-01" name="release" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#virginia-general-assembly" /><akn:FRBRcountry value="us-va" /><akn:FRBRnumber value="title-40.1" /><akn:FRBRname value="act" /></akn:FRBRWork><akn:FRBRExpression><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-40.1/eng@2023-03-01" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-40.1/eng@2023-03-01" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2023-03-01" name="publication" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#lexisnexis" /><akn:FRBRlanguage language="eng" /></akn:FRBRExpression><akn:FRBRManifestation><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-40.1/eng@2023-03-01/main.xml" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-40.1/eng@2023-03-01/main.xml" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="conversion" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#cosilico" /></akn:FRBRManifestation></akn:identification><akn:references source="#cosilico"><akn:TLCOrganization eId="virginia-general-assembly" href="/ontology/organization/us-va/general-assembly" showAs="Virginia General Assembly" /><akn:TLCOrganization eId="lexisnexis" href="/ontology/organization/lexisnexis" showAs="LexisNexis" /><akn:TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="/ontology/organization/cosilico" showAs="Cosilico" /></akn:references></akn:meta><akn:preface><akn:docTitle>Title 40.1. </akn:docTitle></akn:preface><akn:body><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-1"><akn:num>§ 40.1-1</akn:num><akn:heading>Department continued; powers and duties generally; delegation of authority concerning occupational health</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Department of Labor and Industry, hereinafter referred to as the Department, is continued as a department of the state government; the Department shall be responsib le for discharging the provisions of Title 40.1. All powers and duties conferred and imposed on the Bureau of Labor and Industry by any other law are hereby conferred upon and vested in the Department of Labor and Industry. The Department shall be respon sible for administering and enforcing occupational safety and occupational health activities as required by the Federal Occupational Safety and Health Act of 1970 (P.L. 91-596), in accordance with the state plan for enforcement of that act; however, noth ing in the occupational safety and health provisions of this title or regulations adopted hereunder shall apply to working conditions of employees or duties of employers with respect to which the Federal Occupational Safety and Health Act of 1970 does no t apply by virtue of § 4(b)(1) of the federal act. History History. Code 1950, § 40-1; 1962, c. 66; 1970, c. 321; 1972, c. 567; 19 73, c. 425; 1979, c. 354; 1984, c. 590; 1985, c. 449; 1995, c. 373. Annotations Cross references. As to the exemption of regulations adopted under this section from the Administrative Process Act, see § 2.2-4006. Transition provisions. At its regular session of 1968 the General Assembly directed the Code Commission to revise certain titles of the Code, including Title 40, relating to labor and e mployment. In August of 1969 the Commission sent to the Governor and General Assembly its report containing the proposed revision of Title 40, which was published as House Document 4 of the 1970 session. This report contains revisors notes and other explanatory matter which, while valuable, are too lengthy for inclusion here. The Commissions draft of the revision of Title 40, as amended by the General Assembly, became chapter 321 of the Acts of 1970. It repeals Title 40 of the Code and enacts in lieu thereof a new Title 40.1. As required by § 30-152, the Code Commission has incorporated in Title 40.1 the amendments to Title 40 enacted at the 1970 session of the General Assembly. Some of the cases cited in the notes under the various sections of this title were decided under corresponding provisions of former law. Acts 1970, c. 321, cls. 2-5, provide as follows: 2. All acts and parts of acts, all sections of the Code of Virginia, and all provisions of municipal charters inconsistent with the provisions of this act are , except as otherwise provided, repealed to the extent of such inconsistency. 3. The repeal of Title 40 effective October 1, 1970, shall not affect any act or offense done or committed, or any penalty or forfeiture incurred, or any righ t established, accrued or accruing on or before such date, or any prosecution, suit or action pending on that date. Except as in this act otherwise provided, neither the repeal of Title 40 nor the enactment of Title 40.1 shall apply to offenses committed prior to October 1, 1970, and prosecutions for such offenses shall be governed by the prior law, which is continued in effect for that purpose. For the purposes of this act, an offense was committed prior to October 1, 1969, if any of the essential elem ents of the offense occurred prior thereto. 4. Whenever in Title 40.1 any of the conditions, requirements, provisions or contents of any section, article or chapter of Title 40 as such title existed pri or to October 1, 1970, are transferred in the same or in modified form to a new section, article or chapter of Title 40.1 and whenever any such former section, article or chapter of Title 40 is given a new number in Title 40.1, all references to any such former section, article or chapter of Title 40 appearing in the Code of Virginia shall be construed to apply to the new and renumbered section, article or chapter containing such conditions, requirements, provisions or contents or portions thereof. 5. It is the intention of the General Assembly that this act shall be liberally construed to effect the purposes set out herein, and if any clause, sentence, paragraph or section of this act shall ever be declared unconstitutional, it shall be deemed severable, and the remainder of this act shall continue in full force and effect. Editors note. Acts 2021, Sp. Sess. I, c. 2, cl. 1 provides: § 1. The Virginia Board of Workforce Development (the Board), the Department of Labor and Industry (DOLI), and the Department of General Services (DGS) sha ll review the availability of registered apprenticeship programs in the Commonwealth, and evaluate the capacity to build a program that would require contractors engaged in construction contracts with public bodies to participate in apprenticeship traini ng programs for each trade or classification of employees engaged in the construction contract. Additionally, the Board, DOLI, and DGS shall evaluate whether a requirement to limit public procurements to bidders with registered apprenticeship programs wo uld assist the construction industry in meeting its workforce needs. In reviewing these issues, the Board, DOLI, and DGS may consider and evaluate additional workforce models to help the construction industry develop and meet its workforce needs. § 2. In carrying out its responsibilities pursuant to § 1, the Board, DOLI, and DGS may convene a stakeholder advisory group. Such group shall include, at a minimum, representatives from the following: the Virginia State Building and Construction Trades Council, the Alliance for Construction Excellence, and the Joint Apprenticeship Training Council. The advisory group shall also include representatives of career and technical educators, the labor workforce, and small state contractors. § 3. The Board, DOLI, and DGS shall complete its review and complete any advisory group meetings by September 1, 2021, and shall submit to the Governor and the General Assembly an executive summary and a report of its findings and recommendations for publication as a House or Senate document. The executive summary and report shall be submitted as provided in the procedures of the Division of Legislative Au tomated Systems for the processing of legislative documents and reports no later than December 1, 2021. Law Review. For article, Labor Law in Virginia, see 25 Wash. &amp; Lee L. Rev. 193 (1968). For survey of Virginia administrative law and utility regulation for the year 1978-1979, see 66 Va. L. Rev. 193 (1980). For series of articles on testing for drug abuse in the workplace, see 12 G.M.U. L. Rev. 491 et seq. (1990). For article, Labor and Employment Law, see 35 U. Rich. L. Rev. 725 (2001). Research References. Employment Screening (Matthew Bender). Lex K. Larson. Labor and Employment Arbitration (Matthew Bender). Bornstein, Gosline, and Greenbaum. Unjust Dismissal (Matthew Bender). Larson.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-2"><akn:num>§ 40.1-2</akn:num><akn:heading>Definitions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text As used in this title, unless the context clearly requires otherwise, the following terms have the following meanings: Board means the Safety and Health Codes Board. Business establishment means any proprietorship, firm or corporation where people are employed, permitted or suffered to work, including agricultural employment on a farm. Commission means the Safety and Health Codes Board. Commissioner means the Commissioner of Labor and Industry. Except where the context cl early indicates the contrary, any reference to Commissioner shall include his authorized representatives. Department means the Department of Labor and Industry. Domestic service means services related to the care of an individual in a private home or the maintenance of a private home or its premises, on a permanent or temporary basis, including services performed by individuals such as companions, cooks, waiters, butlers, maids, valets, and chauffeurs. Domestic service does not include wo rk that is irregular, uncertain, or incidental in nature and duration. Employ shall include to permit or suffer to work. Employee means any person who, in consideration of wages, salaries or commissions, may be permitted, required or directed by any employer to engage in any employment directly or indirectly. Employer means an individual, partnership, association, corporation, legal representat ive, receiver, trustee, or trustee in bankruptcy doing business in or operating within this Commonwealth who employs another to work for wages, salaries, or on commission and shall include any similar entity acting directly or indirectly in the interest of an employer in relation to an employee. Female or woman means a female 18 years of age or over. Machinery means machines, belts, pulleys, motors, engines, gears, vats, pits, elevator s, conveyors, shafts, tunnels, including machinery being operated on farms in connection with the production or harvesting of agricultural products. History History. Code 1950, § 40-1.1; 1962, c. 66; 1966, c. 90; 1970, c. 321; 1 972, c. 567; 1973, c. 425; 1985, c. 448; 2004, c. 294; 2021, Sp. Sess. I, cc. 509, 513. Annotations Cross references. As to worker misclassification, see § 58.1-1900 et seq. Editors note. Acts 2021, Sp. Sess. I, c. 513, cl. 2 provides: That the provisions of this act may result in a net increase in periods of imprisonment or commitment. Pursua nt to § 30-19.1:4 of the Code of Virginia, the estimated amount of the necessary appropriation cannot be determined for periods of imprisonment in state adult correctional facilities; therefore, Chapter 1289 of the Acts of Assembly of 2020 requires t he Virginia Criminal Sentencing Commission to assign a minimum fiscal impact of $50,000. Pursuant to § 30-19.1:4 of the Code of Virginia, the estimated amount of the necessary appropriation cannot be determined for periods of commitment to the custod y of the Department of Juvenile Justice. The 2004 amendments. The 2004 amendment by c. 294 added the last sentence in the paragraph defining Commissioner; and substituted 18 for eighteen in the paragr aph defining Female. The 2021 Sp. Sess. I amendments. The 2021 amendments by Sp. Sess. I, cc. 509 and 513, effective July 1, 2021, are identical, and inserted the definition for Domestic service. Law Review. For article, The Law of Wrongful Discharge in Virginia, see 10 G.M.U. L. Rev. 133 (1988). CASE NOTES Children Labor Law directed at employment for compensation.  The definitions in this section indicate strongly that the statutes included within the Child Labor Law are directed toward employment for compensation. Lovisi v. Commonwealth, 212 Va. 848, 188 S.E.2d 206, 1972 Va. LEXIS 281, cert. denied, 407 U.S. 922, 92 S. Ct. 2469, 32 L. Ed. 2d 808, 1972 U.S. LEXIS 2162 (1972). Definition of employer.  Individuals who served on the board of directors of the employer were not liable in a collective action for unpaid wages because the individuals were not employer s and the individuals acted directly or indirectly in the interest of an employer in relation to the employees. Cornell v. Benedict, 878 S.E.2d 191, 2022 Va. LEXIS 69 (Va. 2022). CIRCUIT COURT OPINIONS Employers.  Defendants pleas in bar were sustained in this failure to pay wages case; plaintiff alleged that defendants were employers as defined in Va. Code Ann. § 40 .1-2, yet plaintiffs counsel cited Va. Code Ann. § 40.1-28.9, but the court found that defendants did not meet either definition. Defendants power to unilaterally hire and fire employees and modify compensation appeared nonexistent, payroll ch ecks were not stopped by them, and court could not impose personal liability on them for debts belonging to the company. Cornell v. Christian Psychotherapy Servs., P.C., 108 Va. Cir. 200, 2021 Va. Cir. LEXIS 187 (Virginia Beach June 11, 2021). § 40.1-2.01. Certified mail; subsequent mail or notices may be sent by regular mail. Text Whenever in this title the Board, the Commissioner, or the Department is required to send any mail or notice by certified mail and such mail or notice is sent certified mail, return receipt requested, then any subsequent, identical mail or notice that is sent by the Board, the Commissioner, or the Department may be sent by regular mail. History History. 2011, c. 566. § 40.1-2.1. Application of title to Commonwealth and its agencies, etc.; safety and health program for public employees. Text The provisions of this title and any rules and regulations promulgated pursuant thereto shall not apply to the Commonwealth or any of its agencies, institutions, or pol itical subdivisions, or any public body, unless, and to the extent that, coverage is extended by specific regulation of the Commissioner or the Board. The Commissioner is authorized to establish and maintain an effective and comprehensive occupational sa fety and health program applicable to employees of the Commonwealth, its agencies, institutions, political subdivisions, or any public body. Such program shall be subject to any State plan submitted to the federal government for State enforcement of the Federal Occupational Safety and Health Act of 1970 (P.L. 91-596), or any other regulation promulgated under Title 40.1. The Commissioner or the Board shall establish procedures and adopt regulations for enforcing the program that shall include provisions for (i) the issuance of proposed penalties; (ii) the payment of such penalties or a negotiated sum in lieu of such penalties; (iii) the deposit of such payments into the general fund of the state treasury; (iv) fair hearings, including judicial review; and (v) other sanctions to be applied for violations. History History. 1973, c. 425; 2016, c. 526. Annotations Cross references. As to worker misclassification, see § 58.1-1900 et seq. The 2016 amendments. The 2016 amendment by c. 526, deleted Safety and Health Codes in the first sentence, and rewrote the last sentence, which read The Commissioner shall establish procedures for enforcing the program which shall include provisions for fair hearings including judicial review and sanctions to be applied for violations.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-3"><akn:num>§ 40.1-3</akn:num><akn:heading>Title provides for safety, health and welfare of employees</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The provisions of this title are intended to provide solely for the safety, health and welfare of employees and the benefits thereof shall not run to any other person n or shall a third party have any right of action for breach of any provision of this title except as herein otherwise specifically provided. History History. Code 1950, § 40-1.2; 1962, c. 66; 1970, c. 321.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-4"><akn:num>§ 40.1-4</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1984, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>734. Annotations Cross references. For section requiring the Department to submit an annual report to the Governor and the General Assembly, see now § 40.1-4.1. § 40.1-4.1. Annual report. Text The Department shall submit an annual report to the Governor and General Assembly which contains statistical information derived from its programs and activities. History History. 1984, c. 734; 2004, c. 650. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2004, c. 650, cl. 3 provides: That the Division of Legislative Automated Systems shall notify the Governor, the Lieutenant Governor, the Clerk of the Hou se of the Delegates, the Clerk of the Senate, and the Law Librarian of the University of Virginia that the automatic distribution of hard copies of annual and biennial reports pursuant to § 2.2-1127 has been replaced by an on-demand electronic notific ation and report retrieval system available from the General Assemblys website. The Division shall also notify the members of the General Assembly of the availability of the electronic notification and report retrieval system and the additional optio n of receiving hardcopies of reports by request. The 2004 amendments. The 2004 amendment by c. 650 deleted the last sentence, which formerly read: The annual report shall be distributed in accordance with the provisions of § 2.2-1127.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-5"><akn:num>§ 40.1-5</akn:num><akn:heading>Governor to appoint Commissioner of Labor and Industry</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Governor shall appoint, by and with the consent of the General Assembly, some suitable person identified with the labor interests of the Commonwealth, who shall be designated Commissioner of Labor and Industry. The Commissioner shall, upon the request of the Governor, furnish such information as he may require. The Commissioner shall serve at the pleasure of the Governor for a term coincident with that of the Gover nor. History History. Code 1950, § 40-3; 1962, c. 66; 1970, c. 321; 1978, c. 372.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-6"><akn:num>§ 40.1-6</akn:num><akn:heading>Powers and duties of Commissioner</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Commissioner shall: 1. Have general supervision and control of the Department; 2. Enforce the provisions of this title and shall cause to be prosecuted all violations of law relating to employers or business establishments before any court of competent jurisdiction; 3. Make such rules and regulations as may be necessary for the enforcement of this title and procedural rules as are required to comply with the federal Occupational Safety and Health Act of 1970 (P.L. 91-596). All such rules and regulations shall be subject to Chapter 40 (§ 2.2-4000 et seq.) of Title 2.2; 4. In the discharge of his duties, have power to take and preserve testimony, examine witnesses, and administer oaths and to file a written or printed list of relevant interrogatories and require full and complete answers to the same to be returned under oath within 30 days of the receipt of such list of questions; 5. Have power to appoint such representatives as may be necessary to aid the Commissioner in his work, with the duties of such representatives to be prescribed by the Commissioner; 6. Determine the prevailing wage required to be paid under a public contract for public works as provided in § 2.2-4321.3 and perform all other duties imposed on the Commissioner under such section. Any determination of the prevailing wage rate made by the Commissioner shall be based on applicable prevailing wage rate determinations made by the U.S. Secretary of Labor under the provisions of the Davis-Bacon Act, 40 U.S.C. § 276 et seq., as amended; 7. Have power to require that accident, injury, and occupational illness records and reports be kept at any place of employment and that such records and reports be made available to the Commissioner or his duly authorized representatives upon request, and to require employers to develop, maintain, and make available such other records and information as are deemed necessary for the proper enforcement of this title; 8. Have power, upon presenting appropriate credentials to the owner, operator, or agent in charge: a. To enter without delay and at reasonable times any business establishment, construction site, or other area, workplace, or environment where work is performed by an employee of any employer in this Commonwealth; and b. To inspect and investigate, during regular working hours and at other reasonable times and within reasonable limits and in a reasonable manner, without prior notice unless such no tice is authorized by the Commissioner or his representative, any such business establishment or place of employment and all pertinent conditions, structures, machines, apparatus, devices, equipment, and materials therein, and to question privately any s uch employer, officer, owner, operator, agent, or employee. If such entry or inspection is refused, prohibited, or otherwise interfered with, the Commissioner shall have power to seek from a court having equity jurisdiction an order compelling such entry or inspection; 9. Make rules and regulations governing the granting of temporary or permanent variances from all standards promulgated by the Board under this title. Any interested or affected party may appeal to the Board, the Commissioners determination to grant or deny such a variance. The Board may, as it sees fit, adopt, modify, or reject the determination of the Commissioner; 10. Have authority to issue orders to protect the confidentiality of all information reported to or otherwise obtained by the Commissioner, the Board, or the agents or employees of eith er that contains or might reveal a trade secret. Such information shall be confidential and shall be limited to those persons who need such information for purposes of enforcement of this title. Violations of such orders shall be punishable as civil cont empt upon application to the Circuit Court of the City of Richmond. It shall be the duty of each employer to notify the Commissioner or his representatives of the existence of trade secrets where he desires the protection provided herein; and 11. Serve as executive officer of the Virginia Safety and Health Codes Board and of the Apprenticeship Council and see that the rules, regulations, and policies that they promulgate are carried out. History History. Code 1950, § 40-4; 1962, c. 66; 1970, c. 321; 1972, c. 567; 19 73, c. 425; 1984, cc. 590, 734; 1987, c. 165; 1997, c. 919; 1998, c. 97; 2004, c. 592; 2020, cc. 1216, 1243. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2020, cc. 1216 and 1243, cl. 2 provides: That the provisions of this act shall become effective on May 1, 2021. The 1998 amendment, in subdivision 11, deleted shall preceding see that the rules, and in subdivision 12, in the first sentence, substituted Establish the for Establish an, and inserted including the Virginia Workers Comp ensation Commission. The 2004 amendments. The 2004 amendment by c. 592 deleted subdivision (12), which formerly read: Establish the Interagency Migrant Worker Policy Committee, comprised of representa tives from state agencies, including the Virginia Workers Compensation Commission, whose services and jurisdictions involve migrant and seasonal farmworkers and their employees. The committee shall coordinate its activities with the Migrant and Seaso nal Farmworkers Board established in § 2.2-2407. The 2020 amendments. The 2020 amendments by cc. 1216 and 1243, effective May 5, 2021, are identical, and in subdivision 5, substituted the Commissioner in his work, with the dutie s of such representatives to be prescribed by the Commissioner for him in his work; their duties shall be prescribed by the Commissioner; substituted subdivision 6 for (6) [Repealed.]; in subdivision 7, substituted request, and to  for request. Further, he may; in subdivision 10, substituted Have authority to issue orders to protect the confidentiality of all for All in the first sentence and substituted trade secret. Such information shall be confi dential for trade secret shall be confidential in the first and second sentences and deleted the former provisions of the second sentence, which read, The Commissioner shall have authority to issue orders to protect the confidentiality of such information and made stylistic changes. Law Review. For article, Enforcement of Occupational Safety and Health Laws in Virginia: A New Beginning, see 12 U. Rich. L. Rev. 535 (1978). Research References. Bryson on Virginia Civil Procedure (Matthew Bender). Chapter 9 Discovery. § 9.05 Depositions. W. Hamilton Bryson. OPINIONS OF THE ATTORNEY GENERAL Federal preemption.  Federal law governing the employment of unauthorized aliens explicitly and implicitly preempts any Virginia law that would impose civil or criminal sanctions upon persons employing such aliens. Further, imposition of an injunction constitutes a civil sanction, which is preempted by federal law. See opinion of Attorney General to The Honorable Thomas Davis Rust, Member, House of Delegates, 09-071, 2010 Va. AG LEXI S 5 (2/2/10).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-7"><akn:num>§ 40.1-7</akn:num><akn:heading>Attorney for the Commonwealth to prosecute on request of Commissioner</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The attorney for the Commonwealth of the proper county or city, upon the request of the Commissioner, or any of his authorized representatives, shall prosecute any viol ation of law or rule or regulation adopted thereunder which it is made the duty of the Commissioner to enforce. History History. Code 1950, § 40-5; 1962, c. 66; 1970, c. 321.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-8"><akn:num>§ 40.1-8</akn:num><akn:heading>Other officers to furnish information; protected health information under certain circumstances</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. All State, county, town and city officers shall furnish the Commissioner, upon his request, such statistical or other information as may be in their possession as such officers that will assist the Department in the discharge of its duties. B. In the disc harge of his duties to ensure compliance with federal law and regulation relating to the health and safety of Virginias workforce and prevention of work-related injuries, disabilities, and deaths, each licensed emergency medical services agency shall release to the Commissioner or his designee the prehospital patient care report required by § 32.1-116.1 when such records are requested for a patient who has suffered an injury, disability or death resulting from an accident or illness that occurred while engaged in his employment without obtaining consent or authorization for such disclosure from the person who is the subject of the records. The patients health records shall be confidential. The Commissioner and any designee shall only rediscl ose such protected health information in compliance with the regulations concerning patient privacy promulgated by the federal Department of Health and Human Services in compliance with the Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act of 1996, as amended. History History. Code 1950, § 40-6; 1962, c. 66; 1970, c. 321; 2004, c. 163. Annotations The 2004 amendments. The 2004 amendment by c. 163 inserted the A designation at the beginning of the first paragraph; added subsection B; and made a minor stylistic change.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-9"><akn:num>§ 40.1-9</akn:num><akn:heading>How Department maintained</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Department shall be maintained from such appropriations as the General Assembly may make for the purpose. The compensation of the Commissioner and of all other empl oyees of the Department shall be fixed and paid in accordance with law. History History. Code 1950, § 40-7; 1962, c. 66; 1970, c. 321.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-10"><akn:num>§ 40.1-10</akn:num><akn:heading>Offenses in regard to examinations, inspections, etc</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text If any person who may be sworn to give testimony shall willfully fail or refuse to answer any legal and proper question propounded to him concerning the subject of such examination as indicated in § 40.1-6, or if any person to whom a written or printed list of such interrogatories has been furnished by the Commissioner shall neglect or refuse to answer fully and return the same under oath, or if any person in charge of any business establishment shall refuse admission to, or obstruct in any manner the inspection or investigation of such establishment or the proper performance of the authorized duties of the Commissioner or any of his representatives, he shall be gu ilty of a misdemeanor. Such person, upon conviction thereof, shall be fined not exceeding $100 nor less than $25 or imprisoned in jail not exceeding 90 days, or both. History History. Code 1950, § 40-8; 1962, c. 66; 1970, c. 321. Annotations Law Review. For article, Enforcement of Occupational Safety and Health Laws in Virginia: A New Beginning, see 12 U. Rich. L. Rev. 535 (1978). Research References. Bryson on Virginia Civil Procedure (Matthew Bender). Chapter 9 Discovery. § 9.05 Depositions. W. Hamilton Bryson.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-11"><akn:num>§ 40.1-11</akn:num><akn:heading>Using or revealing information gathered</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Neither the Commissioner nor any employee of the Department shall make use of or reveal any information or statistics gathered from any person, company or corporation f or any purposes other than those of this title. History History. Code 1950, § 40-9; 1962, c. 66; 1970, c. 321; 1984, c. 590. § 40.1-11.1. Employment of illegal immigrants. Text It shall be unlawful and constitute a Class 1 misdemeanor for any employer or any person acting as an agent for an employer, or any person who, for a fee, refers an ali en who cannot provide documents indicating that he or she is legally eligible for employment in the United States for employment to an employer, or an officer, agent or representative of a labor organization to knowingly employ, continue to employ, or re fer for employment any alien who cannot provide documents indicating that he or she is legally eligible for employment in the United States. Permits issued by the United States Department of Justice authorizing an alien to work in the United States shall constitute proof of eligibility for employment. All employment application forms used by State and local governments and privately owned businesses operating in the Commonwealth on and after January 1, 1978, shall as k prospective employees if they are legally eligible for employment in the United States. The provisions of this section shall not be deemed to require any employer to use employment application forms. History History. 1977, c. 438; 1979, c. 472. Annotations Cross references. As to punishment for Class 1 misdemeanors, see § 18.2-11. Law Review. For survey of Virginia commercial law for the year 1976-77, see 63 Va. L. Rev. 1377 (1977). For article, The States of Immigration, see 54 Wm. &amp; Mary L. Rev. 1339 (2013). OPINIONS OF THE ATTORNEY GENERAL Non-citizen applicants for business license.  Language in the Immigration Act and § 40.1-11.1 does not justify an extension of the federal immigration policy underlying the law to the issuance of b usiness licenses; Overruling the 2006 Attorney General Opinion, it was opined that commissioner of the revenue or similar local official is not required to deny a business license to a noncitizen applicant who fails to produce a permanent resident card. See opinion of Attorney General to The Honorable Philip J. Kellam, Virginia Beach Commissioner of the Revenue, 19-062, 2020 Va. AG LEXIS 28 (8/7/20). Federal preemption.  Federal law governing the employment of unauthorized aliens explicitly and implicitly preempts any Virginia law that would impose civil or criminal sanctions upon persons employing such aliens. Further, imposition of an injunction constitutes a civil sanction, which is preempted by federal law. See opinion of Attorney General to The Honorable Thomas Davis Rust, Member, House of Delegates, 09-071, 2010 Va. AG LEXI S 5 (2/2/10). Applicant for local business license not legally present in United States.  Federal and state laws prohibit a commissioner of the revenue from issuing a local business license to an applicant not legally present in the United States. Furt her, a commissioner must verify the identity and eligibility of all applicants by examining documents specified by federal law. See opinion of Attorney General to The Honorable Calvin C. Massie, Jr., Commissioner of the Revenue, Campbell County, 06-049, 2006 Va. AG LEXIS 27 (7/24/06) (Overruled by 2020 Va. AG LEXIS 28). § 40.1-11.2. Participation in E-Verify program. Text All agencies of the Commonwealth shall be enrolled in the E-Verify program by December 1, 2012; and on and after December 1, 2012, use the E-Verify program for each new ly hired employee who is to perform work within the Commonwealth. History History. 2010, c. 633. § 40.1-11.3. Human trafficking hotline; posted notice required; civil penalty. Text A. Any employe r who (i) operates a business that provides entertainment commonly called stripteasing or topless entertaining or entertainment that has employees who are not clad above or below the waist and (ii) fails to post notice of the existence of a human traffic king hotline to alert potential human trafficking victims of the availability of assistance, is subject to a civil penalty of $500. Civil penalties under this subsection shall be assessed by the Department and paid to the Literary Fund. The notice requir ed by this subsection shall be posted in the same location where other employee notices required by state or federal law are posted. The provisions of this subsection shall not apply to businesses described in this subsection providing entertainment in t heaters, concert halls, art centers, museums, or similar establishments that are devoted primarily to the arts or theatrical performances, when the performances that are presented are expressing matters of serious literary, artistic, scientific, or polit ical value. B. Any employe r who (i) operates a truck stop and (ii) fails to post notice of the existence of a human trafficking hotline to alert possible witnesses or victims of human trafficking of the availability to report crimes or gain assistance, which failure is not cured within 72 hours following notification to the employer of such failure by the Department, is subject to a civil penalty of $100 per truck stop. Civil penalties under this subsection shall be assessed by the Department and paid to the Literary Fund, provi ded that no civil penalty shall be assessed under this subsection prior to January 1, 2014. The notice required by this subsection shall be posted in the same location where other employee notices required by state or federal law are posted. As used in t his subsection, truck stop means a facility that is capable of fueling a qualified highway vehicle that bears an IFTA identification marker as those terms are defined in § 58.1-2700. C. The Departm ent shall (i) determine the content of the notice which shall include the National Human Trafficking Resource Center Hotline, (ii) determine the size of the notice, (iii) determine the languages in which the notice is to be posted, and (iv) publish the n otice size and notice languages, and make the notice available in each of those languages, on the website of the Department and by any other means of publication the Department deems appropriate. The Department is not otherwise required to produce or dis tribute the notice. An employer is not required to use a notice produced by the Department, provided the notice complies with guidelines established by the Department. The Department may certify that a notice produced by an employer or other entity compl ies with the requirements of this section. History History. 2012, c. 630; 2013, c. 304. Annotations The 2013 amendments. The 2013 amendment by c. 304, in subsection A, deleted payable following $500 at the end of the first sentence, inserted Civil penalties under this subsection shall be assessed by the Department and paid at the beginning of the second sentence, substituted this subsection for this section in the third sentence, and inserted described in this subsection in the fourth sentence; added subsection B and redesignated former subsection B as subsection C; in subsection C, inserted determine following the clause (ii) designator, and added the last two sentences. § 40.1-11.4. Seizure first aid posters. Text The Department shall provide all employers and employees in the Commonwealth with in-color informational posters, at least 8.5 inches by 11 inches in size, with respect to rendering seizure first aid. The information shall be disseminated by means determined by the Department, including electronically, and the information approved by the Department shall be fully consistent with information and guidelines developed by the Epilepsy Foundation of America and any such successor organization. Each employer of 25 or more employees in the Commonwealth shall physically post information on seizure first aid provided by the Department in a prominent position in the employer s workplace that is visible to employees. For the purposes of this section, seizure first aid means procedures to respond, attend, and provide comfort and safety to an individual suffering from a seizure. Seizure first aid does not in clude training to medically treat an individual suffering from a seizure. Nothing in this section shall be construed to supersede any other provision of law, including the exemption from liability for a person rendering emergency care in good faith witho ut compensation pursuant to the provisions of § 8.01-225. History History. 2022, c. 162. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2022, c. 162, cl. 1 was codified as this section at the direction of the Virginia Code Commission. Chapter 2. Employment Agencies. -360§§ 40.1-12 through 40.1-21.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-12"><akn:num>§ 40.1-12</akn:num><akn:heading>40</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>1-12 through 40.1-21. Text Repealed by Acts 1978, c. 840. Chapter 3. Protection of Employees. -360Article 1. General Provisions. -360Article 1.1. Virginia Minimum Wage Act. -360Article 2. Pay; Assignment of Wages; Sale of Merchandise to Employees. -360Article 2.1. Paid Sick Leave. -360Article 3. Employment of Women Generally. -360Article 4. Sanitary Provisions. -360Article 5. Safety Provisions. Article 1. General Provisions. -360§ 40.1-22. Safety and Health Codes Commission continued as Safety and Health Codes Board. -360§ 40.1-22.1. Governor authorized to enter certain agreements. -360§§ 40.1-23 through 40.1-25.1. Repealed by Acts 1988, c. 340, effective January 1, 1989. -360§ 40.1-26. Repealed by Acts 1979, c. 631. -360§ 40.1-27. Preventing employment by others of former employee. -360§ 40.1-27.1. Discharge of employee for absence due to work-related injury prohibited. -360§ 40.1-27.2. Preference for veterans and spouses. -360§ 40.1-27.3. Retaliatory action against employee prohibited. -360§ 40.1-27.4. Discipline for employees medicinal use of cannabis oil prohibited. -360§ 40.1-28. Unlawful to require payment for medical examination as condition of employment. -360§ 40.1-28.01. Nondisclosure or confidentiality agreement; provisions regarding sexual assault; condition of employment. -360§§ 40.1-28.1 through 40.1-28.4:1. Repealed by Acts 2005, c. 823, effective July 1, 2005. -360§ 40.1-28.5. Repealed by Acts 2004, c. 608. -360§ 40.1-28.6. Equal pay irrespective of sex. -360§ 40.1-28.7. Repealed by Acts 1985, c. 421. -360§ 40.1-28.7:1. Genetic testing or genetic characteristics as a condition of employment. -360§ 40.1-28.7:2. Employers to allow crime victims leave to attend criminal proceedings. -360§ 40.1-28.7:3. Earned income tax credit; employer notice to employee. -360§ 40.1-28.7:4. Release of employees personal identifying information. -360§ 40.1-28.7:5. Social media accounts of current and prospective employees. -360§ 40.1-28.7:6. Employers to allow leave for volunteer members of Civil Air Patrol; civil remedy. -360§ 40.1-28.7:7. Misclassification of workers. -360§ 40.1-28.7:8. Covenants not to compete prohibited as to low-wage employees; civil penalty. -360§ 40.1-28.7:9. Limiting employees sharing wage information with other persons prohibited; civil penalty.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-22"><akn:num>§ 40.1-22</akn:num><akn:heading>Safety and Health Codes Commission continued as Safety and Health Codes Board</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text (1) The Safety and Health Codes Commission is continued and shall hereafter be known as the Safety and Health Codes Board. The Board shall consist of fourteen members, twelve of whom shall be appointed by the Governor. One member shall, by reason of previous vocation, employment or affiliation, be chosen to represent labor in the manufacturing industry; one member shall, by reason of previous vocation, employment or affiliation, be chosen to represent labor in the construction industry; one member shall, by reason of previous vocation, employment or affiliation, be chosen to represent industrial employers; one member shall be chosen from and be a representative of the general public; one member shall be a representative of agricultural employers; one member shall, b y reason of previous vocation, employment or affiliation, be chosen to represent agricultural employees; one member shall, by reason of previous vocation, employment or affiliation, be chosen to represent construction industry employers; one member shall be a representative of an insurance company; one member shall be a labor representative from the boiler pressure vessel industry; one member shall be a labor representative knowledgeable in chemicals and toxic substances; one member shall be an employer representative of the boiler pressure vessel industry; one member shall be an industrial representative knowledgeable in chemical and toxic substances, and the Director of the Department of Environmental Quality or his duly authorized representative sha ll be a member ex officio with full membership status. The Commissioner of Health or his duly authorized representative shall also be a member ex officio with full membership status. (2) The first appointive members shall be appointed as follows: one for a term of four years, one for a term of three years, one for a term of two years, and one for a term of one year. Of the members appointed to represent the construction industry, one shall be appo inted for the term of two years and one shall be appointed for the term of four years. Succeeding appointments shall be for terms of four years each but other vacancies shall be filled by appointment for the unexpired term. (3) The Board shall annually select a chairman from its members. The Board shall meet at least once every six months; other meetings may be held upon call of the chairman or any three members of the Board. Five members of the Board shall constitute a quorum. (4) The Board shall study and investigate all phases of safety in business establishments, the application of this title thereto, and shall serve as advisor to the Commissioner. (5) The Board, with the advice of the Commissioner, is hereby authorized to adopt, alter, amend, or repeal rules and regulations to further, protect and promote the safety and health of employees in places of employment over which it has jurisdiction and to effect com pliance with the Federal Occupational Safety and Health Act of 1970 (P.L. 91-596), and as may be necessary to carry out its functions established under this title. The Commissioner shall enforce such rules and regulations. All such rules and regulations shall be designed to protect and promote the safety and health of such employees. In making such rules and regulations to protect the occupational safety and health of employees, the Board shall adopt the standard which most adequately assures, to the ex tent feasible, on the basis of the best available evidence, that no employee will suffer material impairment of health or functional capacity. However, such standards shall be at least as stringent as the standards promulgated by the Federal Occupational Safety and Health Act of 1970 (P.L. 91-596). In addition to the attainment of the highest degree of health and safety protection for the employee, other considerations shall be the latest available scientific data in the field, the feasibility of the st andards, and experience gained under this and other health and safety laws. Whenever practicable, the standard promulgated shall be expressed in terms of objective criteria and of the performance desired. Such standards when applicable to products which are distributed in interstate commerce shall be the same as federal standards unless deviations are required by compelling local conditions and do not unduly burden interstate commerce. (6) Chapter 40 (§ 2.2-4000 et seq.) of Title 2.2 shall apply to the adoption of rules and regulations under this section and to proceedings before the Board. (6a) The Board shall provide, without regard to the requirements of Chapter 40 (§ 2.2-4000 et seq.) of Title 2.2, for an emergency temporary standard to take immediate effect upon publication in a newspaper of general circulation, published in the City of Richmond, Virginia, if it determines that employees are exposed to grave danger from exposure to substances or agents determined to be toxic or physically harmful or from new hazards, and that such emergency standard is necessary to protect employees from such da nger. The publication mentioned herein shall constitute notice that the Board intends to adopt such standard within a period of six months. The Board by similar publication shall prior to the expiration of six months give notice of the time and date of, and conduct a hearing on, the adoption of a permanent standard. The emergency temporary standard shall expire within six months or when superseded by a permanent standard, whichever occurs first, or when repealed by the Board. (7) Any person who may be adversely affected by a standard issued under this title may challenge the validity of such standard in the Circuit Court of the City of Richmond by declaratory judgment. The determination of the Safety and Health Codes Board shall be conclus ive if supported by substantial evidence in the record considered as a whole. Adoption of a federal occupational safety and health standard shall be deemed to be sufficient evidence to support promulgation of such standard. The filing of a petition for d eclaratory judgment shall not operate as a stay of the standard unless the court issues a preliminary injunction. History History. Code 1950, § 40-20; 1962, c. 66; 1968, c. 272; 1970, cc. 321, 649; 1972, c. 567; 1973, c. 425; 1974, c. 195; 1976, c. 607; 1979, c. 656; 1980, c. 728; 1984, c. 590; 1985, c. 448; 1987, c. 165; 1988, c. 467. Annotations Cross references. As to compensation and expenses of boards, commissions and similar bodies, see § 2.2-2813. As to regulations related to migrant labor camps, see § 32.1-211. Law Review. For article, Enforcement of Occupational Safety and Health Laws in Virginia: A New Beginning, see 12 U. Rich. L. Rev. 535 (1978). For note on employee drug testing, see 74 Va. L. Rev. 969 (1988). For article, State Criminal Prosecutions: Putting Teeth in the Occupational Safety and Health Act, see 12 G.M.U. L. Rev. 737 (1990). For a note, Are You Breaking Some Sort of Law?: Protecting an Employees Informal Complaints Under the Fair Labor Standards Acts Anti-Retaliation Prov ision, see 42 Wm. &amp; Mary L. Rev. 319 (2000). CASE NOTES Constitutionality.  Subsection (5) of this section contains sufficient legislative standards and limitations to direct the board in the exercise of the authority delegated to it by t he legislature. Accordingly, the judgment of the trial court holding this subsection unconstitutional was reversed. Bell v. Dorey Elec. Co., 248 Va. 378, 448 S.E.2d 622, 1994 Va. LEXIS 134 (1994). Duty of employer in preventing hazar ds.  An employer need not take steps to prevent hazards which are not generally foreseeable, including idiosyncratic behavior of an employee, but at the same time an e mployer must do all it feasibly can to prevent foreseeable hazards. Floyd S. Pike Elec. Contractor v. Commissioner, Dep't of Labor &amp; Indus., 222 Va. 317, 281 S.E.2d 804, 1981 Va. LEXIS 307 (1981). Safety regulations governing installation of electrical transmission lines were not desi gned to make the employer an insurer of an employees safety. A safe workplace is not necessarily risk-free. Floyd S. Pike Elec. Contractor v. Commissioner, Dep't of Labor &amp; Indus., 222 Va. 317, 281 S.E.2d 804, 1981 Va. LEXIS 307 (1981). § 40.1-22.1. Governor authorized to enter certain agreements. Text The Governor of Virginia is hereby authorized to enter into: 1. Such agreements with the United States Occupational Safety and Health Administration as are necessary to provide training for the employees of the Virginia Department of Labor and Industry and other appropriate agencies of the Commonwealth to assist in the en forcement of Public Law 91-596. 2. Reciprocal agreements with the appropriate authorities of any state within the United States and of the District of Columbia, with respect to the collection of claims for wages and oth er demands upon claims filed with the Department of Labor and Industry. History History. 1976, c. 607; 1997, c. 282. Annotations Law Review. For article, Enforcement of Occupational Safety and Health Laws in Virginia: A New Beginning, see 12 U. Rich. L. Rev. 535 (1978).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-23"><akn:num>§ 40.1-23</akn:num><akn:heading>40</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>1-23 through 40.1-25.1. Repealed by Acts 1988, c. 340, effective January 1, 1989.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-26"><akn:num>§ 40.1-26</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1979, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>631.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-27"><akn:num>§ 40.1-27</akn:num><akn:heading>Preventing employment by others of former employee</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text No person doing business in this Commonwealth, or any agent or attorney of such person after having discharged any employee from the service of such person or after any employee shall have voluntarily left the service of such person shall willfully and maliciously prevent or attempt to prevent by word or writing, directly or indirectly, such discharged employee or such employee who has voluntarily left from obtaining e mployment with any other person. For violation of this section the offender shall be guilty of a misdemeanor and shall, on conviction thereof, be fined not less than $100 nor more than $500. But this section shall not be construed as prohibiting any pers on from giving on application for any other person a truthful statement of the reason for such discharge, or a truthful statement concerning the character, industry and ability of such person who has voluntarily left. History History. Code 1950, § 40-22; 1970, c. 321. Annotations Law Review. For note, Erosion of the Employment-at-Will Doctrine: Recognition of an Employees Right to Job Security, see 43 Wash. &amp; Lee L. Rev. 593 (1986). For comment, Potential Employer Liability for Employee References, see 21 U. Rich. L. Rev. 427 (1987). For article, The Law of Wrongful Discharge in Virginia, see 10 G.M.U. L. Rev. 133 (1988). CASE NOTES Criminal penalties.  This section establishes criminal penalties for willful and malicious prevention of employment by others of former employee. Haigh v. Matsushita Elec. Corp. of Am ., 676 F. Supp. 1332, 1987 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 12113 (E.D. Va. 1987). § 40.1-27.1. Discharge of employee for absence due to work-related injury prohibited. Text It shall be an unfair employment practice for an employer who has established an employment policy of discharging employees who are absent from work for a specified num ber of days to include in the computation of an employees work absence record any day that such employee is absent from work due to a compensable absence under Title 65.2; provided, that such compensable absences can be calculated into an employee s work record for purposes of discharge after all steps of the excessive absenteeism policy have been exhausted. An employer shall not be held in violation of this section if the employees absence exceeds six months or if the employers circu mstances have changed during such employees absence so as to make it impossible or unreasonable not to discharge such employee. History History. 1989, c. 572. Annotations Law Review. For survey on employment law in Virginia for 1989, see 23 U. Rich. L. Rev. 607 (1989). Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 12B M.J. Master and Servant, § 11; 21 M.J. Workers Co mpensation, § 38. CASE NOTES No private right of action.  Former employee summarily alleged a violation of this section, however, no Virginia court has recognized a private right of action for a violation of this statute . Even if such a private right of action existed, the employee provided no evidence that the employer had a policy of terminating HVAC Technicians after a certain number of absences, that the employer incorrectly computed the employees absences due t o injury, or that the employer terminated him due to excessive absenteeism. Taylor v. Wal-Mart Stores, Inc., 376 F. Supp. 2d 653, 2005 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 14040 (E.D. Va.), aff'd, 158 Fed. Appx. 446, 2005 U.S. App. LEXIS 28200 (4th Cir. 2005). § 40.1-27.2. Preference for veterans and spouses. Text A. As used in this section, unless the context requires a different meaning:Disabled veteran means a veteran wh o has been found by the U.S. Department of Veterans Affairs or by the retirement board of one of the several branches of the armed forces to have a compensable service-connected permanent and total disability. Veteran has the same meaning ascribed to such term in § 2.2-2903. B. An employer may grant preference in hiring and promotion to a veteran or the spouse of a disabled veteran. C. Granting pr eference under subsection B does not violate any local or state equal employment opportunity law. History History. 2014, c. 740. § 40.1-27.3. Retaliatory action against employee prohibited. Text A. An employer shall not discharge, discipline, threaten, discriminate against, or penalize an employee, or take other retaliatory action regarding an employees compensation, terms, conditions, location, or privileges of employment, because the employee: 1. Or a person acting on behalf of the employee in good faith reports a violation of any federal or state law or regulation to a supervisor or to any governmental body or law-enforcement official; 2. Is requested by a governmental body or law-enforcement official to participate in an investigation, hearing, or inquiry; 3. Refuses to engage in a criminal act that would subject the employee to criminal liability; 4. Refuses an employers order to perform an action that violates any federal or state law or regulation and the employee informs the employer that the order is being refused for that reason; or 5. Provides information to or testifies before any governmental body or law-enforcement official conducting an investigation, hearing, or inquiry into any alleged violation by the employe r of federal or state law or regulation. B. This sectio n does not: 1. Autho rize an employee to make a disclosure of data otherwise protected by law or any legal privilege; 2. Permit an employee to make statements or disclosures knowing that they are false or that they are in reckless disregard of the truth; or 3. Permit disclosures that would violate federal or state law or diminish or impair the rights of any person to the continued protection of confidentiality of communications provided by c ommon law. C. A person wh o alleges a violation of this section may bring a civil action in a court of competent jurisdiction within one year of the employers prohibited retaliatory action. The court may order as a remedy to the employee (i) an injunction to restrain continue d violation of this section, (ii) the reinstatement of the employee to the same position held before the retaliatory action or to an equivalent position, and (iii) compensation for lost wages, benefits, and other remuneration, together with interest ther eon, as well as reasonable attorney fees and costs. History History. 2020, c. 1136. Annotations CIRCUIT COURT OPINIONS Whistle blower status.  Former employee had sufficiently alleged that she was whistle blower where she had reported the alleged child abuse incidents to the city attorney, the court coul d fairly infer that the city attorney had an agency relationship with the governmental body and his knowledge was imputed to that body, and the former employee had alleged that she had reported to her supervisor. Alexander v. City of Chesapeake, 108 Va. Cir. 161, 2021 Va. Cir. LEXIS 130 (Chesapeake May 20, 2021). Terminated employee alleged sufficient facts to support a claim because the employee, who was a bartender in employers club, alleged that the employee reporte d that a members behavior put the employee and other bartenders in an impossible situation, that the employee would refuse to serve the member if the member was intoxicated, and that the employee was terminated due to the employees stance on the issue. Foster v. Fraternal Order of Eagles, 108 Va. Cir. 409, 2021 Va. Cir. LEXIS 200 (Rockingham County Aug. 19, 2021). Remedy.  While Va. Code § 40.1-27.3(c) specifies a remedy, there is nothing to indicate it provides the exclusive remedy. Chenault v. RBI Corp., 108 Va. Cir. 529, 202 1 Va. Cir. LEXIS 217 (Hanover County Oct. 22, 2021). § 40.1-27.4. Discipline for employees medicinal use of cannabis oil prohibited. Text A. As used in this section, cannabis oil means the same as that term is defined in § 54.1-3408.3. B. No employer shall discharge, discipline, or discriminate against an employee for such employees lawful use of cannabis oil pursuant to a valid written certification issued by a practitioner for the treatment or to eliminate the symptoms of the employees dia gnosed condition or disease pursuant to § 54.1-3408.3. C. Notwithstan ding the provisions of subsection B, nothing in this section shall (i) restrict an employers ability to take any adverse employment action for any work impairment caused by the use of cannabis oil or to prohibit possession during work hours, (ii) req uire an employer to commit any act that would cause the employer to be in violation of federal law or that would result in the loss of a federal contract or federal funding, or (iii) require any defense industrial base sector employer or prospective empl oyer, as defined by the U.S. Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency, to hire or retain any applicant or employee who tests positive for tetrahydrocannabinol (THC) in excess of 50 ng/ml for a urine test or 10 pg/mg for a hair test. History History. 2021, Sp. Sess. I, c. 395. Annotations Effective date. This section is effective July 1, 2021.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-28"><akn:num>§ 40.1-28</akn:num><akn:heading>Unlawful to require payment for medical examination as condition of employment</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text It shall be unlawful for any employer to require any employee or applicant for employment to pay the cost of a medical examination or the cost of furnishing any medical records required by the employer as a condition of employment. Any employer who violates the provisions of this section shall be subject to a civil penalty not to exceed $100 for each violation. The Commissioner shall notify any em ployer who he alleges has violated any provision of this section by certified mail or overnight delivery service. Such notice shall contain a description of the alleged violation. Within 21 days of receipt of notice of the alleged violation, the employer may request an informal conference regarding such violation with the Commissioner. If the employer fails to contest the violation by requesting such an informal conference within 21 days following its receipt of the notice of the alleged violation, the violation and proposed penalty will become a final order of the Commissioner and not subject to review by any court or agency except upon a showing of good cause. Such informal conference shall result in a decision by the Commissioner that will be appeal able to the appropriate circuit court. The Department shall send a copy of the Commissioners decision to the employer by certified mail or overnight delivery service. The employer may file a notice of an appeal only within 30 days from the receipt of the decision. The appeal shall be on the agency record. With respect to matters of law, the burden shall be on the party seeking review to designate and demonstrate an error of law subject to review by the court. With respect to issues of fact, the duty of the court shall be limited to ascertaining whether there was substantial evidence in the record to reasonably support the Commissioners findings of fact. Civil penalties owed under this section shall be paid to the Commissioner for deposit into the general fund of the Treasury of the Commonwealth. The Commissioner shall prescribe procedures for the payment of proposed penalties which are not contested by employers. History History. Code 1950, § 40-22.1; 1952, c. 525; 1962, c. 66; 1970, c. 321; 1973, c. 425; 1982, c. 84; 2015, c. 285. Annotations Cross references. For provisions as to enforcement of this title and rules and regulations adopted pursuant thereto, and penalties for violations, see § 40.1-49.4. The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendment by c. 285, in the second paragraph, deleted the former second sentence, which read A penalty determination by the Commissioner shall be fin al, unless within fifteen days after receipt of such notice the person charged with the violation notifies the Commissioner by certified mail that he intends to contest the proposed penalty before the appropriate general district court and added the remaining sentences. § 40.1-28.01. Nondisclosure or confidentiality agreement; provisions regarding sexual assault; condition of employment. Text A. No employer shall require an employee or a prospective employee to execute or renew any provision in a nondisclosure or confidentiality agreement that has the purpose or effect of concealing the details relating to a claim of sexual assault pursuant to § 18.2-61 , 18.2-67.1, 18.2-67.3, or 18.2-67.4 as a condition of employment. Any such provision is against public policy and is void and unenforceable. B. This sectio n shall in no way limit other grounds that exist at law or in equity for the unenforceability of any such agreement or any provision of such agreement. History History. 2019, c. 131. §§ 40.1-28.1 through 40.1-28.4:1. Repealed by Acts 2005, c. 823, effective July 1, 2005. § 40.1-28.5. Repealed by Acts 2004, c. 608. § 40.1-28.6. Equal pay irrespective of sex. Text No employer having employees shall discriminate, within any establishment in which such employees are employed, between employees on the basis of sex by paying wages to employees in such establishment at a rate less than the rate at which he pays wages to employees of the opposite sex in such establishment for equal work on jobs the performance of which requires equal skill, effort, and responsibility, and which are pe rformed under similar working conditions, except where such payment is made pursuant to (i) a seniority system; (ii) a merit system; (iii) a system which measures earnings by quantity or quality of production; or (iv) a differential based on any other fa ctor other than sex. For purposes of administration and enforcement, any amounts owing to any employee which have been withheld in violation of this section shall be deemed to be unpaid wag es or unpaid overtime compensation and the employee whose wages have been wrongfully withheld in violation of this section shall have a right of action therefor to recover damages to the extent of two times the amount of wages so withheld. This section shall not apply to employers covered by the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 as amended. Every action under this section shall be brought within two years next after the right to bring the same shall have accrued; provided, however, that nothing herein shall be construed to give rise to a cause of action for work performed prior to July 1, 1974. History History. 1974, c. 405. Annotations The number of this section was assigned by the Virginia Code Commission, the number in the 1974 act having been 40.1-28.1. Editors note. For the Fair Labor Standards Act, referred to above, see 29 U.S.C. § 201 et seq. Acts 2020, c. 901, cl. 1 provides: That the Division of Human Rights of the Department of Law (the Division) is directed to develop recommendations regarding the type of information about businesses and their employees and the accompanying methodology that would be required for the Division to proactively enforce the provisions of § 40.1-28.6 of the Code of Virginia requiring equal pay of similarly situate d employees irrespective of sex. Additionally, the Division shall develop recommendations regarding the data and methodological requirements for proactively enforcing a requirement for equal pay irrespective of race. The Division shall also develop recom mendations regarding appropriate enforcement mechanisms, including causes of action and civil remedies, to address discrimination in compensation based on sex and race. In developing such recommendations, the Division shall engage stakeholders representi ng employers and employees in the Commonwealth. The Division shall report its findings and recommendations to the Governor and the General Assembly no later than November 30, 2020. Law Review. For article, The Status of the At-Will Employment Doctrine in Virginia after Bowman v. State Bank of Keysville, see 20 U. Rich. L. Rev. 267 (1986). For article, The Law of Wrongful Discharge in Virginia, see 10 G.M.U. L. Rev. 133 (1988). For article, Employment Law, see 54 U. Rich. L. Rev. 103 (2019). CASE NOTES Applicability.  This section deals only with equal pay for equal work and was not applicable to an action alleging not unequal pay but a discriminatory discharge. Barlow v. AVCO Corp., 527 F. Supp. 269, 1981 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 16973 (E.D. Va. 1981). § 40.1-28.7. Repealed by Acts 1985, c. 421. Annotations Cross references. For present provisions as to remedies for the violation of rights of disabled persons, see § 51.5-46. § 40.1-28.7:1. Genetic testing or genetic characteristics as a condition of employment. Text A. No employer shall: 1. Reque st, require, solicit or administer a genetic test, as defined in § 38.2-508.4, to any person as a condition of employment; or 2. Refuse to hire, fail to promote, discharge or otherwise adversely affect any terms or conditions of employment of any employee or prospective employee solely on the basis of a genetic characteristic, as defined in § 38.2-508.4, or the results of a genetic test, regardless of how the employer obtained such information or results. Nothing in this section shall preclude the use of information related to a criminal investigation. B. The employe e may bring an action in a court of competent jurisdiction over the employer who took adverse action against the employee in violation of this section. Any such action shall be brought within 180 days from the date of the adverse action. The court may, i n its discretion, award actual or punitive damages, including back pay with interest at the judgment rate as provided in § 6.2-302, or injunctive relief. C. Nothing in this section shall be construed to require the Department of Labor and Industry to conduct any investigations or enforcement actions. D. As used in subdivision A 2 of this section, terms and conditions of employment shall not include any long term care, life or disability insurance policy. History History. 2002, cc. 565, 659. Annotations Editors note. Effective October 1, 2010, § 6.2-302 was substituted for § 6.1-330.54 in subsection B to conform to the recodification of Title 6.1 by Acts 2010, c. 794. Law Review. For article surveying developments in labor and employment law in Virginia, see 37 U. Rich. L. Rev. 241 (2002). § 40.1-28.7:2. Employers to allow crime victims leave to attend criminal proceedings. Text A. As used in this section:Criminal proceedings means a proceeding at which the victim has the right or opportu nity to appear involving a crime against the victim, including: 1. The i nitial appearance of the person suspected of committing the criminal offense against the victim; 2. Any proceeding in which the court considers the post-arrest release of the person accused of committing a criminal offense against the victim or the conditions of that release; 3. Any proceeding in which a negotiated plea for the person accused of committing the criminal offense against the victim will be presented to the court; 4. Any sentencing proceeding; 5. Any proceeding in which postconviction release from confinement is considered; 6. Any probation revocation disposition proceeding or any proceedin...</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-29"><akn:num>§ 40.1-29</akn:num><akn:heading>Time and medium of payment; withholding wages; written statement of earnings; agreement for forfeiture of wages; proceedings to enforce compliance; p enalties</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. All employe rs operating a business or engaging an individual to perform domestic service shall establish regular pay periods and rates of pay for employees except executive personnel. All such employers shall pay salaried employees at least once each month and empl oyees paid on an hourly rate at least once every two weeks or twice in each month, except that (i) a student who is currently enrolled in a work-study program or its equivalent administered by any secondary school, institution of higher education, or tra de school, and (ii) employees whose weekly wages total more than 150 percent of the average weekly wage of the Commonwealth as defined in § 65.2-500, upon agreement by each affected employee, may be paid once each month if the institution or employer so chooses. Upon termination of employment an employee shall be paid all wages or salaries due him for work performed prior thereto; such payment shall be made on or before the date on which he would have been paid for such work had his employment not be en terminated. B. Payment of wages or salaries shall be (i) in lawful money of the United States, (ii) by check payable at face value upon demand in lawful money of the United States, (iii) by electronic automated fund transfer in lawful money of the United States into an account in the name of the employee at a financial institution designated by the employee, or (iv) by credit to a prepaid debit card or card account from which the employee is able to withdraw or transfer funds with full written disclosure by the employer of any a pplicable fees and affirmative consent thereto by the employee. However, an employer that elects not to pay wages or salaries in accordance with clause (i) or (ii) to an employee who is hired after January 1, 2010, shall be permitted to pay wages or sala ries by credit to a prepaid debit card or card account in accordance with clause (iv), even though such employee has not affirmatively consented thereto, if the employee fails to designate an account at a financial institution in accordance with clause ( iii) and the employer arranges for such card or card account to be issued through a network system through which the employee shall have the ability to make at least one free withdrawal or transfer per pay period, which withdrawal may be for any sum in s uch card or card account as the employee may elect, using such card or card account at financial institutions participating in such network system. C. No employer shall withhold any part of the wages or salaries of any employee except for payroll, wage or withholding taxes or in accordance with law, without the written and signed authorization of the employee. On each regular pay date, each employer, other than a n employer engaged in agricultural employment including agribusiness and forestry, shall provide to each employee a written statement, by a paystub or online accounting, that shows the name and address of the employer; the number of hours worked during t he pay period if the employee is paid on the basis of (i) the number of hours worked or (ii) a salary that is less than the standard salary level adopted by regulation of the U.S. Department of Labor pursuant to § 13(a)(1) of the federal Fair Labor St andards Act, 29 U.S.C. § 213(a)(1), as amended, establishing an exemption from the Acts overtime premium pay requirements; the rate of pay; the gross wages earned by the employee during the pay period; and the amount and purpose of any deductions therefrom. The paystub or online accounting shall include sufficient information to enable the employee to determine how the gross and net pay were calculated. An employer engaged in agricultural employment including agribusiness and forestry, upon reque st of its employee, shall furnish the employee a written statement of the gross wages earned by the employee during any pay period and the amount and purpose of any deductions therefrom. D. No employer shall require any employee, except executive personnel, to sign any contract or agreement which provides for the forfeiture of the employees wages for time worked as a condition of employment or the continuance therein, except as otherwise provided by law. E. An employer who willfully and with intent to defraud fails or refuses to pay wages in accordance with this section or § 40.1-29.3, unless the failure to pay was because of a bona fide dispute between the employer and its employee: 1. To an employee or employees is guilty of a Class 1 misdemeanor if the value of the wages earned and not paid by the employer is less than $10,000; and 2. To an employee or employees is guilty of a Class 6 felony (i) if the value of the wages earned and not paid is $10,000 or more or (ii) regardless of the value of the wages earned and n ot paid, if the conviction is a second or subsequent conviction under this section or § 40.1-29.3. For purposes of this section, the determination as to the value of the wages earned shall be made by combining all wages the employer failed or refused to pay p ursuant to this section and § 40.1-29.3. F. The Commiss ioner may require a written complaint of the violation of this section and, with the written and signed consent of an employee, may institute proceedings on behalf of an employee to enforce compliance with this section, and to collect any moneys unlawful ly withheld from such employee that shall be paid to the employee entitled thereto. In addition, following the issuance of a final order by the Commissioner or a court, the Commissioner may engage private counsel, approved by the Attorney General, to col lect any moneys owed to the employee or the Commonwealth. Upon entry of a final order of the Commissioner, or upon entry of a judgment, against the employer, the Commissioner or the court shall assess attorney fees of one-third of the amount set forth in the final order or judgment. G. In addition to being subject to any other penalty provided by the provisions of this section, any employer who fails to make payment of wages in accordance with subsection A shall be liable for the payment of all wages due, and an additional equal amount as liquida ted damages, plus interest at an annual rate of eight percent accruing from the date the wages were due. H. Any employe r who knowingly fails to make payment of wages in accordance with subsection A or § 40.1-29.3 shall be subject to a civil penalty not to exceed $1,000 for each violation. The Commissioner shall notify any employer that the Commissioner alleges has vio lated any provision of this section or § 40.1-29.3 by certified mail. Such notice shall contain a description of the alleged violation. Within 15 days of receipt of notice of the alleged violation, the employer may request an informal conference regar ding such violation with the Commissioner. In determining the amount of any penalty to be imposed, the Commissioner shall consider the size of the business of the employer charged and the gravity of the violation. The decision of the Commissioner shall b e final. Civil penalties owed under this section shall be paid to the Commissioner for deposit into the general fund of the State Treasurer. The Commissioner shall prescribe procedures for the payment of proposed assessments of penalties that are not con tested by employers. Such procedures shall include provisions for an employer to consent to abatement of the alleged violation and pay a proposed penalty or a negotiated sum in lieu of such penalty without admission of any civil liability arising from su ch alleged violation. I. Final order s of the Commissioner, the general district courts, or the circuit courts may be recorded, enforced, and satisfied as orders or decrees of a circuit court upon certification of such orders by the Commissioner or the court as appropriate. J. In addition to any civil or criminal penalty provided by this section, and without regard to any exhaustion of alternative administrative remedies provided for in this section, if an employer fails to pay wages to an employee in accordance with this section, the em ployee may bring an action, individually, jointly, with other aggrieved employees, or on behalf of similarly situated employees as a collective action consistent with the collective action procedures of the Fair Labor Standards Act, 29 U.S.C. § 216(b) , against the employer in a court of competent jurisdiction to recover payment of the wages, and the court shall award the wages owed, an additional equal amount as liquidated damages, plus prejudgment interest thereon as provided in subsection G, and re asonable attorney fees and costs. If the court finds that the employer knowingly failed to pay wages to an employee in accordance with this section, the court shall award the employee an amount equal to triple the amount of wages due and reasonable attor ney fees and costs. K. As used in this section, a person acts knowingly if the person, with respect to information, (i) has actual knowledge of the information, (ii) acts in deliberate ignorance of the truth or falsity of the information, or (iii) acts in reckless disregard of th e truth or falsity of the information. Establishing that a person acted knowingly shall not require proof of specific intent to defraud. L. An action u nder this section shall be commenced within three years after the cause of action accrued. The period for filing is tolled upon the filing of an administrative action under subsection F until the employee has been informed that the action has been resolv ed or until the employee has withdrawn the complaint, whichever is sooner. History History. Code 1950, § 40-24; 1962, c. 66; 1966, c. 88; 1968, c. 262; 19 70, c. 321; 1972, c. 848; 1977, c. 308; 1979, c. 50; 1989, c. 583; 1991, c. 499; 1993, c. 600; 2002, c. 321; 2003, c. 638; 2004, c. 358; 2005, cc. 595, 851; 2009, c. 728; 2016, c. 593; 2019, cc. 836, 845; 2020, cc. 202, 868, 1038; 2021, Sp. Sess. I, cc. 445, 513; 2022, cc. 461...</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-30"><akn:num>§ 40.1-30</akn:num><akn:heading>Registration of certain nonresident employers with Department</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text (a) Any employ er domiciled without this Commonwealth and performing any demolition, excavation, installation, paving, repair, maintenance, erection or construction work within this Commonwealth for a fixed price, commission, fee or percentage, when the cost of the und ertaking, order, contract or subcontract is not less than $300 nor more than $60,000, shall, prior to the commencement of each such undertaking or the performance of each such order, contract or subcontract, register with the Department, at Richmond, on such form as may be prescribed by said Department, providing thereon the employers name and address, the name and address of the employers chief officer or owner, the name and address of the person in charge of the work being done, the type of wo rk to be done, the date work will commence, the specific location of the work, the name of the person, firm, corporation, partnership or association for whom the work is being performed, the cost of the undertaking or the amount of the order, contract or subcontract and the approximate number of persons employed by the employer in said undertaking or performance, including the rates of pay and the number of persons employed at each rate and shall be submitted to the Department with a United States posta l service money order or check drawn in favor of the State Treasurer in the amount of $100 for annual registration or $25 for registration for a specific job. Provided, however, nothing in this section shall apply to any such contractor who is registered under the provisions of Title 54.1, Chapter 11. Provided further, that any such employer may apply to the Department for annual registration which, if granted, shall relieve such employer from registration of each specific contract. Annual registration may be granted if the Department shall ascertain that such employer has a permanent and definite place of business outside this Commonwealth. (b) Any employ er failing to register with the Department as required by this section shall be guilty of a misdemeanor and upon conviction shall be fined not less than $100 nor more than $500. Each days failure to register shall constitute a separate offense. (c) This secti on shall be enforceable by the Commissioner and all officers empowered to enforce the criminal laws of this Commonwealth. History History. Code 1950, § 40-24.1; 1966, c. 614; 1968, c. 106; 1970, c. 321 ; 1972, c. 241; 1979, c. 484.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-31"><akn:num>§ 40.1-31</akn:num><akn:heading>Assignment of wages and salaries; requirements</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text No assignment, transfer, pledge or hypothecation of wages or salary due or to become due to any person shall be valid and enforceable against any employer of the assign or, except with the express consent in writing of such employer given to the creditor or assignee, unless and until all of the following requirements have been fully met: (1) Such assignment is printed in type not smaller than pica, is a separate instrument not incorporated in or made a part of any other contract or instrument, and is plainly designated Wage Assignment. (2) Such assignment is executed in triplicate and in person by the assignor, is dated on the date on which it is executed, one executed copy thereof is delivered to the assignor, and on e executed copy is mailed to the employer therein named within fifteen days after the execution thereof; provided, however, that such copy mailed to the employer shall be for his information only, and shall not be construed as giving such employer legal notice of the assignees intention to enforce the terms thereof or as constituting the notice referred to in § 8.01-13. (3) The name of employer of the assignor is written therein before the signing thereof and the total amount, if any, which is to be secured thereby is plainly stated therein. (4) The assignor is, at the time of the execution of the assignment, employed by the employer therein named. (5) Ten days before any notice of the assignees intention to enforce the terms of the assignment is served upon the employer, the assignee gives the assignor notice in writing sent by mail to his last known address that default has been made in his obligation. (6) Notice of the assignees intention to enforce the terms of an assignment has been served on the employer by an officer or other person authorized to serve civil process. Such not ice shall be valid to make the assignment effective only from the time it is served. (7) Whenever the assignor changes his employment after executing an assignment contemplated by this section then any assignee who has otherwise fully complied with the provisions of thi s section may enforce his assignment against the new employer of the assignor provided that he mails a copy of the assignment to the new employer within fifteen days after learning of such change of employment and gives the same notice or notices to the new employer as is required to be given to the original employer and complies with the conditions of subdivision (5) hereof. History History. Code 1950, § 40-30; 1970, c. 321. Annotations Cross references. As to exemption of assignment of earnings to satisfy or retire a support debt or obligation from the requirements of this section, see § 63.2-1945. Law Review. For article, Uniform Consumer Credit Code  A Prospect for Consumer Credit Reform in Virginia, see 28 Wash. &amp; Lee L. Rev. 75 (1971). Research References. Virginia Forms (Matthew Bender). No. 13-101 Assignment of Debt by Creditor. Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 2A M.J. Assignments, § 12; 8A M.J. Exemptions from Execut ion and Attachment, § 22; 12B M.J. Master and Servant, § 10. CASE NOTES Applicability.  This section is confined to wages or salary due or to become due by any employer. Knight v. Peoples Nat'l Bank, 182 Va. 380, 29 S.E.2d 364, 1944 Va. LEXIS 187 (19 44). The application of this section, making unenforceable against any employer any assignment of wages or salary except with the consent of the employer, is optional with the employer. Knight v. Peoples Nat'l Bank, 182 Va. 380, 29 S.E.2d 364, 1944 Va. LEXIS 187 (1944). Purpose.  The dominant purpose of this section is the protection of his interest rather than the protection of the interest of the employee. Knight v. Peoples Nat'l Bank, 1 82 Va. 380, 29 S.E.2d 364, 1944 Va. LEXIS 187 (1944). This section was not intended as a weapon for another creditor of the assignor to fight his way to a more favorable position in line of payment. Knight v. Peoples Nat'l Bank, 182 Va. 380, 29 S.E.2d 364, 1944 Va. LEXIS 187 (1944). Assignment of unearned salary or wag es.  The unearned salary or wages of municipal and state employees can be assigned if, at the time of the assignment, the assignor be employed, although it may not be necessary that his employment be for any particular time. Knight v. Peoples Nat'l Bank, 182 Va. 380, 29 S.E.2d 364, 1944 Va. LEXIS 187 (1944). A municipality is not an employer of a tax assessor appointed by a court, within the mea ning of this section. Knight v. Peoples Nat'l Bank, 182 Va. 380, 29 S.E.2d 364, 1944 Va. LEXIS 187 (1944).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-32"><akn:num>§ 40.1-32</akn:num><akn:heading>Partial assignments invalid</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text No partial assignment of wages shall be enforceable at law or in equity; provided, however, that an assignment of all wages over and above the exemption provided in § 34-29 shall not be considered a partial assignment under the provisions of this section. History History. Code 1950, § 40-31; 1970, c. 321. Annotations Cross references. As to assignment of earnings to satisfy or retire a support debt or obligation, see § 63.2-1945. Research References. Virginia Forms (Matthew Bender). No. 13-101 Assignment of Debt by Creditor; No. 13-103 Assignment of Part of Claim.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-33"><akn:num>§ 40.1-33</akn:num><akn:heading>Certain assignments not affected</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The two preceding sections (§§ 40.1-31, 40.1-32) shall not be construed to apply to assignments of salaries, wages and income for the benefit of creditors as prov ided for in Article 2 (§ 8.01-525.6 et seq.) of Chapter 18.1 of Title 8.01. History History. Code 1950, § 40-32; 1970, c. 321. Annotations Cross references. As to assignment of earnings to satisfy or retire a support debt or obligation, see § 63.2-1945. Editors note. To conform to the recodification of Title 55 by Acts 2019, c. 712, effective October 1, 2019, the following substitution was made at the direction of the Virginia Code Commission: substituted Article 2 (§ 8.01-525.6 et seq.) of Chapter 18.1 of Title 8.01 for §§ 55-161 to 55-167. Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 2A M.J. Assignments, § 12; 8A M.J. Exemptions from Execut ion and Attachment, § 22; 12B M.J. Master and Servant, § 10. § 40.1-33.1. Retaliatory actions prohibited; civil penalty. Text A. An employer shall not discharge, discipline, threaten, discriminate against, or penalize an employee or independent contractor, or take other retaliatory action regarding an employee or independent contractors compensation, terms, conditions, location, or privi leges of employment, because the employee or independent contractor: 1. Has r eported or plans to report to an appropriate authority that an employer, or any officer or agent of the employer, has failed to properly classify an individual as an employee and failed to pay required benefits or other contributions; or 2. Is requested or subpoenaed by an appropriate authority to participate in an investigation, hearing, or inquiry by an appropriate authority or in a court action. B. The provisi ons of subsection A shall apply only if an employee or independent contractor who discloses information about suspected worker misclassification has done so in good faith and upon a reasonable belief that the information is accurate. Disclosures that are reckless or the employee knew or should have known were false, confidential by law, or malicious shall not be deemed good faith reports and shall not be subject to the protections provided by subsection A. C. Any employe e who is discharged, disciplined, threatened, discriminated against, or penalized in a manner prohibited by this section may file a complaint with the Commissioner. The Commissioner, with the written and signed consent of such an employee, may institute proceedings against the employer for appropriate remedies for such action, including reinstatement of the employee and recovering lost wages. D. Any employe r who discharges, disciplines, threatens, discriminates against, or penalizes an employee in a manner prohibited by this section shall be subject to a civil penalty not to exceed the amount of the employees wages that are lost as a result of the viol ation. Civil penalties under this section shall be assessed by the Commissioner and paid to the Literary Fund. History History. 2020, cc. 204, 271. § 40.1-33.2. Discriminatory actions prohibited. Text A. An employer shall not discharge or in any other manner discriminate against an employee because such employee has filed any complaint or instituted or caused to be instituted any proceeding under § 40.1-29, or has testified or is about to testify in any such pro ceeding. B. Any employe e who is discharged or in any other manner discriminated against in a manner prohibited by this section may file a complaint with the Commissioner, and the Commissioner, with the written and signed consent of an employee, may institute proceedings on beh alf of an employee for appropriate remedies for such action, including reinstatement of the employee and recovering lost wages and an additional amount equal to the lost wages as liquidated damages. History History. 2020, cc. 950, 951, § 40.1-33.1. Annotations The number of this section was assigned by the Virginia Code Commission, the number in the 2020 acts having been § 40.1-33.1. Article 2.1. Paid Sick Leave. -360§ 40.1-33.3. Definitions. -360§ 40.1-33.4. Accrual of paid sick leave. -360§ 40.1-33.5. Use of paid sick leave. -360§ 40.1-33.6. Retaliatory action prohibited. § 40.1-33.3. Definitions. Text As used in this article, unless the context requires a different meaning: Employee means a home health worker who works on average at least 20 hours per week o r 90 hours per month. Employee does not include an individual who (i) is licensed, registered, or certified by a health regulatory board within the Department of Health Professions; (ii) is employed by a hospital licensed by the Department of Hea lth; and (iii) works, on average, no more than 30 hours per month. Employer has the same meaning as provided in § 40.1-2. Employer does not in clude any agency of the federal government. Family member means: 1. Regar dless of age, a biological child, adopted or foster child, stepchild, legal ward, child to whom the employee stands in loco parentis, or individual to whom an employee stood in loco parentis when the individual was a minor; 2. A biological parent, foster parent, stepparent, adoptive parent, legal guardian of an employee or an employees spouse, or individual who stood in loco parentis to an employee when the employee or employees spouse was a minor child; 3. An individual to whom an employee is legally married under the laws of any state; 4. A grandparent, grandchild, or sibling, whether of a biological, foster, adoptive, or step relationship, of an employee or the employees spouse; 5. An individual for whom an employee is responsible for providing or arranging care, including helping that individual obtain diagnostic, preventive, routine, or therapeutic health treat ment; or 6. Any other individual related by blood or affinity whose close association with an employee is the equivalent of a family relationship. Home health worker means an individual who provides personal care, respite, or companion services to an individual who receives consumer-directed services under the state plan for medical assistance services.Paid sick leave means leave that i s compensated at the same hourly rate and with the same benefits, including health care benefits, as an employee normally earns during hours worked and is provided by an employer to an employee for the purposes described in § 40.1-33.5; however, such hourly rate shall not be less than the minimum wage amount set forth in § 40.1-28.10 without reduction for any tip credit that the employer would otherwise be permitted to claim. History History. 2021, Sp. Sess. I, c. 449. Annotations Effective date. This section is effective July 1, 2021. § 40.1-33.4. Accrual of paid sick leave. Text A. All employe es shall accrue a minimum of one hour of paid sick leave for every 30 hours worked. Paid sick leave shall be carried over to the year following the year in which it was accrued. An employee shall not accrue or use more than 40 hours of paid sick leave in a year, unless the employer selects a higher limit. B. Employees w ho are exempt from overtime requirements under 29 U.S.C. § 213(a)(1) of the federal Fair Labor Standards Act, 29 U.S.C. § 201 et seq., will be assumed to work 40 hours in each workweek for purposes of paid sick leave accrual unless their normal wor kweek is less than 40 hours, in which case paid sick leave accrues on the basis of that normal workweek. C. Paid sick l eave as provided in this section shall begin to accrue at the commencement of employment. An employer may provide all paid sick leave that an employee is expected to accrue in a year at the beginning of the year. D. Any employe r with a paid leave policy, such as a paid time off policy, that provides an employee an amount of paid leave sufficient to meet the requirements of this section and that may be used for the same purposes and under the same conditions as paid sick leave under this article shall not be required to provide additional paid sick leave to any employee that is eligible for paid leave under the policy. E. Any employe r that has entered into a bona fide collective bargaining agreement that requires the employer to provide an amount of paid leave sufficient to meet the requirements of this section and that may be used for the same purposes and under the same conditions as paid sick leave under this article shall not be required to provide additional paid sick leave to any employee covered by such collective bargaining agreement. History History. 2021, Sp. Sess. I, c. 449. Annotations Effective date. This section is effective July 1, 2021. § 40.1-33.5. Use of paid sick leave. Text A. Paid sick l eave shall be provided to an employee by an employer for: 1. An em ployees mental or physical illness, injury, or health condition; an employees need for medical diagnosis, care, or treatment of a mental or physical illness, injury, or health condition; or an employees need for preventive medical care; or 2. Care of a family member with a mental or physical illness, injury, or health condition; care of a family member who needs medical diagnosis, care, or treatment of a mental or physical illness, injury, or health condition; or care of a family member who needs preventive medical care. B. Paid sick l eave shall be provided upon the request of an employee. Such request may be made orally, in writing, by electronic means, or by any other means acceptable to the employer. When possible, the request shall include the expected duration of the absence. C. When the us e of paid sick leave is foreseeable, the employee shall make a good faith effort to provide notice of the need for such leave to the employer in advance of the use of the paid sick leave and shall make a reasonable effort to schedule the use of paid sick leave in a manner that does not unduly disrupt the operations of the employer. D. An employer that requires notice of the need to use paid sick leave shall provide a written policy that contains procedures for its emplo...</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-34"><akn:num>§ 40.1-34</akn:num><akn:heading>40</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>1-34 through 40.1-38. Repealed by Acts 1974, c. 272. Article 4. Sanitary Provisions. -360§ 40.1-39. Repealed by Acts 1979, c. 354. -360§ 40.1-40. Repealed by Acts 1985, c. 449.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-39"><akn:num>§ 40.1-39</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1979, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>354.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-40"><akn:num>§ 40.1-40</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1985, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>449. Article 5. Safety Provisions. -360§§ 40.1-41 through 40.1-43. Repealed by Acts 1979, c. 354. -360§ 40.1-44. Repealed by Acts 1973, c. 425. -360§ 40.1-44.1. Rules and regulations relating to tramways and other hauling and lifting devices. -360§§ 40.1-45 through 40.1-48. Repealed by Acts 1979, c. 354. -360§ 40.1-49. Repealed by Acts 1973, c. 425. -360§ 40.1-49.1. Repealed by Acts 1976, c. 607. -360§ 40.1-49.2. Repealed by Acts 1979, c. 354. -360§ 40.1-49.3. Definitions. -360§ 40.1-49.4. Enforcement of this title and standards, rules or regulations for safety and health; orders of Commissioner; proceedin gs in circuit court; injunctions; penalties. -360§ 40.1-49.5. Appeals to Court of Appeals. -360§ 40.1-49.6. Same; attorneys for Commonwealth. -360§ 40.1-49.7. Same; publication of orders. -360§ 40.1-49.8. Inspections of workplace. -360§ 40.1-49.9. Issuance of warrant. -360§ 40.1-49.10. Duration of warrant. -360§ 40.1-49.11. Conduct of inspection, testing, or collection of samples for analysis. -360§ 40.1-49.12. Review by courts. -360§ 40.1-49.13. Voluntary Protection Program. -360§ 40.1-50. Repealed by Acts 1985, c. 449. -360§ 40.1-51. State Health Commissioner to provide advice and aid; rules and regulations. -360§ 40.1-51.1. Duties of employers. -360§ 40.1-51.1:1. Repealed by Acts 1979, c. 354. -360§ 40.1-51.2. Rights and duties of employees. -360§ 40.1-51.2:1. Discrimination against employee for exercising rights prohibited. -360§ 40.1-51.2:2. Remedy for discrimination. -360§ 40.1-51.3. Duties of health and safety inspectors. -360§ 40.1-51.3:1. Penalty for giving advance notice of safety or health inspection under this title. -360§ 40.1-51.3:2. Evidence of civil penalty against employer under state, federal, etc., safety codes inadmissible in personal injury or property damage trial. -360§ 40.1-51.4. Repealed by Acts 1979, c. 354. -360§ 40.1-51.4:1. Confidentiality of trade secrets. -360§ 40.1-51.4:2. Penalty for making false statements, etc. -360§ 40.1-51.4:3. Prohibition of use of certain questions on polygraph tests for employment. -360§ 40.1-51.4:4. Prohibition of use of polygraphs in certain employment situations. -360§ 40.1-51.4:5. Immunity of employees for reporting threatening conduct.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-41"><akn:num>§ 40.1-41</akn:num><akn:heading>40</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>1-41 through 40.1-43. Repealed by Acts 1979, c. 354.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-44"><akn:num>§ 40.1-44</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1973, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>425. § 40.1-44.1. Rules and regulations relating to tramways and other hauling and lifting devices. Text (a) The Safety and Health Codes Board in the adoption of rules and regulations under this title shall adopt such reasonable rules and regulations as are designed to protect the safety and health of the employees engaged in the construction, maintenance, repair and ope ration of tramways or any other hauling or lifting device used as a public or employee conveyance, and to protect the safety and health of the public or the employees when using such conveyance in, about, or in connection with recreational areas, excludi ng vehicular travel covered by ICC, SCC, motor vehicle codes and § 36-98.3. (b) The rules and regulations adopted by the Safety and Health Codes Board pursuant to subsection (a) of this section shall be enforced as specified in §§ 40.1-49.3 through 40.1-49.7. History History. 1972, c. 602; 1973, c. 425; 1979, c. 406.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-45"><akn:num>§ 40.1-45</akn:num><akn:heading>40</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>1-45 through 40.1-48. Repealed by Acts 1979, c. 354.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-49"><akn:num>§ 40.1-49</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1973, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>425. Annotations Cross references. For present provisions as to enforcement of this title and rules and regulations adopted pursuant thereto, and penalties for violations, see § 40.1-49.4. § 40.1-49.1. Repealed by Acts 1976, c. 607. Annotations Cross references. For present provisions covering the subject matter of the repealed section, see § 40.1-49.4. § 40.1-49.2. Repealed by Acts 1979, c. 354. Annotations Cross references. For present section covering the subject matter of the repealed section, see § 40.1-49.4. § 40.1-49.3. Definitions. Text For the purposes of §§ 40.1-49.4, 40.1-49.5, 40.1-49.6, 40.1-49.7, and 40.1-51.1 through 40.1-51.3 the following terms shall have the following meanings: Commission means the Virginia Workers Compensation Commission. Commissioner means the Commissioner of Labor and Industry. Except where the context cl early indicates the contrary, any reference to Commissioner shall include his authorized representatives. Employee means an individual who is employed by an employer. Employer means any person that (i) is engaged in business or engages an individual to perform domestic service and (ii) has employees. Employer does not include the United States. Occupational safety and health standard means a standard which requires conditions, or the adoption or use of one or more practices, means, methods, operations, or processes, reasonably necessary or appropriate to provide safe or healthful employment and places of employment. Serious violation means a violation deemed to exist in a place of employment if there is a substantial probability that death or serious physical harm could result from a condition which exists, or from one or more practices, means, methods, operations, or processes which have been adopted or are in use, in such place of employment unless the employer did not, and could not with the exercise of reasonable diligence, know of the presence of the violation. Person means one or more individuals, partnerships, associations, corporations, busine ss trusts, legal representatives, or any organized group of persons. Circuit court means the circuit court of the city or county wherein the violation of t his title or any standard, rule or regulation issued pursuant thereto is alleged to have occurred. Venue shall be determined in accordance with the provisions of §§ 8.01-257 through 8.01-267. History History. 1979, c. 354; 1992, c. 777; 2021, Sp. Sess. I, cc. 509, 513. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2021, Sp. Sess. I, c. 513, cl. 2 provides: That the provisions of this act may result in a net increase in periods of imprisonment or commitment. Pursuan t to § 30-19.1:4 of the Code of Virginia, the estimated amount of the necessary appropriation cannot be determined for periods of imprisonment in state adult correctional facilities; therefore, Chapter 1289 of the Acts of Assembly of 2020 requires the Virginia Criminal Sentencing Commission to assign a minimum fiscal impact of $50,000. Pursuant to § 30-19.1:4 of the Code of Virginia, the estimated amount of the necessary appropriation cannot be determined for periods of commitment to the custody o f the Department of Juvenile Justice. The 2021 Sp. Sess. I amendments. The 2021 amendments by Sp. Sess. I, cc. 509 and 513, effective July 1, 2021, are identical, and rewrote the definitions for Employee and Employer. Law Review. For survey of Virginia administrative law and utility regulation for the year 1978-1979, see 66 Va. L. Rev. 193 (1980). CASE NOTES Foremans knowlege of serious violation imputed to employer.  It is a longstanding principle in the Commonwealth that a foremans knowledge of facts or events on a worksite is imputed to his employer, and this rule applie s to impute a foremans knowledge of a serious violation under this section to his employer. Magco of Maryland, Inc. v. Barr, 33 Va. App. 78, 531 S.E.2d 614, 2000 Va. App. LEXIS 565 (2000), aff'd, 262 Va. 1, 545 S.E.2d 548, 2001 Va. LEXIS 59 ( 2001). Employers constructi ve knowledge of hazard.  Under this section, the Commissioners burden of establishing a serious violation may be met upon a showing that the employer should have known of the violation in the exercise of reasonable diligence. Magco of Maryland, Inc. v. Barr, 33 Va. App. 78, 531 S.E.2d 614, 2000 Va. App. LEXIS 565 (2000), aff'd, 262 Va. 1, 545 S.E.2d 548, 2001 Va. LEXIS 59 (2001). The standard for establishing an employers constructive knowledge of a workplace hazard was met where the companys operations manager and vice president a nd the companys president had primary responsibility for inspecting the site and regularly did so, where the safety hazard posed by uncovered or incompletely covered holes in the roof at the site was open and obvious, and where the company officials were informed about the absence of full coverings for the holes and the safety hazard they posed. Magco of Maryland, Inc. v. Barr, 33 Va. App. 78, 531 S.E.2d 614, 2000 Va. App. LEXIS 565 (2000), aff'd, 262 Va. 1, 545 S.E.2d 548, 2001 Va. LEXIS 59 (2001). Circuit court did not err in finding that the Commissioner of the Virginia Department of Labor and Industry met his burden of proving by a preponderance of the ev idence that a county department of public works and environmental services had actual or constructive knowledge of safety violations because the record contained ample evidence from which one could conclude that the department should have known that its measures to prevent employees from entering permit-required confined spaces in violation of its policies were ineffective and that permit-required confined spaces on private land were not being evaluated; the circuit court correctly found substantial evi dence that the department should have known about the deficiencies in its program and provided training to remedy those issues. Fairfax County Dep't of Pub. Works &amp; Envtl. Servs. v. Davenport, 2009 Va. App. LEXIS 576 (Va. Ct. App. Dec. 22, 2009). Asbestos violations properly classified as other than serious.  Employers violations of employee health and safety standards regarding asbestos exposure were properly classified as other than serious, under subsect ion G of § 40.1-49.4, because, (1) under 16 VAC 25-60-10, an other than serious violation could occur if there were a direct or immediate relationship to employees safety and health, (2) the question presented was whether sufficient credib le evidence showed a direct relationship between an employees exposure to asbestos materials and an employees health and safety, and (3) such evidence was present, as employees exposure to asbestos material was previously established, and tes timony was presented that asbestos was a carcinogen. Nat'l College of Bus. &amp; Tech., Inc. v. Malveaux, 60 Va. App. 22, 723 S.E.2d 270, 2012 Va. App. LEXIS 104 (2012). Respondeat superior.  In affirming citations proposed by the Commissioner of the Virginia Department of Labor and Industry against a construction company for two workplace safety viola tions, the circuit correctly applied respondeat superior principles; relying upon these principles, the circuit courts unchallenged factual findings fully supported its decision to affirm the two citations against the company for serious violations o f the Virginia Occupational Safety and Health Act standards for fall protection. Atl. Envtl. Constr. Co. v. Malveaux, 63 Va. App. 656, 762 S.E.2d 409, 2014 Va. App. LEXIS 292 (2014). CIRCUIT COURT OPINIONS Employers constructi ve knowledge of hazard.  As there was substantial evidence that a county department of public works had or should have had constructive knowledge of the hazards of a wet pond facility whe re its employee sustained fatal injuries, its violations of several subsections of 29 C.F.R. § 1910.146 were properly deemed serious under § 40.1-49.3.Fairfax County Dep't of Pub. Works v. Davenport, 2009 Va. Cir. LEXIS 16 (Fairfax County M ar. 3, 2009), aff'd in part and rev'd in part, No. 0745-09-4, 2009 Va. App. LEXIS 576 (Va. Ct. App. Dec. 22, 2009). VOSH violations not warranted.  As a compliance officer who issued a citation to a county department of public works for failure to review confined-space permits testified that he did not know whether a department of public works employee reviewed the permits, a hearing officer for the Virginia Department of Labor and Industry improperly sustained the citation. Fairfax County Dep't of Pub. Works v. Davenport, 2009 Va. Cir. LEXIS 16 (Fairfax Co unty Mar. 3, 2009), aff'd in part and rev'd in part, No. 0745-09-4, 2009 Va. App. LEXIS 576 (Va. Ct. App. Dec. 22, 2009). Upon entering a manhole, an employee for a county department of public works fell down a shaft and sustained fatal injuries. Substantial evidence supported the fi nding of a hearing officer for the Virginia Department of Labor and Industry that that the wet pond facility the employee entered was a permit-required confined space; the department of public works did not specify acceptable entry conditions as to the s pace; the space was not protected by proper barriers; the department of public works did not verify that conditions were safe for entry; it did not monitor the space, or provide necessary communications, rescue, and emergency equipment; it failed to deve lop procedures for summoning rescue services; and it failed to provide an attendant outside the permit space. Fairfax County Dep't of Pub. Works v. Davenport, 2009 Va. Cir. LEXIS 16 (Fairfax County Mar. 3, 2009), aff'd in part and rev'd in part, No. 0745 -09-4, 2009 Va. App. LEXIS 576 (Va. Ct. App. Dec. 22, 2009). VOSH violations warranted.  Upon entering a manhole, an employee for a county department of public works employee fell down a shaft and sustained fatal injuries. Substantial evidence support ed the finding of a hearing officer for the Virginia Department of Labor and Industry that the failure of the department of public works to provide an attendant ou...</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-50"><akn:num>§ 40.1-50</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1985, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>449.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-51"><akn:num>§ 40.1-51</akn:num><akn:heading>State Health Commissioner to provide advice and aid; rules and regulations</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. The State H ealth Commissioner shall be responsible for advising and providing technical aid to the Commissioner on matters pertaining to occupational health on request. B. The Departm ent of Labor and Industry shall be responsible for drafting and submitting to the Virginia Safety and Health Codes Board for adoption rules and regulations pertaining to control measures to protect the health of workers. In formulating rules and regulati ons pertaining to health, the Department of Labor and Industry shall request the advice and technical aid of the Department of Health. History History. Code 1950, § 40-62.2; 1950, p. 636; 1970, c. 321; 1972, c. 567 ; 1985, c. 449; 2003, c. 445. Annotations The 2003 amendments. The 2003 amendment by c. 445 added the subsection A and B designations; and deleted the former last paragraph, which read: This act shall not be interpreted t o change, affect, or transfer to the Department or to the Commissioner the duties imposed upon the State Corporation Commission by §§ 27-61 through 27-90. Law Review. For note on employee drug testing, see 74 Va. L. Rev. 969 (1988). § 40.1-51.1. Duties of employers. Text A. It shall be the duty of every employer to furnish to each of his employees safe employment and a place of employment that is free from recognized hazards that are causing or are likely to cause death or serious physical harm to his employees and to comply with all applicable occupational safety and health rules and regulations promulgated under this title. B. Every emplo yer shall provide to employees, by such suitable means as shall be prescribed in rules and regulations of the Safety and Health Codes Board, information regarding their exposure to toxic materials or harmful physical agents and prompt information when th ey are exposed to concentration or levels of toxic materials or harmful physical agents in excess of those prescribed by the applicable safety and health standards and shall provide employees or their representatives with the opportunity to observe monit oring or measuring of exposures. Every employer shall also inform any employee who is being exposed of the corrective action being taken and shall provide former employees with access to information about their exposure to toxic materials or harmful phys ical agents. C. Every emplo yer cited for a violation of any safety and health provisions of this title or standards, rules, and regulations promulgated thereunder shall post a copy of such citation at the site of the violations so noted as prescribed in the rules and regulations o f the Safety and Health Codes Board. D. Every emplo yer shall report to the Virginia Department of Labor and Industry within eight hours any work-related incident resulting in a fatality or within 24 hours any work-related incident resulting in (i) the inpatient hospitalization of one or more persons, (ii ) an amputation, or (iii) the loss of an eye, as prescribed in the rules and regulations of the Safety and Health Codes Board. E. Every emplo yer, through posting of notices or other appropriate means, shall keep his employees informed of their rights and responsibilities under this title and of specific safety and health standards applicable to his business establishment. F. An employer representative shall be given the opportunity to accompany the safety and health inspectors on safety or health inspections. G. Nothing in this section shall be construed to limit the authority of the Commissioner pursuant to § 40.1-6 or the Board pursuant to § 40.1-22 to promulgate necessary rules and regulations to protect and promote the safety and health of employees. History History. 1972, c. 602; 1973, c. 425; 1976, c. 607; 1979, c. 354; 1995, c. 373; 2015, c. 270; 2016, c. 336. Annotations The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendment by c. 270, in subsection D, inserted clause (i) and (ii) designations, substituted one or more for three or more in clause (ii) , inserted (iii) an amputation, or (iv) the loss of an eye, and made minor stylistic changes. The 2016 amendments. The 2016 amendment by c. 336, in subsection A, substituted that for which; in subsection D, deleted the former clause (i) designation preceding a fatality, substituted or within 24 hours any work-related incident resulting in (i) for the former clause (ii) designation, and redesignated former clauses (iii) and (iv) as clauses (ii) and (iii). Law Review. For survey of Virginia administrative law and utility regulation for the year 1978-1979, see 66 Va. L. Rev. 193 (1980). For article surveying developments in labor and employment law in Virginia, see 37 U. Rich. L. Rev. 241 (2002). Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 12B M.J. Master and Servant, § 20. CASE NOTES Contractors liability for subcontractors.  Although the Virginia Occupational Safety and Health Program contended a general contractor in control of a worksite should be held liable under tort principles f or a subcontractors Virginia Occupational Safety and Health Act violations, not a word of it can be found in the act or any rules and regulations promulgated under this section; none of these promulgated rules and regulations addresse d the liability interplay between general and subcontractors, much less the imputation of a subcontractors statutory defaults to a general contractor under a tort-based reasonable care standard. Davenport v. Summit Contrs., Inc., 45 Va. App. 526, 612 S.E.2d 239, 2005 Va. App. LEXIS 172 (2005). CIRCUIT COURT OPINIONS Standard of care.  Plaintiff, who sustained injuries while painting a barn roof for farmer, sought to introduce testimony by expert witness that OSHA regulations, OSHAs general duty clause, and this section create a community standard of care, but the court refused to allow the testimony on a community standard of care, in fact, based solely upon OSHA regulations, because OSHA was not intended to create a private civil remedy for damages. Beamer v. Thompson, 77 Va. Cir. 359, 2009 Va. Cir. LEXIS 114 (Patrick County Jan. 15, 2009). § 40.1-51.1:1. Repealed by Acts 1979, c. 354. § 40.1-51.2. Rights and duties of employees. Text (a) It shall b e the duty of each employee to comply with all occupational safety and health rules and regulations issued pursuant to this chapter and any orders issued thereunder which are applicable to his own action and conduct. (b) Employees or their representatives may bring to the attention of their employer any hazardous conditions that exist or bring the matter to the attention of the Commissioner or his authorized representative, without first bringing the matter to the attention of the ir employer. Upon receipt of any complaint of hazardous conditions, the Commissioner or his authorized representative shall cause an inspection to be made as soon as practicable. Within two working days after making the oral complaint the employee or the employee representative shall file a written complaint with the Commissioner on a form prescribed by the Commissioner, if at that time, the Commissioner or his authorized representative has not caused the hazardous condition to be corrected. A copy of s uch written complaint shall be made available to the employer by the Commissioner at the time of such inspection. The name or names of individuals bringing such matters to the attention of the Commissioner shall be held in confidence upon request of such individuals. (c) [Repealed. ] (d) A represen tative of the employees selected by the employees shall be given an opportunity to accompany the Commissioner or his authorized representative during the physical inspection of the work place for the purpose of aiding such inspection. Where there is no a uthorized employee representative, the Commissioner or his authorized representative shall consult with a reasonable number of employees concerning matters of health and safety at the work place. No person shall discharge or in any manner discriminate ag ainst an employee representative for his participation in any safety and health inspection. (e) The employ er and the complaining employee, employees or employee representative shall be notified in writing by the Commissioner or his authorized representative of any decision concerning a complaint, of the reasons for such decision and of the rights of the part ies to redress pursuant to § 40.1-49.4 of the Code. History History. 1972, c. 602; 1973, c. 425; 1976, c. 607. Annotations Law Review. For note on employee drug testing, see 74 Va. L. Rev. 969 (1988). For 1991 survey on employment law, see 25 U. Rich. L. Rev. 759 (1991). § 40.1-51.2:1. Discrimination against employee for exercising rights prohibited. Text No person shall discharge or in any way discriminate against an employee because the employee has filed a safety or health complaint or has testified or otherwise acted to exercise rights under the safety and health provisions of this title for themselves or others. History History. 1979, c. 354. Annotations Law Review. For survey of Virginia administrative law and utility regulation for the year 1978-1979, see 66 Va. L. Rev. 193 (1980). For note, Erosion of the Employment-at-Will Doctrine: Recognition of an Employees Right to Job Security, see 43 Wash. &amp; Lee L. Rev. 593 (1986). For article, The Law of Wrongful Discharge in Virginia, see 10 G.M.U. L. Rev. 133 (1988). CASE NOTES Prerequisites.  Employee failed to state a cause of action under § 40.1-51.2:1 because she failed to file a complaint with the Commissioner of Labor and Industry within 60 day s of the alleged discrimination as a prerequisite to filing a complaint. Reiterman v. Costco Wholesale Mgmt. # 238, No. 5:05CV00012, 2005 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 15219 (W.D. Va. July 28, 2005). Applies to employees, not customers.  Former employees argument that defendants obligation to provide its employees with a safe workplace environment pursuant to § 40.1-51.2:1 should also b e extended to defendants customers, the ...</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-52"><akn:num>§ 40.1-52</akn:num><akn:heading>Authority of labor unions to own, encumber and sell real estate</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The trustees of any unincorporated association organized for mutual benefit and chartered as a labor union for the purpose of collective bargaining and other lawful fun ctions of labor unions, as defined by the laws of this Commonwealth, and having a duly authorized charter as a local labor union, from either a state or national labor organization, shall have the right to own, possess, improve, sell or mortgage real est ate. Such real estate can be acquired for any lawful purpose whatsoever. Property acquired by an unincorporated association under the provisions of this section can be sold, mortgaged or the title transferred by such trustees in the same man ner and to the same extent as if such trustees were natural persons acting for themselves in their individual capacity, under the laws of this Commonwealth. The provisions of this section shall apply to any real estate acquired prior to July 1, 1997, by any such unincorporated association, provided such real estate is real estate that could be legally acquired by such unincorporated association, if acquired after such date. History History. Code 1950, § 40-63; 1966, c. 382; 1970, c. 321; 1997, c. 761. Annotations Law Review. For a comment, Slowing Union Corruption: Reforming the Landrum-Griffin Act to Better Combat Union Embezzlement, see 8 Geo. Mason L. Rev. 527 (2000). Research References. Bryson on Virginia Civil Procedure (Matthew Bender). Chapter 5 Parties. § 5.02 Competency. W. Hamilton Bryson.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-53"><akn:num>§ 40.1-53</akn:num><akn:heading>Preventing persons from pursuing lawful vocations, etc</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>; illegal picketing; injunction. Text No person shall singly or in concert with others interfere or attempt to interfere with another in the exercise of his right to work or to enter upon the performance of any lawful vocation by the use of force, threats of violence or intimidation, or by the use of insulting or threatening language directed toward such person, to induce or attempt to induce him to quit his employment or refrain from seeking employment. No person shall engage in picketing by force or violence, or picket alone or in concert with others in such manner as to obstruct or interfere with free ingress or egre ss to and from any premises, or obstruct or interfere with free use of public streets, sidewalks or other public ways. Any person violating any of the provisions of this section shall be guilty of a misdemeanor, and punished accordingly. Notwithstanding the punishments herein provided any court of general equity jurisdiction may enjoin picketing prohibited by this section, and in addition thereto, may e njoin any picketing or interference with lawful picketing when necessary to prevent disorder, restrain coercion, protect life or property, or promote the general welfare. History History. Code 1950, § 40-64; 1952, c. 674; 1970, c. 321; 1974, c. 254. Annotations Cross references. As to picketing of dwelling places, see §§ 18.2-418 and 18.2-419. Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 11B M.J. Labor, § 9. CASE NOTES Constitutionality.  On its face, this section infringes no right protected by U.S. Const., Amend. I. United Steelworkers v. Dalton, 544 F. Supp. 282, 1982 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 9717 (E.D. Va. 1982). Section not overbroad on its face.  Because this section prohibits only language calculated to coerce, intimidate, or lead to violence, it is not overbroad on its face. The statute does not infringe rights under U.S. Const., Amend. I. For the same reason, the statute is not preempted by § 8(a)(1) of the Labor Management Relations Act. United Steelworkers v. Dalton, 544 F. Supp. 282, 1982 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 9717 (E.D. Va. 1982). Purpose of section.  The plain purpose of this section is to protect the inherent right to work from the clear and present danger of destruction by those who, by the use of fo rce, threats, violence, intimidation, or insulting words, would prevent the exercise of that right. McWhorter v. Commonwealth, 191 Va. 857, 63 S.E.2d 20, 1951 Va. LEXIS 142 (1951); United Steelworkers v. Dalton, 544 F. Supp. 282, 1982 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 97 17 (E.D. Va. 1982). Plain purpose of Virginia picketing and right to work statute is to protect the right to work from infringement by the use of force, threats, violence, intimidati on, or insulting words. Kaufhold v. Bright, 835 F. Supp. 294, 1993 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 16448 (W.D. Va. 1993). The prohibition of this section is within a narrow scope. McWhorter v. Commonwealth, 191 Va. 857, 63 S.E.2d 20, 1951 Va. LEXIS 142 (1951); United Steelworkers v. Dalton, 544 F. Supp. 282, 1982 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 9717 (E.D. Va. 1982). The prohibition in this section is not directed against those in the picket line alone, The prohibition in this section is not directed against those in the picket line alone, but outlaws interference with the right to work by any person singly or in concert with another. McWhorter v. Commonwealth, 191 Va. 857, 63 S.E.2d 20, 1951 Va . LEXIS 142 (1951). Section do es not provide for a civil action for damages.  This is a quasi-criminal statute, the violation of which is punishable as a misdemeanor. In addition to providing for criminal penalties, it also provides for inj unctive relief. Crawford v. United Steel Workers, 230 Va. 217, 335 S.E.2d 828, 1985 Va. LEXIS 272 (1985), cert. denied, 475 U.S. 1095, 106 S. Ct. 1490, 89 L. Ed. 2d 892, 1986 U.S. LEXIS 1017 (1986); Kaufhold v. Bright, 835 F. Supp. 294, 1993 U.S. Dist. L EXIS 16448 (W.D. Va. 1993). Picketing is subject to regu lation by State.  The pattern which emerges to shape the boundaries of state action seems to be that picketing is subject to regulation by the State, either by legislation or by co urt action. But such regulation must have a reasonable basis in prevention of disorder, restraint of coercion, protection of life or property, or promotion of the general welfare. The instrument of state action, whether judicial process or legislative en actment, must be specifically directed to acts or conduct which overstep legal limits, and not include those which keep within the protected area of free speech. Edwards v. Commonwealth, 191 Va. 272, 60 S.E.2d 916, 1950 Va. LEXIS 218 (1950); McWhorter v. Commonwealth, 191 Va. 857, 63 S.E.2d 20, 1951 Va. LEXIS 142 (1951). Section was not designed to end picketing.  There is nothing in this section which supports the assertion that it was designed to end the practice, common to labor disputes, known as picketing. It does not prohibit peaceful picketing or peaceful persuasion in connection with labor disputes which are protected under the constitutional guaranty of freedom of speech. McWhorter v. Commonwealth, 191 Va. 857, 63 S.E.2d 20, 1951 Va. LEXIS 142 (1951). It is not the public policy of this State to prohibit all picketing. Only certain types are prohibited by the picketing statute. Painters &amp; Paperhangers Local 101 8 v. Rountree Corp., 194 Va. 148, 72 S.E.2d 402, 1952 Va. LEXIS 216 (1952). Section does not violate r ight of free speech.  The prohibition in this section against the interference with the right to work by the use of force, threats, violence, intimidation, or insulting words, acts whi ch are inherently wrong and liable to bring about an immediate breach of the peace, is within the police power of the State and does not trespass upon the constitutional right of freedom of speech. McWhorter v. Commonwealth, 191 Va. 857, 63 S.E.2d 20, 19 51 Va. LEXIS 142 (1951) (see Painters &amp; Paperhangers Local 1018 v. Rountree Corp., 194 Va. 148, 72 S.E.2d 402 (1952)). The right or privilege of free speech has its limitations, and it is not violated by a state statute which makes it a crime to address any offensive, derisive, or annoying word to any person lawfully in a public place, or to call him by an offensive or derisive name, which has a direct tendency to cause acts of violence by the person to whom individually the remark is addressed. McWhorter v. Commonwealth, 191 Va. 857, 63 S.E.2d 20, 1951 Va. LEXIS 142 (1951). For case citing San Diego Bldg. Trades Council v. Garmon, 359 U.S. 236, 79 S. Ct. 733, 3 L. Ed. 2d 775 (1959), which held that when an activity is arguably subjec t to § 7 or § 8 of the National Labor Relations Act, as amended by the Taft-Hartley Act, the states as well as the federal courts must defer to the exclusive competence of the National Labor Relations Board, as authority for reversal, see Waxman v. Virginia, 371 U.S. 4, 83 S. Ct. 46, 9 L. Ed. 2d 50, 1962 U.S. LEXIS 520 (1962). Section do es not prohibit insulting words or language.  This section does not prohibit or punish the use of offensive words by one picket toward another picket, or toward one not connected with the particular industria l plant concerned in a labor dispute. Nor does it confine those on the picket line to language suitable only to the drawing room or the parlor car. McWhorter v. Commonwealth, 191 Va. 857, 63 S.E.2d 20, 1951 Va. LEXIS 142 (1951); United Steelworkers v. Da lton, 544 F. Supp. 282, 1982 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 9717 (E.D. Va. 1982). Focus is on intimidating or coercive language.  This section is not aimed at merely insulting language. The statutes focus is on language which the user intends to be, or is in and of itself, intimidating o r coercive. Proscribed is the use of words through which the speaker intends to convey a threat of impending harm. United Steelworkers v. Dalton, 544 F. Supp. 282, 1982 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 9717 (E.D. Va. 1982). Insulting or thr eatening language construed.  The words insulting or threatening language cannot be read in a vacuum. They must be read in the context of the sentence of which they are a part. These w ords are preceded by the words by the use of force, threats of violence or intimidation. Such words precedent color the meaning of the words that follow. Read as a whole, the language of the statute prohibits the use of language violent in nature ; language which can be construed as expressing an actual intention of inflicting injury. United Steelworkers v. Dalton, 544 F. Supp. 282, 1982 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 9717 (E.D. Va. 1982). Profane language used in labor dispute held not to support liability under § 8.01-45. Crawford v. United Steel Workers, 230 Va. 217, 335 S.E.2d 828, 1985 Va. LEXIS 272 (1985), cert. denied, 475 U.S. 1095, 106 S. Ct. 1490, 89 L. Ed. 2d 892, 1986 U.S. LEXIS 1017 (1986). Use of police power not precluded by Labor Management Relations Act.  The hurling of insults is protected under the Labor Management Relations Act, 29 U.S.C. § 141 et seq. The existence of the LMRA, however, does not preclude the states from the exercise of their usual police power. The states remain free to act to protect the public peace and order. United Steelworkers v. Dalton, 544 F. Supp. 282, 1982 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 9717 (E.D. Va. 1982). Fighting words not protected by Labor Management Relations Act.  Violent or intimidating language  fighting words  are not protected under the Labor Management Relations Act, 29 U.S.C. § 141 et seq. As this section i s addressed to unprotected conduct, it does not interfere with the federal scheme. The LMRA does not preempt Virginias right to prohibit such conduct. United Steelworkers v. Dalton, 544 F. Supp. 282, 1982 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 9717 (E.D. Va. 1982). Conduct constituting violati on of section.  The defendant, along with her companions, lay down in front of one of the main entrances to and exits from a large industrial plant in such a manner as to block c ompletely the use of the gate by both pedestrian and vehicular traffic in the ope...</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-54"><akn:num>§ 40.1-54</akn:num><akn:heading>Payment of certain charges by carriers or shippers to or for benefit of labor organization</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text (1) As used in this section, the term labor organization means any organization of any kind, or any agency or employee representation committee or plan, in which employees participate and which exists for the purpose, in whole or in part, of dealing with emplo yers concerning grievances, labor disputes, wages, rates of pay, hours of employment, or conditions of work. (2) It shall b e unlawful for any carrier or shipper of property, or any association of such carriers or shippers, to agree to pay, or to pay, to or for the benefit of a labor organization, directly or indirectly, any charge by reason of the placing upon, delivery to, or movement by rail, or by a railroad car, of a motor vehicle, trailer, or container which is also capable of being moved or propelled upon the highways, and any such agreement shall be void and unenforceable. (3) It shall b e unlawful for any labor organization to accept or receive from any carrier or shipper of property, or any association of such carriers or shippers, any payment described above. (4) Any corpor ation, association, organization, firm or person who agrees to pay, or who does pay, or who agrees to receive, or who does receive, any payment described hereinabove shall be guilty of a misdemeanor and shall be fined not less than $100 nor more than $1, 000 for each offense. Each act of violation, and each day during which such an agreement remains in effect, shall constitute a separate offense. History History. Code 1950, § 40-64.1; 1962, c. 376; 1970, c. 321. § 40.1-54.1. Public policy as to strikes and work stoppages at hospitals. Text It is hereby declared to be the public policy of the Commonwealth that hospitals shall be free from strikes, and work stoppages. History History. Code 1950, § 40-64.2; 1970, c. 720. Annotations The number of this section was assigned by the Virginia Code Commission, the number in the 1970 Act having been 40-64.2. § 40.1-54.2. Strikes and work stoppages at hospitals prohibited; penalty. Text No employee of any hospital shall engage in any strike or work stoppage at such hospital which in any way interferes with the operation of such hospital. Any person violating any of the provisions of this section shall be guilty of a misdemeanor and punished accordingly. Notwithstanding the penalties herein provided, any court of general equity jurisdiction may enjoin conduct proscribed by this section. History History. Code 1950, § 40-64.3; 1970, c. 720. Annotations The number of this section was assigned by the Virginia Code Commission, the number in the 1970 Act having been 40-64.3. § 40.1-54.3. Right to vote by secret ballot on labor organization representation. Text A. As used in this section, labor organization means any organization of any kind, or any agency or employee representation committee or plan, in which employees participate and that exists for the purpose, in whole or in part, of dealing with employers concer ning grievances, labor disputes, wages, rates of pay, hours of employment, or conditions of work. B. In any proc edure providing for the designation, selection, or authorization of a labor organization to represent employees, the right of an individual employee to vote by secret ballot in such a procedure is a fundamental right that shall be guaranteed from infring ement. History History. 2013, c. 484. Article 2. Strikes by Government Employees. -360§ 40.1-55. Employee striking terminates, and becomes temporarily ineligible for, public employment. -360§ 40.1-56. Department head, etc., to notify employee of such termination, etc. -360§ 40.1-57. Appeal by employee from declaration of ineligibility. -360§ 40.1-57.1. Appeal by employer for reemployment of terminated employee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-55"><akn:num>§ 40.1-55</akn:num><akn:heading>Employee striking terminates, and becomes temporarily ineligible for, public employment</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. Any employe e of the Commonwealth, or of any county, city, town or other political subdivision thereof, or of any agency of any one of them, who, in concert with two or more other such employees, for the purpose of obstructing, impeding or suspending any activity or operation of his employing agency or any other governmental agency, strikes or willfully refuses to perform the duties of his employment shall, by such action, be deemed to have terminated his employment and shall thereafter be ineligible for employment in any position or capacity during the next 12 months by the Commonwealth, or any county, city, town or other political subdivision of the Commonwealth, or by any department or agency of any of them. B. The provisi ons of subsection A shall apply to any employee of any county, city, or town or local school board without regard to any local ordinance or resolution adopted pursuant to § 40.1-57.2 by such county, city, or town or school board that authorizes its em ployees to engage in collective bargaining. History History. Code 1950, § 40-65; 1970, c. 321; 2020, cc. 1209, 1276. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2020, cc. 1209 and 1276, cl. 2 provides: That the provisions of this act shall become effective on May 1, 2021. The 2020 amendments. The 2020 amendments by cc. 1209 and 1276, effective May 1, 2021, are identical, and added subsection B and made a stylistic change. Law Review. For article discussing public sector collective bargaining, see 15 Wm. &amp; Mary L. Rev. 57 (1973). For comment, Public Sector Collective Bargaining and Sunshine Laws  A Needless Conflict, see 18 Wm. &amp; Mary L. Rev. 159 (1976). For comment on public employee collective bargaining in Virginia, see 11 U. Rich. L. Rev. 431 (1977). For comment,  Working to the Contract in Virginia: Legal Consequences of Teachers Attempts to Limit Their Contractual Duties, see 16 U. Rich. L. Rev. 449 (1982). For a comment, Slowing Union Corruption: Reforming the Landrum-Griffin Act to Better Combat Union Embezzlement, see 8 Geo. Mason L. Rev. 527 (2000). Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 11B M.J. Labor, § 6.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-56"><akn:num>§ 40.1-56</akn:num><akn:heading>Department head, etc</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>, to notify employee of such termination, etc. Text In any such case the head of any department of the state government, or the mayor of any city or town, or the chairman of the board of supervisors or other governing bo dy of any county, or the head of any other such employing agency, in which such employee was employed, shall forthwith notify such employee of the fact of the termination of his employment and at the same time serve upon him in person or by registered ma il a declaration of his ineligibility for reemployment as before provided. Such declaration shall state the fact upon which the asserted ineligibility is based. History History. Code 1950, § 40-66; 1970, c. 321.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-57"><akn:num>§ 40.1-57</akn:num><akn:heading>Appeal by employee from declaration of ineligibility</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text In the event that any such employee feels aggrieved by such declaration of ineligibility he may within ninety days after the date thereof appeal to the circuit court of the county or the circuit court of the city in which he was employed by filing a petition therein for a review of the matters of law and fact involved in or pertinent to the declaration of ineligibility. A copy of the petition shall be served upon or se nt by registered mail to the official signing the declaration, who may file an answer thereto within ten days after receiving the same. The court or the judge thereof in vacation shall, as promptly as practicable, hear the appeal de novo and notify the e mployee and the signer of the declaration of ineligibility of the time and place of hearing. The court shall hear such testimony as may be adduced by the respective parties and render judgment in accordance with the law and the evidence. Such judgment sh all be final. History History. Code 1950, § 40-67; 1970, c. 321. § 40.1-57.1. Appeal by employer for reemployment of terminated employee. Text Notwithstanding any provision of law to the contrary, in the event that the employer of an individual terminated under this article deems it necessary for the protectio n of the public welfare that such individual be reemployed within the twelve months following his termination, the employer may, within ninety days after the date of the declaration of ineligibility, appeal to the circuit court of the county or the circu it court of the city in which the individual was employed by filing a petition therein setting forth the reasons why the public welfare requires reemployment. A copy of the petition shall be served upon or sent by registered mail to the former employee, who may file an answer therein ten days after receiving the same. The court or the judge thereof in vacation shall notify the employer and former employee of the time and place of the hearing on the appeal, such hearing to be de novo and to be held as pr omptly as possible. The court shall hear such testimony as may be adduced by the respective parties and render judgment in accordance with the law and the evidence. Such judgment shall be final. History History. 1972, c. 792. Annotations Law Review. For article discussing public sector collective bargaining, see 15 Wm. &amp; Mary L. Rev. 57 (1973). Article 2.1. Collective Bargaining for Governmental Employees. -360§ 40.1-57.2. Collective bargaining. -360§ 40.1-57.3. Certain activities permitted. § 40.1-57.2. Collective bargaining. Text A. No state, c ounty, city, town, or like governmental officer, agent, or governing body is vested with or possesses any authority to recognize any labor union or other employee association as a bargaining agent of any public officers or employees, or to collectively b argain or enter into any collective bargaining contract with any such union or association or its agents with respect to any matter relating to them or their employment or service unless, in the case of a county, city, or town, such authority is provided for or permitted by a local ordinance or by a resolution. Any such ordinance or resolution shall provide for procedures for the certification and decertification of exclusive bargaining representatives, including reasonable public notice and opportunity for labor organizations to intervene in the process for designating an exclusive representative of a bargaining unit. As used in this section, county, city, or town includes any local school board, and public officers or employees includ es employees of a local school board. B. No ordinanc e or resolution adopted pursuant to subsection A shall include provisions that restrict the governing bodys authority to establish the budget or appropriate funds. C. For any gov erning body of a county, city, or town that has not adopted an ordinance or resolution providing for collective bargaining, such governing body shall, within 120 days of receiving certification from a majority of public employees in a unit considered by such employees to be appropriate for the purposes of collective bargaining, take a vote to adopt or not adopt an ordinance or resolution to provide for collective bargaining by such public employees and any other public employees deemed appropriate by th e governing body. Nothing in this subsection shall require any governing body to adopt an ordinance or resolution authorizing collective bargaining. D. Notwithstan ding the provisions of subsection A regarding a local ordinance or resolution granting or permitting collective bargaining, no officer elected pursuant to Article VII, Section 4 of the Constitution of Virginia or any employee of such officer is vested wi th or possesses any authority to recognize any labor union or other employee association as a bargaining agent of any public officers or employees, or to collectively bargain or enter into any collective bargaining contract with any such union or associa tion or its agents, with respect to any matter relating to them or their employment or service. History History. 1993, cc. 868, 879; 2020, cc. 1209, 1276. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2020, cc. 1209 and 1276, cl. 2 provides: That the provisions of this act shall become effective on May 1, 2021. The 2020 amendments. The 2020 amendments by cc. 1209 and 1276, effective May 1, 2021, are identical, and added subsections B through D; and in subsection A, substituted city, town  for municipal in the first sentence and added unless, in the case of a county, city, or town, such authority is provided for or permitted by a local ordinance or by a resolution to the end of the first sentence and also added the las t two sentences. OPINIONS OF THE ATTORNEY GENERAL Existing policy favors use of arbitration local governments.  By authorizing local government collective bargaining and the use of arbitration provisions in agreements, and since existing policy favors the use of arbitration by local governments, local governments may include in collective bargaining agreements entered into under § 40.1-57.2 grievance and dispute resolution procedures culminating in final and binding arbitration. See opinion of Attorney General to The Ho norable Charniele Herring, Majority Leader, House of Delegates, 21-009, 2021 Va. AG LEXIS 4 (3/1/21). Labor Relations Administrator.  Local governments may include provisions for a neutral Labor Relations Administrator who can only be terminated prior to the expiration of his or her contract by mutual agreement of the localitys management and its employee unions in collective bargaining ordinances enacted under § 40.1-57.2. Local governments may include such provisions whether or not an employee union has been certified. The inclusion of a binding arbitration provision in a collective bargaining ordinance is a reasonable method to resolve negotiation impasses over non-financial issues and does not violate the Dillon Rule. See opinion of Attorney General to the Honorable Jennifer B. Boys ko, Member, Senate of Virginia; and The Honorable Suhas Subramanyam, Member, Virginia House of Delegates, 21-061/21-071, 2021 Va. AG LEXIS 37 (12/10/21).. Pay raises in collec tive bargaining agreements.  Local governments may include provisions in collective bargaining agreements that allow for employee pay raises over a multi-year period. However, these pay raise s would remain subject to annual appropriations by the locality, which may or may not appropriate the requisite amount of funds each year. See opinion of Attorney General to The Honorable Paul E. Krizek, Member, Virginia House of Delegates, 21-093, 2021 Va. AG LEXIS 40 (12/21/21). § 40.1-57.3. Certain activities permitted. Text Nothing in this article shall be construed to prevent employees of the Commonwealth, of its political subdivisions, or of any governmental agency of any of them from fo rming associations for the purpose of promoting their interests before the employing agency and, if they are employees of a county, city, or town or local school board that has, by a local ordinance or resolution as provided in § 40.1-57.2, authorized its employees to engage in collective bargaining, from doing so as provided in such ordinance or resolution. History History. 1993, cc. 868, 879; 2020, cc. 1209, 1276. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2020, cc. 1209 and 1276, cl. 2 provides: That the provisions of this act shall become effective on May 1, 2021. The 2020 amendments. The 2020 amendments by cc. 1209 and 1276, effective May 1, 2021, are identical, and substituted of its political for its political and added a nd, if they are employees of a county, city, or town or local school board that has, by a local ordinance or resolution as provided in § 40.1-57.2, authorized its employees to engage in collective bargaining, from doing so as provided in such ordinanc e or resolution at the end. Article 3. Denial or Abridgement of Right to Work. -360§ 40.1-58. Policy of article. -360§ 40.1-58.1. Application of article to public employers and employees. -360§ 40.1-59. Agreements or combinations declared unlawful. -360§ 40.1-60. Employers not to require employees to become or remain members of union. -360§ 40.1-61. Employers not to require abstention from membership or officeholding in union. -360§ 40.1-62. Employer not to require payment of union dues, etc. -360§ 40.1-63. Recovery by individual unlawfully denied employment. -360§ 40.1-64. Application of article to contracts. -360§ 40.1-65. Agreement or practice designed to cause employer to violate article declared illegal. -360§ 40.1-66. Conduct causing violation of article illegal; peaceful solicitation to join union. -360§ 40.1-67. Injunctive relief against violation; recovery of damages. -360§ 40.1-68. Service of process on clerk of State Corporation Commission as attorney for union. -360§ 40.1-69. Violation a misdemeanor. Annotations Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 11B M.J. Labor...</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-58"><akn:num>§ 40.1-58</akn:num><akn:heading>Policy of article</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text It is hereby declared to be the public policy of Virginia that the right of persons to work shall not be denied or abridged on account of membership or nonmembership in any labor union or labor organization. History History. Code 1950, § 40-68; 1970, c. 321. Annotations Law Review. For article, Current Trends in Labor Law in Virginia, see 42 Va. L. Rev. 691 (1956). For article discussing public sector collective bargaining, see 15 Wm. &amp; Mary L. Rev. 57 (1973). CASE NOTES Constitutionality.  This article does not violate any provision of the federal or Virginia Constitutions. Finney v. Hawkins, 189 Va. 878, 54 S.E.2d 872, 1949 Va. LEXIS 225 (1949). The Virginia Right to Work Law is not incorporated by the federal Assimilative Crimes Act The Virginia Right to Work Law is not incorporated by the federal Assimilative Crimes Act because the policy of the Virginia statute conflicts with federal law. King v. Gemini Food Servs., Inc., 438 F. Supp. 964, 1976 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 12516 (E.D. Va. 1 976), aff'd, 562 F.2d 297, 1977 U.S. App. LEXIS 11676 (4th Cir. 1977). The Virginia Right to Work Law is not assimilated into federal law by the federal Assimilative Crimes Act and therefore does not apply to federal enclaves. King v . Gemini Food Servs., Inc., 438 F. Supp. 964, 1976 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 12516 (E.D. Va. 1976), aff'd, 562 F.2d 297, 1977 U.S. App. LEXIS 11676 (4th Cir. 1977). Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority compact is federal law and thus controlling by its terms over the Virginia Right-to-Work Statute by way of the Supr emacy Clause. Malone v. Washington Metro. Area Transit Auth., 622 F. Supp. 1422, 1985 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 13496 (E.D. Va. 1985). Federal statute, 10 U.S.C. § 3634, relating to outside employment of military personnel do not violate the Virginia right to work laws. Jenkins v. Rumsfeld, 41 2 F. Supp. 1177, 1976 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 15165 (E.D. Va. 1976). Virginia has delegated power to enforce Right-to-Work Law on WMATA employees.  Under the Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority compact, Virginia has delegated its power to enforce its Right-to-Work Law on WMATA employees. The WMATA compact clearly grants the Authority the power to enter into collective bargaining agreements with a union local over employees working conditions. Implicit in its right to enter into collective bargaining agreements, WMATA has the authorization to e nter into a union shop agreement. Malone v. Washington Metro. Area Transit Auth., 622 F. Supp. 1422, 1985 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 13496 (E.D. Va. 1985). Picketing in violation of article.  The State, consistently with the Constitution of the United States, may enjoin peaceful picketing when it is carried on for purposes in conflict with the Virginia Right to Work Statute. Local Union 10, United Ass'n of Journeymen Plumbers &amp; Steamfitters v. Graham, 345 U.S. 192, 73 S. Ct. 585, 97 L. Ed. 946, 51 Ohio Op. 137, 68 Ohio Law Abs. 269, 1953 U.S. LEXIS 2612 (1953). Finding that picketing was carried on for purposes in conflict with the provisions of the Right to Work Statute of the State was held to have a reasonable basis i n the evidence. Local Union 10, United Ass'n of Journeymen Plumbers &amp; Steamfitters v. Graham, 345 U.S. 192, 73 S. Ct. 585, 97 L. Ed. 946, 51 Ohio Op. 137, 68 Ohio Law Abs. 269, 1953 U.S. LEXIS 2612 (1953). Violation not shown.  In. Painters &amp; Paperhangers Local 1018 v. Rountree Corp., 194 Va. 148, 72 S.E.2d 402 (1952) it was held that the record failed to disclose any violation of the Vi rginia Right to Work Statute . No error in reinstatement an d back pay award.  Trial court did not err in awarding airport authority employee who was fired after joining the union back pay and ordering his reinstatement; the award was equita ble and consistent with the relief authorized by the right to work law. Norfolk Airport Auth. v. Nordwall, 246 Va. 391, 436 S.E.2d 436, 10 Va. Law Rep. 447, 1993 Va. LEXIS 134 (1993). § 40.1-58.1. Application of article to public employers and employees. Text As used in this article, the words, person, persons, employer, employees, union, labor union, association, o rganization and corporation shall include but not be limited to public employers, public employees and any representative of public employees in this Commonwealth. The application of this article to public employers, public employees and thei r representatives shall not be construed as modifying in any way the application of § 40.1-55 to government employees. History History. 1973, c. 79. Annotations Law Review. For article discussing public sector collective bargaining, see 15 Wm. &amp; Mary L. Rev. 57 (1973). For comment, Public Sector Collective Bargaining and Sunshine Laws  A Needless Conflict, see 18 Wm. &amp; Mary L. Rev. 159 (1976). For comment on public employee collective bargaining in Virginia, see 11 U. Rich. L. Rev. 431 (1977). CASE NOTES Union representation of public employees.  The legislature of Virginia has the right to and has determined not to recognize union representation of public employees. Such determination is not in conflict w ith the Labor Management Relations Act, §§ 1, 7, as amended, 29 U.S.C. §§ 151, 157. In the absence of legislation a local government has no authority to recognize a labor organization as representative of city employees. It is not a matter of constitutional right, but legislative. Teamsters Local Union 822 v. City of Portsmouth, 423 F. Supp. 954, 1975 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 16627 (E.D. Va. 1975), aff'd, 534 F.2d 328, 1976 U.S. App. LEXIS 11355 (4th Cir. 1976).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-59"><akn:num>§ 40.1-59</akn:num><akn:heading>Agreements or combinations declared unlawful</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Any agreement or combination between any employer and any labor union or labor organization whereby persons not members of such union or organization shall be denied th e right to work for the employer, or whereby such membership is made a condition of employment or continuation of employment by such employer, or whereby any such union or organization acquires an employment monopoly in any enterprise, is hereby declared to be against public policy and an illegal combination or conspiracy. History History. Code 1950, § 40-69; 1970, c. 321. Annotations Law Review. For survey of Virginia law on business associations for the year 1970-1971, see 57 Va. L. Rev. 1541 (1971). CASE NOTES Intent of § 14 (b) of the Taft-Hartley Act is to permit state regulation of union-sec urity agreements which otherwise would be allowed under § (8) (a) (3) of the act. State regulation of such agreements, whether oral or written, is not only consistent with the intent of the act, but also consistent with the language of § 14 (b). Mo ore v. Plumbers &amp; Steamfitters Local 10, 211 Va. 520, 179 S.E.2d 15, 1971 Va. LEXIS 206 (1971). Jurisdiction.  State court has jurisdiction to entertain an action if it involves a consummated union-security agreement, oral or written, between the employer and the union. Mo ore v. Plumbers &amp; Steamfitters Local 10, 211 Va. 520, 179 S.E.2d 15, 1971 Va. LEXIS 206 (1971). Allegation sufficient to withstand motion to dismiss.  A workers allegation that the employer and the union had acted in concert to deny him employment because he was not a member of the union was a sufficient all egation of the existence of a union-security agreement between the employer and the union to withstand the assault of a demurrer or motions to dismiss on the grounds that the workers action was based on an unfair labor practice under the National Lab or Relations Act, and that the said act gave sole and exclusive jurisdiction to the National Labor Relations Board. Moore v. Plumbers &amp; Steamfitters Local 10, 211 Va. 520, 179 S.E.2d 15, 1971 Va. LEXIS 206 (1971).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-60"><akn:num>§ 40.1-60</akn:num><akn:heading>Employers not to require employees to become or remain members of union</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text No person shall be required by an employer to become or remain a member of any labor union or labor organization as a condition of employment or continuation of employm ent by such employer. History History. Code 1950, § 40-70; 1970, c. 321.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-61"><akn:num>§ 40.1-61</akn:num><akn:heading>Employers not to require abstention from membership or officeholding in union</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text No person shall be required by an employer to abstain or refrain from membership in, or holding office in, any labor union or labor organization as a condition of emplo yment or continuation of employment. History History. Code 1950, § 40-71; 1970, c. 321; 2002, c. 422. Annotations The 2002 amendments. The 2002 amendment by c. 422 inserted or officeholding in the section catchline; and in the section text inserted or holding office in. Law Review. For article surveying developments in labor and employment law in Virginia, see 37 U. Rich. L. Rev. 241 (2002). CASE NOTES Courts may not intervene in cases committed to jurisdiction of NLRB.  Since both this section and § 8 (a) (3) of the National Labor Relations Act of 1935 are aimed at proscribing the same practices, the danger that conflicting re medies might be brought to bear on the same activity precludes either federal or State courts from intervening in such cases, which are committed to the jurisdiction of the National Labor Relations Board. Bukovac v. Daniel Constr. Co., 469 F. Supp. 176, 1979 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 13182 (W.D. Va. 1979). Constitutional issues.  This section had no bearing on a constitutional claim seeking to have declared invalid resolutions of the York County Board of Supervisors which prohibit supervis ors in the fire department from belonging to a union in which rank and file fire fighters are members. York County Fire Fighters Ass'n, Local 2498 v. County of York, 589 F.2d 775, 1978 U.S. App. LEXIS 6754 (4th Cir. 1978). No error in reinstatement an d back pay award.  Trial court did not err in awarding airport authority employee who was fired after joining the union back pay and ordering his reinstatement; the award was equita ble and consistent with the relief authorized by the right to work law. Norfolk Airport Auth. v. Nordwall, 246 Va. 391, 436 S.E.2d 436, 10 Va. Law Rep. 447, 1993 Va. LEXIS 134 (1993).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-62"><akn:num>§ 40.1-62</akn:num><akn:heading>Employer not to require payment of union dues, etc</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text No employer shall require any person, as a condition of employment or continuation of employment, to pay any dues, fees or other charges of any kind to any labor union or labor organization. History History. Code 1950, § 40-72; 1970, c. 321. Annotations CASE NOTES Virginia has delegated power to enforce Right-to-Work Law on WMATA employees.  Under the Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority compact, Virginia has delegated its power to enforce its Right-to-Work Law on WMATA employees. The WMATA compact clearly grants the Authority the power to enter into collective bargaining agreements with a union local over employees working conditions. Implicit in its right to enter into collective bargaining agreements, WMATA has the authorization to e nter into a union shop agreement. Malone v. Washington Metro. Area Transit Auth., 622 F. Supp. 1422, 1985 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 13496 (E.D. Va. 1985).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-63"><akn:num>§ 40.1-63</akn:num><akn:heading>Recovery by individual unlawfully denied employment</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Any person who may be denied employment or be deprived of continuation of his employment in violation of §§ 40.1-60, 40.1-61 or § 40.1-62 or of one or more of such sections, shall be entitled to recover from such employer and from any other person, firm, corporation or association acting in concert with him by appropriate action in the courts of this Commonwealth such damages as he may have sustained by reason of such denial or deprivation of employment. History History. Code 1950, § 40-73; 1970, c. 321.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-64"><akn:num>§ 40.1-64</akn:num><akn:heading>Application of article to contracts</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The provisions of this article shall not apply to any lawful contract in force on April 30, 1947, but they shall apply in all respects to contracts entered into thereaf ter and to any renewal or extension of an existing contract. History History. Code 1950, § 40-74; 1970, c. 321.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-65"><akn:num>§ 40.1-65</akn:num><akn:heading>Agreement or practice designed to cause employer to violate article declared illegal</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Any agreement, understanding or practice which is designated to cause or require any employer, whether or not a party thereto, to violate any provision of this article is hereby declared to be an illegal agreement, understanding or practice and contrary to public policy. History History. Code 1950, § 40-74.1; 1954, c. 431; 1970, c. 321.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-66"><akn:num>§ 40.1-66</akn:num><akn:heading>Conduct causing violation of article illegal; peaceful solicitation to join union</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Any person, firm, association, corporation, or labor union or organization engaged in lockouts, layoffs, boycotts, picketing, work stoppages or other conduct, a purpose of which is to cause, force, persuade or induce any other person, firm, association, corporation or labor union or organization to violate any provision of this article shall be guilty of illegal conduct contrary to public policy; provided that nothing herein contained shall be construed to prevent or make illegal the peaceful and orderly solicitation and persuasion by union members of others to join a union, unaccompanied by any intimidation, use of force, threat of use of force, reprisal or threat of reprisal, and provided that no such solicitation or persuasion shall be conducted so as to interfere with, or interrupt the work of any employee during working hours. History History. Code 1950, § 40-74.2; 1954, c. 431; 1970, c. 321. Annotations Law Review. For article discussing public sector collective bargaining, see 15 Wm. &amp; Mary L. Rev. 57 (1973). CASE NOTES Profane language used in labor dispute held not to support liability under § 8.01-45. Crawford v. United Steel Workers, 230 Va. 217, 335 S.E.2d 828, 1985 Va. LEXIS 272 (1985), cert. denied, 475 U.S. 1095, 106 S. Ct. 1490, 89 L. Ed. 2d 892, 1986 U.S. LEXIS 1017 (1986).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-67"><akn:num>§ 40.1-67</akn:num><akn:heading>Injunctive relief against violation; recovery of damages</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Any employer, person, firm, association, corporation, labor union or organization injured as a result of any violation or threatened violation of any provision of this article or threatened with any such violation shall be entitled to injunctive relief against any and all violators or persons threatening violation, and also to recover from such violator or violators, or person or persons, any and all damages of any cha racter cognizable at common law resulting from such violations or threatened violations. Such remedies shall be independent of and in addition to the penalties and remedies prescribed in other provisions of this article. History History. Code 1950, § 40-74.3; 1954, c. 431; 1970, c. 321. Annotations CASE NOTES Profane language used in labor dispute held not to support liability under § 8.01-45. Crawford v. United Steel Workers, 230 Va. 217, 335 S.E.2d 828, 1985 Va. LEXIS 272 (1985), cert. denied, 475 U.S. 1095, 106 S. Ct. 1490, 89 L. Ed. 2d 892, 1986 U.S. LEXIS 1017 (1986).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-68"><akn:num>§ 40.1-68</akn:num><akn:heading>Service of process on clerk of State Corporation Commission as attorney for union</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Any labor union or labor organization doing business in this Commonwealth, all of whose officers and trustees are nonresidents of this Commonwealth, shall by written po wer of attorney, filed with the Department of Labor and Industry and the State Corporation Commission, appoint the clerk of the State Corporation Commission its attorney or agent upon whom all legal process against the union or organization may be served , and who shall be authorized to enter an appearance on its behalf. The manner of service of process on the clerk of the State Corporation Commission, the mailing thereof to the labor union or organization, the fees therefor, the effect of judgments, dec rees and orders, and the procedure in cases where no power of attorney is filed as required, shall be the same as provided for in cases of foreign corporations. History History. Code 1950, § 40-74.4; 1954, c. 431; 1956, c. 430; 1970, c. 321 . Annotations Research References. Bryson on Virginia Civil Procedure (Matthew Bender). Chapter 3 Active Jurisdiction. § 3.01 Process. W. Hamilton Bryson.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-69"><akn:num>§ 40.1-69</akn:num><akn:heading>Violation a misdemeanor</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Any violation of any of the provisions of this article by any person, firm, association, corporation, or labor union or organization shall be a misdemeanor. History History. Code 1950, § 40-74.5; 1954, c. 431; 1970, c. 321; 1973, c. 425 . Annotations Cross references. For present provisions as to enforcement of this title and rules and regulations adopted pursuant thereto, and penalties for violations, see § 40.1-49.4. Article 4. Mediation and Conciliation of Labor Disputes. -360§ 40.1-70. Department designated agency to mediate disputes. -360§ 40.1-71. Notice of proposed termination or modification of collective bargaining contract; notice prior to work stoppage; injunct ions and penalties. -360§ 40.1-72. Commissioner to notify Governor of disputes; mediation and conciliation. -360§ 40.1-73. Commissioner to keep Governor informed of negotiations, etc. -360§ 40.1-74. Right of entry. -360§ 40.1-75. Article not applicable when National Railway Labor Act applies.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-70"><akn:num>§ 40.1-70</akn:num><akn:heading>Department designated agency to mediate disputes</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Department is hereby designated as the state agency authorized to mediate and conciliate labor disputes. History History. Code 1950, § 40-95.1; 1952, c. 697; 1970, c. 321. Annotations Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 11B M.J. Labor, § 6.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-71"><akn:num>§ 40.1-71</akn:num><akn:heading>Notice of proposed termination or modification of collective bargaining contract; notice prior to work stoppage; injunctions and penalties</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Whenever there is in effect a collective bargaining contract covering employees of any utility engaged in the business of furnishing water, light, heat, gas, electric p ower, transportation or communication, the utility or the collective bargaining agent recognized by the utility and its employees shall not terminate or modify such contract until the party desiring such termination or modification serves written notice upon the Department of the proposed termination or modification at least thirty days prior to the expiration date thereof or, in the event such contract contains no expiration date, at least thirty days prior to the date it is proposed to make such termi nation or modification; provided, however, that a party having given notice of modification as provided herein shall not be required to give a notice of termination of the same contract. Where there is no collective bargaining contract in effect, the utility or its employees shall give at least thirty days notice to the Department prior to any work stoppage which would affect the operations of the utility engaged in the business of furnishing any of the utilities as described in this section. If the utility or its employees, or the collective bargaining agent recognized by the utility and its employees, as the case may be, fails to give thirty days notic e as required by this section, the utility or its employees or such collective bargaining agent, as the case may be, may file a bill of complaint with the clerk of the circuit court having equity jurisdiction over the place of employment asking the court to temporarily enjoin such termination, modification or work stoppage until the proper notice has been served and the thirty-day period has been observed. The court shall have the authority to impose against any person who violates the notice provisions of this section a fine of up to $100 for each day such termination, modification or work stoppage continues until proper notice has been served and observed or against the collective bargaining agent the court shall have the authority to impose a fine o f up to $1,000 for each day such termination or modification continues until proper notice has been served and observed. History History. Code 1950, § 40-95.2; 1952, c. 697; 1966, c. 92; 1970, c. 321; 1979, c. 515.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-72"><akn:num>§ 40.1-72</akn:num><akn:heading>Commissioner to notify Governor of disputes; mediation and conciliation</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Upon receipt of notice of any labor dispute affecting operation of the utility, the Commissioner shall forthwith notify the Governor and inform him of the nature of the dispute. If the Governor deems it necessary the Commissioner, or his designated agent, shall offer to meet and confer with the parties in interest and undertake to mediate and conciliate their differences. If the Governor deems it advisable, it shall be the duty of the utility and its employees, or designated representatives, to meet and confer with the Commissioner or his agent, at a time and place designated by the Commissioner, for the purpose of mediating and conciliating their differences. History History. Code 1950, § 40-95.3; 1952, c. 697; 1966, c. 92; 1970, c. 321.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-73"><akn:num>§ 40.1-73</akn:num><akn:heading>Commissioner to keep Governor informed of negotiations, etc</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Commissioner shall keep the Governor fully informed as to the progress of the negotiations between the utility and its employees and shall report as soon as practic al whether in his judgment a strike or lockout appears to be probable in any such dispute or, if a strike or lockout begins, whether continuation thereof is probable. History History. Code 1950, § 40-95.4; 1952, c. 697; 1970, c. 321.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-74"><akn:num>§ 40.1-74</akn:num><akn:heading>Right of entry</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text In order to carry out the duties imposed by this article, the Commissioner or his designated agent shall have the right to enter upon the property of the utility. History History. Code 1950, § 40-95.5; 1952, c. 697; 1970, c. 321.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-75"><akn:num>§ 40.1-75</akn:num><akn:heading>Article not applicable when National Railway Labor Act applies</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Nothing in this article shall apply to any utility to which the National Railway Labor Act is applicable. History History. Code 1950, § 40-95.6; 1952, c. 697; 1970, c. 321. Article 5. Registration of Labor Unions, Labor Associations and Labor Organizations. -360§§ 40.1-76, 40.1-77. Repealed by Acts 1991, c. 443.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-76"><akn:num>§ 40.1-76</akn:num><akn:heading>40</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>1-76, 40.1-77. Repealed by Acts 1991, c. 443. Chapter 5. Child Labor. -360§ 40.1-78. Employment of children under fourteen and sixteen. -360§ 40.1-79. Repealed by Acts 1991, c. 511. -360§ 40.1-79.01. Exemptions from chapter generally. -360§ 40.1-79.1. Exemptions from chapter generally; participation in volunteer fire company activities. -360§ 40.1-80. Repealed by Acts 1991, c. 511. -360§ 40.1-80.1. Employment of children. -360§ 40.1-81. Repealed by Acts 1972, c. 480. -360§ 40.1-81.1. Records to be kept by employers. -360§ 40.1-82. Repealed by Acts 1979, c. 219. -360§ 40.1-83. Repealed by Acts 1991, c. 511. -360§ 40.1-84. Employment certificate required. -360§ 40.1-85. Kinds of employment certificates. -360§ 40.1-86. Repealed by Acts 1979, c. 219. -360§ 40.1-87. Vacation or part-time employment certificate. -360§ 40.1-88. Work-training certificate. -360§ 40.1-89. Work-training certificate; employment not allowed; revocation of certificate. -360§§ 40.1-90, 40.1-91. Repealed by Acts 1991, c. 511. -360§ 40.1-92. Issuance of certificates. -360§ 40.1-93. Proof required for employment certificate. -360§ 40.1-94. Proofs of age. -360§ 40.1-95. Repealed by Acts 1991, c. 511. -360§ 40.1-96. Contents of employment certificates. -360§ 40.1-97. Repealed by Acts 1972, c. 480. -360§§ 40.1-98, 40.1-99. -360§ 40.1-100. Certain employment prohibited or limited. -360§ 40.1-100.1. Employment where hazard capable of causing serious physical harm or death. -360§ 40.1-100.2. Employment involving sexually explicit visual material prohibited. -360§ 40.1-101. Qualifications as to theaters. -360§ 40.1-102. Issuance of theatrical permit. -360§ 40.1-103. Cruelty and injuries to children; penalty; abandoned infant. -360§ 40.1-104. Age certificates. -360§ 40.1-105. Repealed by Acts 1991, c. 511. -360§§ 40.1-106 through 40.1-108. -360§ 40.1-109. Newspaper carriers on regular routes; hours. -360§ 40.1-110. Repealed by Acts 1979, c. 219. -360§ 40.1-111. Repealed by Acts 1991, c. 511. -360§ 40.1-112. Solicitation generally. -360§ 40.1-113. Child labor offenses; civil penalties. -360§ 40.1-114. Enforcement of child labor law. -360§ 40.1-115. School attendance. -360§ 40.1-116. Curfew ordinances not affected. Annotations Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 12B M.J. Master and Servant, § 95.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-78"><akn:num>§ 40.1-78</akn:num><akn:heading>Employment of children under fourteen and sixteen</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. No child un der fourteen years of age shall be employed, permitted or suffered to work in, about or in connection with any gainful occupation except as specified in this chapter. B. No child un der sixteen years of age shall be employed, permitted or suffered to work in, about or in connection with any gainful occupation during school hours unless he has reached the age of fourteen and is enrolled in a regular school work-training program and a work-training certificate has been issued for his employment as provided in § 40.1-88. C. Nothing in this section shall affect the provisions of §§ 40.1-100 A, 40.1-100.1, 40.1-100.2, 40.1-101 and 40.1-102. History History. Code 1950, § 40-96; 1956, c. 567; 1960, c. 434; 1968, c. 264; 1970, c. 321; 1991, c. 511. Annotations Cross references. As to issuance by judges of juvenile and domestic relations courts of special work permits to children not qualified to obtain work permits under other provisions of law, see § 16.1-241, subsection H. As to power of the Virginia Lottery Board to license agents and restrict the employment of minors, see § 58.1-4007. CASE NOTES In general.  The Child Labor Law, as enacted in 1914 and codified in the Code of 1919 as § 1809 et seq., has been amended and other statutes for the protection of infants h ave been since enacted, from time to time. See Michies Code 1942, and Michies Suppl. 1948, §§ 1808a to 1808q, codified as this chapter. These statutes forbid the employment of infants within certain ages in gainful occupations (with some ex ceptions), or within designated hours, except upon terms stated in the statutes, and annex penalties upon employers, parents, guardians, etc., for their violation (§ 40.1-113). These penalties are the means provided by law for enforcement of obedience to the statutes. Prior to the enactment in 1918 of the Workers Compensation Act (now codified as § 65.2-100 et seq.), if these statutes were violated, there was no remedy against the wrongdoer except to enforce the penalties and a common-law acti on by the injured party, aided by the provisions of § 8.01-221. This common-law action was subject to all the common-law defenses. Humphries v. Boxley Bros. Co., 146 Va. 91, 135 S.E. 890, 1926 Va. LEXIS 314 (1926). For other decisions relating to actions under the Child Labor Law, see Standard Red Ceda r Chest Co. v. Monroe, 125 Va. 442, 99 S.E. 589, 1919 Va. LEXIS 36 (1919); Miller Mfg. Co. v. Loving, 125 Va. 255, 99 S.E. 591, 1919 Va. LEXIS 20 (1919); Ocean Accident &amp; Guarantee Corp. v. Washington Brick &amp; Terra Cotta Co., 148 Va. 829, 139 S.E. 513, 1 927 Va. LEXIS 280 (1927); Miller Mfg. Co. v. Aetna Life Ins. Co., 150 Va. 495, 143 S.E. 747, 1928 Va. LEXIS 330 (1928). Purpose.  The principal object of the Child Labor Law is the protection of the infant. He is also entitled to the equal protection of the law with adults; and if benefits a nd protection are afforded to adults by the Workers Compensation Act (now § 65.2-100 et seq.), they should be extended to infants also whenever it can be done consistently with the language and spirit of such laws. The care and welfare of the infa nt should be carefully borne in mind in the interpretation of these statutes. Humphries v. Boxley Bros. Co., 146 Va. 91, 135 S.E. 890, 1926 Va. LEXIS 314 (1926). The object of a child labor statute is to preserve the lives and limbs of children. Standard Red Cedar Chest Co. v. Monroe, 125 Va. 442, 99 S.E. 589, 1919 Va. LEX IS 36 (1919). Construction of statute.  This section should be construed in harmony with the intention of the legislature as expressed in § 40.1-113. Clover Creamery Co. v. Kanode, 142 Va. 542, 129 S .E. 222, 1925 Va. LEXIS 357 (1925). Relative duty of proprietor and parent to prevent employment.  This section provides that no child under 14 years of age shall be employed, permitted or suffered to work, etc. These words do not impose upon the propri etor of a business the duty to prevent, or use reasonable care to prevent, the child from engaging in the business. The section only prohibits the employment of the child and the phrase permitted or suffered to work was intended to make the paren t or other person in control, acquiescing in the employment, equally guilty with the proprietor of the business. Clover Creamery Co. v. Kanode, 142 Va. 542, 129 S.E. 222, 1925 Va. LEXIS 357 (1925). Proprietor s liability as dependent upon knowledge.  Construing this section in the light of the other provisions of the Child Labor Law, it is manifest that the words permitted or suffered to work impose no duty or obligation upon the proprietor except where, after acquiring knowledge that a child within the prohibited age has been employed in his business, he permits or suffers him to remain in his service. Clover Creamery Co. v. Kanode, 142 Va. 542, 129 S.E. 222, 1925 Va. LEXIS 357 (1925). It cannot be said that the proprietor has permitted or suffered a child to work in his business, when he has no knowledge that the child is engaged in his service. The words suffered and permitted necessarily imply knowledge. Clover Creamery Co. v. Kanode, 142 Va. 542, 129 S.E. 222, 1925 Va. LEXIS 357 (1925). When employer guilty of actionable negligence under former statute.  Under § 1809 of the Code of 1919 (similar to this section) the employment of a child by a factory owner to work in his factory, with knowledge of the fact that he was within the prohibited age, was to be regarded per se as the proximate cause of an injury received by the child in the course of his employment. And where a child was knowingly employed contrary to the provisions of the statute and was injured in such employment, the employer was guilty of actionable negligence as a matter of law. The unlawful hiring constitutes the causal connection between the violation of the statute and the injury. Standard Red Cedar Chest Co. v. Monroe, 125 Va. 442, 99 S.E. 589, 1919 Va. LEXIS 36 (1919). Ratification of illegal employment by acquiescence.  Acquiescence by the master in the illegal employment of a child by his servant constitutes ratification and makes the employment by the servant the employment of the master. Clover Creamery Co. v. Kanode, 142 Va. 542, 129 S.E. 222, 1925 Va. LEXIS 357 (1925). No private cause of action for violation of statute.  Under the child labor law, which provides a civil penalty for violation, there exists no private cause of action for mere hiring of an underage child, but ordinar y cases of negligence may still lie in cases involving a child unlawfully hired. Howarth v. Rockingham Publishing Co., 20 F. Supp. 2d 959, 1998 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 15661 (W.D. Va. 1998). Defendants servant permitting child to assist in the delivery of milk.  A servant permitted a child to ride in defendants milk wagon and assist him in the delivery of milk, and gave him presents. While thus assisting defendant s servant the child was run over and killed. Defendant had in force a rule prohibiting its drivers, who had neither authority nor necessity for employing assistants, from allowing boys to ride on its wagons or assist in the delivery of milk. This rule wa s enforced by defendant. Defendant had no knowledge that the driver had violated the rule by permitting the child to ride on the wagon or assist in the delivery of the milk. It was held that the act of the driver in securing the child to assist him was b eyond the scope of his authority and defendant not having ratified such employment was not bound by the act of his servant, and the defendant having no knowledge of the drivers act, could not be said to have permitted or suffered the child to work in his service. Clover Creamery Co. v. Kanode, 142 Va. 542, 129 S.E. 222, 1925 Va. LEXIS 357 (1925). Workers Compensation Act.  Liability imposed upon employers by the Workers Compensation Act is in aid of the Child Labor Law, rather than opposed to it. And infants, whether lawfully em ployed or not, are within the language and intent of the Act. Humphries v. Boxley Bros. Co., 146 Va. 91, 135 S.E. 890, 1926 Va. LEXIS 314 (1926); Chalkley v. Nolde Bros., 184 Va. 553, 35 S.E.2d 827, 1945 Va. LEXIS 176 (1945). And the remedy afforded by the Workers Compensation Act is exclusive of all other remedies against the employer (at least where the Act applies). Hence, an in fant injured while in employment covered by the Act cannot maintain a common-law action against his employer. Humphries v. Boxley Bros. Co., 146 Va. 91, 135 S.E. 890, 1926 Va. LEXIS 314 (1926); Chalkley v. Nolde Bros., 184 Va. 553, 35 S.E.2d 827, 1945 Va . LEXIS 176 (1945). An illegal contract of employment can be pleaded in bar of an action for damages against the employer, where the remedy should be under the Workers Compensati on Act. Chalkley v. Nolde Bros., 184 Va. 553, 35 S.E.2d 827, 1945 Va. LEXIS 176 (1945).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-79"><akn:num>§ 40.1-79</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1991, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>511. Annotations Cross references. For present provision relating to exemptions from chapter generally, see § 40.1-79.01. § 40.1-79.01. Exemptions from chapter generally. Text A. Nothing in this chapter, except the provisions of §§ 40.1-100 A, 40.1-100.1, 40.1-100.2, and 40.1-103, shall apply to: 1. A chi ld engaged in domestic work when such work is performed in connection with the childs own home and directly for his parent or a person standing in place of his parent; 2. A child employed in occasional work performed outside school hours where such work is in connection with the employers home but not in connection with the employers business, t rade, or profession; 3. A child 12 or 13 years of age employed outside school hours on farms, in orchards or in gardens with the consent of his parent or a person standing in place of his parent; 4. A child between the ages of 12 and 18 employed as a page or clerk for either the House of Delegates or the Senate of Virginia; 5. A child participating in the activities of a volunteer emergency medical services agency; 6. A child under 16 years of age employed by his parent in an occupation other than manufacturing; or 7. A child 12 years of age or older employed by an eleemosynary organization or unit of state or local government as a referee for sports programs sponsored by that eleemosynary, state, o r local organization or by an organization of referees sponsored by an organization recognized by the United States Olympic Committee under 36 U.S.C. § 220522. B. Nothing in this chapter, except §§ 40.1-100.1, 40.1-100.2, and 40.1-103, shall be construed to apply to a child employed by his parent or a person standing in place of his parent on farms, in orchards or in gardens owned or operated by such parent or person. History History. 1991, c. 511; 1998, c. 30; 2003, c. 380; 2015, cc. 502, 503. Annotations The 1998 amendment, in subsection A, in subdivision 5, deleted or at the end, in subdivision 6, added or and added subdivision 7. The 2003 amendments. The 2003 amendment by c. 380 in subdivisions A 3, A 4 and A 7, substituted 12 for twelve; in subdivision A 3, substituted 13 for thirt een; subdivision A 4, substituted 18 for eighteen and in subdivision A 6, substituted 16 for sixteen. The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendments by cc. 502 and 503 are identical, and substituted emergency medical services agency for rescue squad in subdivision A 5. CASE NOTES Application of § 40.1-103.  The language of this section implies that § 40.1-103 is applicable to a person standing in loco parentis. Lovisi v. Commonwealth, 212 Va. 848, 188 S.E.2d 206, 1972 Va. LEXIS 281, cert. denied, 407 U.S. 922, 92 S. Ct. 2469, 32 L. Ed. 2d 808, 1972 U.S. LEXIS 2162 (1972) (decided under former § 40.1-79). § 40.1-79.1. Exemptions from chapter generally; participation in volunteer fire company activities. Text A. Any county, city or town may authorize by ordinance any person residing anywhere in the Commonwealth, aged 16 years or older, who is a member of a volunteer fire company within such county, city, or town with parental or guardian approval, (i) to seek certification under National Fire Protection Association 1001, level one, firefighter standards, as administered by the Department of Fire Programs; and (ii) to work with or participate in activities of such volunteer fire company, provided such person has attained c ertification under National Fire Protection Association 1001, level one, firefighter standards, as administered by the Department of Fire Programs. Nothing in this chapter shall prohibit participation by such persons in nonhazardous activities of a volun teer fire company, including fire prevention efforts and training courses approved by the Virginia Fire Services Board that are designed to provide situational awareness. Such ordinance shall not require a minor who achieved certification under National Fire Protection Association 1001, level one, firefighter standards, as administered by the Department of Fire Programs, on or before January 1, 2006, between the ages of 15 and 16, to repeat the certification after his sixteenth birthday. B. Any trainer or instructor of such persons mentioned in subsection A and any member of a paid or volunteer fire company who supervises any such persons shall be exempt from the provisions of § 40.1-103, provided that the provisions of § 40.1-100 have not been violated, when engaged in activities of a volunteer fire company, and provided that the volunteer fire company or the governing body of such county, city or town has purchased insurance which provides coverage for injuries to or the death of such persons in their performance of activities under this section. History History. 1982, c. 344; 1983, c. 123; 1991, c. 511; 2005, c. 151; 2006, c. 462; 2018, c. 181. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2018, c. 181, cl. 2 provides: That the Virginia Fire Services Board shall adopt a junior member policy that provides guidance to fire and rescue departme nts in developing and administering nonhazardous training courses and programs that comply with the provisions of this act. The 2005 amendments. The 2005 amendment by c. 151, effective March 20, 2005, in subsection A, substituted residing anywhere in the Commonwealth, aged 16 years for sixteen years of age, inserted clause (i), inserted clause (ii) designator; inserted provided that the provisions of § 40.1-100 have not been violated in subsection B, and made minor stylistic changes. The 2006 amendments. The 2006 amendment by c. 462 added the last sentence in subsection A. The 2018 amendments. The 2018 amendment by c. 181, in the first sentence of subsection A, substituted participate in activities for participate fully in all activities in clause (ii) of the first sentence and added the second sentence; in subsection B, deleted of this section following subsection A.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-80"><akn:num>§ 40.1-80</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1991, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>511. Annotations Cross references. For present provision relating to employment of children, see § 40.1-80.1. § 40.1-80.1. Employment of children. Text A. Except as p rovided in §§ 40.1-79.01, 40.1-88, 40.1-102, and 40.1-109, no child under sixteen years of age shall be employed, permitted or suffered to work in, about or in connection with any gainful occupation more than the number of hours per week or more th an the number of hours per day or during the hours of the day that the Commissioner shall determine by regulations to be detrimental to the lives, health, safety or welfare of children. These regulations shall incorporate the standards contained in regu lations promulgated by the United States Secretary of Labor pursuant to the Fair Labor Standards Act (29 U.S.C. § 201 et seq.) concerning the number of hours per week, hours per day, and the hours of the day that children under the age of sixteen may work in, about, or in connection with, any gainful occupation. B. No child sh all be employed or permitted to work for more than five hours continuously without an interval of at least thirty minutes for a lunch period, and no period of less than thirty minutes shall be deemed to interrupt a continuous period of work. History History. 1991, c. 511.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-81"><akn:num>§ 40.1-81</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1972, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>480. § 40.1-81.1. Records to be kept by employers. Text Every employer employing minors under sixteen years of age shall keep a time book or time cards or other appropriate records for such minor employees which shall show t he beginning and ending time of work each day together with the amount of time designated as a free-from-duty meal period, which is deductible from the schedule of hours of work. The record for the preceding twelve months for each such minor employee sha ll be kept on the premises for a period of thirty-six months from the date of the latest work period recorded for the minor employee involved. History History. 1972, c. 480; 1982, c. 134; 1991, c. 511.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-82"><akn:num>§ 40.1-82</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1979, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>219.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-83"><akn:num>§ 40.1-83</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1991, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>511.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-84"><akn:num>§ 40.1-84</akn:num><akn:heading>Employment certificate required</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text No child under sixteen years of age shall be employed, permitted or suffered to work, in, about or in connection with any gainful occupation with the exception of volun teer work or work on farms, orchards and in gardens and except as provided in §§ 40.1-79.01, 40.1-101, and 40.1-102 unless the person, firm or corporation employing such child, procures and keeps on file and accessible to any school attendance offi cer, representative of the Department or other authorized persons, charged with the enforcement of this chapter, the employment certificate as hereinafter provided, issued for such child. History History. Code 1950, § 40-100; 1960, c. 434; 1966, c. 603; 1970, c. 321; 1972, cc. 480, 824; 1974, cc. 283, 525; 1979, c. 219; 1991, c. 511. Annotations CASE NOTES Liability of employer when certificate not obtained.  Under former wording of this section, it was held that the employment of a boy over 14 and under 16 years of age without having procured the required certificate was a tort, and an injury to the child occurring in the performance of duties under such employment was to be referred to the unlawful employment as the proximate cause of such injury. In such case it was also held that the doctrine of contributory negli gence was applicable in an action for such injury. Miller Mfg. Co. v. Loving, 125 Va. 255, 99 S.E. 591, 1919 Va. LEXIS 20 (1919); Miller Mfg. Co. v. Aetna Life Ins. Co., 150 Va. 495, 143 S.E. 747, 1928 Va. LEXIS 330 (1928). Where the defendant employed the plaintiff and permitted him to be put to work at a dangerous machine, with knowledge of the fact that he was between the ages of 14 and 16 years, without having obtained the required employment certificate, such hiring constituted an offense for which the defendant was liable to a fine, and, under § 8.01-221 and the decisions, to damages for any injury suffered by the plaintiff in the course of his employment, unless his right of action was barred by his own contributory negligence (or the case was covered by former Title 65.1 (now Title 65.2)). Miller Mfg. Co. v. Loving, 125 Va. 255, 99 S.E. 591, 1919 Va. LEXIS 20 (1919). Liability of employers insurer.  When a statute forbids the employment of a child under 14 years of age in any event and also of one under 16 years of age, unless the employer procures and keeps on file and accessible to a factory inspector, or any other authorized officer, the required certificate, in either event the employer is debarred from making the defense that no negligence is shown, and the insurer is not liable. The employment is the a ct guarded against by the exception in the policy. Miller Mfg. Co. v. Aetna Life Ins. Co., 150 Va. 495, 143 S.E. 747, 1928 Va. LEXIS 330 (1928).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-85"><akn:num>§ 40.1-85</akn:num><akn:heading>Kinds of employment certificates</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Employment certificates shall be of two kinds: work-training certificate and vacation or part-time employment certificate. History History. Code 1950, § 40-100.1; 1970, c. 321; 1982, c. 135; 1991, c. 51 1.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-86"><akn:num>§ 40.1-86</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1979, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>219.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-87"><akn:num>§ 40.1-87</akn:num><akn:heading>Vacation or part-time employment certificate</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A vacation or part-time employment certificate shall permit the employment of a child between fourteen and sixteen years of age only during school vacation periods or o n days when school is not in session, or outside school hours on school days. History History. Code 1950, § 40-100.3; 1958, c. 164; 1970, c. 321; 1979, c. 21 9; 1982, c. 136; 1991, c. 511.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-88"><akn:num>§ 40.1-88</akn:num><akn:heading>Work-training certificate</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A work-training certificate shall permit the employment of a child between fourteen and sixteen years of age during school hours when enrolled in a regular school work- training program pursuant to a written agreement containing the same provisions as specified in § 40.1-89. History History. Code 1950, § 40-100.4; 1970, c. 321; 1979, c. 219; 1982, c. 67 0. Annotations Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 12B M.J. Master and Servant, § 95.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-89"><akn:num>§ 40.1-89</akn:num><akn:heading>Work-training certificate; employment not allowed; revocation of certificate</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text No child shall be employed pursuant to a work-training certificate as provided in § 40.1-88 where such employment requires such child to work in any occupation which is deemed hazardous under § 40.1-100 A or regulations promulgated thereunder. However, a child sixteen or seventeen years of age may be employed in certain such occupations as part of a work-training program in accordance with rules and regulations promulgated by the Commissioner. No child shall work in a work-training program except pursuant to a written agreement which shall provide: (1) that the work of such child shall be incidental to his training, shall be intermittent and for short periods of time and shall be under the direct and close supervision of a competent and experienced person; (2) that safety instruction shall be given by the school and correlated with on-the-job training given by the employer; and (3) that a schedule of organize d and progressive work processes to be performed shall have been prepared. Such written agreement shall set forth the name of the child so employed and shall be signed by the employer and the coordinator of schools having jurisdiction. Copies of such a greement shall be retained by the school and the employer, and a copy thereof shall be filed with the Department. Any such work-training certificate or written agreement may be revoked at any time that it shall appear that reasonable precautions for the safety of such child have no t been observed. History History. Code 1950, § 40-100.4:1; 1960, c. 434; 1968, c. 277; 1970, c. 321; 1982, c. 252; 1991, c. 511.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-90"><akn:num>§ 40.1-90</akn:num><akn:heading>40</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>1-90, 40.1-91. Repealed by Acts 1991, c. 511.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-92"><akn:num>§ 40.1-92</akn:num><akn:heading>Issuance of certificates</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. The Commiss ioner shall prescribe the procedures for minors and employers concerning issuance and maintenance of employment certificates. The Commissioner may issue certificates both directly and electronically. Employment certificates shall be issued by the Departm ent only upon application of the child desiring employment. The employment certificate shall not be valid unless permission is granted by a parent, guardian, or custodian through means specified by the Commissioner. The Department shall have authority to make any investigation or examination necessary for the issuance thereof. No fee shall be charged for issuing any such certificate nor for rendering any services in respect thereto. The Commissioner shall file and preserve such certificates and related documents. B. No person s hall, with the intent to assist a minor to procure employment, make a false statement by any means, including by submitting falsified forms electronically, to any employer or to any representative of the Commissioner in order to obtain the issuance of an employment certificate. History History. Code 1950, § 40-101; 1960, c. 434; 1970, c. 321; 1979, c. 219; 1991, c. 511; 2013, c. 15. Annotations The 2013 amendments. The 2013 amendment by c. 15 rewrote the section.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-93"><akn:num>§ 40.1-93</akn:num><akn:heading>Proof required for employment certificate</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Department shall not issue an employment certificate until it has received, examined, approved, and filed the following: 1. Excep t for work coming within one of the exceptions in § 40.1-79.01, a statement signed by the prospective employer, or someone duly authorized on his behalf, stating that he expects to give such child present employment, setting forth the specific nature of the occupation in which he intends to employ such child, and the number of hours per day and of days per week which said child shall be employed and of the period for lunch. Such statement shall be submitted by means specified by the Commissioner; and 2. A statement, signed by the prospective employer or someone duly authorized on his behalf, submitted by means specified by the Commissioner, that the employer has verified the age of su ch minor. The employer shall procure and keep on file, accessible to the Department or other authorized persons charged with the enforcement of this chapter, the proof of age as provided in § 40.1-94. History History. Code 1950, § 40-102; 1960, c. 434; 1970, c. 321; 1972, c. 480; 1991, c. 511; 2013, c. 15. Annotations The 2013 amendments. The 2013 amendment by c. 15 substituted Department shall not issue an employment certificate until it has for person authorized to issue an employment certificate shall not issue such certificate until he has and deleted papers at the end of the introductory paragraph; added the last sentence in subdivision 1; and inserted the first sentence and The employer shall procure and keep on f ile, accessible to the Department or other authorized persons charged with the enforcement of this chapter, the at the beginning of subdivision 2.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-94"><akn:num>§ 40.1-94</akn:num><akn:heading>Proofs of age</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The evidence of age required by this chapter shall consist of one of the following proofs of age, which shall be required in the order herein designated: (1) A bi rth certificate or attested transcript issued by a registrar of vital statistics or other officer charged with the duty of recording births. (2) A baptismal record or duly certified transcript thereof showing the date of birth and place of baptism of the child. (3) Other documentary proof of age specified by the Commissioner. History History. Code 1950, § 40-103; 1970, c. 321.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-95"><akn:num>§ 40.1-95</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1991, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>511.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-96"><akn:num>§ 40.1-96</akn:num><akn:heading>Contents of employment certificates</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The employment certificate required to be issued shall state the name, sex, date of birth, and place of residence of the child. It shall certify that all the conditions and requirements for issuing an employment certificate under the provisions of this chapter have been fulfilled and shall be signed by the Commissioner. It shall state the kind of evidence of age accepted for the employment certificate. Except for work coming within one of the exceptions in § 40.1-79.01, the certificate shall show the name and address of the employer for whom and the nature of the specific occupation in which the employment certificate authorizes the child to be employed and shall b e valid only for the occupation so designated. It shall bear a number, shall show the date of its issue, and shall be signed by the child for whom it is issued by means specified by the Commissioner. The employment certificate shall be issued to the empl oyer, by means specified by the Commissioner, on or prior to the first day of employment. The employer and Commissioner shall retain a manual or electronic copy of the certificate, so long as the youth is employed or for a period of 36 months, whichever is longer. History History. Code 1950, § 40-105; 1960, c. 434; 1970, c. 321; 1978, c. 596; 1991, c. 511; 2013, c. 15. Annotations The 2013 amendments. The 2013 amendment by c. 15 substituted Commissioner for person issuing it at the end of the second sentence, substituted issued by means spec ified by the Commissioner for issued in the presence of the person issuing it at the end of the fifth sentence, deleted the former sixth sentence, which read: It shall be issued in triplicate, one copy to be mailed to the employer, one co py to be sent to the Commissioner and one copy to be retained and kept on file by the issuing officer. and added the last two sentences.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-97"><akn:num>§ 40.1-97</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1972, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>480.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-98"><akn:num>§ 40.1-98</akn:num><akn:heading>40</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>1-98, 40.1-99. Text Repealed by Acts 1991, c. 511.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-100"><akn:num>§ 40.1-100</akn:num><akn:heading>Certain employment prohibited or limited</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. No child un der 18 years of age shall be employed, permitted, or suffered to work: 1. In an y mine, quarry, tunnel, underground scaffolding work; in or about any plant or establishment manufacturing or storing explosives or articles containing explosive components; in any occupation involving exposure to radioactive substances or to ionizing ra diations including X-ray equipment; 2. At operating or assisting to operate any grinding, abrasive, polishing or buffing machine, any power-driven metal forming, punching or shearing machine, power-driven bakery machine, po wer-driven paper products machine, any circular saw, band saw or guillotine shear, or any power-driven woodworking machine; 3. In oiling or assisting in oiling, wiping and cleaning any such machinery; 4. In any capacity in preparing any composition in which dangerous or poisonous chemicals are used; 5. In any capacity in the manufacturing of paints, colors, white lead, or brick tile or kindred products, or in any place where goods of alcoholic content are manufactured, bottled, or so ld for consumption on the premises except in places (i) licensed pursuant to subdivision 6 of § 4.1-206.1, provided that a child employed at the premises shall not serve or dispense in any manner alcoholic beverages or (ii) where the sale of alcoholic beverages is merely incidental to the main business actually conducted, or to deliver alcoholic goods; 6. In any capacity in or about excavation, demolition, roofing, wrecking or shipbreaking operations; 7. As a driver or a helper on an automobile, truck, or commercial vehicle; however, children who are at least 17 years of age may drive automobiles or trucks on public roadways if: a. The automobile or truck does not exceed 6,000 pounds gross vehicle weight, the vehicle is equipped with seat belts for the driver and any passengers, and the employer requires the employee to use the seatbelts when driving the automobile or truck; b. Driving is restricted to daylight hours; c. The employee has a valid State license for the type of driving involved and has no record of any moving violations at the time of hire; d. The employee has successfully completed a State-approved driver education course; e. The driving does not involve: (i) the towing of vehicles; (ii) route deliveries or route sales; (iii) the transportation for hire of property, goods, or passengers; (iv) urgent, t ime-sensitive deliveries; or (v) the transporting at any time of more than three passengers, including the employees of the employer; f. The driving performed by the employee does not involve more than two trips away from the primary place of employment in any single day for the purpose of delivering goods of the e mployees employer to a customer; g. The driving performed by the employee does not involve more than two trips away from the primary place of employment in any single day for the purpose of transporting passengers, other than employees of the employer; h. The driving takes place within a 30-mile radius of the employees place of employment; and i. The driving is only occasional and incidental to the employees employment and involves no more than one third of the employees work time in any workday and no more than 20 percent work time in any work week; 8. In logging or sawmilling, or in any lath mill, shingle mill or cooperage-stock mill, or in any occupation involving slaughtering, meatpacking, processing or rendering; 9. In any occupation determined and declared hazardous by rules and regulations promulgated by the Commissioner of Labor and Industry, except as otherwise provided in subsection D.Notwith standing the provisions of this section, children 16 years of age or older who are serving a voluntary apprenticeship as provided in Chapter 6 (§ 40.1-117 et seq.) of this title may be employed in any occupation in accordance with rules and regulation s promulgated by the Commissioner. B. Except as p art of a regular work-training program in accordance with §§ 40.1-88 and 40.1-89, no child under 16 years of age shall be employed, permitted or suffered to work: 1. In an y manufacturing or mechanical establishment, in any commercial cannery; in the operation of any automatic passenger or freight elevator; in any dance studio; or in any hospital, nursing home, clinic, or other establishment providing care for resident pat ients as a laboratory helper, therapist, orderly, or nurses aide; in the service of any veterinarian while treating farm animals or horses; in any warehouse; in processing work in any laundry or dry cleaning establishment; in any undertaking establis hment or funeral home; in any curb service restaurant, in hotel and motel room service; in any brick, coal or lumber yard or ice plant or in ushering in theaters. Children 14 years of age or more may be engaged in office work of a clerical nature in bona fide office rooms in the above types of establishments. 2. In any scaffolding work or construction trade; or in any outdoor theater, cabaret, carnival, fair, floor show, pool hall, club, or roadhouse; or as a lifeguard at a beach. C. Children 14 years of age or more may be employed by dry cleaning or laundry establishments in branch stores where no processing is done on the premises, and in hospitals, nursing homes, and clinics where they may be engaged in kitchen work, tray service or room and hall cleaning. Children 14 years of age or more may be employed in bowling alleys completely equipped with automatic pin setters, but not in or about such machines, and in soda fountains, restaurants and hotel and motel food service departments. Childre n 14 years of age or more may work as gatekeepers and in concessions at swimming pools and may be employed by concessionaires operating on beaches where their duties and work pertain to the handling and distribution of beach chairs, umbrellas, floats and other similar or related beach equipment. D. Notwithstan ding any other provision of this chapter: 1. Child ren age 16 years or older employed on farms, in gardens or in orchards may operate, assist in operating, or otherwise perform work involving a truck, excluding a tractor trailer, or farm vehicle as defined in § 46.2-1099, in their employment; 2. Children age 14 years or older employed on farms, in gardens or in orchards may perform work as a helper on a truck or commercial vehicle in their employment, while engaged in such wor k exclusively on a farm, in a garden or in an orchard; 3. Children age 16 years or older may participate in all activities of a volunteer fire company; however, any such child shall not enter a burning structure or a structure which contains burning materials prior to obtaining certification under National Fire Protection Association 1001, level one, fire fighter standards, pursuant to the provisions of clause (i) of subsection A of § 40.1-79.1, except where entry into a structure that co ntains burning materials is during training necessary to attain certification under National Fire Protection Association 1001, level one, firefighter standards, as administered by the Department of Fire Programs. History History. Code 1950, § 40-109; 1956, cc. 443, 463; 1958, c. 321; 1960, c . 434; 1964, c. 503; 1968, c. 278; 1970, c. 321; 1972, c. 824; 1973, c. 13; 1979, cc. 219, 348; 1991, c. 511; 1994, c. 156; 2005, c. 151; 2007, c. 645; 2008, c. 552; 2009, c. 218; 2020, cc. 1113, 1114. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2020, cc. 1113 and 1114, cl. 3, as amended by Acts 2021, Sp. Sess. I, c. 82, cls. 2 and 3, provides: That the provisions of the first, second, and fou rth enactments of this act shall become effective on January 1, 2022, except for the provisions of the first enactment that amend the definition of low alcohol beverage cooler set forth in § 4.1-100 of the Code of Virginia, as amended by this act, wh ich shall become effective July 1, 2020. The 2005 amendments. The 2005 amendment by c. 151, effective March 20, 2005, added except as otherwise provided in subsection D at the end of subdivision A 9, substituted  aged 16 years or older for sixteen years of age or more in subdivision D 1, substituted aged 14 years or older for fourteen years of age or more in subdivision D 2, added subdivision D 3, and made minor stylistic changes. The 2007 amendments. The 2007 amendment by c. 645 in subdivision A 5, inserted clause (i) and the clause (ii) designation. The 2008 amendments. The 2008 amendment by c. 552 deleted the second sentence in subdivision A 7, which read: The provisions of this paragraph shall not apply to the drivers of sc hool buses. The 2009 amendments. The 2009 amendment by c. 218, in subsection A, rewrote subdivision A 7, which read: As a driver or a helper on a truck or commercial vehicle of more than two axles. The 2020 amendments. The 2020 amendments by cc. 1113 and 1114, effective January 1, 2022, are identical, and in subdivision A 5, substituted subdivision 6 of § 4.1-206.1 fo r subdivision 5 of § 4.1-207 in clause (i); and in subsection D, substituted age for aged wherever it occurs. Cross references. As to prohibition of persons under 18 from working in or around mines, see § 45.2-504. Law Review. For survey of Virginia criminal law for the year 1978-1979, see 66 Va. L. Rev. 241 (1980). For annual survey article, Labor and Employment Law, see 44 U. Rich. L. Rev. 513 (2009). § 40.1-100.1. Employment where hazard capable of causing serious physical harm or death. Text No person shall employ, suffer, or permit a child to work in any gainful occupation that exposes such child to a recognized hazard capable of causing serious physical h arm or death to such child. Any person violating this section shall be subject to a civil monetary penalty in accordance with § 40.1-113 of this chapter. History History. 1991, c. 511. § 40.1-100.2. Employment involving sexually explicit visual material prohibited. Text A person under eighteen years of age shall not perform in or be a subject...</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-101"><akn:num>§ 40.1-101</akn:num><akn:heading>Qualifications as to theaters</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Notwithstanding the provisions of §§ 40.1-100 and 40.1-100.1, a child under sixteen years of age, whether a resident or nonresident of the Commonwealth, may be em ployed, permitted or suffered to participate in the presentation of a drama, play, performance, concert or entertainment, provided the management of the theater or other public place where such performance is to be held in the Commonwealth shall secure a permit from the Commissioner; provided, that no such permit shall be required for any nonprofit dance or music recital, nor for any television or radio broadcast in which the children participating are selected by the television or radio broadcasting st ation for sustaining noncommercial programs. History History. Code 1950, § 40-110; 1960, c. 434; 1970, c. 321; 1973, c. 13; 1979, c. 348; 1991, c. 511.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-102"><akn:num>§ 40.1-102</akn:num><akn:heading>Issuance of theatrical permit</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text No permit shall be issued unless the Commissioner is satisfied that the environment in which the drama, play, performance, concert or entertainment is to be produced is a proper environment for the child and that the conditions of such employment are not detrimental to the health or morals of such child and that the childs education will not be neglected or hampered by its participation in such drama, play, perform ance, concert or entertainment. Applications for permits and every permit granted shall specify the name, age and sex of each child, together with such other facts as may be necessary for the proper identification of each child and the dates when, and th e theaters or other places of amusement in which such drama, play, performance, concert or entertainment is to be produced and shall specify the name of the drama, play, performance, concert or entertainment in which each child is permitted to participat e. Such application shall be filed with the Commissioner not less than five days before the date of such drama, play, performance, concert or entertainment. A permit shall be revocable by the Commissioner should it be found that the environment in which the drama, play, performance, concert or entertainment is being produced is not a proper environment for the child and that the conditions of such employment are detrimental to the health or morals of such child. The Commissioner shall prescribe and supp ly the forms required for carrying out the provisions of this section. History History. Code 1950, § 40-111; 1960, c. 434; 1970, c. 321.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-103"><akn:num>§ 40.1-103</akn:num><akn:heading>Cruelty and injuries to children; penalty; abandoned infant</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. It shall be unlawful for any person employing or having the custody of any child willfully or negligently to cause or permit the life of such child to be endangered or the health of such child to be injured, or willfully or negligently to cause or permit such child to be placed in a situation that its life, health or morals may be endangered, or to cause or permit such child to be overworked, tortured, tormented, mutilated, beaten or cruelly treated. Any person violating this section is guilty of a Class 6 felony. B. If a prosec ution under this section is based solely on the accused parent having left the child at a hospital or emergency medical services agency, it shall be an affirmative defense to prosecution of a parent under this section that such parent safely delivered th e child within the first 30 days of the childs life to (i) a hospital that provides 24-hour emergency services, (ii) an attended emergency medical services agency that employs emergency medical services personnel, or (iii) a newborn safety device loc ated at and operated by such hospital or emergency medical services agency. In order for the affirmative defense to apply, the child shall be delivered in a manner reasonably calculated to ensure the childs safety. History History. Code 1950, § 40-112; 1970, c. 321; 1991, c. 511; 2003, cc. 816 , 822; 2006, c. 935; 2015, cc. 502, 503; 2022, cc. 80, 81. Annotations Cross references. As to exemption from this section of trainers, instructors, or supervisors of persons 16 years of age or older who are authorized by local ordinance to participat e in volunteer fire company activities, see § 40.1-79.1. As to immunity of hospital or rescue squad personnel for acceptance of infants under subsection B of this section, see § 8.01-226.5:2. As to the Virginia Child Protection Accountability System, see § 63.2-1530. As to punishment for Class 6 felonies, see § 18.2-10. As to seizure of property used in connection with certain offenses, see § 19.2-386.35. The 2003 amendments. The 2003 amendments by cc. 816 and 822 are identical, and designated the existing provisions of the section as subsection A and added subsection B. The 2006 amendments. The 2006 amendment by c. 935 added the last sentence of subsection B. The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendments by cc. 502 and 503 are identical, and substituted is guilty for shall be guilty in subsection A; and in subsection B, substitu ted emergency medical services agency for rescue squad throughout the subsection and emergency medical services personnel for emergency medical technicians. The 2022 amendments. The 2022 amendments by cc. 80 and 81 are identical, and in subsection B, inserted within the first 30 days of the childs life, (i), and (i i), deleted or to following 24-hour emergency services, and substituted or (iii) a newborn safety device located at and operated by such hospital or emergency medical services agency for within the first 14 days of the chi lds life; and made a stylistic changes. Law Review. For 2006 survey article, Family and Juvenile Law, see 41 U. Rich. L. Rev. 151 (2006). For annual survey article, Criminal Law and Procedure, see 46 U. Rich. L. Rev. 59 (2011). Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 9B M.J. Infants, § 89; 14A M.J. Parent and Child, § 22 . CASE NOTES St atute language unconstitutionally vague and inclusive.  Where the instant charges arose from a perception by law-enforcement officials that the conduct of the defendants may have threatened the life, health or mora ls of children under the statute, use of the term may by the legislature criminalizes any act which presents a possibility of physical or moral harm to the child, thus the vague and inclusive statutory language clearly failed to adequ ately inform law enforcement of the precise conduct prohibited and is thus unconstitutional. Commonwealth v. Carter, 21 Va. App. 150, 462 S.E.2d 582, 1995 Va. App. LEXIS 741 (1995). Constitutional challenge untimely.  Record did not establish good cause for defendants failure to make a timely pre-trial challenge to the constitutionality of § 40.1-103; fact that a portion of the statute had already been declared unconstitutionally vague was information to which defendant had access between his indictment in late 2018 and his trial in mid-2019, plus defendant could have asked for a bill of particulars, then lodged his vag ueness challenge prior to trial rather than waiting until after conviction. Mollenhauer v. Commonwealth, 2021 Va. App. LEXIS 109 (Va. Ct. App. July 6, 2021). Retroactive application of Carter.  A new rule for prosecutions under this section  the ruling in Commonwealth v. Carter , 21 Va. App. 150, 462 S.E.2d 582 (1995) declaring provisions of this section unconstitutionally void for vagueness  applied retroactively. Therefore, defendant who was indict ed, his jury instructed and he ultimately convicted on precisely that unconstitutional provision had his conviction overturned. Herrera v. Commonwealth, 24 Va. App. 490, 483 S.E.2d 492, 1997 Va. App. LEXIS 190 (1997). Although defendant failed to raise constitutionality of provision of this section he was convicted under at trial or on appeal, court of appeals could consider issue sua sponte with regard to trial courts jurisdiction to convict defendant. Herrera v. Commonwealth, 24 Va. App. 490, 483 S.E.2d 492, 1997 Va. App. LEXIS 190 (1997). Double jeopardy.  Because the two statutes require proof of additional facts, and they therefore constitute two distinct offenses, the double jeopardy clause was not offended by de fendants convictions under § 18.2-47 and this section. Long v. Commonwealth, 1995 Va. App. LEXIS 874 (Va. Ct. App. Dec. 5, 1995). Defendants convictions for child abuse and child endangerment under §§ 18.2-371.1 and 40.1-103 were appropriate because his double-jeopardy rights were not violated since each statute required proof of additional facts not found in the other and thus constituted two distinct offenses. Child endangerment did not require serious injury, or any injury at all; child endangerment, but not child abuse, requir ed that the childs life, health, or morals be endangered; and endangerment of a childs moral well-being was not a violation of the child abuse statute. King v. Commonwealth, 56 Va. App. 133, 692 S.E.2d 249, 2010 Va. App. LEXIS 166 (2010). Evidence insufficient.  Where no evidence showed that either appellant or her boyfriend ingested the drugs before or while operating the vehicle, or that the children understood their mo ther had just purchased illegal drugs and the moral significance associated thereto, defendants conviction was not supported by sufficient evidence of actions that may have endangered her children. Riggs v. Commonwealth, 1996 Va. App. LEXIS 591 (Va. Ct. App. Sept. 10, 1996). Notwithstanding that a fire resulted from defendants failure to turn off a gas jet stove just before stepping out of her apartment to visit a friend while her daughters slept in a closed bedroom, the evidence did not show that defendant acted with the requisite knowledge or callous indifference to support a conviction under this section. Ellis v. Commonwealth, 29 Va. App. 548, 513 S.E.2d 453, 1999 Va. App. LE XIS 231 (1999). Criminal negligence.  The negligence required in a criminal proceeding must be more than the lack of ordinary care and precaution; it must be something more than mere inadvertence or m isadventure; it is a recklessness or indifference incompatible with a proper regard for human life. Thus, where neither jury instruction defined criminal negligence, they invited the imposition of criminal liability upon a finding of simple negligence, w hich constituted reversible error. Mosby v. Commonwealth, 23 Va. App. 53, 473 S.E.2d 732, 1996 Va. App. LEXIS 564 (1996). Although defendant argued that the Commonwealth of Virginia failed to prove both the necessary scienter, in that the evidence did not show that she had actual kno wledge of the presence and character of the illegal drugs in her home, and the requisite mens rea, in that the evidence did not show that her acts or omissions rose to a level of criminal negligence, the court found that defendants contention that by failing to establish her guilt for the drug possession charges, the Commonwealth necessarily also failed to prove she had knowledge that drugs were present in the wardrobe was not supported by the record when viewed in its entirety, and while the jury m ay have found that the Commonwealth had not proven beyond a reasonable doubt that defendant exercised dominion and control over the drugs, it could also have found the evidence was sufficient to prove that she was nonetheless aware of the presence and ch aracter of the drugs for purposes of determining whether she was guilty of the child endangerment charges under subsection A of this section. Carosi v. Commonwealth, 280 Va. 545, 701 S.E.2d 441, 2010 Va. LEXIS 262 (2010). Mens rea.  Not only can commission of either involuntary manslaughter or child abuse and neglect result in serious bodily injury to the child victim, but also the requisite mens rea is the same for both crimes; to the extent that the child abuse statute requires a showing of willfulness, that requirement incorporates willful negligence. King v. King George Dep't of Soc. Servs., 69 Va. App. 206, 817 S.E.2d 658, 2018 Va. App. LEXIS 226 (2018). Evidence sufficient to suppo rt conviction.  Where the child was taken out into a temperature of forty-eight degrees and the child was clothed only in a sleeper that was not snapped and did not cover the childs bare feet, the evidence was sufficient to support defendants conviction for negligently causing or permitting the life of the child to be endangered or the health of the child to be injured. Morrison v. Commonwealth, 1996 Va. App. LEX IS 783 (Va. Ct. App. Dec. 10, 1996). Evidence was sufficient where child displayed m...</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-104"><akn:num>§ 40.1-104</akn:num><akn:heading>Age certificates</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text An age certificate shall be issued, upon request of the employer or the worker, for a person sixteen years of age or over. It shall be issued by the person authorized t o issue employment certificates under the provisions of this chapter upon presentation of the same evidence of age as required for an employment certificate. The age certificate shall show the persons name and address, his date of birth and signature , the signature of the person issuing the certificate and the evidence accepted as proof of age. An employment or age certificate duly issued shall be conclusive evidence of the age of the person for whom issued in any proceeding involving the employment of the per son under any of the labor laws of this Commonwealth as to any act occurring subsequent to its issuance and prior to its revocation. History History. Code 1950, § 40-113; 1970, c. 321; 1972, c. 824; 1979, c. 219.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-105"><akn:num>§ 40.1-105</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1991, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>511.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-106"><akn:num>§ 40.1-106</akn:num><akn:heading>40</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>1-106 through 40.1-108. Text Repealed by Acts 1979, c. 219.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-109"><akn:num>§ 40.1-109</akn:num><akn:heading>Newspaper carriers on regular routes; hours</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Notwithstanding the other provisions of this chapter, any child between twelve and sixteen years of age may daily engage in the occupation of distributing newspapers on regularly established routes between the hours of four oclock ante meridian and seven oclock post meridian, excluding the time public schools are actually in session. History History. Code 1950, § 40-118; 1960, c. 434; 1962, c. 352; 1970, c. 321; 1972, c. 807; 1973, c. 13; 1979, c. 219; 1982, c. 83; 1991, c. 511. Annotations CASE NOTES No private cause of action for violation of statute.  This section does not grant a child employed under the age of 12 a private right of action to enforce the provisions of the child labor laws. Howarth v. Rockingha m Publishing Co., 20 F. Supp. 2d 959, 1998 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 15661 (W.D. Va. 1998).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-110"><akn:num>§ 40.1-110</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1979, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>219.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-111"><akn:num>§ 40.1-111</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1991, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>511.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-112"><akn:num>§ 40.1-112</akn:num><akn:heading>Solicitation generally</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. In order to provide for enforcement of the child labor laws and the protection of employees, it shall be unlawful for any person, firm or corporation, except a nonprofit organization as defined in § 501 (c) (3) of the United States Internal Revenue Code, to enga ge in or to employ any person for, or suffer or permit any person in his employment to work in, any trade in any street or public place, including but not limited to candy sales or soliciting for commercial purposes, selling, or obtaining subscription co ntracts or orders for books, magazines or other periodical publications other than newspapers, without obtaining from the Commissioner a permit to conduct such business. No permit shall be required for the placement of advertisements or literature on or near a business or private residence, if there is no attempt, in person, to solicit business or make a sale at the time of the placement of the material. B. Such permit s shall be valid from the date of issuance until June 30 next following the date of issuance. Applications may be made not more than thirty days prior to the requested date of issuance on forms furnished by the Commissioner, and the applicant shall suppl y such information as is required concerning his place or places of business, the prospective number of his employees, and the proposed hours of work and rate of compensation for such employees. A separate permit shall be required for each place of busin ess which the applicant operates within this Commonwealth. C. Each permit tee shall maintain such records as may be prescribed by the Commissioner showing the name, residence address and age of each employee, the hours worked by each employee, the place where such work was performed, and the compensation paid and payable to su ch employee. Such records shall be available for inspection by the Commissioner or a representative designated by him during business hours. D. No child sh all be employed or permitted to work by or for any permittee unless all the following conditions are satisfied: 1. The c hild is at least sixteen years of age; 2. The permittee has a permanent business address within this Commonwealth; and 3. The child works at all times under the immediate supervision of an adult. E. No child sh all be required, permitted or directed to make any false statement representing himself, his employer or products or services in his employment. F. Any person violating any provision or condition of this section shall be guilty of a Class 1 misdemeanor for each such violation. Any violation of this section by a permittee or with his knowledge and consent shall in addition be grounds for revocation of the permi t. History History. Code 1950, § 40-118.3; 1964, c. 315; 1966, c. 603; 1968, c. 74 3; 1970, c. 321; 1973, c. 13; 1979, c. 219; 1982, c. 137; 1991, c. 511; 1998, c. 157. Annotations Cross references. As to punishment for Class 1 misdemeanors, see § 18.2-11. The 1998 amendment, in subsection A, in the first sentence, substituted or soliciting for commercial purposes, selling for solicitation, sale, and deleted of preceding subscription, and added the second sentence; and in the last sentence of subsection B, substituted business which the applicant for business or location at which applicant. Law Review. For survey of Virginia criminal law for the year 1978-1979, see 66 Va. L. Rev. 241 (1980).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-113"><akn:num>§ 40.1-113</akn:num><akn:heading>Child labor offenses; civil penalties</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. Whoever emp loys, procures, or, having under his control, permits a child to be employed in violation of any of the provisions of this chapter other than §§ 40.1-100.2, 40.1-103 and 40.1-112, shall be subject to a civil penalty that (i) shall not exceed $10,00 0 for each violation that results in the employment of a child who is seriously injured or who dies in the course of that employment and (ii) shall not exceed $1,000 for each other violation. In determining the amount of such penalty, the appropriateness of such penalty to the size of the business of the person charged and the gravity of the violation shall be considered. B. The Commiss ioner shall notify any employer who he alleges has violated any provision of this section by certified mail or overnight delivery service. Such notice shall contain a description of the alleged violation. Within 21 days of receipt of notice of the allege d violation, the employer may request an informal conference regarding such violation with the Commissioner. If the employer fails to contest the violation by requesting such an informal conference within 21 days following receipt of the notice of the al leged violation, the violation and proposed penalty will become a final order of the Commissioner and not subject to review by any court or agency except upon a showing of good cause. Such informal conference shall result in a decision by the Commissione r that will be appealable to the appropriate circuit court. The Department shall send a copy of the Commissioners decision to the employer by certified mail or overnight delivery service. The employer may file a notice of an appeal only within 30 day s from the receipt of the decision. The appeal shall be on the agency record. With respect to matters of law, the burden shall be on the party seeking review to designate and demonstrate an error of law subject to review by the court. With respect to iss ues of fact, the duty of the court shall be limited to ascertaining whether there was substantial evidence in the record to reasonably support the Commissioners findings of fact. C. Civil penal ties owed under this section shall be paid to the Commissioner for deposit into the general fund of the treasury of the Commonwealth. The Commissioner shall prescribe procedures for the payment of proposed penalties which are not contested by employers. History History. Code 1950, § 40-119; 1964, c. 504; 1970, c. 321; 1973, c. 425; 1979, c. 348; 1982, c. 416; 1991, c. 511; 2007, c. 667; 2015, c. 285. Annotations Cross references. For provisions as to enforcement of this title and rules and regulations adopted pursuant thereto, and penalties for violations, see § 40.1-49.4. The 2007 amendments. The 2007 amendment by c. 667 inserted the language beginning that (i) shall and ending and (ii) shall and made minor stylistic changes. The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendment by c. 285, in subsection A, deleted , or issues an employment certificate, following child to be employed in the first sentence , and deleted The determination by the Commissioner shall be final, unless within fifteen days after receipt of such notice the person charged with the violation notifies the Commissioner by certified mail that he intends to contest the proposed pena lty before the appropriate general district court. at the end; added subsection B and redesignated former subsection B as subsection C. Law Review. For 2007 annual survey article, Labor and Employment Law, see 42 U. Rich. L. Rev. 489 (2007). CASE NOTES Classes of persons liable.  This section imposes a penalty upon only four classes of persons, namely, the proprietor of the business (or his agent) who employs the child, the person who proc ures the employment of the child, the parent (or other person in control) who permits the child to be employed, and the official who issues the false employment certificate. Clover Creamery Co. v. Kanode, 142 Va. 542, 129 S.E. 222 (1925), In accord with Clover Creamery Co. v. Kanode, 142 Va. 542, 129 S.E. 222 (1925) (see Howarth v. Rockingham Publishing Co., 20 F. Supp. 2d 959 (W.D. Va. 1998)). Construction of statute.  Section 40.1-78 should be construed in harmony with the legislative intent as expressed in this section. Clover Creamery Co. v. Kanode, 142 Va. 542, 129 S.E. 222, 1925 Va. LEXIS 357 (1925).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-114"><akn:num>§ 40.1-114</akn:num><akn:heading>Enforcement of child labor law</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Commissioner, with the assistance of state and local law-enforcement officers, shall enforce the provisions of this chapter and shall have authority to appoint such representatives as may be necessary to secure the enforcement of this chapter. He shall make all necessary rules and regulations for carrying out the purposes of this chapter, and shall prescribe such forms as may be required for carrying out the provis ions of this chapter. History History. Code 1950, § 40-120; 1970, c. 321; 1979, c. 219; 2015, c. 285. Annotations The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendment by c. 285, in the last sentence, substituted prescribe such forms for and supply to the proper officials blanks for employment cert ificates and such other forms.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-115"><akn:num>§ 40.1-115</akn:num><akn:heading>School attendance</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Nothing contained in this chapter shall be construed as qualifying in any way the provisions of the compulsory education laws of this Commonwealth, nor as authorizing t he employment of any child who is absent unlawfully from school. History History. Code 1950, § 40-121; 1970, c. 321.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-116"><akn:num>§ 40.1-116</akn:num><akn:heading>Curfew ordinances not affected</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Nothing in this chapter shall be construed to permit the violation of a curfew ordinance of any city. History History. Code 1950, § 40-122; 1970, c. 321. Chapter 6. Voluntary Apprenticeship. -360§ 40.1-117. Apprenticeship Council; membership and terms of office; meetings and duties. -360§ 40.1-118. Authority of Council. -360§ 40.1-119. Local and state joint apprenticeship committees. -360§ 40.1-120. Definitions. -360§ 40.1-120.1. Discrimination prohibitions for registered apprenticeship programs. -360§ 40.1-121. Requisites of apprentice agreement. -360§ 40.1-122. Approval of agreement by Commissioner; signing. -360§ 40.1-123. Agreement binding after apprentices majority. -360§ 40.1-124. Agreement signed by organization of employers or of employees. -360§ 40.1-125. Commissioner to administer chapter. -360§ 40.1-126. Operation and application of chapter. -360§ 40.1-127. Reserved. Annotations Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 2A M.J. Apprentices, § 1.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-117"><akn:num>§ 40.1-117</akn:num><akn:heading>Apprenticeship Council; membership and terms of office; meetings and duties</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. The Governo r shall appoint an Apprenticeship Council, composed of four representatives each from employer and employee organizations respectively, and all of whom shall be familiar with apprenticeable occupations. The Commissioner of the Virginia Employment Commiss ion, the Chancellor of the Virginia Community College System, or their designated representatives, and a local superintendent from a school division that provides apprenticeship-related instruction, shall be members, ex officio, of the Council. At the be ginning of each year the Governor shall designate one member to serve as chairman. Each member shall be appointed for a term of three years. Any member appointed to fill a vacancy occurring prior to the expiration of the term of his predecessor shall be appointed for the remainder of such term. All members, including ex officio members, shall have voting privileges. B. The Apprent iceship Council shall meet at the call of the chairman of the Council and shall formulate policies for the effective administration of this chapter. C. The Apprent iceship Council shall establish standards for apprentice agreements which shall not be lower than those prescribed by this chapter and those established pursuant to Article 3 (§ 54.1-1128 et seq.) of Chapter 11 of Title 54.1, and shall perform such ot her functions as may be necessary to carry out the intent and purposes of this chapter. Not less than once a year the Council shall make a report of its activities and findings to the General Assembly and to the public. History History. Code 1950, § 40-123; 1968, c. 273; 1970, c. 321; 1978, c. 206; 1980, c. 728; 1981, c. 331; 1987, c. 165; 1992, c. 231. Annotations Cross references. As to compensation and expenses of boards, commissions and similar bodies, see § 2.2-2813.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-118"><akn:num>§ 40.1-118</akn:num><akn:heading>Authority of Council</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Council may: 1. Deter mine standards for apprentice agreements, which standards shall not be lower than those prescribed by this chapter; 2. Appoint the secretary of the Apprenticeship Council to act as secretary of each state joint apprenticeship committee; 3. Review decisions of local joint apprenticeship committees relating to apprenticeship disputes pursuant to subdivision C 3 of § 40.1-119; 4. Perform such other duties as are necessary to carry out the intent of this chapter; and 5. Advise the Commissioner on policies to coordinate apprenticeship-related instruction delivered by state and local public education agencies. History History. Code 1950, § 40-124; 1970, c. 321; 1978, c. 206; 1990, c. 614; 1996, cc. 134, 486; 2014, c. 734; 2015, cc. 63, 86. Annotations The 2014 amendments. The 2014 amendment by c. 734 deleted subdivisions 3 through 7 and 9 and redesignated the remaining subdivisions accordingly; in subdivision 3, deleted and sta te following local and substituted relating to for adjusting and subdivision C 3 of § 40.1-119 for § 40.1-119, C 3; added subdivision 4 and made related changes. The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendments by cc. 63 and 86 are identical, and substituted Commissioner for State Board for Community Colleges in subdivision 5.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-119"><akn:num>§ 40.1-119</akn:num><akn:heading>Local and state joint apprenticeship committees</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. A local joi nt apprenticeship committee may be established in any trade or group of trades in a city or trade area whenever the apprentice training needs of such trade or group of trades justify such establishment. B. When two or more local joint apprenticeship committees have been established in the state for a trade or group of trades or at the request of any trade or group of trades, a state apprenticeship committee may be established for such trade or group of trades. Such l ocal and state joint apprenticeship committees shall be composed of an equal number of employer and employee representatives chosen from names submitted by the respective employer and employee organizations in such trade or group of trades. In a trade or group of trades in which there is no bona fide employer or employee organization, the committee shall be appointed from persons known to represent the interests of employers and of employees respectively. C. The functio ns of a local joint apprenticeship committee shall be: 1. To co operate with school authorities in regard to the education of apprentices; 2. In accordance with standards established by the Apprenticeship Council, to establish local standards of apprenticeship regarding schedule of operations, application of wage rates, work ing conditions for apprentices, and the number of apprentices which shall be employed locally in the trade; and 3. To adjust apprenticeship disputes. D. The functio ns of a state trade apprenticeship committee shall be to assist in an advisory capacity in the development of statewide standards of apprenticeship and in the development of local standards and local committees. History History. Code 1950, § 40-125; 1970, c. 321; 1990, c. 614; 2014, c. 734. Annotations The 2014 amendments. The 2014 amendment by c. 734, in subsection A, substituted established for appointed, deleted by the Apprenticeship Council following  or trade area in the first sentence and deleted the last sentence, which read Sponsors not signatory to a bargaining agreement may operate an individual apprenticeship program or, at the option and under guidelines prescribed by a joint committee , participate in an apprenticeship program operated by a joint apprenticeship committee; deleted the Apprenticeship Council may appoint following of any trade or group of trades and inserted may be established in the first sen tence of subsection B.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-120"><akn:num>§ 40.1-120</akn:num><akn:heading>Definitions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text As used in this chapter, the following terms shall have the following meanings unless the context indicates otherwise: Apprenticeable occupation means a skilled occupation having the following characterist ics: 1. It is customarily learned in a practical way through a structured systematic program of on-the-job supervised work experience; 2. It is clearly identifiable and recognized throughout an industry; 3. It involves manual, mechanical or technical skills which require a minimum of 2,000 hours of on-the-job work experience of new apprenticeable trades not otherwise established; and 4. It requires related instruction to supplement the on-the-job work experience. Apprentice means a person at least 16 years of age who is covered by a written agreeme nt with an employer and approved by the Commissioner. The agreement shall provide for not less than 2,000 hours of reasonably continuous employment for such person, for his participation in an approved schedule of work experience through employment, and for the amount of related instruction required in the occupation. Employer means any person or organization employing a registered apprentice, whether o r not such person or organization is a party to an apprenticeship agreement with a sponsor. Joint apprenticeship committee means a group equally representative of management and labor representatives which works under a bargaining agreement and is established to carry out the administration of an apprenticeship training program. Sponsor means either an individual employer, a group of employers, or an association o r organization operating an apprenticeship program, and in whose name the program is registered. History History. Code 1950, § 40-126; 1960, c. 336; 1970, c. 321; 1978, c. 206; 1990, c. 614; 2014, c. 734. Annotations The 2014 amendments. The 2014 amendment by c. 734, in the definition of Apprenticeable occupation, substituted occupation for trade; in the definition of A pprentice, substituted 16 for sixteen and Commissioner for Apprenticeship Council in the first sentence and deleted in new apprenticeship trades not otherwise established following continuous employment and substituted occupation for craft or trade in the second sentence; and in the definition of Employer, substituted whether or not such person or organization is a for who is. § 40.1-120.1. Discrimination prohibitions for registered apprenticeship programs. Text A. Notwithstan ding the provisions of the Virginia Human Rights Act (§ 2.2-3900 et seq.), for purposes of this chapter a sponsor of a registered apprenticeship program shall not discriminate against an apprentice or applicant for apprenticeship on the basis of race, color, religion, national origin, sex, sexual orientation, gender identity, age if the age of the individual is 40 years of age or older, genetic information, or disability. B. Notwithstan ding any other provisions of this title, it shall not be an unlawful practice for an employer to fail or refuse to hire and employ any individual for any position in a registered apprenticeship program, or for any registered apprenticeship program to fai l or refuse to accept or admit any individual to any registered apprenticeship program, if: 1. The o ccupancy of such position, or access to the premises in or upon which any part of the duties of such position is performed or is to be performed, is subject to any requirement imposed in the interest of the national security of the United States under an y security program in effect pursuant to or administered under any statute of the United States or any Executive Order of the President; and 2. Such individual has not fulfilled or has ceased to fulfill any requirement set forth in subdivision 1. C. The sole re medy for a violation of subsection A shall be as provided in subdivision B 5 of § 40.1-125. History History. 2020, c. 1228.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-121"><akn:num>§ 40.1-121</akn:num><akn:heading>Requisites of apprentice agreement</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Every apprentice agreement entered into under this chapter shall contain: 1. The n ames, signatures, and addresses of the contracting parties; 2. The date of birth of the apprentice; 3. The contact information of the Program Sponsor and the Division of Registered Apprenticeship; 4. A statement of the occupation or business that the apprentice is to be taught and the time at which the apprenticeship will begin and end; 5. A statement showing the number of hours to be spent by the apprentice in work and the number of hours to be spent in related or supplemental instruction; 6. A statement setting forth a schedule of the processes in the occupation or industry division in which the apprentice is to be taught and the approximate time to be spent at each proces s; 7. A statement of the graduated scale of wages to be paid the apprentice and whether the required related instruction shall be compensated; 8. A statement providing for a period of probation of not less than 500 hours of employment and instruction extending over not less than four months, during which time the apprentice agre ement shall be terminated by the Commissioner at the request in writing of either party, and providing that after such probationary period the apprentice agreement may be terminated by the Commissioner by mutual agreement of all parties thereto, or cance lled by the Commissioner for good and sufficient reason; 9. A reference incorporating as part of the agreement the standards of the apprenticeship program as they exist on the date of the agreement and as they may be amended during the period o f the agreement; 10. A statement that the apprentice will be accorded equal opportunity in all phases of apprenticeship employment and training without discrimination as provided in § 40.1-120.1; 11. Contact information, including name, address, phone number, and email if appropriate, of the appropriate authority designated under the program to receive, process, and make disposi tion of controversies or differences arising out of the apprenticeship agreement when the controversies or differences cannot be adjusted locally or resolved in accordance with the established procedure or applicable collective bargaining provisions; 12. A provision that an employer who is unable to fulfill his obligation under the apprentice agreement may, with the approval of the Commissioner, transfer such contract to any other e mployer if (i) the apprentice consents, (ii) such other employer agrees to assume the obligations of the apprentice agreement, and (iii) the transfer is reported to the registration agency within 30 days of the transfer; and 13. Such additional terms and conditions as may be prescribed or approved by the Commissioner not inconsistent with the provisions of this chapter. History History. Code 1950, § 40-127; 1960, c. 336; 1970, c. 321; 1990, c. 614; 2014, c. 734; 2020, c. 1228. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2020, c. 1137, amended subdivision 10 by inserting sexual orientation, or gender identity in the phrase on the basis of race, color, religion, na tional origin, or sex, which was deleted by Acts 2020, c. 1228. The 2014 amendments. The 2014 amendment by c. 734 added subdivisions 3 and 9 - 11, and redesignated the remaining subdivisions accordingly; in subdivision 4, substituted occupatio n for trade, craft, that for which, and made a minor stylistic change; in subdivision 6, substituted occupation for trade; in subdivision 7, substituted related instruction for schooltime; in su bdivisions 8, 12, and 13, substituted Commissioner for Council throughout; and in subdivision 12, substituted 30 for thirty. The 2020 amendments. The 2020 amendment by c. 1228, substituted as provided in § 40.1-120.1 for on the basis of race, color, religion, national origin, or sex in su bdivision 10.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-122"><akn:num>§ 40.1-122</akn:num><akn:heading>Approval of agreement by Commissioner; signing</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text No apprentice agreement under this chapter shall be effective until approved by the Commissioner. Every apprentice agreement shall be signed by the employer, or by an a ssociation of employers or an organization of employees as provided in § 40.1-124, and by the apprentice, and, if the apprentice is a minor, by the minors father or mother, provided, that if both father and mother be dead or legally incapable of g iving consent or have abandoned their children, then by the guardian of the minor. History History. Code 1950, § 40-128; 1970, c. 321; 1974, c. 272; 2014, c. 734. Annotations The 2014 amendments. The 2014 amendment by c. 734 substituted Commissioner for Council.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-123"><akn:num>§ 40.1-123</akn:num><akn:heading>Agreement binding after apprentices majority</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text When a minor enters into an apprentice agreement under this chapter for a period of training extending into his majority, the apprentice agreement shall likewise be bin ding for such a period as may be covered during the apprentices majority. History History. Code 1950, § 40-129; 1970, c. 321.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-124"><akn:num>§ 40.1-124</akn:num><akn:heading>Agreement signed by organization of employers or of employees</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text For the purpose of providing greater diversity of training or continuity of employment, any apprentice agreement made under this chapter may in the discretion of the Co mmissioner be signed by an association of employers or an organization of employees instead of by an individual employer. In such a case the apprentice agreement shall expressly provide that the association of employers or organization of employees does not assume the obligation of an employer but agrees to use its best endeavors to procure employment and training for such apprentice with one or more employers who will accept full responsibility, as herein provided, for all the terms and conditions of e mployment and training set forth in the agreement between the apprentice and employer association or employee organization during the period of each such employment. The apprentice agreement in such a case shall also expressly provide for the transfer of the apprentice, subject to the approval of the Commissioner, to such employer or employers as shall sign a written agreement with the apprentice, and if the apprentice is a minor with his parent or guardian, as specified in § 40.1-122, contracting to employ the apprentice for the whole or a definite part of the total period of apprenticeship under the terms and conditions of employment and training set forth in the agreement entered into between the apprentice and the employer association or employe e organization. History History. Code 1950, § 40-130; 1970, c. 321; 2014, c. 734. Annotations The 2014 amendments. The 2014 amendment by c. 734 substituted Commissioner for Council twice.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-125"><akn:num>§ 40.1-125</akn:num><akn:heading>Commissioner to administer chapter</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. The Commiss ioner, with the advice and guidance of the Council, shall be responsible for administering the provisions of this chapter. B. The Commiss ioner shall: 1. Appro ve, if approval is in the best interests of the apprentice, any apprenticeship agreement that meets the standards established under this chapter; 2. Terminate or cancel any apprenticeship agreement in accordance with the provisions of such agreement; 3. Keep a record of apprenticeship agreements and their disposition; 4. Issue certificates of completion upon the completion of the apprenticeship; 5. Initiate deregistration proceedings when an apprenticeship program is not conducted, operated, and administered in accordance with the registered provisions, except that deregistration proceedings for violation of equal opportunity requirements shall be processed in accordance with the provisions of the Virginia State Plan for Equal Employment Opportunity in Apprenticeship; 6. Establish policies governing the provision of apprenticeship-related instruction delivered by state and local public education agencies and shall provide for the administration and sup ervision of related and supplemental instruction for apprentices; and 7. Perform such other duties as are necessary to carry out the intent of this chapter. History History. Code 1950, § 40-131; 1970, c. 321; 2014, c. 734; 2015, cc. 63, 86. Annotations The 2014 amendments. The 2014 amendment by c. 734 designated the existing provisions as subsection A and added subsection B. The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendments by cc. 63 and 86 are identical, and added subdivision B 6 and made related changes.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-126"><akn:num>§ 40.1-126</akn:num><akn:heading>Operation and application of chapter</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Nothing in this chapter or in any apprentice agreement approved under this chapter shall invalidate any apprenticeship provision in any collective agreement between emp loyers and employees establishing higher apprenticeship standards regarding ratios of apprentices to journeymen, probationary periods, or length of the program. But none of the terms or provisions of this chapter shall apply to any person, firm, corpora tion, or craft unless, until and only so long as such person, firm, corporation, or craft voluntarily elects that the terms and provisions of this chapter shall apply. History History. Code 1950, § 40-132; 1970, c. 321; 1990, c. 614.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-127"><akn:num>§ 40.1-127</akn:num><akn:heading>Reserved</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Chapter 7. Passenger Tramway Safety. -360§§ 40.1-128 through 40.1-134.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-128"><akn:num>§ 40.1-128</akn:num><akn:heading>40</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>1-128 through 40.1-134. Text Repealed by Acts 1991, c. 152. Annotations Cross references. As to present provision relating to amusement devices which include passenger tramways, see § 36-98.3. Chapter 8. Register of Safety and Health Law Violators. -360§§ 40.1-135 through 40.1-138.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-135"><akn:num>§ 40.1-135</akn:num><akn:heading>40</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>1-135 through 40.1-138. Text Not effective. Annotations Editors note. These sections were enacted by Acts 1991, c. 662, cl. 1, and Acts 1991, c. 662, cl. 2, as amended by Acts 1992, c. 798, cl. 1, provided that the provisions of the 1991 act would not become effective unless reenacted by the 1993 Session of the General Assembly. The 1991 act was not reenacted at the 1993 Session. Chapter 9. Industrial Hygiene and Safety Profession Title Protection Act. -360§ 40.1-139. Definitions. -360§ 40.1-140. Prohibited actions. -360§ 40.1-141. Enforcement. -360§ 40.1-142. Exemptions.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-139"><akn:num>§ 40.1-139</akn:num><akn:heading>Definitions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text As used in this chapter: American Board of Industrial Hygiene or ABIH means a nonprofit corporation established to improve the practice and educational standards of the profession of industrial hygiene by c ertifying individuals who meet its education, experience, examination and maintenance requirements. Associate Safety Professional or ASP means an individual who has been certified by the Board of Certified Safety Professionals as an Associate Safety Professional and whose certificat ion has not lapsed or been revoked. Board of Certified Safety Professionals or BCSP means a nonprofit corporation established to improve the practice and educational standards of the safety profession by certifying individuals who meet its education, experience, examination, and maintenance requirements. Certified Associate Industrial Hygienist or CAIH means an individual who has been certified by the American Board of Industrial Hygiene as a Certified Associate Industrial Hygieni st and whose certification has not lapsed or been revoked. Certified Industrial Hygienist or CIH means an individual who has been certified by the American Board of Industrial Hygiene as a Certified Industrial Hygienist and whose certificat ion has not lapsed or been revoked. Certified Safety Professional or CSP means an individual who has been certified by the Board of Certified Safety Professionals as a Certified Safety Professional and whose certificati on has not lapsed or been revoked. Construction Health and Safety Technologist or CHST means an individual who, by virtue of education, experience and examination, has been certified by the American Board of Industria l Hygiene and the Board of Certified Safety Professionals as a Construction Health and Safety Technologist and whose certification has not lapsed or been revoked. Industrial Hygiene means the science and art devoted to the anticipation, recognition, evaluation, and control of environmental factors and stresses arising in or from the workplace that may cause sickness, impaired health and well-being, or significant discomfort among workers, and that may also affect the workplaces community. Industrial Hygienist in Training or IHIT means an individual certified by the American Board of Industrial Hygiene as an Industrial Hygienist in Training and whose certification has n ot lapsed or been revoked. Occupational Health and Safety Technologist or OHST means an individual certified by the American Board of Industrial Hygiene and the Board of Certified Safety Professionals as an Oc cupational Health and Safety Technologist and whose certification has not lapsed or been revoked. Safety Profession means the science and discipline concerned with the preservation of human and material resources through the systematic application of principles drawn from technological advancements in the fields of education, design, chemistry, the physical and biological sciences, ergonomics, psychology, physiology, and management fo r anticipating, identifying and evaluating potentially hazardous systems, conditions and practices, and for developing, implementing, administering, and advising others on hazard control design, methods, procedures, and programs. History History. 2001, c. 742.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-140"><akn:num>§ 40.1-140</akn:num><akn:heading>Prohibited actions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. No person s hall use in conjunction with his name the letters or words Industrial Hygienist in Training, IHIT, Certified Associate Industrial Hygienist, CAIH, Certified Industrial Hygienist, CIH, or a variation of tho se words, or represent to the public that he is certified as such, unless he possesses the applicable certification issued by the American Board of Industrial Hygiene. B. No person s hall use in conjunction with his name the letters or words Associate Safety Professional, ASP, Certified Safety Professional, CSP, or a variation of those words, or represent to the public that he is certified as such, unl ess he possesses the applicable certification issued by the Board of Certified Safety Professionals. C. No person s hall use in conjunction with his name the letters or words Occupational Health and Safety Technologist, OHST, Construction Health and Safety Technologist, CHST, or variation of those words, or represent to the public that he is certified as such, unless he possesses the applicable certification issued by the American Board of Industrial Hygiene and the Board of Certified Safety Professionals. D. No person s hall represent to the public that he is an Industrial Hygienist in Training, Certified Associate Industrial Hygienist, Certified Industrial Hygienist, Associate Safety Professional, Certified Safety Professional, Construction Health and Safety Technologi st, or Occupational Health and Safety Technologist unless he has been certified as such by the ABIH, BCSP, or both, as applicable, and such certification has not lapsed or been revoked. History History. 2001, c. 742.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-141"><akn:num>§ 40.1-141</akn:num><akn:heading>Enforcement</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Attorney General or any aggrieved person may cause an action to be brought in the circuit court of the city or county in which a violation of this chapter has occur red for the issuance of an injunction to enjoin and restrain the continuance of such violation. If it appears to the satisfaction of the court that the defendant has, in fact, violated this chapter, an injunction may be issued by such court enjoining and restraining any further violation, without requiring proof that any person has, in fact, been injured or damaged thereby. The circuit court having jurisdiction may enjoin such violations, notwithstanding the existence of an adequate remedy at law. History History. 2001, c. 742.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_40.1-142"><akn:num>§ 40.1-142</akn:num><akn:heading>Exemptions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. The provisi ons of this chapter shall not prohibit any person who is not certified as a Certified Associate Industrial Hygienist, Certified Industrial Hygienist, Industrial Hygienist in Training, Certified Safety Professional, Associate Safety Professional, Occupati onal Health and Safety Technologist, or Construction Health and Safety Technologist from performing industrial hygiene and safety functions so long as such person does not represent himself to the public as being a Certified Associate Industrial Hygienis t, Certified Industrial Hygienist, Industrial Hygienist in Training, Certified Safety Professional, Associate Safety Professional, Occupational Health and Safety Technologist, or Construction Health and Safety Technologist. B. Nothing in this chapter shall be construed as authorizing a person certified as a Certified Associate Industrial Hygienist, Certified Industrial Hygienist, Industrial Hygienist in Training, Certified Safety Professional, Associate Safety Professional, Occupational Health and Safety Technologist, or Construction Health and Safety Technologist to engage in the practice of architecture or engineering, nor to restrict or otherwise affect the rights of any person licensed as an architect or professional engineer under Chapter 4 (§ 54.1-400 et seq.) of Title 54.1. C. Nothing in this chapter shall apply to employees of the Department while they are engaged in the business of the Commonwealth; however, this subsection shall not be construed to authorize an employee of the Department to use any of the certifications defined in § 40.1-139 unless such employee has been certified as such by the ABIH, BCSP, or both, as applicable, and such certification has not lapsed or been revoked. D. Nothing in this chapter shall bar an otherwise qualified expert witness from testifying in a court of this Commonwealth. History History. 2001, c. 742.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section></akn:body></akn:act></akn:akomaNtoso>