<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akn:akomaNtoso xmlns:akn="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><akn:act><akn:meta><akn:identification source="#cosilico"><akn:FRBRWork><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-50" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-50" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2023-03-01" name="release" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#virginia-general-assembly" /><akn:FRBRcountry value="us-va" /><akn:FRBRnumber value="title-50" /><akn:FRBRname value="act" /></akn:FRBRWork><akn:FRBRExpression><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-50/eng@2023-03-01" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-50/eng@2023-03-01" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2023-03-01" name="publication" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#lexisnexis" /><akn:FRBRlanguage language="eng" /></akn:FRBRExpression><akn:FRBRManifestation><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-50/eng@2023-03-01/main.xml" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-50/eng@2023-03-01/main.xml" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="conversion" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#cosilico" /></akn:FRBRManifestation></akn:identification><akn:references source="#cosilico"><akn:TLCOrganization eId="virginia-general-assembly" href="/ontology/organization/us-va/general-assembly" showAs="Virginia General Assembly" /><akn:TLCOrganization eId="lexisnexis" href="/ontology/organization/lexisnexis" showAs="LexisNexis" /><akn:TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="/ontology/organization/cosilico" showAs="Cosilico" /></akn:references></akn:meta><akn:preface><akn:docTitle>Title 50. </akn:docTitle></akn:preface><akn:body><akn:section eId="sec_50-1"><akn:num>§ 50-1</akn:num><akn:heading>50-1 through 50-43</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>12. Text Repealed by Acts 1996, c. 292, effective January 1, 2000. Annotations Cross references. As to general partnerships, see now § 50-73.79 et seq. Chapter 2. Limited Partnerships. -360§§ 50-44 through 50-73.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_50-44"><akn:num>§ 50-44</akn:num><akn:heading>50-44 through 50-73</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Repealed by Acts 1985, c. 607. Annotations Cross references. As to limited partnerships, see now § 50-73.1 et seq. Chapter 2.1. Virginia Revised Uniform Limited Partnership Act. -360Article 1. General Provisions. -360Article 2. Formation: Certificate of Limited Partnership. -360Article 3. Limited Partners. -360Article 4. General Partners. -360Article 5. Finance. -360Article 6. Distributions and Withdrawal. -360Article 7. Assignment of Partnership Interests. -360Article 7.1. Merger. -360Article 8. Dissolution. -360Article 9. Foreign Limited Partnerships. -360Article 10. Derivative Actions. -360Article 11. Annual Registration Fees. -360Article 12. Miscellaneous. Article 1. General Provisions. -360§ 50-73.1. Definitions. -360§ 50-73.2. Name. -360§ 50-73.3. Reserved name. -360§ 50-73.4. Principal office, registered office, and registered agent. -360§ 50-73.5. Change of registered office or registered agent. -360§ 50-73.6. Resignation of registered agent. -360§ 50-73.7. Service on limited partnership. -360§ 50-73.8. Records to be kept. -360§ 50-73.9. Nature of business. -360§ 50-73.10. Business transactions of partner with partnership. -360§ 50-73.10:1. Unlawful to transact or offer to transact business as a limited partnership unless authorized; penalty. § 50-73.1. Definitions. Text As used in this chapter, unless the context requires a different meaning: Certificate of limited partnership means the certificate referred to in § 50-73.11, and the certificate as amended or restated. Commission means the State Corporation Commission. Contribution means any cash, property, services rendered, or a promissory note or othe r binding obligation to contribute cash or property or to perform services, which a partner contributes to a limited partnership in his capacity as a partner. Domestic, with respect to an entity, means an entity governed as to its internal affai rs by the organic law of the Commonwealth. Domestic business trust has the same meaning as specified in § 13.1-1201. Domestic corporation has the same meaning as specified in § 13.1-603. Domestic limited liability company has the same meaning as specified in § 13.1-1002 . Domestic nonstock corporation has the same meaning as domestic corporation as specified in § 13.1-803. Domestic partnership means an association of two or more persons to carry on as co-own ers a business for profit formed under § 50-73.88, or predecessor law of the Commonwealth, and includes, for all purposes of the laws of the Commonwealth, a registered limited liability partnership. Effective date, when referring to a document for which effectiveness is contingent upo n the filing with or issuance of a certificate by the Commission, means the time and date determined in accordance with subsection C of § 50-73.17. Entity includes any domestic or foreign limited partnership or other business entity, any estate or trust, and any state, the United States, and any foreign government. Event of withdrawal of a general partner means an event that causes a person to cease to be a general partner as provided in § 50-73.28. Foreign, with respect to an entity, means an entity governed as to its internal affair s by the organic law of a jurisdiction other than the Commonwealth. Foreign business trust has the same meaning as specified in § 13.1-1201. Foreign corporation has the same meaning as specified in § 13.1-603. Foreign limited liability company has the same meaning as specified in § 13.1-1002. Foreign limited partnership means a partnership formed under the laws of any state or jurisdiction other than the Commonwealth and having as partners one or more general partners and one or more limited partners. Foreign partnership means an association of two or more persons to carry on as co-owne rs of a business for profit formed under the laws of any state or jurisdiction other than the Commonwealth, and includes, for all purposes of the laws of the Commonwealth, a foreign registered limited liability partnership. Foreign registered limited liability partnership has the same meaning as specified in § 50-73.79. General partner means a person who has been admitted to a limited partnership as a gen eral partner in accordance with the partnership agreement and named in the certificate of limited partnership as a general partner. Jurisdiction of formation means the state or country the law of which includes the org anic law governing a domestic or foreign limited partnership or other business entity. Limited partner means a person who has been admitted to a limited partnership as a lim ited partner in accordance with the partnership agreement. Limited partnership and domestic limited partnership mean a partnership formed by two or more persons under the laws of the Commonwealth and having one or more general partners and on e or more limited partners. Liquidating trustee means a person, other than a general partner, but including a limi ted partner, who carries out the winding up of a limited partnership as provided in this chapter. Organic law means the statute governing the internal affairs of a domestic or foreign limited partnership or eligible entity. Other business entity means a domestic or foreign stock corporation, nonstock corporat ion, business trust, limited liability company, or partnership. Partner means a limited or general partner. Partnership agreement means any valid agreement, written or oral, of the partners as t o the affairs of a limited partnership and the conduct of its business. Partnership interest means a partners share of the profits and losses of a limited partnership and the right to receive distributions of partnership assets. Person means an individual, partnership, limited partnership (domestic or foreign), tr ust, estate, association, corporation, or any other legal or commercial entity. Principal office means the office, in or out of the Commonwealth, where the principal executive offices of a domestic or foreign limited partnership are located. Any reference to a specified office contained in the records of the Commission as of July 1, 2010, shall be deemed, in all instances, to be a reference to the principal office of a domestic or foreign limited partnership. Protected series has the same meaning as specified in § 13.1-1002. Registered limited liability partnership means a limited partnership or general partne rship formed under the laws of the Commonwealth that is registered under § 50-73.132. State means a state, territory, or possession of the United States, the District of Co lumbia, or the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico. History History. 1985, c. 607; 1987, c. 702; 1990, c. 343; 1992, c. 575; 1997, c. 190; 2003, c. 340; 2007, c. 631; 2010, c. 675; 2021, Sp. Sess. I, c. 487. Annotations Uniform law cross references. For other signatory state provisions of the Uniform Limited Partnership Act (2001 or earlier version), see: Alaska: Alaska Stat. § 32.11.010 et seq. Arizona: A.R.S. § 29-301 et seq. Arkansas: A.C.A. § 4-47-101 et seq. California: Cal Corp. Code § 15900 et seq. Colorado: C.R.S. 7-62-101 et seq. Connecticut: Conn. Gen. Stat. § 34-9 et seq. Delaware: 6 Del. C. § 17-101 et seq. Florida: Fla. Stat. § 620.1101 et seq. Georgia: O.C.G.A. § 14-9-100 et seq. Hawaii: HRS § 425E-101 et seq. Illinois: 805 ILCS 215/0.01 et seq. Indiana: Burns Ind. Code Ann. § 23-16-1-1. Iowa: Iowa Code § 488.101 et seq. Kansas: K.S.A. § 56-1a01 et seq. Kentucky: KRS § 362.2-102 et seq. Maine: 31 M.R.S. § 1301 et seq. Maryland: Md. Corporations and Associations Code Ann. § 10-101 et seq. Massachusetts: ALM GL ch. 109, § 1 et seq. Michigan: MCLS § 449.1101 et seq. Minnesota: Minn. Stat. § 321.0101 et seq. Mississippi: Miss. Code Ann. § 79-14-101 et seq. Missouri: § 359.011 R.S.Mo. et seq. Montana: Mont. Code Anno., § 35-12-501 et seq. Nebraska: R.R.S. Neb. § 67-233 et seq. Nevada: NRS § 87A.005 et seq. New Hampshire: RSA 304-B:1 et seq. New Jersey: N.J. Stat. § 42:2A-1 et seq. New Mexico: N.M. Stat. Ann. § 54-2A-101 et seq. New York: NY CLS Partn. § 120.101 et seq. North Carolina: N.C. Gen. Stat. § 59-101 et seq. North Dakota: N.D. Cent. Code, § 45-10.2-01 et seq. Ohio: ORC Ann. § 1776.01 et seq. Oklahoma: 54 Okl. St. § 500-101A et seq. Oregon: ORS § 70.005 et seq. Pennsylvania: 15 Pa. C. S. § 8611 et seq. Rhode Island: R.I. Gen. Laws § 7-13-1 et seq. South Carolina: S.C. Code Ann. § 33-42-10 et seq. South Dakota: S.D. Codified Laws § 48-7-101 et seq. Tennessee: Tenn. Code Ann. § 61-2-101 et seq. Texas: Tex. Business Organizations Code § 153.001 et seq. Utah: Utah Code Ann. § 48-2e-101 et seq. Vermont: 11 V.S.A. § 3401 et seq. Virgin Islands: 26 V.I.C. § 321 et seq. Washington: Rev. Code Wash. § 25.10.006 et seq. West Virginia: W. Va. Code § 47-9-1 et seq. Wisconsin: Wis. Stat. § 179.01 et seq. Wyoming: Wyo. Stat. § 17-14-201 et seq. Editors note. Acts 2003, c. 340, cl. 2, provides: That the provisions of this act that amend and reenact §§ 8.9A-406, 8.9A-408, 13.1-1001.1, 13.1-1003, 13.1-1012, 50- 73.2, 50-73.84, and 50-73.144 of the Code of Virginia and that amend the Code of Virginia by adding sections numbered 13.1-1010.4 and 13.1-1023.1 shall become effective on July 1, 2003, and that all other provisions of this act shall become effective on October 1, 2003. Acts 2021, Sp. Sess. I, c. 487, cl. 4 provides: That the provisions of this act (i) shall be applied prospectively only; (ii) shall not affect the validity of any filing made, or other action taken, prior to July 1, 2021, with respect to the name of a stock corporation, nonstock corporation, limited liability company, business trust, or limited partnership; and (iii) shall not be construed to require any such stock corporation, nonstock corporation, limited liability company, business trust, or limited partnership that was in compliance with applicable laws regarding the distinguishability of its name prior to July 1, 2021, to change its name or take...</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_50-74"><akn:num>§ 50-74</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1996, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>292, effective July 1, 1997.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_50-75"><akn:num>§ 50-75</akn:num><akn:heading>50-75 through 50-78</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Repealed by Acts 1997, c. 188.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section></akn:body></akn:act></akn:akomaNtoso>