<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akn:akomaNtoso xmlns:akn="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><akn:act><akn:meta><akn:identification source="#cosilico"><akn:FRBRWork><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-11" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-11" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2023-03-01" name="release" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#virginia-general-assembly" /><akn:FRBRcountry value="us-va" /><akn:FRBRnumber value="title-11" /><akn:FRBRname value="act" /></akn:FRBRWork><akn:FRBRExpression><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-11/eng@2023-03-01" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-11/eng@2023-03-01" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2023-03-01" name="publication" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#lexisnexis" /><akn:FRBRlanguage language="eng" /></akn:FRBRExpression><akn:FRBRManifestation><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-11/eng@2023-03-01/main.xml" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-11/eng@2023-03-01/main.xml" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="conversion" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#cosilico" /></akn:FRBRManifestation></akn:identification><akn:references source="#cosilico"><akn:TLCOrganization eId="virginia-general-assembly" href="/ontology/organization/us-va/general-assembly" showAs="Virginia General Assembly" /><akn:TLCOrganization eId="lexisnexis" href="/ontology/organization/lexisnexis" showAs="LexisNexis" /><akn:TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="/ontology/organization/cosilico" showAs="Cosilico" /></akn:references></akn:meta><akn:preface><akn:docTitle>Title 11. </akn:docTitle></akn:preface><akn:body><akn:section eId="sec_11-1"><akn:num>§ 11-1</akn:num><akn:heading>Certain contracts void as to creditors and purchasers unless in writing; law governing validity of contracts creating security interests</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Every contract, not in writing, made in respect to real estate or goods and chattels in consideration of marriage, or made for the conveyance or sale of real estate, or a term therein of more than five years, and, except as otherwise provided in § 8.2-402 of the Uniform Commercial Code, every bill of sale or contract for the sale of goods and chattels when the possession is allowed to remain with the seller, shall b e void, both at law and in equity, as to purchasers for value and without notice and creditors; provided, however, that if any such contract or bill of sale as is mentioned in this section creates a security interest as defined in the Uniform Commercial Code, its validity and enforceability shall be governed by the provisions of that Code. History History. Code 1919, § 5192; 1964, c. 314; 1966, c. 397. Annotations Cross references. As to when deed or will necessary to convey estate in lands, and invalidity of parol partition or gift of land, see § 55.1-101. As to recordation of written contracts or bills of sale mentioned in this section, see §§ 55.1-406 through 55.1-408. Law Review. For survey of the Virginia law on contracts and sales for the year 1961-1962, see 48 Va. L. Rev. 1333 (1962). For note on the developing law in Virginia on installment land contracts, see 37 Wash. &amp; Lee L. Rev. 1161 (1980). Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 2A M.J. Attachment and Garnishment, § 73; 8B M.J. Frauds, Statute of, § 2; 11A M.J. Judgments and Decrees, § 68; 15 M.J. Recording Acts, § 4; 19 M.J. Trusts and Trustees, § 46. Research References. Friends Virginia Pleading and Practice (Matthew Bender). Chapter 24 Contract Actions. § 24.11 Oral and Written Contracts and the Statute of Frauds. Friend. Virginia Forms (Matthew Bender). Chapter XIII Contracts. No. 13-101. Assignment of Debt by Creditor, et seq. CASE NOTES Applicability.  Transfer of property to a debtors spouse pursuant to the terms of a marital agreement was deemed not to have occurred until the marital agreement was perfecte d by recording, pursuant to § 11-1 and § 55-96. Prunty v. Terry, 408 Bankr. 79, 2009 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 45623 (E.D. Va. 2009), aff'd, 388 Fed. Appx. 299, 2010 U.S. App. LEXIS 14613 (4th Cir. 2010). The manifest purpose of this section and §§ 55-95 and 55-96 is to protect creditor s against debtors who give a deceptive appearance of ownership by retaining possession after title has passed to a stranger to the creditor-debtor relationship. Graves Constr. Co. v. Rockingham Nat'l Bank, 220 Va. 844, 263 S.E.2d 408, 1980 Va. LEXIS 175 (1980). The history and purpose of this section is given in Straley v. Esser, 117 Va. 135, 83 S. E. 1075 (1915). Its purpose was to change the law as declared in Floyd v. Harding, 69 Va. (28 Gratt.) 401 (1877), and subsequent cases following the doctrine that a purchaser under a parol contract who had paid the purchase money and had been put in poss ession of the land had a valid equitable title not subject to the lien of a subsequent judgment creditor of the vendor. See Barnes v. American Fertilizer Co., 144 Va. 692, 130 S.E. 902, 1925 Va. LEXIS 228 (1925). One of the objects of § 2463 of the Code of 1887 (similar to this section) was to place a purchaser of land under a parol contract, as to purchasers for valuab le consideration without notice and creditors, in the same condition as purchasers under a writing who had failed to record it as provided by §§ 55-95 and 55-96. Norfolk &amp; Portsmouth Traction Co. v. C.B. White &amp; Bros., 113 Va. 102, 73 S.E. 467, 191 2 Va. LEXIS 14 (1912). This section is not directly related to § 17 of the English Statute of Frauds, but was enacted in 1887 to rectify an odd development in Virginias recording laws which had put a purchaser of land under an unrecorded oral contract in a stronger position than a purchaser of land under an unrecorded written contract. Stein v. Pulaski Furn. Corp., 217 F. Supp. 587, 1963 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 7604 (W.D. Va. 1963). The anomalous condition of the law, by which a parol agreement for a lien took precedence of subsequent judgment liens, while a written unrecorded mortgage did no t, was remedied by § 2463 of the Code of 1887. Page v. Old Dominion Trust Co., 257 F. 402, 1919 U.S. App. LEXIS 2216 (4th Cir. 1919). Oral agreement for sale of real estate .  Where debtors in a Chapter 7 bankruptcy purportedly sold property to a purchaser prior to the bankruptcy filing pursuant to an oral agreement, although the debtor s and the purchaser produced several documents to support the existence of their contract, the parties never recorded their transaction for the property, and the bankruptcy court determined that the oral, unrecorded contract was invalid; thus, pursuant t o 11 U.S.C.S. § 544(a)(3) the Trustee took legal title to the property, but the purchaser had an equitable interest in the property in the form of a constructive trust in the amount of $31,600.00  the amount the purchaser had paid towards the sale s price. Lubman v. Wells, 296 Bankr. 728, 2003 Bankr. LEXIS 884 (Bankr. E.D. Va. 2003). In a suit between individuals to set aside as a fraudulent conveyance a deed of trust regarding certain real property, where an intervenor bank did not have a cla im to this property by an equitable lien from its possession and a certain contract regarding the property, even if the bank had an equitable interest in the property, its interest was junior to that of the parties because it failed to comply with state recording statutes, and under § 11-1, a contract for the conveyance of real estate had to be in writing, and under § 55-96, a contract conveying property was void as to all bona fide purchasers or creditors without notice of it until it was recorde d. Hung-Lin Wu v. Tseng, 459 F. Supp. 2d 468, 2006 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 75608 (E.D. Va. 2006). A parol contract for the purchase of a right of way for a street railway over a strip of land is a contract made in respect to real estate within the meaning of this section. Norfolk &amp; Portsmouth Traction Co. v. C.B. White &amp; Bros., 113 Va. 102, 73 S.E. 467, 1912 Va. LEXIS 14 (1912). Lease for two years with privilege of four successive renewals.  A contract which provides for an actual demise of real estate for two years and one month, with the privilege to the lessee at his option of four successive renew als, each for a period of one year, is a contract for a term of more than five years in real estate within the meaning of this section, and as against a subsequent purchaser for value and without notice must, under § 55-96, be recorded. Great Atl. &amp; P ac. Tea Co. v. Cofer, 129 Va. 640, 106 S.E. 695, 1921 Va. LEXIS 123 (1921). This section h as no application to resulting trusts.  Where one holds a legal title to real estate which is impressed in his hands with a resulting trust, such trust may be enforced and is good against his judgment c reditors. A different rule prevails where it is sought to set up by parol a resulting trust against subsequent purchasers for value and without notice. Savings &amp; Loan Corp. v. Bear, 155 Va. 312, 154 S.E. 587, 1930 Va. LEXIS 166 (1930) (citing Ransome v. Watson, 145 Va. 669, 134 S.E. 707 (1926)). This section has no application to resulting trusts arising from the payment of the purchase money by one party while the conveyance is to another, and a judgment against the trustee does not bind the beneficial interest. Straley v. Esser, 117 Va. 135, 83 S.E. 1075, 1915 Va. LEXIS 17 (1915). This section has no application to resulting trusts. In re Smith, 348 F. Supp. 1290, 1972 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 11686 (E.D. Va. 1972). Where one holds the legal title to real estate which is impressed in his hands with a resulting trust, such trust may be enforced and is good against his judgment creditors. In re Smith, 348 F. Supp. 1290, 1972 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 11686 (E.D. Va. 1972). Nor to contracts embodied in decrees.  The provision of this section that contracts not in writing, for the conveyance or sale of real estate, shall be void as to purchasers for value, does not apply t o contracts embodied in valid decrees entered by courts of equity. Barnes v. American Fertilizer Co., 144 Va. 692, 130 S.E. 902, 1925 Va. LEXIS 228 (1925). This section does not extend to an agreement for transfer of husbands real estate to wife in settlement of alimony and property rights where such agreement wa s approved by the court and embodied in its decree. Barnes v. American Fertilizer Co., 144 Va. 692, 130 S.E. 902, 1925 Va. LEXIS 228 (1925). An agreement which is the basis of a constructive trust may be proven by parol evidence and does not violate the statute of frauds. Leonard v. Counts, 221 Va. 582, 272 S.E.2d 190, 1980 Va. LEXIS 278 (1980). Access to inventory not deceptive possession.  When a creditor knows that his debtor is engaged in the construction of a building and is also selling inventory stored on the job site to the owner of the buildi ng, the debtors mere access to the inventory does not constitute the deceptive possession this section addresses. Graves Constr. Co. v. Rockingham Nat'l Bank, 220 Va. 844, 263 S.E.2d 408, 1980 Va. LEXIS 175 (1980). CIRCUIT COURT OPINIONS Agency established.  Arbitration provision was enforceable under § 8.01-581.01, because a valid written power of attorney delivered to the residential home at the time of the execu tion of the agreement was proof of agency of the executor to sign on behalf of the decedent; the agreements failure to nominate arbitrators did not invalidate the agreement. Fink v. Colonial Home, LLC, 81 Va. Cir. 207, 2010 Va. Cir. LEXIS 124 (Portsm outh Sept. 16, 2010). Demurrer granted.  Defendants demurrer was granted to plaintiffs breach of contract claim because the rules and regulations handbook of a condominium unit owners associa tion was not a contract between any of the parties since plaintiff did not plead facts to show the elements of contract formation; even if the handbook was a contract, there was no evi...</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_11-2"><akn:num>§ 11-2</akn:num><akn:heading>When written evidence required to maintain action</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Unless a promise, contract, agreement, representation, assurance, or ratification, or some memorandum or note thereof, is in writing and signed by the party to be charg ed or his agent, no action shall be brought in any of the following cases: 1. To ch arge any person upon or by reason of a representation or assurance concerning the character, conduct, credit, ability, trade, or dealings of another, to the intent or purpose that such other may obtain thereby, credit, money, or goods; 2. To charge any person upon a promise made after attaining the age of majority, to pay a debt contracted during infancy, or upon a ratification after attaining the age of majority, of a promise or simple contract made during infancy; 3. To charge a personal representative upon a promise to answer any debt or damages out of his own estate; 4. To charge any person upon a promise to answer for the debt, default, or misdoings of another; 5. Upon any agreement made upon consideration of marriage; 6. Upon any contract for the sale of real estate, or for the lease thereof for more than a year; 7. Upon any agreement or contract for services to be performed in the sale of real estate by a party defined in § 54.1-2100 or § 54.1-2101; 8. Upon any agreement that is not to be performed within a year; or 9. Upon any agreement or promise to lend money or extend credit in an aggregate amount of $25,000 or more. The consideration need not be set forth or expressed in the writing, and it may be proved (where a consideration is necessary) by other evidence. History History. Code 1919, § 5561; 1976, c. 157; 1990, c. 570. Annotations Law Review. For note on crops as personalty or realty relative to the statute of frauds, see 39 Va. L. Rev. 1116 (1953). For discussion of this section, see 45 Va. L. Rev. 1423 (1959). For article on the care of the aged and the Virginia statute of frauds, see 19 Wash. &amp; Lee L. Rev. 23 (1962). For survey of Virginia law on property for the year 1974-1975, see 61 Va. L. Rev. 1834 (1975). For survey of Virginia law on domestic relations for the year 1975-1976, see 62 Va. L. Rev. 1431 (1976). For survey of Virginia property law for the year 1975-1976, see 62 Va. L. Rev. 1469 (1976). For survey of Virginia law on wills, trusts, and estates for year 1979-80, see 67 Va. L. Rev. 369 (1981). For survey on employment law in Virginia for 1989, see 23 U. Rich. L. Rev. 607 (1989). For survey on property law in Virginia for 1989, see 23 U. Rich. L. Rev. 773 (1989). For article, Reconsidering Inducement, see 76 Va. L. Rev. 877 (1990). For article, Civil Practice and Procedure, see 45 U. Rich. L. Rev. 183 (2010). For note, Applying Equitable Estoppel to ERISA Pension Benefit Claims, see 54 Wm. &amp; Mary L. Rev. 627 (2013). Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 3A M.J. Brokers, § 6; 3C M.J. Commercial Law, § 3; 5C M.J. Deeds, §§ 5, 9; 8B M.J. Frauds, Statute of, §§ 2, 3, 5, 11, 15, 18-20; 9B M.J. Infants and Juveniles, § 10; 11B M.J. Landlord and Tenant, § 8; 13A M.J. Mines and Minerals, § 15; 19 M.J. Trusts and Trustees, § 5. CASE NOTES Analysis I. In General. II. Ratification of Infants Promise. III. Promises by Personal Representatives. IV. Promise to Answer for Debt, Etc., of Another. A. In General. B. Consideration. C. Original and Collateral Undertakings. 1. In General. 2. Undertakings Within the Statute. 3. Undertakings Not Within the Statute. V. Agreements Upon Consideration of Marriage. VI. Contracts Relating to Land. A. In General. B. Nature of Property. C. Nature of Contract. D. Partnerships and Joint Ventures. VII. Agreements Not to Be Performed Within Year. VIII. The Writing. A. In General. B. Effect of Agency. C. Particular Writings. IX. Operation and Effect of Statute. A. In General. B. Part Performance. C. Parol Trusts. X. Defense and Procedure. I.In General. The statute of frauds set out in this section is a wise and salutary law, and should be fairly and fully carried into execution by the courts. Cutler v. Hinton, 27 Va. (6 Rand.) 509, 1828 Va. LEXIS 29 (1828) (see Wright v. Pucket, 63 Va. (22 Gratt.) 370 (1872); Plunkett v. Bryant, 101 Va. 814, 45 S.E. 742 (1903)). Its object is to prevent frauds and perjuries, and not to perpetrate them, and the statu te is never enforced when by the effect of it a fraud and a wrong would be perpetrated. Wheat v. Wheat, 3 Va. L. Reg. (n.s.) 177, affd by divided court, 119 Va. 861, 91 S.E. 827 (1916); T. v. T., 216 Va. 867, 224 S.E.2d 148, 1976 Va. LEXIS 217 (1976 ). It was not intended that the statute should perpetrate frauds. Its primary object is to prevent the setting up of pretended agreements and then supporting them by perjury. Wright v. Pucket, 63 Va. (22 Gratt.) 370, 1872 Va. LEXIS 26 (1872); Plunkett v. Bryant, 101 Va. 814, 45 S.E. 742, 1903 Va. LEXIS 92 (1903); Reynolds v. Dixon, 187 Va. 101, 46 S.E.2d 6, 1948 Va. LEXIS 203 (1948). The statute will not be applied when the result is to cause a fraud or perpetrate a wrong, because the object of the statute is to prevent frauds. Murphy v. Nolte &amp; Co., 226 Va. 76, 307 S.E.2d 242, 1983 Va. LEXIS 270 (1983). And it manifests the policy of requiring certain contracts to be in writing.  The statute manifests the policy of requiring contracts of an important nature, such as the sale and purchase of real estate, to be reduced to writing, since othe rwise, from the imperfection of memory and the honest mistakes of witnesses, it often happens either that the specific contract is incapable of exact proof or that it is unintentionally varied from its original terms. Wright v. Pucket, 63 Va. (22 Gratt.) 370, 1872 Va. LEXIS 26 (1872); Plunkett v. Bryant, 101 Va. 814, 45 S.E. 742, 1903 Va. LEXIS 92 (1903); Reynolds v. Dixon, 187 Va. 101, 46 S.E.2d 6, 1948 Va. LEXIS 203 (1948). The purposes of this section are to provide reliable evidence of the existence and terms of certain types of contracts and to reduce the likelihood that contracts within the scope of this statute can be created or altered by acts of perjury or fraud. Lindsay v. McEnearney Assocs., 260 Va. 48, 531 S.E.2d 573, 2000 Va. LEXIS 94 (2000). Modification must also be in writing.  When a contract is required to be in writing pursuant to this section, any modification of that contract must also be in writing and signed by the party to be cha rged or his agent. Lindsay v. McEnearney Assocs., 260 Va. 48, 531 S.E.2d 573, 2000 Va. LEXIS 94 (2000). This section deals only with the legal enforceability and not with the substantive validity of oral agreements which fall within its scope. Stein v. Pulaski Furn. Corp., 217 F. Supp. 587, 1963 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 7604 (W.D. Va. 1963). This section is not concerned with the validity of the contract but merely with its enforceability. Brown v. Valentine, 240 F. Supp. 539, 1965 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 69 79 (W.D. Va. 1965). The statute is procedural or remedial in nature, and is concerned not with the validity of the contract, but with its enforceability. T. v. T., 216 Va. 867, 224 S .E.2d 148, 1976 Va. LEXIS 217 (1976); Murphy v. Nolte &amp; Co., 226 Va. 76, 307 S.E.2d 242, 1983 Va. LEXIS 270 (1983). The statute of frauds is concerned with the enforceability of contracts, not their validity. Because its object is to prevent fraud, it will not be applied when t o do so would result in a fraud or perpetrate a wrong. Troyer v. Troyer, 231 Va. 90, 341 S.E.2d 182, 1986 Va. LEXIS 168 (1986). Under the parol evidence rule, the merger clause in guaranty agreements with the creditor bank precluded the introduction into evidence of alleged oral agreements between the creditor and the guarantors that would change the nature of the contract between the parties to advance funds and release certain property of the debtor. The statute of frauds was not applicable. Wachovia Bank, N.A. v. Dresdner (In re Brookl and Park Plaza, LLC), No. 09-34495-KRH, No. 09-03164, 2009 Bankr. LEXIS 3241 (Bankr. E.D. Va. Oct. 13, 2009). There is no prohibition in this section on the ability of third-party beneficiaries to sue upon oral contracts generally. To so hold would be to judicially amend the statute of frauds, an action the Supreme Court of Virginia declines to take. Thorsen v. Richmond SPCA, 292 Va. 257, 786 S.E.2d 453, 2016 Va. LEXIS 68 (2016) (but see § 64.2-520.1 and notes thereunder). And will n ot be applied to perpetrate a wrong.  The statute of frauds is concerned with the enforceability of contracts, not their validity. Because its object is to prevent fraud, it will not be applied when t o do so would result in a fraud or perpetrate a wrong. Troyer v. Troyer, 231 Va. 90, 341 S.E.2d 182, 1986 Va. LEXIS 168 (1986). It is procedural , or remedial, in nature.  This section is procedural, or remedial, in nature and accordingly no action may be brought in this State on an oral contract of employment not to be performed wi thin a year, regardless of its validity and enforceability in the jurisdiction where it was made. Stein v. Pulaski Furn. Corp., 217 F. Supp. 587, 1963 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 7604 (W.D. Va. 1963). The effect of this section is only procedural. Hewitt v. Hutter, 574 F.2d 182, 1978 U.S. App. LEXIS 12858 (4th Cir. 1978). Equitable estoppel will thwart the pleading of the statute of frauds in Virginia even wi thout the showing of fraud or deceit. Nargi v. Camac Corp., 820 F. Supp. 253, 1992 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 21322 (W.D. Va. 1992). To escape statute of frauds.  The controlling principles are well settled. To escape the statute of frauds, the oral agreement must be definite, certain, and unequivocal in all its terms. Cert ainty means that each term is expressed in an exact manner; by contrast, uncertainty means that terms are expressed inexactly, indefinitely, and obscurely so that the intent is not ascertainable. Further, the acts the plaintiff relied on to establish par t performance must be consistent with no theory other than the existence of an oral contract. Finally, the agreement must be so far executed that a refusal to require full ...</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_11-3"><akn:num>§ 11-3</akn:num><akn:heading>Sealed writings; writings not purporting to be sealed</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Any writing to which a natural person, corporation, limited liability company or partnership, whether general or limited, making it affixes a scroll by way of a seal, s hall be of the same force as if it were actually sealed. The impression or stamping of a corporate or an official seal on paper or parchment alone shall be as valid as if made on wax or other adhesive substance. And any writing to which a natural person, corporation, limited liability company or partnership, whether general or limited, making it affixes his signature, or their signatures, and which writing in its body says this deed, or this indenture, or other words importing a sealed i nstrument, or recognizes a seal, shall be of the same force as if it were actually sealed by such person, corporation, limited liability company or partnership, although no seal or scroll be attached; and any writing signed by a natural person, corporati on, limited liability company or partnership, whether general or limited, and regularly acknowledged before an officer authorized to take acknowledgments of deeds to be recorded in this Commonwealth, in the body of which writing it clearly appears that t he person so signing and acknowledging the same intends to and does grant or convey unto the grantee named therein certain real estate as therein described, and in which the writing is not said to be a deed or an indenture, and does not purport to be sea led, and to which no seal or scroll is attached, such writing shall pass the title to such real estate as effectually as if it were written and executed in strict accordance with the provisions of § 55.1-300; and any such writing admitted to record pr ior to June 19, 1946, shall be of the effect as if made and recorded thereafter, except as to vested rights already attached contrary to such writing. History History. Code 1919, § 5562; 1934, p. 524; 1946, pp. 59, 426; 1975, c. 5 00; 1996, c. 265. Annotations Cross references. As to definition of Seal, see § 1-241. Editors note. To conform to the recodification of Title 55 by Acts 2019, c. 712, effective October 1, 2019, the following substitution was made at the direction of the Virginia Code Commission: substituted 55.1-300 for 55-48. Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 1A M.J. Agency, §§ 13, 46, 76; 5C M.J. Deeds, § 29; 13A M.J. Mortgages and Deeds of Trust, § 27; 16 M.J. Seals and Sealed Instruments, § 1. CASE NOTES The law as to seals with respect to natural persons has been relaxed, etc. The law as to seals with respect to natural persons has been relaxed by this section. Co vington Virginian, Inc. v. Woods, 182 Va. 538, 29 S.E.2d 406, 1944 Va. LEXIS 202 (1944). The rule at common law has been changed by this section. Any writing to which a natural person making it shall affix a scroll by way of seal shall be of the same force as if actually sealed. Smith v. Plaster, 151 Va. 252, 144 S.E. 417, 1928 Va. LEXIS 229 (1928). Since the foregoing decisions, the 1946 amendment of this section has made applicable to partnerships the provisions formerly applying only to natural persons. General Assembly has engaged the common-law seal requirement but has never abolished it altogether for deeds governed by the Statute of Conveyances. Game Place, L .L.C. v. Fredericksburg 35, LLC, 295 Va. 396, 813 S.E.2d 312, 2018 Va. LEXIS 54 (2018). Statute does not abolish the seal requirement, but instead, it relaxes the seal requirement by offering a limited list of specific substitutes for a seal; the sta tute does not identify when a seal is necessary but instead only addresses ways to make a written instrument compliant with the seal requirement if either the common law or a statute require a seal. Game Place, L.L.C. v. Fredericksburg 35, LLC, 295 Va. 3 96, 813 S.E.2d 312, 2018 Va. LEXIS 54 (2018). But it was not relaxed as to corporations prior to 1975 amendment.  See Merchant Bank v. Goodin, 76 Va. 503, 1882 Va. LEXIS 55 (1882); Covington Virginian, Inc. v. Woods, 182 Va. 538, 29 S.E.2d 406, 1944 Va. LEXIS 202 (1944). The distinction between sealed and unsealed instruments has not been changed by this sec tion. Covington Virginian, Inc. v. Woods, 182 Va. 538, 29 S.E.2d 406, 1944 Va. LEXIS 202 (1944). (But since the foregoing decision, the 1946 amendment of this section has provided that unsealed writings which purport to convey real estate, and which are signed and acknowledged by natural persons or partnerships, shall pass the title to real estate as effectually as if they had been regularly executed sealed instruments.). There is no distinction between actual seals and scrolls, so far as constituting a writi ng a specialty, and either may be affixed to the signature. Bradley Salt Co. v. Norfolk Importing &amp; Exporting Co., 95 Va. 461, 28 S.E. 567, 1897 Va. LEXIS 57 (1897). Scrolls were in common use long before the statute of 1788 (now found in this section) w as enacted, and affixing a scroll to a writing for the purpose of making it a specialty was considered, as was said in Jones v. Logwood, 1 Va. (1 Wash.) 42 (1791), to be an act as solemn and as valid as making an impression upon wax for that purpose and as a good substitute for a seal. Bradley Salt Co. v. Norfolk Importing &amp; Exporting Co., 95 Va. 461, 28 S.E. 567, 1897 Va. LEXIS 57 (1897). Valid scrolls.  A paper which had the word seal affixed to the signature of the maker, and which met then existing common-law requirements, was held to be a sealed instru ment within the meaning of the statute. Lewis v. Overby, 69 Va. (28 Gratt.) 627, 1877 Va. LEXIS 88 (1877). Where a printed form of bond was executed by the obligors signing their names to the printed stamps or scrolls thereon, which were recognized as their seals in th e body of the bond, this was a sealed instrument within the statute. Buckner v. Mackay, 29 Va. (2 Leigh) 488, 1831 Va. LEXIS 3 (1831). Proof of scroll used as seal.  A typewritten copy of a deed showing the signature of the grantor, followed by parenthesis marks inclosing a blank space, is prima facie evidence that the origina l instrument had a scroll used by way of seal. Virginia &amp; W. Va. Coal Co. v. Charles, 251 F. 83, 1917 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 780 (D. Va. 1917), aff'd, 254 F. 379, 1918 U.S. App. LEXIS 1313 (4th Cir. 1918). Where it is stated at the foot of an instrument that it was signed, sealed and acknowledged in the presence of two attesting witnesses, and the instrument is afte rwards duly proved by the witnesses in court, it sufficiently appears that the person making the instrument affixed the scroll by way of seal. Parks v. Hewlett, 36 Va. (9 Leigh) 511, 1838 Va. LEXIS 39 (1838). Proof that s croll affixed without knowledge of maker.  Parol evidence is admissible to show that, after an unsealed paper had been executed, delivered and recorded, a scroll by way of seal was affixed to the name of t he maker, both on the original paper, and on the record, without the knowledge or consent of the maker. Burnette v. Young, 107 Va. 184, 57 S.E. 641, 1907 Va. LEXIS 24 (1907). Effect of extra seal.  The validity of a trust deed is not affected by having on it an extra seal. Ward v. Churn, 59 Va. (18 Gratt.) 801, 1868 Va. LEXIS 36 (1868); Miller v. Fletcher, 6 8 Va. (27 Gratt.) 403, 1876 Va. LEXIS 35 (1876); Kyger v. Sipe, 89 Va. 507, 16 S.E. 627, 1892 Va. LEXIS 127 (1892). Compliance.  By statute, the words this deed or this indenture must appear in the body of the instrument, not merely the title; the relative ease with which a party can comply with a statute is hardly a basis for excusing him or her when he or she does not even comply with the minimal requirements imposed on him or her, and if anything, the opposite is true. Game Place, L.L.C. v. Fredericksburg 35, LLC, 295 Va . 396, 813 S.E.2d 312, 2018 Va. LEXIS 54 (2018). Whether a paper declared on as a simple contract is sealed cannot be raised by demurrer, but is a matter of fact to be presented at the hearing by proper plea or motion. It cannot be raised by craving oyer and demurring. Grubbs v. National Life Maturity Ins. Co., 94 Va. 589, 27 S.E. 464, 1897 Va. LEXIS 112 (1897). Corporate seal is prima facie proof of corporate act.  The presence of corporate seal establishes, prima facie, that the instrument to which it is affixed is the act of the corporation, and dispenses with the necessit y of any proof, on the part of the person claiming under it, that it was executed by the proper officers, that they had authority to so execute it, and that all proceedings, of whatever character, necessary to such authority, had been duly given, unless the corporation shall first by competent evidence on its part have rebutted the presumption arising from the presence of the common seal. Pascoe Steel Corp. v. Shannon, 224 Va. 530, 298 S.E.2d 97, 1982 Va. LEXIS 325 (1982). The word Corp. typed above the printed word (SEAL) is evidence of the in tent of the parties to the instrument that it was to be evidence of a corporate debt. Pascoe Steel Corp. v. Shannon, 224 Va. 530, 298 S.E.2d 97, 1982 Va. LEXIS 325 (1982). Validity of unsealed note executed by corporation prior to 1970.  A note executed in 1970 by a corporation, but without the corporations seal affixed thereon was a valid obligation of the corporation, and the chancellors reliance on Covington Virginian, Inc. v. Woods, 182 Va. 538, 29 S.E.2d 406 (1944), in erroneously holding that the note was invalid because the raised seal was not affixed was misplaced, since that case does not stand for the proposition that at the tim e this note was made all instruments executed by a corporation had to be sealed to be valid. White House Motel Corp. v. Bias, 219 Va. 19, 245 S.E.2d 241, 1978 Va. LEXIS 154 (1978). Contract under seal imports a valuable consideration. Consideration is presumed from an instrument under seal unless there is proof to the contrary. Henderson v. United States Fid. &amp; Guar. Co., 831 F.2d 519, 1987 U.S. App. LEXIS 14104 (4th Cir. 1987). Lea...</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_11-4"><akn:num>§ 11-4</akn:num><akn:heading>Sizes of type in printed contracts</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text No contract in writing entered into between a citizen of this Commonwealth and any person, firm, company or corporation, domestic or foreign, doing business in this Com monwealth, for the sale and future delivery of any goods or chattels, machinery or mechanical devices, or personal property of any kind or sort whatsoever, shall be binding upon the purchaser, where the form is printed and furnished by the person, firm, company or corporation, unless all of the provisions of such contract are clearly and plainly printed or written; and, where printed, such provisions and covenants and all stipulations as to the rights of the vendor shall be in type of not less than the size known as ten point; and, wherever in such contract, printed upon a form furnished by the vendor, it is stipulated that the vendor is not to be bound by any verbal agreement or modification of the terms of such printed contract, then such stipulation shall be printed as a separate paragraph or paragraphs and in type not smaller than pica. Should any of the contract, including the special stipulation hereinbefore mentioned, be printed in less than the size of type hereby prescribed, and the agent or salesman of such person, firm, company or corporation enter into any verbal or written or collateral agreement with the vendee, on the part of the person, firm, company or corporation, modifying or changing such printed agreement or the parts of the cont ract which are printed, then the vendee may, in any action instituted to enforce such contract, or the payment of any sum of money agreed to be paid under such contract, be allowed to introduce such collateral agreement, or contract in modification there of, or any verbal statement made by the agent or salesman in modification thereof, in evidence in such action, and the same, if proved, shall be considered by the court or jury trying the case as a part of such printed contract. History History. 1920, p. 362; Michie Code 1942, § 5562a. Annotations Sizes of type illustrated. The sizes of type mentioned in this section are as follows: This is ten point type. Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 3C M.J. Commercial Law, §§ 11, 17, 36, 95, 99; 4A M.J. Contracts, § 54. CASE NOTES This section, which specifies sizes of type in printed contracts, held inconsistent with subsection (2) of § 8.2-316, which requires that a limiting term or clause need only be conspicuous, and therefore, did not apply to a transaction to which subsection (2) of § 8.2-316 was applicable. Armco, Inc. v. New Horizon Dev. Co., 229 V a. 561, 331 S.E.2d 456, 1985 Va. LEXIS 232 (1985). This section merely changes the common-law rule as to contemporaneous parol agreements altering and modifying contracts of the particular description therein mentioned, which are not printed or written in the manner and form required by the section. Piedmont Mt. Airy Guano Co. v. Buchanan, 146 Va. 617, 131 S.E. 793, 1926 Va. LEXIS 351 (1926 ); Hogue-Kellogg Co. v. G.L. Webster Canning Co., 22 F.2d 384, 1927 U.S. App. LEXIS 3337 (4th Cir. 1927), cert. denied, 277 U.S. 592, 48 S. Ct. 529, 72 L. Ed. 1004, 1928 U.S. LEXIS 775 (1928); Moore v. Aetna Cas. &amp; Sur. Co., 155 Va. 556, 155 S.E. 707, 19 30 Va. LEXIS 181 (1930); Jones v. Franklin, 160 Va. 266, 168 S.E. 753, 1933 Va. LEXIS 205 (1933). And it does not invalidate contracts.  This section is a statute affecting the remedy on certain types of contracts; and with respect to contracts not printed in the size of type required, its effect i s not to invalidate them, but to abrogate the rule which forbids that evidence be received of a contemporaneous parol agreement to add to, alter or deny them. Hogue-Kellogg Co. v. G.L. Webster Canning Co., 22 F.2d 384, 1927 U.S. App. LEXIS 3337 (4th Cir. 1927), cert. denied, 277 U.S. 592, 48 S. Ct. 529, 72 L. Ed. 1004, 1928 U.S. LEXIS 775 (1928). This section is for the protection of a purchaser of goods sold for future delivery on t he representations of an agent. Moore v. Aetna Cas. &amp; Sur. Co., 155 Va. 556, 155 S.E. 707, 1930 Va. LEXIS 181 (1930). And it does not apply to a contract evidencing a present sale and delivery of an automob ile and reserving title in the seller. Jones v. Franklin, 160 Va. 266, 168 S.E. 753, 1933 Va. LEXIS 205 (1933). Nor to an application for a surety bon d.  This section does not apply to an application by a contracting corporation to a surety company for a bond, although the application contains an assignment of the contracting corporations property to protect the surety company. Moore v. Aetna Cas. &amp; Sur. Co., 155 Va. 556, 155 S.E. 707, 1930 Va. LEXIS 181 (1930). Effect of stipulation between counse l.  Where it was stipulated between counsel that the size of type in a contract of sale was smaller than that required by this section, the seller was bound by verbal agreements or modifications of the contract made by its agent. Whaley Bros. v. Stevens, 159 Va. 388, 165 S.E. 645, 1932 Va. LEXIS 204 (1932). § 11-4.1. Certain indemnification provisions in construction contracts declared void. Text Any provision contained in any contract relating to the construction, alteration, repair or maintenance of a building, structure or appurtenance thereto, including movi ng, demolition and excavation connected therewith, or any provision contained in any contract relating to the construction of projects other than buildings by which the contractor performing such work purports to indemnify or hold harmless another party to the contract against liability for damage arising out of bodily injury to persons or damage to property suffered in the course of performance of the contract, caused by or resulting solely from the negligence of such other party or his agents or emplo yees, is against public policy and is void and unenforceable. This section applies to such contracts between contractors and any public body, as defined in § 2.2-4301. This section shall not affect the validity of any insurance contract, workers compensation, or any agreement issued by an admitted insurer. The provisions of this section shall not apply to any provision of any contract entered into prior to July 1, 1973. History History. 1973, c. 273; 1974, c. 430; 1991, c. 363. Annotations CASE NOTES Construction.  Unambiguous language of § 11-4.1 requires courts to look to the contract containing the provision, not the circumstances from which the claim for indemnificati on arose, to determine whether an indemnification provision violates § 11-4.1.Uniwest Constr., Inc. v. Amtech Elevator Servs., 280 Va. 428, 699 S.E.2d 223, 2010 Va. LEXIS 234 (2010), op. withdrawn in part, 281 Va. 509, 714 S.E.2d 560, 2011 Va. LEXIS 1 07 (2011). Indemnification requirement void for violation of public policy.  Operative language of paragraph 10 of the subcontract stated if any claims be made or asserted, whether or not such claims were based upon the negligence of t he corporation, the company agreed to indemnify and save harmless the corporation from any and all such claims; the plain meaning of that language clearly obligated the company to indemnify the corporation whether or not the claim was based upon the negligence of the corporation. Those words irreconcilably conflicted with the public policy expressed in § 11-4.1, which voided any contractual provision that purported to indemnify or hold harmless the corporation against liability for damage caused by or resulting solely from the negligence of the corporation; therefore, because paragraph 10 clearly reached beyond the negligence of other parties and indemnified the corporation, it violated § 11-4.1 and was void. Uniwest Constr., Inc. v. Amtech E levator Servs., 280 Va. 428, 699 S.E.2d 223, 2010 Va. LEXIS 234 (2010), op. withdrawn in part, 281 Va. 509, 714 S.E.2d 560, 2011 Va. LEXIS 107 (2011). CIRCUIT COURT OPINIONS Indemnification requirement void for violation of public policy.  Contractors claims against subcontractors for indemnification by express contract failed because the indemnity provisions of the subcontracts were void, and a contract did not exist between the contractor and one of the subcontractors. Supchak v. Fuller Constr. Corp., 86 Va. Cir. 517, 2013 Va. Cir. LEXIS 75 (Chesapeake July 12, 2013). Indemnification requirement not void .  Contractor was not entitled to summary judgment in an owners third-party negligence action because, while the parties agreed in writing that New Jersey law wo uld govern and the New Jersey statute violated Virginia public policy, the provision was valid under Virginia law where the agreement at issue was not so broad as to permit the contractor to indemnify the owner for the owners own negligence. Prum v. Linde Gas N. Am. LLC, 2016 Va. Cir. LEXIS 106 (Hopewell July 5, 2016). In a case in which it was alleged that the contractor hired to perform utility work on a project breached the contract by incorrectly installing various water lin es and causing damage to other utility lines, the contractors demurrer, asserting that the indemnification provision was void, unenforceable, and contrary to public policy, was overruled because the language within the four corners of the contract di d not expressly allow the owner to be indemnified for its own negligence; and the contract indicated that only the contractor was to perform the work in the parties agreement. Wasa Props., L.L.C. v. Chesapeake Bay Contrs., Inc., 103 Va. Cir. 423, 2019 Va . Cir. LEXIS 1184 (Chesapeake Dec. 11, 2019). § 11-4.1:1. Waiver of payment bond claims and contract claims; construction contracts. Text A subcontractor as defined in § 43-1, lower-tier subcontractor, or material supplier may not waive or diminish his right to assert payment bond claims or his right t o assert claims for demonstrated additional costs in a contract in advance of furnishing any labor, services, or materials. A provision that waives or diminishes a subcontractors, lower-tier subcontractors, or material suppliers right t...</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_11-5"><akn:num>§ 11-5</akn:num><akn:heading>11-5 through 11-7</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Repealed by Acts 1964, c. 219. § 11-7.1. Certain entities authority to extend performance agreements. Text A. The Departm ent of Small Business and Supplier Diversity, the Virginia Economic Development Partnership Authority, the Virginia Tourism Authority, the Tobacco Region Revitalization Commission, a nonprofit, nonstock corporation created pursuant to § 2.2-2240.1, an y county, city, or town, or local or regional industrial or economic development authorities created in accordance with law have the authority, upon the agreement of the parties, to extend the performance period for any performance agreement. B. For the pur poses of this section, performance agreement means any agreement, contract, or memorandum of understanding that imposes an obligation for minimum private investment or the creation of new jobs in exchange for grants or other funds, or loans of mo ney from an entity specified in subsection A. C. Nothing in this section shall be construed or interpreted to authorize or allow for any payment or appropriation of funds except as provided in the general appropriation act. History History. 2009, c. 224; 2013, c. 482. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2009, c. 224 has been codified as § 11-7.1 at the direction of the Virginia Code Commission. At the direction of the Virginia Code Commission, the reference to Tobacco Region Revitalization Commission was substituted for Tobacco Indemnificatio n and Community Revitalization Commission in subsection A to conform to Acts 2015, cc. 399 and 433. The 2013 amendments. The 2013 amendment by c. 482, effective January 1, 2014, substituted Small Business and Supplier Diversity for Business Assistance near the beginn ing of subsection A.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_11-8"><akn:num>§ 11-8</akn:num><akn:heading>Instruments executed by minors or surviving spouses to obtain benefits under certain federal legislation</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Any person under the age of 18 or surviving spouse who has not remarried who is eligible for a guaranty of credit under the provisions of Title III of an Act of Congres s of the United States approved June 22, 1944, entitled the Servicemens Readjustment Act of 1944, as now or hereafter amended, or other like federal law, shall be upon complying with the terms of this section, qualified to contract for and pu rchase any real or personal property with respect to which the guaranteed loan is to be made, to execute the note or other evidence of the loan indebtedness and to secure the debt by the execution of a deed of trust or chattel mortgage, or other instrume nt, upon the real or personal property acquired as aforesaid in connection with the proposed loan or theretofore acquired by such person, whether by purchase or otherwise, and such person shall, in all respects, be bound by such contracts or other instru ments entered into as though he were of full age. When any such person is under the age of 18 years, no contract, note, deed of trust, mortgage, or other instrument required to obtain benefits under such federal legisl ation shall be executed by such person unless the circuit or corporation court of the city or county, or judge thereof in vacation, in which the property is located or to be used, after a petition signed by any such person has been filed with it or him, approves the same. Such petition shall set forth the facts pertaining to the proposed transaction and shall state why the judge or court should approve and authorize the execution of the necessary instruments. The petition shall be heard by the court without a jury, and its decision thereon shall be final. A guardian ad litem shall be appointed who shall make an investigation and report in writing whether in his opinion the best interest of the petitioner would be served by permitting the petitioner to enter into such transaction, and the report shall be filed with the papers in the case. No such petition shall be approved b y the court unless such approval is recommended by the report of the guardian ad litem and unless it is also recommended by the testimony of at least two disinterested and qualified witnesses appointed by the court, or the judge thereof in vacation. The order of approval shall recite the recommendation of the guardian ad litem and the witnesses and also their names and addresses. And the judge of the court hearing the case shall fix a reasonable fee for the attorneys and guardians ad litem. The court, if of opinion that entry into such transaction would benefit the petitioner, shall approve the prayer of the petition, and the petitioner, if he enters into such transaction and executes any instrument required therein, shall be bound thereby as if of full age whether all or part of the obligation secured is so guaranteed. All rights that have accrued or obligations that have arisen under this section prior to January 30, 1947, are hereby declared valid and binding. If the court approves the prayer of the petition, such approval shall operate to vest title and confer the power to encumber or convey title to real or personal propert y acquired pursuant to such approval. Any infant spouse of an infant veteran permitted by the court to make loans under this section may unite in any conveyance to effectuate such a loan as if he were a spo use of an adult signing as provided under the provisions of former § 55-42, relating to the removal of disability of infancy in certain cases. History History. 1946, p. 432; Michie Suppl. 1946, § 5760a; 1947, p. 102; 1954, c. 602; 1972, c. 825; 2020, c. 900. Annotations Editors note. To conform to the recodification of Title 55 by Acts 2019, c. 712, effective October 1, 2019, the following substitution was made at the direction of the Virginia Code Commission: substituted former § 55-42 for § 55-42. The 2020 amendments. The 2020 amendment by c. 900, in the first paragraph, substituted surviving spouse for widow and he were for he or she were; in th e second paragraph, substituted has been filed with it or him, approves for shall have been filed with it or him, approve; in the fourth paragraph, substituted enters for enter, executes for execute and is so guaranteed for be so guaranteed; in the fifth paragraph, substituted that for which twice; in the sixth paragraph, substituted approves for approve; in the seventh paragraph, substituted he were  for he or she was and made stylistic changes. Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 9B M.J. Husband and Wife, § 95.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_11-9"><akn:num>§ 11-9</akn:num><akn:heading>Writing payable to deceased person</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A bond, note or other writing to a person or persons who, or some of whom, are dead at the time of its execution, shall be as valid as if such person or persons were th en alive. History History. Code 1919, § 5761. Annotations Cross references. As to proceedings on writing binding deceased person, see § 8.01-11. §§ 11-9.1 through 11-9.7. Repealed by Acts 2010, cc. 455 and 632, cl. 2. Annotations Cross references. For current provisions, see the Uniform Power of Attorney Act, § 64.2-1600 et seq. Editors note. Former § 11-9.1, relating to when power of attorney, etc., not terminated by principals disability; exception, was derived from Acts 1954, c. 486; 1984, c. 101; 1995, c. 369; 1997, c. 921; 2004, c. 380; 2007, c. 520. Former § 11-9.2, relating to powers of attorney not revoked, prior to their termination date, until actual notice of death or disability, was derived from Acts 1954, c. 486; 1984, c. 101; 1995, c. 369; 1997, c. 921; 2004, c. 380; 2007, c. 520. Former § 11-9.3, relating to powers of attorney executed by members of armed services listed as missing in action, was derived from Acts 1968, c. 118. Former § 11-9.4, relating to contingent powers of attorney, was derived from Acts 1987, c. 340. Former § 11-9.5, relating to gifts under power of attorney, was derived from Acts 1992, c. 544. Former § 11-9.6, relating to certain duties of attorneys-in-fact and agents empowered to act under § 11-9.1, was derived from Acts 1995, c. 369; 1999, c. 76 ; 2007, cc. 385, 520. Former § 11-9.7, relating to failure to deliver power of attorney, was derived from Acts 2003, c. 269. § 11-9.8. Construction of certain terms of offer to contract; use of experience modification factor prohibited. Text A. As used in this section:Contract means an agreement for the provision of construction services under which t he contractor will be required to have and maintain a policy of insurance as defined in § 38.2-119.Experience modification factor means a value assigned to an employer as determined by a rate service organization in accordance with its uniform experience rating plan required to be filed pursuant to subsection D of § 38.2-1913. Offer to contract means a solicitation of bids, Request for Proposals, or similar invitation to enter into a contract that is extended to potential contractors for construction services.Person means any in dividual; firm; cooperative; association; corporation; limited liability company; trust; business trust; syndicate; partnership; limited liability partnership; joint venture; receiver; trustee in bankruptcy; club, society, or other group or combination a cting as a unit; or public body, including but not limited to (i) the Commonwealth; (ii) any other state; and (iii) any agency, department, institution, political subdivision, or instrumentality of the Commonwealth or any other state. B. A term of a n offer to contract issued that requires that the successful bidder have a specified experience modification factor is prohibited. C. Any contrac t or offer to contract that requires the contractor or bidder responding to the offer to contract to have a specified experience modification factor is prohibited. History History. 2016, c. 754. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2016, c. 754, cl. 2 provides: That the provisions of this act shall apply to any offer to contract, as defined in § 11-9.8 of the Code of Virginia, as created in this act; Invitation to Bid; or Request for Proposal for construction services issued on or after July 1, 2016. Chapter 2. Compromise and Satisfaction. -360§ 11-10. Compromise by creditor with co-obligor, etc. -360§ 11-11. Crediting contract; surety. -360§ 11-12. Part performance extinguishing obligation. -360§ 11-13. Right of contribution not affected.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_11-10"><akn:num>§ 11-10</akn:num><akn:heading>Compromise by creditor with co-obligor, etc</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A creditor may compound or compromise with any joint contractor or co-obligor, and release him from all liability on his contract or obligation, without impairing the c ontract or obligation as to the other joint contractors or co-obligors. History History. Code 1919, § 5763. Annotations Law Review. For article, The Duty to Settle, see 76 Va. L. Rev. 1113 (1990). Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 16 M.J. Release, § 8. Research References. Friends Virginia Pleading and Practice (Matthew Bender). Chapter 5 Parties. § 5.04 Contract Actions. Friend. CASE NOTES This section changed the rule as to the release of joint obligors.  Formerly, the release of one joint obligor operated to release all. First &amp; Merchants Nat'l Bank v. Bank of Waverly, 170 Va. 496, 197 S.E. 462, 1938 Va. LEXIS 205 (1938). But did not change the rule respecting joint wrongdoers.  The fact that the General Assembly changed the general rule respecting the release of joint obligors, and left unimpaired the rule respecting joint wrongdoers, is persuasive that it was satisfied with and approved the law applicable to the release of joint wrongdoers. First &amp; Merchants Nat'l Bank v. Bank of Waverly, 170 Va. 496, 197 S.E. 462, 1938 Va. LEXIS 205 (1938). In an action to recover for losses caused by defendants failure to properly perform its duties as co-executor and cotrustee of an estate, it was held that pla intiffs release of the other acting co-executor and cotrustee operated as a release and discharge of defendant, even though the defendants discharge was not intended. First &amp; Merchants Nat'l Bank v. Bank of Waverly, 170 Va. 496, 197 S.E. 462, 193 8 Va. LEXIS 205 (1938). Creditor may sue without joining released obligor.  A creditor who has compromised with one of several joint obligors, and received his full share of the obligation, may sue the other obligors without making the re leased obligor a party. Penn v. Bahnson, 89 Va. 253, 15 S.E. 586, 1892 Va. LEXIS 90 (1892).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_11-11"><akn:num>§ 11-11</akn:num><akn:heading>Crediting contract; surety</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text When such compounding or compromise is made, the contract or obligation shall be credited with a full share of the party released, except where the compounding or compr omise is with a surety or cosurety, and in that case, as between the creditor and principal, the credit shall be for the sum actually paid by the compounding debtor. History History. Code 1919, § 5764.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_11-12"><akn:num>§ 11-12</akn:num><akn:heading>Part performance extinguishing obligation</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Part performance of an obligation, promise or undertaking, either before or after a breach thereof, when expressly accepted by the creditor in satisfaction and rendered in pursuance of an agreement for that purpose, though without any new consideration, shall extinguish such obligation, promise, or undertaking. History History. Code 1919, § 5765. Annotations Cross references. As to compromise of claim for death by wrongful act, see §§ 8.01-51 and 8.01-55. As to compromises relating to persons under disability and fiduciaries, see §§ 8.01-424 and 8.01-425. For accord and satisfaction by use of an instrument, see § 8.3A-311. Law Review. For discussion of settlement for less than the creditors claim under this section, see 53 Va. L. Rev. 1220 (1967). Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 1A M.J. Accord and Satisfaction, §§ 4, 6; 4A M.J. Comp romise and Settlement, § 8; 4A M.J. Contracts, § 34; 14B M.J. Payment, §§ 4, 18. CASE NOTES Section relates to accord and satisfaction. Campbell v. Howard, 133 Va. 19, 112 S.E. 876, 1922 Va. LEXIS 83 (1922). And changes the common-law rule. Hogan v. Callas, 139 Va. 137, 123 S.E. 361, 1924 Va. LEX IS 91 (1924). The making of an offer and the acceptance thereof in satisfaction are essential elements of an accord and satisfaction. Where the evidence showed defendants desired or intended the check to be in satisfaction of plaintiffs demand but also clearly showed that there was no acceptance, express or implied, on the part of plaintiffs, there n ever was any meeting of the minds of the parties in an agreement and defendants failed to bring themselves within this section. Atkins v. Boatwright, 204 Va. 450, 132 S.E.2d 450, 1963 Va. LEXIS 171 (1963). Burden upon de btor to show agreement and acceptance.  The burden is upon the debtor to show that the payment of less than was due was expressly accepted by his creditor in satisfaction and rendered in pursuance o f an agreement for that purpose. Standard Sewing Mach. Co. v. Gunter, 102 Va. 568, 46 S.E. 690, 1904 Va. LEXIS 103 (1904); Thomas v. Brown, 116 Va. 233, 81 S.E. 56, 1914 Va. LEXIS 25 (1914); McGuire v. Martin, 152 Va. 453, 147 S.E. 265, 1929 Va. LEXI S 182 (1929); Kasco Mills, Inc. v. Ferebee, 197 Va. 589, 90 S.E.2d 866, 1956 Va. LEXIS 126 (1956); Atkins v. Boatwright, 204 Va. 450, 132 S.E.2d 450, 1963 Va. LEXIS 171 (1963). Where tenants are obligated to pay a certain sum per month, during a certain period, under a sealed contract of lease, they can only be excused from its performan ce by showing that smaller amounts were expressly accepted by the owners in satisfaction and received in pursuance of an agreement for that purpose. The inference growing out of the silent acceptance of smaller sums is not sufficient under the statute. H ogan v. Callas, 139 Va. 137, 123 S.E. 361, 1924 Va. LEXIS 91 (1924). Appl ication of money by creditor held express acceptance.  An agreement between a debtor and his creditor, fixing the amount of an unliquidated demand, constituted an accord, and the application by the creditor of one-hal f of the money received from the sale of a certificate of stock given him by the debtor for that purpose to the satisfaction in full of the indebtedness and his complete acquittance of the debtor from the obligation thereof, in pursuance of a prior agree ment authorizing him so to do, while that agreement still existed, executed the accord; so that, at common law, the accord and satisfaction became complete. And even if the indebtedness was a liquidated demand, the application of the money was an express acceptance thereof by the creditor in full satisfaction of the debt, in pursuance of the prior agreement; so that, under this section, the same result followed. Hibbs v. First Nat'l Bank, 133 Va. 94, 112 S.E. 669, 1922 Va. LEXIS 86 (1922). Whether acceptance of remittance amounts to accord and satisfaction depends upon circumstances.  The question whether the acceptance of a check or other remittance by a creditor in payment of an indebtedness to him amounts to an accord and satisfaction depend s upon the circumstances surrounding the transaction, taking into consideration the conduct and declaration of the respective parties with relation thereto. This cannot be determined without a consideration of all the pertinent facts. Kasco Mills, Inc. v . Ferebee, 197 Va. 589, 90 S.E.2d 866, 1956 Va. LEXIS 126 (1956). The fact that a check is marked In Full constitutes prima facie evidence of acceptance in full settlement. But there is no accord and satisfaction unless the creditor intends so to accept. Kasco Mills, Inc. v. Ferebee, 197 Va. 589, 90 S.E.2d 866, 1956 Va. LEXIS 126 (1956). Repudiated stipulation in county warrant not evidence of agreement.  Neither at common law nor under this section was an ex parte stipulation in a warrant for an attorneys expenses while rendering professional services for the county evidence of an agreement on his part to the terms of such stipulation in regard to his fee for such services, when he was not present at the board meeting which ordered the issuance of the warrant, never agreed to the stipulation, promptly repudia ted its binding force upon him as soon as he received the warrant, and at once gave constructive notice thereof to the county before he presented the warrant and received payment from the county. Campbell v. Howard, 133 Va. 19, 112 S.E. 876, 1922 Va. LEX IS 83 (1922). The accord must be executed while it is in existence. This is as necessary to constitute an accord and satisfaction as the accord itself. Campbell v. Howard, 133 Va. 19, 112 S.E. 876, 1922 Va. LEXIS 83 (1922).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_11-13"><akn:num>§ 11-13</akn:num><akn:heading>Right of contribution not affected</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Nothing contained in §§ 11-10 through 11-12 shall affect or impair the right of contribution between joint contractors and co-obligors. History History. Code 1919, § 5766. Annotations Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 4B M.J. Contribution and Exoneration, § 10. CASE NOTES The release of a surety by compromise with the creditor cannot affect or impair the righ t of any other surety, who may have been required to pay more of the debt than was so released, to call on him for contribution. And when a surety has conveyed all his property in trust to secure ratably all his debts, said property is liable to contribu tion to his cosurety. Yuille v. Wimbish, 77 Va. 308, 1883 Va. LEXIS 59 (1883). Chapter 3. Gaming Contracts. -360§ 11-14. Gaming contracts void. -360§ 11-15. Recovery of money or property lost in gaming. -360§ 11-16. Bill by loser; repayment discharges winner from punishment. -360§ 11-16.1. Exemption from the chapter. -360§ 11-16.2. Exemption; authorized sports betting.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_11-14"><akn:num>§ 11-14</akn:num><akn:heading>Gaming contracts void</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Except as otherwise provided in this section, all wagers, conveyances, assurances, and all contracts and securities whereof the whole or any part of the consideration i s money or other valuable thing won, laid, or bet, at any game, horse race, sport or pastime, and all contracts to repay any money knowingly lent at the time and place of such game, race, sport or pastime, to any person for the purpose of so gaming, bett ing, or wagering, or to repay any money so lent to any person who shall, at such time and place, so pay, bet or wager, shall be utterly void. Notwithstanding any other provision of law, a contract governing the distribution of state lottery proceeds shall be valid and enforceable as between the parties to the contract. History History. Code 1919, § 5558; 1998, c. 400. Annotations Cross references. As to award of prize money for charitable games, see § 18.2-340.22. As to award of prize money for pari-mutuel wager placed at racetrack or satellite facility, see § 59.1-364. The 1998 amendment, in the first paragraph, added Except as otherwise provided in this section and substituted is money for be money, and added the second paragraph. Law Review. For survey of Virginia commercial law for the year 1969-1970, see 56 Va. L. Rev. 1387 (1970). For note, Judicial Review of Arbitration Awards Under State Law, 96 Va. L. Rev. 887 (2010). Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 3C M.J. Commercial Law, § 61; 4A M.J. Contracts, § 39; 9A M.J. Gaming and Gaming Contracts, § 22. CASE NOTES Analysis I. In General. II. Speculative Transactions in Stocks or Commodities. III. Wills and Administration. IV. Equitable Relief. I.In General. Constitutionality.  The refusal of a state to permit the enforcement in its courts of a gambling contract, as is stated in this section, presents no constitutional question, state or federal. Kennedy v. Annandale Boys Club, Inc., 221 Va. 504, 272 S.E.2d 38, 1980 Va. LEXIS 271 (1980). The mandate of the Full Faith and Credit statute prevails over Virginias strongly-expressed policy which prohibits the enforcement of gambling debts. Coghill v. Boardwalk Regency Corp., 240 Va. 230, 396 S.E.2d 838, 1990 Va. LEXIS 113 (1990). The legislatures refusal to permit enforcement in its courts of a gambling contract presents no constitutional question, state or federal. Resorts Int'l Hotel , Inc. v. Agresta, 569 F. Supp. 24, 1983 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 14879 (E.D. Va. 1983), aff'd, 725 F.2d 676 (4th Cir. 1984). Legislative intent.  The language of this section makes it plain that the General Assembly has not made the state court system available to unpaid gambling winners. There can be no cl aim made on any contract founded upon gaming. Resorts Int'l Hotel, Inc. v. Agresta, 569 F. Supp. 24, 1983 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 14879 (E.D. Va. 1983), aff'd, 725 F.2d 676 (4th Cir. 1984). The public policy of the Commonwealth expressed through statutory provisions has been si nce 1740 that all promises, agreements, mortgages, securities, and the like, where the consideration was based on wagers, are void. Resorts Int'l Hotel, Inc. v. Agresta, 569 F. Supp. 24, 1983 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 14879 (E.D. Va. 1983), aff'd, 725 F.2d 676 (4 th Cir. 1984). Section should be construed strictly. Resorts Int'l Hotel, Inc. v. Agresta, 569 F. Supp. 24, 1983 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 14879 (E.D. Va. 1983), aff'd, 725 F.2d 676 (4th Cir. 1984). A contract is not a contract of wager when all the profit or loss is to be on one of the parties. Brown v. Speyers, 61 Va. (20 Gratt.) 296, 1871 Va. LEXIS 6 (1871). Where the expectancy of hitting the lottery jackpot was not just the material cause but the sole cause of the agreement, and the whole reason for entering into the agreement was to pool funds so that each player could increase his chances of winning money in the lottery, the agreement constituted a gaming contract within the meaning of this section. Hughes v. Cole, 251 Va. 3, 465 S.E.2d 820, 1996 Va. LEXIS 16 (1996) (decided prior to 1998 amendment to this section). Bond given for gaming consideration is void.  M. having won money of W. at cards, and J. having won the same sum of M., the bond of W. given at the request of M. to J. for that sum is void. Woodson v. Barrett , 12 Va. (2 Hen. &amp; M.) 80, 1808 Va. LEXIS 22 (1808). And money lent to be bet upon an election is not recoverable by suit. Machir v. Moore, 4 3 Va. (2 Gratt.) 257, 1845 Va. LEXIS 42 (1845). But loan t o pay gambling obligation is valid.  It would not be more unlawful to lend money to a man to be used in paying an old obligation, which he could resist under this section, than it would be to lend hi m money to pay an old debt barred by time. Krake v. Alexander, 86 Va. 206, 9 S.E. 991, 1889 Va. LEXIS 27 (1889). There was judgment against surety on note for money borrowed to be used as margins on grain and pork options. Surety obtained money to pay judgment, securing lend er by trust deed on land. Lender was not shown to have had any connection with, or knowledge of, the options. On a creditors bill to take an account of liens on suretys land it was held that the trust deed to lender was not void as against the ot her creditors, under this section, as being based on a gambling consideration. Krake v. Alexander, 86 Va. 206, 9 S.E. 991, 1889 Va. LEXIS 27 (1889). As is discount of note where proceeds used for gambling in stocks, if bank had no notice of object.  The fact that the indorser of a note knew that the proceeds of the note were to be used by the maker in gambling in stocks cannot affect the rights of the bank wh ich discounted the note for the maker in ignorance of the use to be made of the money. Such a discount by the bank is not within the purview of this section and the note is not affected by the circumstances that it subsequently passed into the hands of t he indorser, who had notice of the object to which the proceeds were to be applied. Citizens' Nat'l Bank v. McDannald, 116 Va. 834, 83 S.E. 389, 1914 Va. LEXIS 95 (1914). Notes given for gambling losses are invalid, even in the hands of a holder in due course . Glassman v. FDIC, 210 Va. 650, 173 S.E.2d 843, 1970 Va. LEXIS 177 (1970). Enforcement of a note executed in order to pay a gambling debt incurred in another state would be against the express public policy and positive law of the Common wealth. Resorts Int'l Hotel, Inc. v. Agresta, 569 F. Supp. 24, 1983 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 14879 (E.D. Va. 1983), aff'd, 725 F.2d 676 (4th Cir. 1984). Rescission or restitution not available remedy for gambling contract parties.  As gambling contracts are illegal or immoral, Virginia law simply leaves the litigants in the plight in which they have seen fit to place themselves without under taking to balance benefits or burdens, and a party to such contracts cannot sue for rescission or restitution. Rahmani v. Resorts Int'l Hotel, Inc., 20 F. Supp. 2d 932, 1998 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 14236 (E.D. Va. 1998), aff'd, 182 F.3d 909, 1999 U.S. App. LEXI S 23421 (4th Cir. 1999). II.Speculative Transactions in Stocks or Commodities. Validity depends upon intention to make delivery.  A contract for the purchase of future-delivery cotton, neither the purchase nor delivery of actual cotton being contemplated by the parties, but the settl ement in respect to which is to be upon the basis of the mere difference between the contract price and the market price of said cotton futures, according to the fluctuations in the market, is a wagering contract and void under this section. Embr ey v. Jemison, 131 U.S. 336, 9 S. Ct. 776, 33 L. Ed. 172, 1889 U.S. LEXIS 1825 (1889). III.Wills and Administration. Direction to pay debts is not applicable to gaming debt.  Testators direction that all his just debts be paid out of the sales of certain lands does not authorize the payment of a gaming debt of his out of the procee ds of such sales. Carter's Ex'rs v. Cutting, 19 Va. (5 Munf) 223, 1816 Va. LEXIS 39 (1816). And payment of gaming debt is not a credit to executor.  An executor ought not to be allowed a credit for paying a debt of his testator, appearing, on the face of the written instrument intended to secure it, to have be en for money won at unlawful gaming. Carter's Ex'rs v. Cutting, 19 Va. (5 Munf) 223, 1816 Va. LEXIS 39 (1816). IV.Equitable Relief. Equity may relieve against gaming consideration.  Where part of a bond is on gaming consideration, and the other part on lawful consideration, equity will relieve against the part which is vicious, and sustain th at which is good; the obligor being plaintiff. Skipwith v. Strother, 24 Va. (3 Rand.) 214, 1825 Va. LEXIS 16 (1825). And against judgment on gaming debt.  A court of equity has jurisdiction to relieve against a judgment founded on a gaming debt, although the party failed to defend himself at law, and gives no good r eason for such failure. Skipwith v. Strother, 24 Va. (3 Rand.) 214 (1825), cited in White v. Washington, 1848 Va. LEXIS 50, 46 Va. (5 Gratt.) 645 (1848). A judgment was obtained against the obligor in a bond given for a gaming consideration, and a writ of elegit was issued against his lands. A suit was brought by t he assignee of the bond against the sheriff for an error committed in executing such writ, and a judgment obtained. It was held that a court of equity will relieve the obligor, and the sheriff also, on the ground of the turpitude of the original transact ion. Woodson v. Barrett, 12 Va. (2 Hen. &amp; M.) 80, 1808 Va. LEXIS 22 (1808). Although no effort was made to obtain new trial in law court.  Where defendant, in an action at law on a promise founded on a gaming consideration, was surprised at the trial, and there was a judgment against him, he may come into equity for relief, though he made no effort to obtain a new trial in the law court. White v. Washington, 46 Va. (5 Gratt.) 645, 1848 Va. LEXIS 50 (1848).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_11-15"><akn:num>§ 11-15</akn:num><akn:heading>Recovery of money or property lost in gaming</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Any person who shall, by playing at any game or betting on the sides or hands of such as play at any game, lose within twenty-four hours, the sum or value of five dolla rs, or more, and pay or deliver the same, or any part thereof, may, within three months next following, recover from the winner, the money or the value of the goods so lost and paid or delivered, with costs of suit in civil action, either by suit or warr ant, according to the amount or value thereof. History History. Code 1919, § 5559. Annotations CASE NOTES Section applies to various forms of gambling.  This section should be liberally construed to apply to every form of gambling which comes fairly within its terms. McIntyre v. Smyth, 108 Va. 736, 62 S.E. 930, 19 08 Va. LEXIS 93 (1908). This section cannot be applied to losses that occur lawfully outside of Virginia. Rahman i v. Resorts Int'l Hotel, Inc., 20 F. Supp. 2d 932, 1998 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 14236 (E.D. Va. 1998), aff'd, 182 F.3d 909, 1999 U.S. App. LEXIS 23421 (4th Cir. 1999). Public policy against gambling does not override choice of law.  Section 11-15 did not make a casinos claim against a debtor for a gambling debt unenforceable in a bankruptcy case since the public policy of Virginia against gambling was not so fundamental that the court should ignore the choice of law provision in favor of Maryland law in light of Virginias state lottery system and the approval of historical horse racing gaming devices and pari-mutuel wagering at a Vir ginia horsetrack. In re Chu, 599 Bankr. 519, 2019 Bankr. LEXIS 1164 (Bankr. E.D. Va. 2019).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_11-16"><akn:num>§ 11-16</akn:num><akn:heading>Bill by loser; repayment discharges winner from punishment</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Such loser may file a bill in equity against such winner, who shall answer the same, and upon discovery and repayment of the money or property so won, or its value, suc h winner shall be discharged from any forfeiture or punishment which he may have incurred for winning the same. History History. Code 1919, § 5560. Annotations Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 9A M.J. Gaming and Gaming Contracts, § 24. § 11-16.1. Exemption from the chapter. Text This chapter shall not apply to any bet, wager, or casino gaming permitted by Chapter 41 (§ 58.1-4100 et seq.) of Title 58.1 or to any contract, conduct, or transact ion arising from conduct lawful thereunder. History History. 2020, cc. 1197, 1248. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2020, cc. 1197 and 1248, cl. 2 provides: That the provisions of this act may result in a net increase in periods of imprisonment or commitment. Pursuant to § 30-19.1:4 of the Code of Virginia, the estimated amount of the necessary appropriation cannot be determined for periods of imprisonment in state adult correctional facilities; therefore, Chapter 854 of the Acts of Assembly of 2019 requires the Vi rginia Criminal Sentencing Commission to assign a minimum fiscal impact of $50,000. Pursuant to § 30-19.1:4 of the Code of Virginia, the estimated amount of the necessary appropriation cannot be determined for periods of commitment to the custody of t he Department of Juvenile Justice. Acts 2020, cc. 1197 and 1248, cl. 3 provides: That the Virginia Lottery Board shall promulgate regulations to implement the provisions of this act to be effec tive within 280 days of its enactment. § 11-16.2. Exemption; authorized sports betting. Text This chapter shall not apply to any sports betting or related activity that is lawful under Article 2 (§ 58.1-4030 et seq.) of Chapter 40 of Title 58.1. History History. 2020, cc. 1218, 1256, § 11-16.1. Annotations The number of this section was assigned by the Virginia Code Commission, the number in the 2020 acts having been § 11-16.1. Editors note. Acts 2020, cc. 1218 and 1256, cl. 2 provides: That the Virginia Lottery Board (the Board) shall promulgate regulations implementing the provisions of this act . The Boards initial adoption of regulations shall be exempt from the Administrative Process Act (§ 2.2-4000 et seq. of the Code of Virginia), except that the Board shall provide an opportunity for public comment on the regulations prior to adopti on. The Board shall complete work on such regulations no later than September 15, 2020. Chapter 4. Public Contracts in General. -360§ 11-17. Repealed by Acts 1982, c. 647. -360§ 11-17.1. (Repealed) Expired. -360§§ 11-18 through 11-23.5.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_11-17"><akn:num>§ 11-17</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1982, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>647. Annotations Cross references. For present provisions as to public contracts, see the Virginia Public Procurement Act, § 2.2-4300 et seq. § 11-17.1. (Repealed) Expired. Annotations Editors note. This section expired by the terms of Acts 1980, c. 95, cl. 2, on July 1, 1983.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_11-18"><akn:num>§ 11-18</akn:num><akn:heading>11-18 through 11-23</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>5. Text Repealed by Acts 1982, c. 647. Chapter 4.1. Use of Domestic Steel in Public Works Projects. -360§§ 11-23.6 through 11-23.10. §§ 11-23.6 through 11-23.10. Text Expired. Annotations Editors note. This chapter expired by the terms of Acts 1981, c. 379, cl. 2, on June 30, 1986. Chapter 5. Burial, etc., Contract. -360§§ 11-24 through 11-29.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_11-24"><akn:num>§ 11-24</akn:num><akn:heading>11-24 through 11-29</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Repealed by Acts 1989, c. 684. Annotations Cross references. As to preneed funeral contracts, see now Article 5 (§ 54.1-2820 et seq.) of Chapter 28 of Title 54.1. Chapter 6. Credit Cards. -360§§ 11-30 through 11-34.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_11-30"><akn:num>§ 11-30</akn:num><akn:heading>11-30 through 11-34</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Repealed by Acts 2010, c. 794, cl. 11, effective October 1, 2010. Annotations Cross references. For current provisions related to credit cards, see Article 3 (§ 6.2-424 et seq.) of Chapter 4 of Title 6.2. Editors note. This chapter, relating to credit cards, was repealed by Acts 2010, c. 794, cl. 11. Acts 2010, c. 794, recodified former Title 6.1, as well as this chapter and for mer Chapter 2.3 (§§ 59.1-21.19 through 59.1-21.28) of Title 59.1 as Title 6.2. For general notes on the recodification, see Editors notes under § 6.2-100. For former §§ 11-30 through 11-34, see Article 3 (§ 6.2-424 et seq.) of Chapt er 4 of Title 6.2. Chapter 6.1. Energy and Operational Efficiency Performance-Based Contracting Act. -360§§ 11-34.1 through 11-34.4. §§ 11-34.1 through 11-34.4. Text Repealed by Acts 2021, Sp. Sess. I, c. 387, cl. 11, effective October 1, 2021. Annotations Cross references. For § 11-34.2 as effective October 1, 2021, see § 45.2-1702. For § 11-34.3 as effective October 1, 2021, see § 45.2-1703. For § 11-34.4 as effective October 1, 2021, see § 45.2-1704. Editors note. Former § 11-34.1, pertaining to legislative intent, derived from 2001, c. 219. Former § 11-34.2, pertaining to definitions, derived from 2001, c. 219. For § 11-34.2 as effective October 1, 2021, see § 45.2-1702. Former § 11-34.3, pertaining to Energy Performance-Based Contract Procedures; required contract provisions, derived from 2001, c. 219; 2004, c. 197; 2009, c. 3 99; 2013, c. 583; 2017, c. 259. For § 11-34.3 as effective October 1, 2021, see § 45.2-1703. Former § 11-34.4, pertaining to application of chapter, derived from 2001, c. 219. For § 11-34.4 as effective October 1, 2021, see § 45.2-1704. Acts 2021, Sp. Sess. I, c. 387, cl. 3 provides: That the regulations of any department or agency affected by the revision of Title 45.1 or such other titles o f the Code of Virginia as are in effect on the effective date of this act shall continue in effect to the extent that they are not in conflict with this act and shall be deemed to be regulations adopted under this act. Acts 2021, Sp. Sess. I, c. 387, cl. 4 provides: That the provisions of § 30-152 of the Code of Virginia shall apply to the revision of Title 45.1 and repea l of Title 67 (§§ 67-100 through 67-1700) of the Code of Virginia so as to give effect to other laws enacted by the 2021 Session of the General Assembly, notwithstanding the delay in the effective date of this act. Acts 2021, Sp. Sess. I, c. 387, cl. 5 provides: That the repeal of Chapter 6.1 (§§ 11-34.1 through 11-34.4) of Title 11, Title 45.1 (§§ 45.1-161.1 through 45.1-399), §§ 62.1-195.1 and 62.1-195.3, and Title 67 (§§ 67-100 through 67-1700) of the Code of Virginia, effective October 1, 2021, shall not affect any act or offense done or committed, any penalty incurred, or any right establish ed, accrued, or accruing on or before such date, or any proceeding, prosecution, suit, or action pending on that date. Except as otherwise provided in this act, neither the repeal of Chapter 6.1 (§§ 11-34.1 through 11-34.4) of Title 11, Title 45.1 (§§ 45.1-161.1 through 45.1-399), § 62.1-195.1 and 62.1-195.3, and Title 67 (§§ 67-100 through 67-1700) of the Code of Virginia, nor the enactment of Title 45.2 shall apply to offenses committed prior to October 1, 2021, and prosecution fo r such offenses shall be governed by the prior law, which is continued in effect for that purpose. For the purposes of this enactment, an offense was committed prior to October 1, 2021, if any of the essential elements of the offense occurred prior there to. Acts 2021, Sp. Sess. I, c. 387, cl. 6 provides: That any notice given, recognizance taken, or process or writ issued before October 1, 2021, shall be valid al though given, taken, or to be returned to a day after such date, in like manner as if Title 45.2 had been effective before the same was given, taken, or issued. Acts 2021, Sp. Sess. I, c. 387, cl. 7 provides: That if any clause, sentence, paragraph, subdivision, or section of Title 45.2 shall be adjudged in any court of competent jurisdiction to be invalid, the judgment shall not affect, impair, or invalidate the remainder thereof but shall be confined in its operation to the clause, sentence, paragraph, subdivision, or section thereof directly involved in the contro versy in which the judgment shall have been rendered, and to this end the provisions of Title 45.2 are declared severable. Acts 2021, Sp. Sess. I, c. 387, cl. 8 provides: That the repeal of Chapter 6.1 (§§ 11-34.1 through 11-34.4) of Title 11, Title 45.1 (§§ 45.1-161.1 through 45.1-399), §§ 62.1-195.1 and 62.1-195.3, and Title 67 (§§ 67-100 through 67-1700) of the Code of Virginia, effective as of October 1, 2021, shall not affect the validity, enforceability, or legality of any loan agreement or other con tract, or any right established or accrued under such loan agreement or other contract, that existed prior to such repeal. Acts 2021, Sp. Sess. I, c. 387, cl. 9 provides: That the repeal of Chapter 6.1 (§§ 11-34.1 through 11-34.4) of Title 11, Title 45.1 (§§ 45.1-161.1 through 45.1-399), §§ 62.1-195.1 and 62.1-195.3, and Title 67 (§§ 67-100 through 67-1700) of the Code of Virginia, effective October 1, 2021, shall not affect the validity, enforceability, or legality of any properly recorded deed that was r ecorded prior to such repeal. Acts 2021, Sp. Sess. I, c. 387, cl. 10 provides: That the repeal of Chapter 6.1 (§§ 11-34.1 through 11-34.4) of Title 11, Title 45.1 (§§ 45.1-161. 1 through 45.1-399), §§ 62.1-195.1 and 62.1-195.3, and Title 67 (§§ 67-100 through 67-1700) of the Code of Virginia, effective as of October 1, 2021, shall not affect the validity, enforceability, or legality of any bond or other debt obligat ion authorized, issued, or outstanding prior to such repeal. Acts 2021, Sp. Sess. I, c. 387, cl. 12 provides: That the provisions of this act shall not affect the existing terms of persons currently serving as members o f any agency, board, authority, commission, or other entity and that appointees currently holding positions shall maintain their terms of appointment and continue to serve until such time as the existing terms might expire or become renewed. However, any new appointments made on or after October 1, 2021, shall be made in accordance with the provisions of this act. Acts 2021, Sp. Sess. I, c. 387, cl. 13 provides: That the provisions of this act shall become effective on October 1, 2021. Acts 2021, Sp. Sess. I, c. 532 amended § 11-34.3 effective October 1, 2021, to substitute Department of Energy for Department of Mines, Minerals an d Energy. Acts 2021, Sp. Sess. I, c. 387 repeals and recodifies this section as § 45.2-1703. The recodified section was rewritten in such a way that the Department name no longer appears and so the amendment was not given effect. Chapter 7. Virginia Public Procurement Act. -360§§ 11-35 through 11-80.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_11-35"><akn:num>§ 11-35</akn:num><akn:heading>11-35 through 11-80</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Repealed by Acts 2001, c. 844, cl. 13, effective October 1, 2001. Annotations Cross references. For current provisions of the Virginia Public Procurement Act, see § 2.2-4300 et seq. Editors note. Acts 2001, c. 844, recodified Titles 2.1 and 9. In addition, Acts 2001, c. 844, rewrote the Virginia Public Procurement Act, formerly § 11-35 et seq., as § 2.2-4300 et seq. For provisions relating to Acts 2001, c. 844, and the 2001 recodification, see Editors note under § 2.2-100.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section></akn:body></akn:act></akn:akomaNtoso>