<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akn:akomaNtoso xmlns:akn="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><akn:act><akn:meta><akn:identification source="#cosilico"><akn:FRBRWork><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-61.1" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-61.1" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2023-03-01" name="release" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#virginia-general-assembly" /><akn:FRBRcountry value="us-va" /><akn:FRBRnumber value="title-61.1" /><akn:FRBRname value="act" /></akn:FRBRWork><akn:FRBRExpression><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-61.1/eng@2023-03-01" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-61.1/eng@2023-03-01" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2023-03-01" name="publication" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#lexisnexis" /><akn:FRBRlanguage language="eng" /></akn:FRBRExpression><akn:FRBRManifestation><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-61.1/eng@2023-03-01/main.xml" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-61.1/eng@2023-03-01/main.xml" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="conversion" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#cosilico" /></akn:FRBRManifestation></akn:identification><akn:references source="#cosilico"><akn:TLCOrganization eId="virginia-general-assembly" href="/ontology/organization/us-va/general-assembly" showAs="Virginia General Assembly" /><akn:TLCOrganization eId="lexisnexis" href="/ontology/organization/lexisnexis" showAs="LexisNexis" /><akn:TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="/ontology/organization/cosilico" showAs="Cosilico" /></akn:references></akn:meta><akn:preface><akn:docTitle>Title 61.1. </akn:docTitle></akn:preface><akn:body><akn:section eId="sec_61.1-1"><akn:num>§ 61.1-1</akn:num><akn:heading>Issue of receipt for goods not received</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A warehouseman, or any officer, agent or servant of a warehouseman, who issues or aids in issuing a receipt knowing that the goods for which such receipt is issued have not been actually received by such warehouseman, or are not under his actual control at the time of issuing such receipt, shall be guilty of a misdemeanor, and shall be punished as provided in § 18.2-12. History History. Code 1950, § 61-53; 1968, c. 69. Annotations Cross references. For provisions of Uniform Commercial Code relating to warehouse receipts, bills of lading and other documents of title, see §§ 8.7-101 through 8.7-603. Transition provisions. At its regular session of 1966 the General Assembly directed the Code Commission to revise certain titles of the Code, including Title 61, relating to warehouses, cold storage and refrigerated locker plants. In June of 1967 the Commission sent to the Governor and General Assembly its report containing the proposed revision of Title 61, which was published as House Document 4 of the 1968 session. This report conta ined revisors notes and other explanatory matter, which, while valuable, are too lengthy for inclusion here. The Commissions draft of the revision of Title 61, as amended by the General Assembly, became chapter 69 of the Acts of 1968. Effective O ct. 1, 1968, it repealed Title 61 of the Code and enacted a new Title 61.1. Many of the cases cited in the notes under the various sections of this title were decided under corresponding provisions of former Title 61. Acts 1968, c. 69, clauses 3-5 and 7, provide as follows: 3. All acts and parts of acts, all sections of the Code of Virginia, and all provisions of municipal charters inconsistent with the provisions of this act are , except as otherwise provided, repealed to the extent of such inconsistency. 4. The repeal of Title 61 effective as of October 1, 1968, shall not affect any act or offense done or committed, or any penalty or forfeiture incurred, or an y right established, accrued or accruing on or before such date, or any prosecution, suit or action pending on that date. Except as in this act otherwise provided, neither the repeal of Title 61 of the Code of Virginia nor the enactment of Title 61.1 sha ll apply to offenses committed prior to October 1, 1968, and prosecutions for such offenses shall be governed by the prior law, which is continued in effect for that purpose. For the purposes of this act, an offense was committed prior to October 1, 1968 , if any of the essential elements of the offense occurred prior thereto. 5. Whenever in Title 61.1 any of the conditions, requirements, provisions or contents of any section, article or chapter of Title 61, as such title existed pr ior to October 1, 1968, are transferred in the same or in modified form to a new section, article or chapter of Title 61.1, and whenever any such former section, article or chapter of Title 61 is given a new number in Title 61.1, all references to any su ch former section, article or chapter of Title 61 appearing elsewhere in the Code of Virginia than in Title 61.1 shall be construed to apply to the new or renumbered section, article or chapter containing such conditions, requirements, provisions or cont ents or portions thereof. 7. It is the intention of the General Assembly that this act shall be liberally construed to effect the purposes set out herein, and if any clause, sentence, paragraph or section of this act shall ever be declared unconstitutional, it shall be deemed severable, and the remainder of this act shall continue in full force and effect. Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 19 M.J. Warehouses and Warehousemen, §§ 1, 7.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_61.1-2"><akn:num>§ 61.1-2</akn:num><akn:heading>Issue of receipt containing false statement</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A warehouseman, or any officer, agent or servant of a warehouseman, who fraudulently issues or aids in fraudulently issuing a receipt for goods knowing that it contains any false statement, shall be guilty of a misdemeanor, and shall be punished as provided in § 18.2-12. History History. Code 1950, § 61-54; 1968, c. 69.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_61.1-3"><akn:num>§ 61.1-3</akn:num><akn:heading>Issue of duplicate receipts not so marked</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A warehouseman, or any officer, agent or servant of a warehouseman, who issues or aids in issuing a duplicate or additional negotiable receipt for goods, knowing that a former negotiable receipt for the same goods or any part of them is outstanding and uncanceled, without plainly placing upon the face thereof the word Duplicate, except as otherwise provided by law, shall be guilty of a misdemeanor. History History. Code 1950, § 61-55; 1968, c. 69.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_61.1-4"><akn:num>§ 61.1-4</akn:num><akn:heading>Failure to state in receipt warehousemans interest in goods</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Where there are deposited with or held by a warehouseman goods of which he is the owner, either solely or jointly in common with others, such warehouseman, or any of hi s officers, agents or servants, who knowing this ownership, issues or aids in issuing a negotiable receipt for such goods which does not state such ownership, shall be guilty of a misdemeanor, and upon conviction shall be punished as provided for misdeme anors generally in § 18.2-12. History History. Code 1950, § 61-56; 1968, c. 69.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_61.1-5"><akn:num>§ 61.1-5</akn:num><akn:heading>Delivery of goods without obtaining negotiable receipt</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A warehouseman, or any officer, agent or servant of a warehouseman, who delivers goods out of the possession of such warehouseman, knowing that a negotiable receipt the negotiation of which would transfer the right to the possession of such goods is outstanding and uncanceled, without obtaining the possession of such receipt at or before the time of such delivery, shall, except as otherwise provided by law, be guilty o f a misdemeanor, and upon conviction shall be punished as provided in § 18.2-12. History History. Code 1950, § 61-57; 1968, c. 69.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_61.1-6"><akn:num>§ 61.1-6</akn:num><akn:heading>Fraudulent negotiation of receipt for mortgaged goods</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Any person who deposits goods to which he has not title, upon which there is a lien or security interest, and who takes for such goods a negotiable receipt which he aft erwards negotiates for value with intent to deceive, and without disclosing his want of title or the existence of the lien or security interest, shall be guilty of a misdemeanor, and upon conviction shall be punished as provided in § 18.2-12. History History. Code 1950, § 61-58; 1968, c. 69. Chapter 2. Cold-Storage Warehouses. -360§§ 61.1-7 through 61.1-21.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_61.1-7"><akn:num>§ 61.1-7</akn:num><akn:heading>61</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>1-7 through 61.1-21. Text Repealed by Acts 1988, c. 149. Chapter 3. Refrigerated Locker Plants. -360§§ 61.1-22 through 61.1-37.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_61.1-22"><akn:num>§ 61.1-22</akn:num><akn:heading>61</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>1-22 through 61.1-37. Text Repealed by Acts 1972, c. 447. Chapter 4. Tobacco Warehouses and Regulations in General. -360§ 61.1-38. Establishment and discontinuance of warehouses. -360§ 61.1-39. Weighing leaf tobacco; itemized statements furnished seller. -360§ 61.1-40. Accounts of warehouse sales required. -360§ 61.1-41. Monthly reports to Commissioner; results classified. -360§ 61.1-42. Commissioner to keep record and publish in bulletin. -360§ 61.1-43. Penalty for failure to report sales. -360§ 61.1-44. Manufactured tobacco; false branding. -360§ 61.1-45. Nesting punished. -360§ 61.1-46. Publication of insurance. -360§ 61.1-46.1. Maximum charges for tobacco auction warehouse services.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_61.1-38"><akn:num>§ 61.1-38</akn:num><akn:heading>Establishment and discontinuance of warehouses</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Tobacco warehouses, which were public warehouses on the day before this Code takes effect, shall continue to be such; and the several circuit and corporation courts may hereafter authorize the erection of tobacco warehouses, or may establish the same, as public warehouses within their respective counties and cities; which warehouses shall be constructed, or shall have been constructed, so as to keep safely, and guard a gainst fire and weather, as far as practicable, all tobacco stored therein, and shall be kept in good repair and at all times, Sunday excepted, be open for receiving, storing, selling and delivering tobacco; but the owner of any such warehouse shall have the right to discontinue the same as a public warehouse, after having published a notice of his intention to do so once a week for four successive weeks in some newspaper published in the county or city, wherein such warehouse is situated, or if no news paper be published therein, after having posted such notice at the front door of the courthouse of such county or city for four successive weeks. History History. Code 1950, § 61-95; 1968, c. 69. Annotations Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 19 M.J. Warehouses and Warehousemen, §§ 2, 3. CASE NOTES Editors note. The cases below were decided under prior law. Stored does not necessarily imply long duration, but can equally describe tobacc o remaining in an auction warehouse awaiting removal by the purchaser. Export Leaf Tobacco Co. v. American Ins. Co., 260 F.2d 839, 1958 U.S. App. LEXIS 5144 (4th Cir. 1958). Tobacco warehouses are affected by a public interest, and the statutes of Virginia have for many years provided for inspection, weighing, charging fees, monthly reports, and many other details. Reaves Whse. v. Commonwealth, 141 Va. 194, 126 S.E. 87, 1925 Va. LEXIS 400 (1925), writ of error dismissed, 271 U.S. 690, 46 S. Ct. 481, 70 L. Ed. 1 154, 1926 U.S. LEXIS 840 (1926); Danville Whse. Co. v. Tobacco Growers Coop. Ass'n, 143 Va. 741, 129 S.E. 739, 1925 Va. LEXIS 301 (1925). And they may be regulated under the police power. Reaves Whse. v. Commonwealth, 141 Va. 194, 126 S.E. 87, 1925 Va. LEXIS 400 (1925), writ of error dismissed, 271 U.S. 690, 46 S. Ct. 481, 70 L. Ed. 1154, 1926 U.S. LEXIS 840 (1926); Danville Whse. Co. v. Tobacco Growers Coop. Ass'n, 143 Va. 741, 129 S.E. 739, 1925 Va. LEXIS 301 (1925).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_61.1-39"><akn:num>§ 61.1-39</akn:num><akn:heading>Weighing leaf tobacco; itemized statements furnished seller</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The proprietor of each and every warehouse shall render to each seller of tobacco at his warehouse a bill plainly stating the amount charged for weighing and handling, the amount charged for auction fees, and the commission charged on such sale, or any other charges made for selling and handling such tobacco. Any person violating the provisions of this section shall be guilty of a misdemeanor and shall be punished as provided in § 18.2-12. History History. Code 1950, § 61-108; 1968, c. 69.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_61.1-40"><akn:num>§ 61.1-40</akn:num><akn:heading>Accounts of warehouse sales required</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The proprietor of each and every leaf tobacco warehouse doing business in this Commonwealth shall keep a correct account of the number of pounds of leaf tobacco sold up on the floor of his warehouse daily. History History. Code 1950, § 61-109; 1968, c. 69. Annotations CASE NOTES This section is ap plicable to auction warehouses.  Export Leaf Tobacco Co. v. American Ins. Co., 260 F.2d 839, 1958 U.S. App. LEXIS 5144 (4th Cir. 1958) (decided under prior law).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_61.1-41"><akn:num>§ 61.1-41</akn:num><akn:heading>Monthly reports to Commissioner; results classified</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text On or before the tenth day of each succeeding month the warehouse proprietors shall make a statement, under oath, of all the tobacco so sold upon the floor of his wareh ouse during the past month and shall transmit the statement, at once, to the Commissioner of Agriculture and Consumer Services. The reports so made shall be so arranged and classified as to show the number of pounds of tobacco sold for the producers of t obacco from first hand; the number of pounds sold for dealers and the number of pounds resold by the proprietor of the warehouse for his own account or for the account of some other warehouse. History History. Code 1950, § 61-110; 1968, c. 69. Annotations CASE NOTES This section is ap plicable to auction warehouses.  Export Leaf Tobacco Co. v. American Ins. Co., 260 F.2d 839, 1958 U.S. App. LEXIS 5144 (4th Cir. 1958) (decided under prior law).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_61.1-42"><akn:num>§ 61.1-42</akn:num><akn:heading>Commissioner to keep record and publish in bulletin</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Commissioner of Agriculture and Consumer Services shall cause such statement to be accurately copied into a book to be kept for this purpose and shall keep separate and apart the statements returned to him from each leaf tobacco market in the Commonwealth, so as to show the number of pounds of tobacco sold by each market for the sale of leaf tobacco; the number of pounds sold by producers, and the number of pounds resold upon each market. The Commissioner shall keep such books open to the inspection of the public, and shall, on or before the twentieth day of each month, after the receipt of the reports above required to be made to him on or before the tenth day of each month, cause the reports to be published in the bulletin issued by the Department of Agriculture and Consumer Services, and in one or more journals published in the interest of the growth, sale, and manufacture of tobacco in the Commonwealth, or ha ving a large circulation therein. History History. Code 1950, § 61-111; 1968, c. 69. Annotations CASE NOTES This section is ap plicable to auction warehouses.  Export Leaf Tobacco Co. v. American Ins. Co., 260 F.2d 839, 1958 U.S. App. LEXIS 5144 (4th Cir. 1958) (decided under prior law).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_61.1-43"><akn:num>§ 61.1-43</akn:num><akn:heading>Penalty for failure to report sales</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Any warehouse failing to make the report as required by § 61.1-40 shall be subject to a penalty of twenty-five dollars and the costs in the case, to be recovered by any person suing for same. History History. Code 1950, § 61-112; 1968, c. 69.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_61.1-44"><akn:num>§ 61.1-44</akn:num><akn:heading>Manufactured tobacco; false branding</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text If any person use, or permit to be used, on any cask, box or keg of manufactured tobacco, any brand or mark indicating a place or a manufacturer different from the plac e in which, or the manufacturer by whom, it was really manufactured, he shall be guilty of a misdemeanor and shall be punished as provided in § 18.2-12. None of the provisions of this chapter, other than this section, shall be construed to apply to manufactured tobacco. History History. Code 1950, § 61-136; 1968, c. 69.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_61.1-45"><akn:num>§ 61.1-45</akn:num><akn:heading>Nesting punished</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text If any person nest a basket or parcel of tobacco with inferior tobacco, or other things, with intent to defraud the purchaser, he shall be guilty of a misdemeanor and s hall be punished as provided in § 18.2-12. History History. Code 1950, § 61-137; 1968, c. 69.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_61.1-46"><akn:num>§ 61.1-46</akn:num><akn:heading>Publication of insurance</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Every proprietor of a public tobacco warehouse shall keep posted in some conspicuous place upon the premises, a statement showing the amount of insurance he has on such warehouse, the companies in which the insurance has been effected, and the length of time the policies have to run. History History. Code 1950, § 61-141; 1968, c. 69. § 61.1-46.1. Maximum charges for tobacco auction warehouse services. Text Notwithstanding any other provisions of law to the contrary, on and after July 1, 1970, no tobacco auction warehouse shall charge the grower for services rendered in th e sale and handling of flue-cured tobacco any amount or sum in excess of the following: (a) Ware house charges: ten cents per 100 pounds or fraction thereof; (b) Auction fee: twenty-five cents per basket and commission of 2 1/2 percent of the gross amount of each sale. History History. 1970, c. 140. Chapter 5. Prevention of Frauds in Sale of Leaf Tobacco. -360§ 61.1-47. Person making delivery must impart true name of owner; record of purchase or delivery. -360§ 61.1-48. Record and information required where tobacco delivered by person other than grower or landlord; exception. -360§ 61.1-49. Ticket or card to be placed upon tobacco. -360§ 61.1-50. Tickets or cards open to inspection for ten days after delivery of tobacco. -360§ 61.1-51. Violations constituting misdemeanors. -360§ 61.1-52. Punishment for misdemeanor. -360§ 61.1-53. Warehouseman defined. -360§ 61.1-54. Purpose of chapter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_61.1-47"><akn:num>§ 61.1-47</akn:num><akn:heading>Person making delivery must impart true name of owner; record of purchase or delivery</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Every person who shall deliver any leaf tobacco to a warehouseman or to a cooperative marketing association for sale, offer for sale or display for sale thereof, shall impart to such warehouseman or cooperative marketing association, the true name of the owner of such leaf tobacco; and it shall be the duty of such warehouseman or cooperative marketing association to keep a record of such purchase or delivery showing th e quantity of leaf tobacco so delivered, and the name of the owner thereof, given as provided herein. History History. Code 1950, § 61-146; 1968, c. 69. Annotations Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 19 M.J. Warehouses and Warehousemen, § 3. CASE NOTES Editors note. The cases below were decided under prior law. This chapter is constitutional and valid. It is not class legislation, nor does it deny warehousemen the equal protection of the law. Reaves Whse. v. Commonwealth, 141 Va. 194, 126 S.E. 87, 1925 Va. LEXIS 400 (1925), writ of error dismissed, 271 U.S. 690, 46 S. Ct. 481, 70 L. Ed. 1154, 1926 U.S. LEXIS 840 (1926). This chapter does not violate the Fourth Amendment of the federal Constitution or Art. I, § 10 of the Virginia Bill of Rights, prohibiting general search warra nts. The privileges granted by the chapter have no application to search warrants for the detection of crime. Reaves Whse. v. Commonwealth, 141 Va. 194, 126 S.E. 87, 1925 Va. LEXIS 400 (1925), writ of error dismissed, 271 U.S. 690, 46 S. Ct. 481, 70 L. E d. 1154, 1926 U.S. LEXIS 840 (1926); Danville Whse. Co. v. Tobacco Growers Coop. Ass'n, 143 Va. 741, 129 S.E. 739, 1925 Va. LEXIS 301 (1925). It is within the police power of the State, and is not an arbitrary interference with pr ivate business; indeed it recognizes and accommodates itself to the customary methods of such business. Reaves Whse. v. Commonwealth, 141 Va. 194, 126 S.E. 87, 1925 Va. LEXIS 400 (1925), writ of error dismissed, 271 U.S. 690, 46 S. Ct. 481, 70 L. Ed. 115 4, 1926 U.S. LEXIS 840 (1926); Danville Whse. Co. v. Tobacco Growers Coop. Ass'n, 143 Va. 741, 129 S.E. 739, 1925 Va. LEXIS 301 (1925). And is a general law.  This chapter does not violate Va Const., Art. IV, § 14. As it applies throughout the State to all persons and property within the classes specified, and as the classification is reasonable and not arbitrary, the statute is not special, but general. Reaves Whse. v. Commonwealth, 141 Va. 194, 126 S.E. 87, 1925 Va. LEXIS 400 (1925), writ of error dismissed, 271 U.S. 690, 46 S. Ct. 481, 70 L. Ed. 1154, 1926 U.S. L EXIS 840 (1926); Danville Whse. Co. v. Tobacco Growers Coop. Ass'n, 143 Va. 741, 129 S.E. 739, 1925 Va. LEXIS 301 (1925). It was adopted to prevent frauds and if there had been a universal custom of warehouseme n to indulge in such subterfuges whereby frauds were promoted, then it is manifest that the occasion had arisen for the State to intervene to prevent them. Reaves Whse. v. Commonwealth, 141 Va. 194, 126 S.E. 87, 1925 Va. LEXIS 400 (1925), writ of error d ismissed, 271 U.S. 690, 46 S. Ct. 481, 70 L. Ed. 1154, 1926 U.S. LEXIS 840 (1926) (see § 61.1-54.).Danville Whse. Co. v. Tobacco Growers Coop. Ass'n, 143 Va. 741, 129 S.E. 739, 1925 Va. LEXIS 301 (1925). Its motive and effec t are legislative questions.  Whether the motive and effect of this chapter are to promote the business of cooperative marketing associations and to injure that of warehousemen are questions o f public propriety and advantage, which belong exclusively to the legislature and not to the courts. Danville Whse. Co. v. Tobacco Growers Coop. Ass'n, 143 Va. 741, 129 S.E. 739, 1925 Va. LEXIS 301 (1925). Also its wisdom, expediency, justice or injustice are questions to be determined by the General Assembly, and not by the courts. Reaves Whse. v. Commonwealth, 141 Va. 194, 126 S.E. 87, 1925 Va. LEXIS 400 (1925), writ of error dismissed, 271 U.S. 690, 46 S. Ct. 481, 70 L. Ed. 1154, 1926 U.S. LEXIS 840 (1926); Danville Whse. Co. v. Tobacco Gr owers Coop. Ass'n, 143 Va. 741, 129 S.E. 739, 1925 Va. LEXIS 301 (1925). Using fictitious name and refusing inspection are violations.  Placing fictitious name on a pile of tobacco and denying an agent of the cooperative association permission to read the tags upon pile of tobacco in the warehouse are clear violations of this chapter. Reaves Whse. v. Commonwealth, 141 Va. 194, 126 S.E. 87, 1925 Va. LEXIS 400 (1925), writ of error dismissed, 271 U.S. 690, 46 S. Ct. 481, 70 L. Ed. 1154, 1926 U.S. LEXIS 840 (1926). Warehouseman also a dealer.  The true construction of this chapter, considered in its entirety, requires frankness and publicity of the warehouseman at all stages of the transaction and he ca nnot escape these requirements simply because he is likewise a dealer as referred to in the proviso to § 61.1-48. Reaves Whse. v. Commonwealth, 141 Va. 194, 126 S.E. 87, 1925 Va. LEXIS 400 (1925), writ of error dismissed, 271 U.S. 690, 46 S. Ct. 481, 70 L. Ed. 1154, 1926 U.S. LEXIS 840 (1926) (see note to § 61.1-48). Danville Whse. Co. v. Tobacco Growers Coop. Ass'n, 143 Va. 741, 129 S.E. 739, 1925 Va. LEXIS 301 (1925).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_61.1-48"><akn:num>§ 61.1-48</akn:num><akn:heading>Record and information required where tobacco delivered by person other than grower or landlord; exception</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Where leaf tobacco is delivered to a warehouseman or cooperative marketing association for sale, offer for sale or display for sale, by a person other than the grower t hereof, or the landlord of the land upon which the tobacco was grown, it shall be the duty of a warehouseman or cooperative marketing association to keep a record showing the facts required in § 61.1-47; and in addition thereto if possible the name of the person from whom the person delivering the tobacco obtained the same, and the name of the original grower thereof, and the name of the landlord upon whose land the tobacco was grown, if the same was grown by a tenant. And such person, other than the grower or landlord, shall impart to the warehouseman or cooperative marketing association the true name of the person from whom he obtained the tobacco, and the name of the grower thereof and the landlord. Provided, however, that this section shall not apply to licensed leaf tobacco dealers offering for resale tobacco once sold upon the warehouse floor, and with respect to which the provisions of this chapter have previously been complied with. History History. Code 1950, § 61-147; 1968, c. 69. Annotations CASE NOTES The proviso is limited to this section, and does not apply to the other sections of this chapter or relieve the warehouseman of his obligations under any of such sections. Reaves Whse. v. Commonwealth, 141 Va. 194, 126 S.E. 87, 1925 Va. LEXIS 400 (1925), writ of error dismissed, 271 U.S. 690, 46 S. Ct. 481, 70 L. Ed. 1154, 1926 U.S. LEXIS 8 40 (1926) (decided under prior law). And does not affect du ties under other sections.  Notwithstanding the proviso, it is the duty of the warehouseman under § 61.1-47 to keep a true record, and it is also his duty under § 61.1-49 to display up on tobacco offered for sale the ticket or card showing the record required by this section. And, under § 61.1-51, the warehouseman who buys or sells tobacco, as set forth in this chapter, knowing that the name used is false or fictitious, is guilty of a misdemeanor. Reaves Whse. v. Commonwealth, 141 Va. 194, 126 S.E. 87, 1925 Va. LEXIS 400 (1925), writ of error dismissed, 271 U.S. 690, 46 S. Ct. 481, 70 L. Ed. 1154, 1926 U.S. LEXIS 840 (1926) (decided under prior law).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_61.1-49"><akn:num>§ 61.1-49</akn:num><akn:heading>Ticket or card to be placed upon tobacco</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Such warehouseman or cooperative marketing association shall also place upon all leaf tobacco delivered to him or to it for sale, offer for sale, or display for sale, a ticket or card which shall state the matters and things required to be recorded by the warehouseman or cooperative marketing association by §§ 61.1-47 and 61.1-48. History History. Code 1950, § 61-148; 1968, c. 69.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_61.1-50"><akn:num>§ 61.1-50</akn:num><akn:heading>Tickets or cards open to inspection for ten days after delivery of tobacco</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text All cards or tickets kept, prepared or placed upon tobacco as required herein, shall, for the period of ten days after the delivery of such tobacco, be open to the insp ection of the representative of any public tobacco warehouse, or tobacco growers cooperative association, during regular business hours and such representative shall have access to the place where such cards or tickets are kept for the purpose of such in spection. History History. Code 1950, § 61-149; 1968, c. 69.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_61.1-51"><akn:num>§ 61.1-51</akn:num><akn:heading>Violations constituting misdemeanors</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Any person who shall give a fictitious or false name to the warehouseman or cooperative marketing association hereinbefore referred to, or who shall fail to give to suc h warehouseman or cooperative marketing association the true name of the owner of such leaf tobacco or the person from whom the tobacco was obtained, or the grower and the landlord, upon delivering the same as aforesaid, shall be guilty of a misdemeanor. Any warehouseman or cooperative marketing association who shall fail to comply with any of the provisions of this chapter, or who shall deny to any such representative the privilege of inspection or access as provided in § 61.1-50, shall be guilty of a misdemeanor. Any warehouseman or cooperative marketing association who shall buy or sell leaf tobacco as above set forth, knowing that the name in which the tobacco is sold, or any name given pursuant to the provisions hereof, is false or fictitious, shall be guilty of a misdemeanor. History History. Code 1950, § 61-150; 1968, c. 69.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_61.1-52"><akn:num>§ 61.1-52</akn:num><akn:heading>Punishment for misdemeanor</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Any person guilty of a misdemeanor under the provisions of this chapter shall be punished as provided in § 18.2-12. History History. Code 1950, § 61-151; 1968, c. 69.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_61.1-53"><akn:num>§ 61.1-53</akn:num><akn:heading>Warehouseman defined</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The term warehouseman as used in this chapter means any person, firm or corporation engaged in the business of selling leaf tobacco at auction, for a commission or for any other consideration. History History. Code 1950, § 61-152; 1968, c. 69.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_61.1-54"><akn:num>§ 61.1-54</akn:num><akn:heading>Purpose of chapter</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The purpose of this chapter is to prevent frauds in the handling and sale of leaf tobacco. History History. Code 1950, § 61-153; 1968, c. 69. Chapter 6. Fees for Sale of Burley Tobacco. -360§ 61.1-55. Commission and basket charge. -360§ 61.1-56. Penalty for violation.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_61.1-55"><akn:num>§ 61.1-55</akn:num><akn:heading>Commission and basket charge</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text No person, firm, association, corporation, partnership, copartnership or other legal entity, who or which operates any warehouse in which burley tobacco is sold at publ ic auction, shall charge or receive any commission in excess of four percent of the sales price of such tobacco, nor shall any basket charge be in excess of twenty-five cents per basket, which commission and basket charge shall constitute the entire amou nt charged by the warehouse operator in connection with such sale; provided, however, that on or before the opening day of the market in any year, the warehouse operator may elect to charge a commission of not exceeding seventy-five cents per 100 pounds, which commission shall constitute the entire charge made in connection with the sale of tobacco throughout that market season at the warehouse for which such election is made. History History. Code 1950, § 61-154; 1968, c. 69; 2000, c. 380. Annotations The 2000 amendments. The 2000 amendment by c. 380 substituted four percent for three percent. Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 19 M.J. Warehouses and Warehousemen, § 3.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_61.1-56"><akn:num>§ 61.1-56</akn:num><akn:heading>Penalty for violation</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Any such operator of a warehouse violating the provisions of this chapter shall be guilty of a misdemeanor, and upon conviction shall be punished as provided in § 18 .2-12. History History. Code 1950, § 61-155; 1968, c. 69. Chapter 7. Handling and Sale of Burley Tobacco. -360§ 61.1-57. Enforcement by Commissioner of Agriculture and Consumer Services; rules and regulations. -360§ 61.1-58. Commingling burley and other tobacco; moving tobacco before sale. -360§ 61.1-59. Sales of burley tobacco. -360§ 61.1-60. Information to be accurate and substantiated. -360§ 61.1-61. Penalty for violation.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_61.1-57"><akn:num>§ 61.1-57</akn:num><akn:heading>Enforcement by Commissioner of Agriculture and Consumer Services; rules and regulations</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Board of Agriculture and Consumer Services shall have authority to establish rules and regulations for the enforcement of this chapter. The Commissioner is hereby v ested with the authority to administer and enforce the provisions of this law and to enforce reasonable rules and regulations not inconsistent with the provisions hereof, for the purpose of carrying out the provisions of this chapter. History History. Code 1950, § 61-156; 1950, p. 66; 1968, c. 69.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_61.1-58"><akn:num>§ 61.1-58</akn:num><akn:heading>Commingling burley and other tobacco; moving tobacco before sale</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text It shall be unlawful for any person to commingle, mix, place in same basket with other tobacco or in any other manner or means to handle tobacco so as to lose its ident ity, for the purpose of sale at auction, loose-leaf tobacco grown by one producer with loose-leaf burley tobacco grown by any other producer, or of the same producer after being placed on the loose-leaf floor. After tobacco is weighed and set upon the warehouse floor for sale no basket of tobacco shall be moved, without the consent of the owner, from its place on the floor un til sale is confirmed by the owner of same. This shall not apply to official inspectors of the Department of Agriculture and Consumer Services, who in the course of their duties find it necessary to move piles of tobacco. History History. Code 1950, § 61-157; 1950, p. 66; 1968, c. 69.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_61.1-59"><akn:num>§ 61.1-59</akn:num><akn:heading>Sales of burley tobacco</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Sales of burley tobacco at warehouses or loosefloors shall be conducted so as to conform to one of the following methods: (1) Sale s to be at the rate of not more than 90,000 pounds per hour, per set of buyers, or (2) Sales to be at the rate of not more than 360 baskets per hour per set of buyers. History History. Code 1950, § 61-158; 1950, p. 66; 1968, c. 69.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_61.1-60"><akn:num>§ 61.1-60</akn:num><akn:heading>Information to be accurate and substantiated</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Any information pertaining to weights of tobacco sold, prices paid or amounts of tobacco handled, disseminated by any warehouseman, his employees or agents shall be acc urate and substantiated by records kept at the warehouse or loosefloor. History History. Code 1950, § 61-159; 1950, p. 67; 1968, c. 69.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_61.1-61"><akn:num>§ 61.1-61</akn:num><akn:heading>Penalty for violation</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The violation of any provision of this law or valid rules and regulations promulgated hereunder shall constitute a misdemeanor and shall be punishable by fine of not le ss than $50 for the first offense and for each subsequent offense shall be punished by a fine of not less than $500 or imprisonment in jail not less than thirty days, or both such fine and imprisonment in the discretion of the court or jury. History History. Code 1950, § 61-160; 1950, p. 67; 1968, c. 69.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section></akn:body></akn:act></akn:akomaNtoso>