<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akn:akomaNtoso xmlns:akn="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><akn:act><akn:meta><akn:identification source="#cosilico"><akn:FRBRWork><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-05.1" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-05.1" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2023-03-01" name="release" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#virginia-general-assembly" /><akn:FRBRcountry value="us-va" /><akn:FRBRnumber value="title-05.1" /><akn:FRBRname value="act" /></akn:FRBRWork><akn:FRBRExpression><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-05.1/eng@2023-03-01" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-05.1/eng@2023-03-01" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2023-03-01" name="publication" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#lexisnexis" /><akn:FRBRlanguage language="eng" /></akn:FRBRExpression><akn:FRBRManifestation><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-05.1/eng@2023-03-01/main.xml" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-05.1/eng@2023-03-01/main.xml" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="conversion" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#cosilico" /></akn:FRBRManifestation></akn:identification><akn:references source="#cosilico"><akn:TLCOrganization eId="virginia-general-assembly" href="/ontology/organization/us-va/general-assembly" showAs="Virginia General Assembly" /><akn:TLCOrganization eId="lexisnexis" href="/ontology/organization/lexisnexis" showAs="LexisNexis" /><akn:TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="/ontology/organization/cosilico" showAs="Cosilico" /></akn:references></akn:meta><akn:preface><akn:docTitle>Title 05.1. </akn:docTitle></akn:preface><akn:body><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-1"><akn:num>§ 5.1-1</akn:num><akn:heading>(Effective until September 1, 2025) Definitions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text When used in this title, unless expressly stated otherwise: Aircraft means any contrivance now known, or hereafter invented, used, or designed for navigation of or flight in the air, including a balloon or other contrivance designed for maneuvering in airspace at an altitude greater than 24 inches above ground or water level, except that any contrivance now or hereafter invented of fixed or flexib le wing design, operating without the assistance of any motor, engine, or other mechanical propulsive device, which is designed to utilize the feet and legs of the operator or operators as the sole means of initiating and sustaining forward motion during the launch and of providing the point of contact with the ground upon landing and commonly called a hang glider shall not be included within this definition. Aircraft based in this Commonwealth means an aircraft that is either (i) domiciled in a county, city, or town in the Commonwealth or (ii) parked in a county, city, or town in the Commonwealth when not in flight for the period of time specified in § 5.1-5. Airman means any individual, including the person in command and any pilot, mechanic, or member of the crew, who engages in the navigation of aircraft while under way within Virginia airspace; any individual who is directly in charge of the inspection, maintenance, overhauling, or repair of aircraft, aircraft engines, propellers, or acces sories; and any individual who serves in the capacity of aircraft dispatcher. Air navigation facility means any airport ground or air navigation facility, other tha n one owned and operated by the United States, used in, available for use in, or designed for use in aid of air navigation, including any structures, buildings, mechanisms, lights, beacons, markers, communicating systems, or other instrumentalities or de vices, and any combination of any or all of such facilities, used or useful as an aid, or constituting any advantage or convenience, to the safe taking off, navigation, and landing of aircraft; in the safe and efficient operation or maintenance of an air port; in the safe, efficient and convenient handling or processing of aviation passengers, mail or cargo; or in the servicing or maintenance of aircraft or ground equipment. Airport means any area of land or water which is used, or intended for public use, for the landing and takeoff of aircraft, and any appurtenant areas that are used, or intended for use, for airport buildings or other airport facilities or rights-of-way, easements and together with all airport buildings and facilities located thereon. Airport hazard means any structure, object or natural growth, or use of land that obst ructs the airspace required for the flight of aircraft in landing or taking off at an airport or is otherwise hazardous to such landing or taking off of aircraft. Airspace means all that space above the land and waters within the boundary of the Com monwealth. Board means the Virginia Aviation Board. Civil aircraft means any aircraft other than a public aircraft. Commercial aircraft means any civil aircraft used in flight activity for compensation or for hire. Contract carrier by aircraft or contract carrier means any person not included under the definitions of common carrier by aircraft or restricted common carrier by aircraf t as defined in § 5.1-89 who, under special and individual contracts or agreements, and whether directly or by a lease or any other arrangement, transports passengers or property by aircraft for compensation and in the transportation of passengers does not charge individual fares. Department means the Department of Aviation. Drop zone means any locality whether over land or water that is used, or intended for use, for the landing and recovery of sky divers or parachutists using a parachute or other contrivance designed for sport jumping. Fighter or attack jet means a jet-powered aircraft designed for military (i) combat tr aining or (ii) operational mission execution. Landing area or landing field means any locality, whether over land or water, including airports and intermediate landing fields, which is used or intended to be used for the landing and takeoff of aircraft and open to the public for such use, whether or not facilities are provided for the sheltering, servicing, or repair of aircraft or for receiving or discharging passengers or cargo. Person means any individual, corporation, government, political subdivision of the Com monwealth, or governmental subdivision or agency, business trust, estate, trust, partnership, two or more of any of the foregoing having a joint or common interest, or any other legal or commercial entity. Public aircraft means an aircraft used exclusively in the service of any state, or pol itical subdivision thereof, or the federal government. Public aircraft includes any fighter or attack jet that is leased or owned by a private entity, provided that the aircraft operations are conducted exclusively for the purpose of military com bat training in service to the federal government. History History. Code 1950, § 5-1; 1966, c. 576; 1970, c. 717; 1975, c. 561; 19 79, c. 272; 1980, c. 721; 1988, c. 588; 2011, c. 809; 2018, cc. 357, 441. Annotations Editors note. At its regular session of 1964 the General Assembly directed the Virginia Code Commission to revise certain titles of the Code, including Title 5, relating to avi ation, and in July, 1965, the Commission sent to the Governor and General Assembly its report containing the proposed revision of Title 5, which was published as House Document 2 of the 1966 session. The Code Commissions draft of the revision, as ame nded by the General Assembly, became chapter 576 of the Acts of 1966. Effective July 1, 1966, it repealed Title 5 and enacted in lieu thereof a new Title 5.1. Some of the cases cited in the notes under the various sections of this title were decided under corresponding provisions of Title 5. Acts 1966, c. 576, clauses 3-6, provide as follows: 3. All acts and parts of acts, all sections of the Code of Virginia, and all provisions of municipal charters inconsistent with the provisions of this act are , except as otherwise provided, repealed to the extent of such inconsistency. 4. The repeal of Title 5 effective as of July 1, 1966, shall not affect any act or offense done or committed, or any penalty or forfeiture incurred, or any ri ght established, accrued or accruing on or before such date, or any prosecution, suit or action pending on that date. Except as in this act otherwise provided, neither the repeal of Title 5 of the Code of Virginia nor the enactment of Title 5.1 shall app ly to offenses committed prior to July 1, 1966, and prosecutions for such offenses shall be governed by the prior law, which is continued in effect for that purpose. For the purposes of this act, an offense was committed prior to July 1, 1966 if any of t he essential elements of the offense occurred prior thereto. 5. Whenever in Title 5.1 any of the conditions, requirements, provisions or contents of any section, article or chapter of Title 5, as such title existed prio r to July 1, 1966, are transferred in the same or in modified form to a new section, article or chapter of Title 5.1, and whenever any such former section, article or chapter of Title 5 is given a new number in Title 5.1, all references to any such forme r section, article or chapter of Title 5 appearing elsewhere in the Code of Virginia than in Title 5.1 shall be construed to apply to the new or renumbered section, article or chapter containing such conditions, requirements, provisions or contents or po rtions thereof. 6. It is the intention of the General Assembly that this act shall be liberally construed to effect the purposes set out herein, and if any clause, sentence, paragraph or section of this act shall ever be declared unconstitutional, it shall be deemed severable, and the remainder of this act shall continue in full force and effect. Chapter 717 of the Acts of 1966 provides: Whenever, during the regular session of the General Assembly of Virginia of nineteen hundred sixty-six there shall h ave been enacted any statute purporting to revise, rearrange, amend and recodify any title of the Code of Virginia, such statute shall be deemed to have been enacted prior in time to any other statute enacted at such session adding to, repealing or amend ing and reenacting any portion of such title; and every such other statute shall be deemed to have so added to, repealed or amended and reenacted, as the case may be, such title as so revised, rearranged, amended and recodified; provided, however, that e ffect shall be given to any such other, or subsequent, statute only to the extent of any apparent changes in the law as it existed prior to such session. Acts 2018, c. 441, cl. 2, as amended by Acts 2022, c. 136, cl. 1 provides: That the provisions of this act shall expire on July 1, 2025. Acts 2018, cc. 357 and 441, cl. 2 provides: That the provisions of this act shall expire on July 1, 2025. The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendment by c. 809 rewrote the section. The 2018 amendments. The 2018 amendments by cc. 357 and 441 are identical, expire July 1, 2025, and added the definition for Fighter or attack jet; and in the definition for Public aircraft, added the second sentence. For expiration date, see Editors note. Law Review. For survey of Virginia law on administrative law and utility regulation for the year 1978-1979, see 66 Va. L. Rev. 193 (1980). For an article, Thou Canst Not Fly High With Borrowed Wings: Airline Finance and Bankruptcy Code Section 110, see 8 Geo. Mason L. Rev. 41 (1999). CASE NOTES Ti tle applies to airports operated by government agencies.  The reenactment and amendment of Title 5 in 1966 as Title 5.1 emphasizes the intention of the General Assembly to make the general law apply to the operation of a irports by governmental sub...</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-2"><akn:num>§ 5.1-2</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1979, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>272. § 5.1-2.1. Virginia Aviation Commission continued as Virginia Aviation Board; membership; terms; Chairman. Text A. The Virgini a Aviation Commission, a public body corporate and politic, is hereby continued within the Department of Aviation as a political subdivision of the Commonwealth and shall hereafter be known as the Virginia Aviation Board. The Board shall consist of eight members, selected so far as practicable from different geographic areas of the Commonwealth, appointed by the Governor, subject to confirmation by the General Assembly, to serve at the pleasure of the Governor. Members shall serve for four-year terms an d no member shall serve for more than two full successive terms. Initial appointments to the Board shall be made as follows: one shall be for a term of one year, two shall be for terms of two years, two shall be for terms of three years, and two shall be for terms of four years each and thereafter all appointments shall be for terms of four years each. The Chairman of the Board shall be appointed by the Governor. B. Whenever th e Board shall acquire ownership or jurisdiction over an airport or airports previously operated by an agency of the United States, there may be a member appointed to the Board by the President of the United States. Such member shall have the powers and d uties of other members of the Board only with respect to the airport or airports so acquired. C. There may b e a member of the Board from any county or city wherein the Board acquires or constructs an airport, to be elected by the governing body of the county or city and to serve at its pleasure. Such member shall have the powers and duties of other members of the Board only with respect to such airport. If the Board acquires an airport which was constructed by one political subdivision but is located in another, the political subdivision which constructed the airport, rather than the political subdivision in which it is located, shall be represented on the Board. History History. 1979, c. 272; 1980, c. 750; 1985, c. 448. Annotations Law Review. For survey of Virginia law on administrative law and utility regulation for the year 1978-1979, see 66 Va. L. Rev. 193 (1980). § 5.1-2.2. Powers and duties of Board. Text The Board shall exercise the following powers and duties: 1. Provi de a means of citizen access to the Department; 2. Provide a means of publicizing the policies and programs of the Department in order to educate the public and elicit public support for Department activities; 3. Monitor the policies and activities of the Department and have the right of access to departmental information; 4. Advise the Governor and the Director on matters relating to the Commonwealths aviation policies and programs; 5. Promulgate such rules and regulations relating to airports, landing fields and other aviation facilities, aircraft, and such other kindred matters and things as may be proper and neces sary to promote and develop safe aviation practices and operations; and 6. Develop on behalf of the Department recommendations for distribution of funds to localities by the State Corporation Commission for aviation development through the end of the 1978-80 biennium, after which time the Board shall be responsible for the allocation on behalf of the Department of all such funds as provided in this act, which funds shall be distributed by the Department in accordance with such allocation. History History. 1979, c. 272; 1980, c. 306; 1984, c. 720; 2017, c. 793. Annotations Editors note. The words this act in subdivision 6 of this section refer to Acts 1979, c. 272, which enacted §§ 5.1-1.1 through 5.1-1.7 and amended former §§ 2.1-1, 2.1-51.24 and numerous sections throughout this title. The 2017 amendments. The 2017 amendment by c. 793, in subdivision 5, deleted air traffic, construction and inspection of aircraft, qualifications and licensing of airmen, stunt fl ying following and other aviation facilities, aircraft. § 5.1-2.2:1. Further powers and duties of the Board. Text The Board shall have all the powers necessary or convenient to carry out the purposes of this chapter including, but not limited to, the power: 1. To su e in its own name, to have a seal, and to have perpetual succession; 2. To execute such contracts and other instruments and take such other action as may be necessary or convenient to carry out the purposes of this chapter; 3. To plan, establish, develop, construct, enlarge, improve, maintain, equip, operate, regulate, and protect airports and air navigation facilities, within this Commonwealth and within an y adjoining state, including the acquisition, construction, installation, equipment, maintenance, and operation at such airports of buildings and other facilities for the servicing of aircraft or for the comfort and accommodation of air travelers, and th e purchase and sale of supplies, goods, and commodities as an incident to the operation of its airport properties. For such purposes the Board may, by purchase, gift, devise, lease, condemnation, or otherwise, acquire property, real or personal, or any i nterest therein, including easements in airport hazards or land outside the boundaries of an airport or airport site, as are necessary to permit the removal, elimination, obstruction marking or obstruction lighting of airport hazards or to prevent the es tablishment of airport hazards, or for the enlargement of an airport constructed or acquired under this subdivision 3; provided, however, such power of eminent domain shall not extend to the taking of any radio or television towers or installation in exi stence on June 27, 1958; 4. To acquire, by purchase, gift, devise, or lease, existing airports and air navigation facilities; 5. To establish or acquire and maintain airports in, over, and upon any public waters of this Commonwealth or any submerged lands under such public waters; and to construct and maintain t erminal buildings, landing floats, causeways, roadways, and bridges for approaches to or connecting with any such airport, and landing floats and breakwaters for the protection thereof; 6. To construct, or permit the construction of, for sale or lease, on such terms and conditions as the Board may deem proper, industrial, commercial or recreational facilities and approac hes thereto and appurtenances thereof, on any lands of the Board not acquired by eminent domain and not needed for operational use of an airport owned or operated by it; provided, that any such factory or manufacturing facility shall be so constructed as not to constitute an airport hazard. In the exercise of the powers conferred by this subdivision, the Board shall comply with any applicable zoning restrictions of the political subdivision in which any airport or facility is, or is proposed to be locat ed. History History. 1980, c. 750. Annotations OPINIONS OF THE ATTORNEY GENERAL Aviation Board may borrow money and issue note for infrastructure projects.  If infrastructure projects fall within the context of constructing, enlarging, or improving an airport facility, the Aviation Board may enter into, execute, and d eliver a loan agreement to borrow money and issue a note, subject to the receipt of appropriations or grants. See opinion of Attorney General to Mr. George P. Ramsey III, Chairman, Virginia Aviation Board, 01-032, 2001 Va. AG LEXIS 15 (3/23/01). § 5.1-2.2:2. Commercial air service plan. Text A. The Board s hall develop and review every five years a commercial air service plan for commercial air service airports within the Commonwealth. In developing and reviewing such plan, the Board shall (i) analyze trends in commercial air service generally, (ii) analyz e the current and projected future demographic and economic trends related to air travel needs in the Commonwealth, (iii) solicit input from other appropriate stakeholders, (iv) consider any other factors determined to be appropriate by the Board, and (v ) establish reasonable goals for commercial air service based on clauses (i) through (iv). B. In developi ng the plan pursuant to subsection A, the Board shall coordinate with each commercial air service airport. C. Prior to th e allocation of funds pursuant to § 33.2-1526.6, the Board shall ensure that any requested funds are not inconsistent with the Boards commercial air service plan and that no commercial service airport is penalized for not meeting goals set forth i n such commercial air service plan. History History. 2017, c. 709; 2020, cc. 1230, 1275. Annotations The 2020 amendments. The 2020 amendments by cc. 1230 and 1275 are identical and substituted § 33.2-1526.6 for subdivision A 3 of § 58.1-638 in subsection C. § 5.1-2.2:3. Transparency and accountability in the use of Commonwealth Aviation Fund revenues. Text A. By November 1 of each year, the Board shall report to the Governor and the General Assembly on the use of Commonwealth Aviation Fund revenues the previous fiscal year. The report shall include at a minimum the following: 1. The u se of entitlement funds allocated pursuant to subdivision B 1 of § 33.2-1526.6 by each air carrier airport, including the amount of funds that are unobligated; 2. The award and use of discretionary funds allocated for air carrier and reliever airports pursuant to subdivision B 2 a (1) of § 33.2-1526.6 by every such airport; 3. The award and use of discretionary funds allocated for general aviation airports pursuant to subdivision B 2 a (2) of § 33.2-1526.6 by every such airport; and 4. The award and use of discretionary funds allocated for all airports pursuant to subdivision B 2 b of § 33.2-1526.6 by every such airport.Such report shall also include the status of ongoing projects funded in whole or in part by the Commonwealth Aviation Fund pursuant to § 33.2-1526.6. B. Each year p rior to the release of entitlement funds allocated pursuant to subdivision B 1 of § 33.2-1526.6, each air carrier airport shall submit a plan that outlines the plann...</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-3"><akn:num>§ 5.1-3</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1979, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>272. Annotations Cross references. As to the Department of Aviation, see §§ 5.1-1.1 through 5.1-1.7. As to the Virginia Aviation Board, see §§ 5.1-2.1 through 5.1-2.3.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-4"><akn:num>§ 5.1-4</akn:num><akn:heading>Aircraft for use of Department; construction, etc</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>, of aviation facilities by Department. Text Within the limits of appropriations made for such purposes, the Department is authorized to purchase aircraft for the use of the Department, provided, however, that the Department shall not purchase any new or used executive aircraft unless specifically requested in the Governors budget and approved by the General Assembly in the Appropriations Act, and to purchase land for and to construct, maintain and improve ai rports, landing fields and other aviation facilities within the Commonwealth for the promotion of aviation in the interest of the public; and neither the appropriations nor any part thereof may be transferred or used for any other purpose than is specifi ed in this section. History History. Code 1950, § 5-4; 1966, c. 576; 1970, c. 717; 1979, c. 272.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-5"><akn:num>§ 5.1-5</akn:num><akn:heading>Registration of aircraft</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. Every resid ent of the Commonwealth owning a civil aircraft, every nonresident owning a civil aircraft based in the Commonwealth for more than 90 days during any calendar year, and every owner of an aerial application aircraft operating within the Commonwealth or of a civil aircraft operated in the Commonwealth as a for-hire intrastate air carrier shall register such aircraft with the Department before such aircraft is operated in the Commonwealth. Any owner of an unmanned aircraft as defined in § 19.2-60.1 shal l not be required to register such aircraft. B. The Departm ent shall provide for the issuance, expiration, suspension, and revocation of aircraft registration in accordance with regulations promulgated by the Board. For the purposes of the tax imposed pursuant to Chapter 15 (§ 58.1-1500 et seq.) of Title 58.1 , including any credit granted pursuant to § 58.1-1504 against such tax, such aircraft registration shall be considered the licensure required by such chapter. The Department shall furnish any necessary forms pursuant to the issuance of such registrat ion and may assess a fee for such issuance not in excess of $5 annually. The Department may, in lieu of issuing aircraft registration required by subsection A, issue commercial aircraft registration to air carriers and commercial dealers and issue to non commercial dealers noncommercial dealer fleet registration, to cover all aircraft owned by such dealers and all aircraft for sale held by dealers on a consignment basis from an aircraft manufacturer. The Department may assess a fee not in excess of $50 a nnually for any such noncommercial dealer fleet registrations issued and a fee not in excess of $100 annually for any such commercial fleet registrations issued. The fee for a commercial single aircraft registration shall not be in excess of $10 annually . C. Notwithstan ding the provisions of subsection A, no aircraft shall be required to be registered if the aircraft is brought into the Commonwealth solely for major maintenance or major repair. An aircraft owner shall provide proof that the aircraft is based at an airp ort in another state, shown by evidence of a hangar or tie-down lease for a minimum of 12 months prior to the aircraft being brought into the Commonwealth, and proof of the work being performed in the Commonwealth, shown by presentation of invoices that describe such work. History History. Code 1950, § 5-5; 1966, c. 576; 1970, c. 717; 1974, c. 431; 19 79, c. 272; 1980, c. 721; 2017, c. 793; 2020, c. 1255; 2021, Sp. Sess. I, cc. 45, 46, 372. Annotations Cross references. As to taxes levied on sale and use of aircraft, see § 58.1-1502. The 2017 amendments. The 2017 amendment by c. 793 rewrote the section. The 2020 amendments. The 2020 amendment by c. 1255, in subsection A, substituted 90 days during any calendar year for 60 days during any 12-month period and added subs ection C. The 2021 Sp. Sess. I amendments. The 2021 amendments by Sp. Sess. I, cc. 45 and 46, effective July 1, 2021, are identical, and added the last sentence in subsection A. The 2021 amendment by Sp. Sess. I, c. 372, effective July 1, 2021, in subsection B, substituted For the for Such aircraft registration or registration requirement shall be considered the licensure or licensure requirement for and added including any credit granted pursuant to § 58.1-1504 against such tax, such aircraft registration shall be considered the licensure required by such chapter.  Law Review. For survey of Virginia law on taxation for the year 1973-1974, see 60 Va. L. Rev. 1607 (1974). For survey of Virginia administrative law and utility regulation for the year 1978-1979, see 66 Va. L. Rev. 193 (1980). CASE NOTES Tax consequences for nonresident owners.  Section 58.1-1502 levies a tax on the use in the Commonwealth of any aircraft required to be licensed by the Department of Aviation pursuant to this section, whic h requires that every nonresident owning a civil aircraft based in Virginia over sixty days during any 12 month period shall obtain a license; thus plaintiffs aircraft was required to be licensed and was properly taxed accordingly. Charles E. Smith M gt., Inc. v. Department of Taxation, 251 Va. 353, 467 S.E.2d 772, 1996 Va. LEXIS 35 (1996).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-6"><akn:num>§ 5.1-6</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1988, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>45.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-7"><akn:num>§ 5.1-7</akn:num><akn:heading>Licensing of airports and landing areas</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Except as provided in § 5.1-7.2, every person, before operating an airport or landing area or adding or extending a runway, shall first secure from the Department a license. The application therefor shall be made on the form prescribed and furnished by the Department and shall be accompanied by a fee not exceeding $100. Such license shall be issued for a period not to exceed seven years and shall be renewed every seven years. Before issuing such license, the Department shall require th e holder of such license to furnish proof of financial responsibility prescribed in Chapter 8.2 (§ 5.1-88.7 et seq.). It shall be unlawful for any person to operate any airport or landing area which is open to the general public for the landing or departure of any aircraft until a lice nse therefor shall be issued by the Department. Before issuing such license for the establishment of a new airport, the Department shall investigate the location of such airport or landing area with the relation to i ts proximity to and its runway orientation in relation to any other airport or landing area and shall provide for the safety of civil aircraft alighting thereon or departing therefrom. If the proposed airport or landing area shall be so situated as to en danger aircraft using the same or any other airport or landing area in close proximity, and if proper provisions have not been made in all other respects for the safety of aircraft alighting thereon or departing therefrom, the license shall not be grante d. To be licensed, an airport required to be licensed under § 5.1-7.2 must meet this criterion and any applicable requirement provided for in regulation promulgated under this section, but no others. The Board may, by regulation, adopt any other requirements for licensure that are related to the safety of civil aircraft using such airport or landing area. Any airpor t having a license issued prior to October 1, 1995, and not meeting one or more minimum standards as defined in Part III (24 VAC 5-20-120 et seq.) of the Virginia Aviation Regulations, shall be exempt from having to comply with those noncomplying standar ds for as long as the airport remains an active public-use facility unless those noncomplying standards are caused by natural growth. Should such airport cease to be open to the public for one year, and subsequently reopen, it shall be required to comply with all applicable minimum standards for licensure. In addition to the above safety requirements, before a license is initially issued, the Department shall consider the reviews and comments of appropriate state agencies coordinated by the Department of Environmental Quality, and shall cause a public hearing to be held concerning the economic, social and environmental effects of the location or runway orientation of the airport or landing area if the facility is listed in the Virginia Air Transportation System Plan; however, such coordinated review by the Department of Environmental Quality shall not exceed 90 days after the Department has requested review by the Department of Environmental Quality. The public hearing required by this section shall be conducted by the Department of Environmental Quality in the jurisdiction in which the airport or landing area is located, after publication of notice of the hearing in a newspaper of general circulation in such jurisdict ion at least 10 days in advance of such hearing. Any license issued shall describe the number of runways, the length and orientation of each runway and/or, if appropriate, the landing area. If a runway is to be extended or new runways are to be added, a revised license shall be applied for from the Department. If the airport or landing area is listed in th e Virginia Air Transportation System Plan, the Department shall consider the reviews and comments of appropriate state agencies, coordinated by the Department of Environmental Quality, and shall cause a public hearing to be held concerning the economic, social and environmental effects of such changes to the license. Whenever a public hearing is called for herein, if there has been a public hearing associated with the development of any environmental documents to comply with the rec eipt of federal funds, the Department and the Department of Environmental Quality may rely on such document or hearing in carrying out their respective duties set out in this section. If an airport or landing area cannot meet the requirements for licensure that have been adopted by the Virginia Aviation Board, or having met those requirements cannot maintain compliance, the Department may issue conditional licenses to allow time for the airport or landing areas to take steps to meet those requirements or may revoke any license issued, if requirements for licensure are not met or cannot be met. Any party aggrieved by the granting or refusal to grant any such license shall have a right of appeal to the circuit court of the jurisdiction where the airport or land ing area is to be located, which appeal shall be filed in accordance with the Administrative Process Act (§ 2.2-4000 et seq.). All airports or landing areas that hold licenses or permits shall be issued new licenses, without charge, on or before October 1, 1995, describing the number, length an d orientation of the runway or runways or, if appropriate, the landing area, which shall be valid for up to seven years. The length of the new license term may be staggered so that all licenses will not become renewable at the same time. If any airport l anding area does not meet the current requirements for licensure, a new license may be issued. History History. Code 1950, § 5-7; 1966, c. 576; 1979, c. 272; 1980, c. 721; 19 81, c. 326; 1991, c. 126; 1995, cc. 682, 690; 1996, cc. 148, 303; 2011, c. 75. Annotations The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendment by c. 75 deleted of this title from the end of the second paragraph; in the first sentence in the fifth paragraph, inserted (24 VAC 5-20-120 et seq.), deleted (VR 165-01-02:1) following Virginia Aviation Regulations, and added unless those noncomplying standards are caused by natural growth; made minor stylistic changes in the sixth paragraph; and updated the statutory reference in the next-to-last paragraph. Law Review. For article on state constitutions and the environment, see 58 Va. L. Rev. 193 (1972). For survey of Virginia administrative law and utility regulation for the year 1978-1979, see 66 Va. L. Rev. 193 (1980). CASE NOTES Editors note. The cases annotated below were decided under former § 5.1-8. This section is a licensing statute, which makes it unlawful for any person, city, count y or department of government to operate any airport without first obtaining a permit therefor from the Commission (now Board). Lillard v. Fairfax County Airport Auth., 208 Va. 8, 155 S.E.2d 338, 1967 Va. LEXIS 177 (1967). And should be applied meaningfully.  This section should be applied meaningfully. Whitman v. Waltrip, 210 Va. 40, 168 S.E.2d 109, 1969 Va. LEXIS 192 (1969). The University of Virginia is within the terms of this section requiring a permit to ope rate an airport engaged in commercial aviation. And the State Corporation Commission may issue it a permit although the main purpose of the University is the training of students in scientific aeronautics, and only an incidental portion of the transactio ns at the airport are commercial. Batcheller v. Commonwealth, 176 Va. 109, 10 S.E.2d 529, 1940 Va. LEXIS 238 (1940). Board must investigate safety conditions before issuing permit.  Before issuing a permit to operate an airport, the Commission (now Board) shall investigate and determine certain safety conditions with regard to the operation o f the airport, its location, its proximity to other airports, and whether in the proposed use thereof proper provisions have not been made in other respects for the safety of aircraft alighting thereon or departing therefrom. In the event of unfa vorable findings, the permit shall be refused. Lillard v. Fairfax County Airport Auth., 208 Va. 8, 155 S.E.2d 338, 1967 Va. LEXIS 177 (1967). Duty of Board not altered by act creating county airport authority.  Chapter 642, Acts 1964, authorizing the establishment of the Fairfax County Airport Authority does not deprive the State Corporation Commission of the power and d uty imposed on it by this section. Lillard v. Fairfax County Airport Auth., 208 Va. 8, 155 S.E.2d 338, 1967 Va. LEXIS 177 (1967). Matters not requiring denial of perm it.  The noise incident to the operation of an airport engaged in commercial aviation, the mere apprehension of injury to homes in the vicinity from the falling of air planes, the depreciation of the value of property in the community and the presence of nearby historic shrines were held not to require denial of a permit under this section. Batcheller v. Commonwealth, 176 Va. 109, 10 S.E.2d 529, 1940 Va. LEXIS 238 (194 0). OPINIONS OF THE ATTORNEY GENERAL Authority to operate airport.  The Louisa Industrial Development Authority (IDA) presently lacks legal authority to operate an airport. Contracting out certain airport operations does not chang e the fact that the IDA is the airport operator, nor does the certification of the IDAs attorney that the IDA has authority to conduct certain airport activities create that authority where it does not exist under applicable law. The Board of Supervi sors may limit the number and type of projects undertaken by the IDA, but the Board may not limit the debt incurred by the IDA on a particular project. See opinion of Attorney General to Michael W. S. Lockaby, Esquire, County Attorney for Louisa County, No. 14-070 2015 Va. AG LEXIS 2 (1/30/15). § 5.1-7.1. Repealed by Acts 1980, c. 56. § 5.1-7.2. Registration of private landing areas not within five miles of commercial airport. Text Any person owning an area for landing any aircraft, which area is not within five miles of a commercial airport and has been cons...</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-8"><akn:num>§ 5.1-8</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1995, cc</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>682 and 690, effective October 1, 1995.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-9"><akn:num>§ 5.1-9</akn:num><akn:heading>Disposition of fees</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text All fees or sums collected by the Department under the provisions of this chapter shall be paid into the special fund created by § 5.1-51. History History. Code 1950, § 5-9; 1966, c. 576; 1979, c. 272. § 5.1-9.1. Certain privately owned airports declared to be works of public improvement; exemption from local taxation authorized. Text (a) Any public use privately owned airport in this Commonwealth, or any improvements made thereto, which is open to the public at no charge and which has been licensed by the Department is hereby declared to be a work of internal improvement. (b) The govern ing body of any city, town or county in this Commonwealth is authorized to exempt from local taxation, as an inducement to their location, the runways and taxiways of any privately owned, public use airport, which is available to the public at no charge and which has been licensed by the Department. History History. Code 1950, § 5-9.1; 1966, c. 221; 1970, c. 717; 1979, c. 272; 1980, c. 721. Annotations The number of this section was assigned by the Virginia Code Commission, the 1966 act having assigned no number. § 5.1-9.2. Contract carriers; permit and registration required. Text No person shall operate or engage in the business of a contract carrier by aircraft intrastate in the airspace of this Commonwealth unless such person has secured from the Department a permit authorizing him to conduct such operation or to engage in such business and has registered under § 5.1-5 all aircraft used in this Commonwealth. History History. Code 1950, § 5.1-103; 1970, c. 708; 1979, c. 357; 1980, c. 721 ; 2017, c. 793. Annotations The 2017 amendments. The 2017 amendment by c. 793 substituted registered for licensed. § 5.1-9.3. Same; application for permit; fee; action of Department. Text Any person desiring a permit under this chapter shall file with the Department an application in the form prescribed by the Department with a fee of fifty dollars. Such application shall contain a promise of compliance by the applicant with the provisions of this title and with the lawful rules and regulations of the Department governing the operations of contract carriers by aircraft in the airspace of the Commonwealt h. Such application may be filed with the Department by the applicant in person or transmitted by registered mail. Upon being satisfied that the provisions of this chapter and the lawful rules and regulations of the Department adopted pursuant hereto, wh ich are prerequisite to the granting of a permit, have been complied with, the Department shall issue such permit to such applicant, subject to such terms, limitations and restrictions as the Department may deem proper, without further proceedings. History History. Code 1950, § 5.1-104; 1970, c. 708; 1972, c. 232; 1980, c. 721 . § 5.1-9.4. Repealed by Acts 1988, c. 45. § 5.1-9.5. Contract carriers; bonds, insurance or certificate of insurance required prior to issuance of registration or permit; securities deposited in lieu the reof. Text A. No registra tion or permit shall be issued by the Department to any contract carrier by aircraft until and after such contract carrier has filed with the Department an insurance policy, a bond underwritten by an insurer, or certificate of insurance in lieu thereof, which certificate shall certify that such policy or bond covers the liability of such contract carrier in accordance with the provisions of this statute. B. Such policy , bond or certificate of insurance shall be issued or underwritten only by an insurer approved or authorized to do business in Virginia, or by one who is eligible as a surplus lines insurer pursuant to Chapter 48 (§ 38.2-4805.1 et seq.) of Title 38.2, and shall be in amounts not less than the following minimum limits: liability for bodily injury to or death of any one person, passenger or other, aboard the aircraft; $75,000, liability for each occurrence in any one aircraft of at least an amount equa l to the sum produced by multiplying $75,000 by seventy-five percent of the total number of passenger seats installed in the aircraft; and liability for loss or damage to cargo owned by others than the insured of at least $10,000 for each occurrence. How ever, the holder of a registration or permit issued by the Department shall not be required to file any cargo insurance, bond, or bonds for cargo liability for the hauling of property transported under contract. C. In no event shall the limits required herein for contract carriers be less than those prescribed for like carriers by the Civil Aeronautics Board or the Federal Aviation Administration or their successors. D. In lieu of such policy, underwritten bond or certificate of insurance, a contract carrier may, with the consent of the Department, submit bonds, in an amount approved by the Department, of the United States of America, the Commonwealth of Virginia, or of any munici pality of this Commonwealth as security for its bond. Such federal, state, or municipal bonds shall be deposited with the State Treasurer, and shall not be reduced in amount, pledged as security, or otherwise encumbered for any other purpose during the l ife of such registration or permit, except with the prior written approval of the Department. History History. 1980, c. 721; 2017, c. 793. Annotations Editors note. At the direction of the Virginia Code Commission, 38.2-4805.1 was substituted for 38.2-4800 in subsection B. The 2017 amendments. The 2017 amendment by c. 793 substituted registration for license throughout the section. § 5.1-9.6. Same; duration and custody of bonds, etc. Text Insurance policies, bonds, certificates of insurance, or federal, state, or municipal bonds filed with the Department shall be kept in full force at all times. The poli cy, bond, or certificate of insurance shall remain in the custody of the Department six months after the insurance or bond has expired or has been canceled for any cause. If federal, state, or municipal bonds are deposited with the State Treasurer as sec urity, such bonds shall remain so deposited until six months after the authority for use of equipment insured has expired or is cancelled for any cause, unless otherwise ordered by the Department. History History. 1980, c. 721. § 5.1-9.7. Same; condition of bond, etc. Text The insurance bond, or other security, shall obligate the insurer or surety to pay any final judgment for damages sustained by the passengers, shippers, or consignees f or injury to any passenger or passengers, or for loss or damage to property entrusted to such contract carrier when a cargo policy is required, and for any and all injuries to persons and loss of, or damage to, property resulting from the negligent opera tion of any aircraft. History History. 1980, c. 721. § 5.1-9.8. Same; effect of failure to give or maintain adequate security. Text Failure of any contract carrier holding a registration or permit issued by and under the authority of the Department to comply with any of the provisions of §§ 5. 1-9.5 through 5.1-9.7 shall be a Class 1 misdemeanor and punishable as such. History History. 1980, c. 721; 2017, c. 793. Annotations Cross references. As to punishment for Class 1 misdemeanors, see § 18.2-11. The 2017 amendments. The 2017 amendment by c. 793 substituted registration for license. § 5.1-9.9. Same; duration of permits; suspension or revocation; penalty. Text A. Contract ca rrier permits issued pursuant to this chapter shall be effective from the date of issuance and shall remain in effect only so long as the contract carriers insurance, underwritten bond or certificate of insurance required by § 5.1-9.5 remains in f ull force and effect. B. The Departm ent may suspend or revoke such permit for violation of any of the aviation laws of this Commonwealth or of the United States of America, or for violation of any of the rules and regulations of the Virginia Aviation Board. C. Willful mis representation of any material fact in obtaining a contract carrier permit shall be a Class 1 misdemeanor and punishable as such. History History. 1980, c. 721. Annotations Cross references. As to punishment for Class 1 misdemeanors, see § 18.2-11.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-10"><akn:num>§ 5.1-10</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1979, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>272.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-11"><akn:num>§ 5.1-11</akn:num><akn:heading>Government-owned aircraft</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text This article shall not apply to public aircraft owned by the United States but shall apply to all other public aircraft. History History. Code 1950, § 5-14; 1966, c. 576; 1980, c. 721.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-12"><akn:num>§ 5.1-12</akn:num><akn:heading>Federally certificated airlines and interstate service</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text This article shall not apply to any aircraft operated by any air carrier operating under Federal Aviation Regulation Part 121 or Part 135 if operating with an exemption from Title IV of the Federal Aviation Act to provide scheduled passenger service. History History. Code 1950, § 5-14; 1966, c. 576; 1980, c. 721; 1988, c. 45; 19 91, c. 535. Article 2. Illegal Operation, etc.; Procedure; Penalties. -360§ 5.1-13. Operation of aircraft while under influence of intoxicating liquors or drugs; reckless operation. -360§ 5.1-14. Operation of unregistered aircraft. -360§ 5.1-15. Operation of aircraft by unlicensed persons. -360§ 5.1-16. Tampering with, etc., airplanes or markings of airports, landing fields or other aeronautical facilities. -360§ 5.1-16.1. Misuse of licensed airports. -360§ 5.1-17. Use of aircraft for hunting. -360§§ 5.1-18, 5.1-19. Repealed by Acts 1988, c. 45. -360§ 5.1-20. Pilot may restrain or arrest person interfering with operation of aircraft carrying passengers for hire. -360§ 5.1-21. Powers of conservator of the peace conferred upon pilot. -360§ 5.1-21.1. Powers of conservators of the peace conferred upon airport managers or designees. -360§ 5.1-22. Interference with operation of aircraft; penalties; venue. -360§ 5.1-23. Jurisdiction of local and State Police. -360§ 5.1-24. Penalties. -360§ 5.1-25. Operation of aircraft by nonresident.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-13"><akn:num>§ 5.1-13</akn:num><akn:heading>Operation of aircraft while under influence of intoxicating liquors or drugs; reckless operation</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Any person who shall operate any aircraft within the airspace over, above or upon the lands or waters of this Commonwealth, while under the influence of intoxicating li quor or of any narcotic or any habit-forming drugs shall be guilty of a felony and shall be confined in a state correctional facility not less than one nor more than five years, or, in the discretion of the court or jury trying the case, be confined in j ail not exceeding twelve months and fined not exceeding $500, or both such fine and imprisonment. Any person who shall operate any aircraft within the airspace over, above or upon the lands or waters of this Commonwealth carelessly or heedlessly in willful or wanton disregard of the rights or safety of others, or without due caution and circumspection and in a manner so as to endanger any person or property, shall be guilty of a misdemeanor. History History. Code 1950, § 5-10.1; 1964, c. 416; 1966, c. 576. Annotations CASE NOTES As to meaning of being intoxicated or under the influence of intoxicating li quor, see Gardner v. Commonwealth, 195 Va. 945, 81 S.E.2d 614, 1954 Va. LEXIS 172 (1954). A pilot has a right to assume that another pilot will obey air traffic regulations until he realizes, or in the exercise of ordinary care should have realized, that the other pilot is not going to do so. Mackey v. Miller, 221 Va. 715, 273 S.E.2d 550, 1981 Va. LEXIS 200 (1981). Violation of section was negli gence per se.  Air Force pilots violation of this section constituted negligence per se, where he flew his plane at such a low altitude that the turbulence from its wake cau sed a large limb from a tree to fall on and severely injure a timber cutter. Musick v. United States, 768 F. Supp. 183, 1991 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 9219 (W.D. Va. 1991).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-14"><akn:num>§ 5.1-14</akn:num><akn:heading>Operation of unregistered aircraft</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Any person who operates or causes to be operated any civil aircraft within the airspace over, above or upon the lands or waters of this Commonwealth, which aircraft has not been and is not at the time of such operation properly certificated under and in accordance with existing federal law and registered under and in accordance with the existing laws of this Commonwealth and rules and regulations promulgated in pursuan ce thereof, shall be guilty of a misdemeanor. History History. Code 1950, § 5-10.2; 1966, c. 576; 2017, c. 793. Annotations The 2017 amendments. The 2017 amendment by c. 793 substituted registered for licensed.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-15"><akn:num>§ 5.1-15</akn:num><akn:heading>Operation of aircraft by unlicensed persons</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Any person who operates any civil aircraft within the airspace over, above, or upon the lands or waters of this Commonwealth, without being, at the time of such operati on, in possession of a valid airmans certificate for such operation, issued under and in accordance with existing federal law shall be deemed to be guilty of a Class 1 misdemeanor. History History. Code 1950, § 5-10.3; 1966, c. 576; 1988, c. 45. Annotations Cross references. As to punishment for Class 1 misdemeanors, see § 18.2-11.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-16"><akn:num>§ 5.1-16</akn:num><akn:heading>Tampering with, etc</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>, airplanes or markings of airports, landing fields or other aeronautical facilities. Text It shall be unlawful for any person to tamper with, alter, destroy, remove, carry away, or cause to be carried away, an airplane or other flying device or instrumentali ty or any objects used for the marking of airports, landing fields, drop zones or other aeronautical facilities, or in any way change their position or location, except by and under the direction of the proper authorities charged with the maintenance and operation of such facilities. Any person violating any of the provisions of this section or who shall illegally have in his possession any objects or devices used for such markings, shall be guilty of a misdemeanor. History History. Code 1950, § 5-10.4; 1966, c. 576. Annotations Cross references. As to breaking, injuring, defacing, destroying or preventing the operation of aircraft, see § 18.2-146. § 5.1-16.1. Misuse of licensed airports. Text It shall be unlawful for any person or persons to use licensed airport runways, taxiways or ramp areas for other than aeronautical purposes without written approval of the controlling authority of such airport. History History. 1970, c. 717.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-17"><akn:num>§ 5.1-17</akn:num><akn:heading>Use of aircraft for hunting</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text It shall be unlawful for any person to hunt, pursue or kill any wild waterfowl or other birds or animals by any means whatever during such time as such person is in fli ght in an aircraft in the airspace over the lands or waters of this Commonwealth. A violation of this section shall be deemed a misdemeanor. History History. Code 1950, § 5-10.5; 1966, c. 576. Annotations Cross references. As to hunting from aircraft feral hogs, see § 29.1-114.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-18"><akn:num>§ 5.1-18</akn:num><akn:heading>5</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>1-18, 5.1-19. Repealed by Acts 1988, c. 45.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-20"><akn:num>§ 5.1-20</akn:num><akn:heading>Pilot may restrain or arrest person interfering with operation of aircraft carrying passengers for hire</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The pilot of any aircraft carrying passengers for hire, or any person subject to his direction, may take such action as is reasonably necessary to restrain or arrest an y person who interferes with, or threatens to interfere with, the operation of the aircraft in flight over the territory of this Commonwealth or to a destination within this Commonwealth. History History. Code 1950, § 5-14.1; 1958, c. 561, § 1; 1966, c. 576.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-21"><akn:num>§ 5.1-21</akn:num><akn:heading>Powers of conservator of the peace conferred upon pilot</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The pilot of any aircraft carrying passengers for hire while actively engaged in the operation of such aircraft shall be a special policeman and have all the powers of a conservator of the peace in the enforcement of order on such aircraft and while in pursuit of persons for disorder upon such aircraft and until such persons as may be arrested by him shall have been placed in confinement or delivered to the custody of some other conservator of the peace or police officer. History History. Code 1950, § 5-14.2; 1958, c. 561, § 2; 1966, c. 576. § 5.1-21.1. Powers of conservators of the peace conferred upon airport managers or designees. Text The airport manager of any licensed Virginia airport or in his absence not more than two employees who are designated by him shall be special policemen and have all the powers of conservators of the peace in the enforcement of this title and its regulations as promulgated by the Board. Persons arrested by them shall be placed in confinement or delivered to the custody of some other conservator of the peace or police of ficer. History History. 1970, c. 717; 1979, c. 272; 1991, c. 339.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-22"><akn:num>§ 5.1-22</akn:num><akn:heading>Interference with operation of aircraft; penalties; venue</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Any person who interferes with or threatens to interfere with the operation of any aircraft, unless he is authorized by the Federal Aviation Administration or the armed forces of the United States, on or over the territory of the Commonwealth shall be guilty of a Class 1 misdemeanor. Where the act or acts of interference or threatened interference are of such a nature as to endanger the life of the aircrafts operat or or the life of any other person, the person interfering or threatening to interfere shall be guilty of a Class 6 felony. Any person who knowingly and intentionally projects a point of light from a laser, laser gun sight, or any other device that simul ates a laser at an aircraft is guilty of a Class 1 misdemeanor. Venue for the issuance of a warrant for the arrest and trial of any such person is hereby conferred upon any court having criminal jurisdiction in the political subdivision in the Commonweal th where the aircraft either took off prior to such offense, or where it lands or comes to rest subsequent to such offense, or in or over which the offense occurred. History History. Code 1950, § 5-14.3; 1958, c. 561, § 3; 1966, c. 576; 1983, c. 560; 2012, c. 398. Annotations Cross references. As to punishment for Class 6 felonies, see § 18.2-10. As to punishment for Class 1 misdemeanors, see § 18.2-11. The 2012 amendments. The 2012 amendment by c. 398 inserted unless he is authorized by the Federal Aviation Administration or the armed forces of the United States, in the firs t sentence; inserted the third sentence; and substituted the Commonwealth for this Commonwealth twice. Law Review. For article surveying developments in criminal law and procedure in Virginia from July 2001 to September 2002, see 37 U. Rich. L. Rev. 45 (2002). CASE NOTES Intent.  Specific intent is not an element of § 5.1-22. Johnson v. Commonwealth, 37 Va. App. 634, 561 S.E.2d 1, 2002 Va. App. LEXIS 160 (2002). Proof of misdemeanor.  Proof of a misdemeanor violation of § 5.1-22 does not require proof that the pilot or any other person was endangered, which is an element of the related felon y. Johnson v. Commonwealth, 37 Va. App. 634, 561 S.E.2d 1, 2002 Va. App. LEXIS 160 (2002).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-23"><akn:num>§ 5.1-23</akn:num><akn:heading>Jurisdiction of local and State Police</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The local police authorities of any city, incorporated town or county shall have jurisdiction on the premises of any airport, drop zone or landing field operated hereun der, either individually or jointly and the State Police shall have jurisdiction to investigate any aircraft accident. In the exercise of such jurisdiction the State Police and officers of the department of law enforcement of any city or county with an o ptional form of government may enter with immunity and without a warrant upon private property for the purpose of conducting such investigations. This section shall not repeal the provisions of any city charter in conflict herewith. History History. Code 1950, § 5-37; 1966, c. 576; 1968, c. 737; 1979, c. 394; 1 980, c. 721. Annotations Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 2C M.J. Aviation, § 8.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-24"><akn:num>§ 5.1-24</akn:num><akn:heading>Penalties</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Any person violating any of the provisions of this chapter, or violating any of the rules or regulations promulgated pursuant thereto by the Board, except as otherwise specifically provided, shall be deemed guilty of a misdemeanor and upon conviction shall be punished by a fine of not more than $100 or imprisonment in jail not exceeding one month, or both, in the discretion of the judge or jury trying the case; provide d, that any person (excepting any government, political subdivision of the Commonwealth, or governmental subdivision or agency) establishing or operating an airport without first obtaining a permit as provided in § 5.1-8 shall, upon conviction, be fin ed not less than $100 nor more than $500 for each offense, and each day that the airport is operated without such permit shall be construed as a separate offense. History History. Code 1950, § 5-11; 1966, c. 576; 1979, c. 272.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-25"><akn:num>§ 5.1-25</akn:num><akn:heading>Operation of aircraft by nonresident</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A nonresident of this Commonwealth may operate aircraft engaged in operations other than for hire or reward in accordance with regulations promulgated by the Board, pro vided such nonresident and the aircraft to be so operated shall have been certified under federal law and shall have complied with the laws of the state in which such nonresident resides relative to aircraft and the operation thereof. A nonresident-owned aircraft engaged in intrastate operation for hire or reward must be licensed with the Department in accordance with this title and the Boards regulations. History History. Code 1950, § 5-12; 1966, c. 576; 1970, c. 717; 1979, c. 272; 1 988, c. 45. Article 3. Structures Dangerous to Aircraft. -360§ 5.1-25.1. Permit required for erection of certain structures. -360§ 5.1-25.2. Application for permit; notice and hearing. -360§ 5.1-25.3. When permit issued or denied; conditions to issuance. -360§ 5.1-25.4. Injunctions. § 5.1-25.1. Permit required for erection of certain structures. Text It shall be unlawful for any person to erect any structure, any part of which penetrates into or through any licensed airports or United States government or milita ry air facilitys clear zone, approach zone, imaginary surface, obstruction clearance surface, obstruction clearance zone, or surface or zone as described in regulations of the Department of Aviation or the Federal Aviation Administration, without sec uring a permit for its erection from the Board. This section shall not apply to any structure to be erected in a county, city or town which has an ordinance regulating the height of such structures to prevent the penetration of zones and surfaces provid ed for in Federal Aviation Regulation Part 77 and Rule 19 of the Department of Aviation. For the purpose of this section, structure shall mean any object, including a mobile object, constructed or erected by man, including but not limited to buildings, towers, cranes, smokestacks, earth formations, overhead transmission lines, flag poles, and ship masts. History History. 1968, c. 744; 1979, c. 272; 1981, c. 326; 1989, cc. 202, 255; 199 0, c. 384. Annotations The numbers of §§ 5.1-25.1 through 5.1-25.4 were assigned by the Virginia Code Commission, the 1968 act having assigned no numbers. § 5.1-25.2. Application for permit; notice and hearing. Text Any person desiring to erect or cause to be erected any such structure shall make application to the Department for the issuance of a permit for such erection. Such app lication shall be forwarded immediately to the Board. The Department shall undertake an appropriate review of such application and submit its contents in writing to the Board as expeditiously as possible. The Board, after such notice to the public as it deems necessary, shall hold a public hearing not less than thirty days after the giving of such notice at which all interested parties shall be admitted to attend and state any objection which they may have to the erection of such structure. History History. 1968, c. 744; 1979, c. 272. § 5.1-25.3. When permit issued or denied; conditions to issuance. Text The Board, if it finds that the erection of such structure will not be dangerous to aircraft using the airways of this Commission, shall issue the permit requested; but if it shall find that the erection of such structure will create a hazard to aircraft using such airways, it shall refuse the issuance of such a permit. The Board may, as a condition to the issuance of any permit, require the installation and maintenanc e of warning lights and any other devices which may be reasonably required to reduce the hazard which might be presented by the erection of such structure. History History. 1968, c. 744. § 5.1-25.4. Injunctions. Text If any person commences the erection of a structure of the nature described in § 5.1-25.1 without securing the permit therein required, the Department shall have pow er to apply forthwith to the circuit court of the jurisdiction in which the structure is located or is to be located, for injunctive relief. History History. 1968, c. 744; 1979, c. 272. Annotations Law Review. For survey of Virginia administrative law and utility regulation for the year 1978-1979, see 66 Va. L. Rev. 193 (1980). Chapter 2. Aviation Advisory Committee. -360§§ 5.1-26 through 5.1-30.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-26"><akn:num>§ 5.1-26</akn:num><akn:heading>5</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>1-26 through 5.1-30. Text Repealed by Acts 1979, c. 272. Annotations Cross references. As to the Virginia Aviation Board, see §§ 5.1-2.1 through 5.1-2.24. Chapter 2.1. Virginia Airports Revolving Fund. -360§ 5.1-30.1. Definitions. -360§ 5.1-30.2. Creation and management of Virginia Airports Revolving Fund. -360§ 5.1-30.3. Deposit of money; expenditures; investments. -360§ 5.1-30.4. Collection of money due Fund. -360§ 5.1-30.5. Loans to local governments. -360§ 5.1-30.6. Pledge of loans to secure bonds of Authority. -360§ 5.1-30.7. Sale of loans. -360§ 5.1-30.8. Powers of the Authority. -360§ 5.1-30.9. Report to the General Assembly and Governor. -360§ 5.1-30.10. Liberal construction of chapter. § 5.1-30.1. Definitions. Text As used in this chapter, unless the context requires otherwise: Authority means the Virginia Resources Authority created in Chapter 21 (§ 62.1-197 et seq.) of Title 62.1. Cost, as applied to any project financed under the provisions of this chapter, means t he total of all costs incurred by the local government as reasonable and necessary for carrying out all works and undertakings necessary or incident to the accomplishment of any project. It includes, without limitation, all necessary developmental, plann ing and feasibility studies, surveys, plans and specifications; architectural, engineering, financial, legal or other special services; the cost of acquisition of land and any buildings and improvements thereon, including the discharge of any obligations of the sellers of such land, buildings or improvements; site preparation and development, including demolition or removal of existing structures; construction and reconstruction; labor; materials, machinery and equipment; the reasonable costs of financi ng incurred by the local government in the course of the development of the project; carrying charges incurred before placing the project in service; interest on funds borrowed to finance the project to a date subsequent to the estimated date the project is to be placed in service; necessary expenses incurred in connection with placing the project in service; the funding of accounts and reserves which the Authority may require; and the cost of other items which the Authority determines to be reasonable and necessary. Fund means the Virginia Airports Revolving Fund created by this chapter. Local government means any county, city, town, municipal corporation, authority, distr ict, commission or political subdivision created by the General Assembly or pursuant to the Constitution or laws of the Commonwealth or any combination of any two or more of the foregoing. Project means all or any part of an airport as defined in § 5.1-1 and may consist o f or include any or all facilities related to the needs or convenience of passengers, shipping companies, and airlines, together with any or all buildings or other structures, improvements, additions, extensions, replacements, machinery or equipment, and any or all appurtenances, lands, rights in land, avigation rights, water rights, rights-of-way, franchises, furnishings, landscaping, utilities, approaches, roadways, or other facilities necessary or desirable in connection therewith or incidental there to. History History. 1999, c. 897. § 5.1-30.2. Creation and management of Virginia Airports Revolving Fund. Text There shall be set apart as a permanent and perpetual fund, to be known as the Virginia Airports Revolving Fund, sums appropriated to the Fund by the General As sembly, all receipts by the Fund from loans made by it to local governments, all income from the investment of moneys held in the Fund, and any other sums designated for deposit to the Fund from any source public or private, including without limitation any federal grants, awards or other forms of assistance received by the Commonwealth that are eligible for deposit therein under federal law. The Authority shall administer and manage the Fund, and establish the interest rates and repayment terms of such loans as provided in this chapter, in accordance with a memorandum of agreement with the Board. The Board shall direct the distribution of loans from the Fund to particular local governments. Consistent with this chapter, the Board shall, after consulta tion with all interested parties, develop a guidance document governing project eligibility and project priority criteria. In order to carry out the administration and management of the Fund, the Authority, in consultation with the Board, is granted the power to employ officers, employees, agents, advisers and consultants, including, without limitation, attorneys, financial advisers, engineers and other technical advisers and public accountants and, the provisions of any other law to the contrary notwit hstanding, to determine their duties and compensation without the approval of any other agency or instrumentality. The Authority may disburse from the Fund its reasonable costs and expenses incurred in the administration and management of the Fund and a reasonable fee to be approved by the Board for its management services. History History. 1999, c. 897. § 5.1-30.3. Deposit of money; expenditures; investments. Text All money belonging to the Fund shall be deposited in an account or accounts in banks or trust companies organized under the laws of the Commonwealth or in national ban king associations located in Virginia or in savings institutions located in Virginia organized under the laws of the Commonwealth or the United States. The money in these accounts shall be paid by check signed by the Executive Director of the Authority o r other officers or employees designated by the Board of Directors of the Authority. All deposits of money shall, if required by the Authority, be secured in a manner determined by the Authority to be prudent, and all banks, trust companies and savings i nstitutions are authorized to give security for the deposits. Money in the Fund shall not be commingled with other money of the Authority. Money in the Fund not needed for immediate use or disbursement may be invested or reinvested by the Authority in ob ligations or securities which are considered lawful investments for public funds under the laws of the Commonwealth. History History. 1999, c. 897. § 5.1-30.4. Collection of money due Fund. Text The Authority is empowered to collect, or to authorize others to collect on its behalf, amounts due to the Fund under any loan to a local government, including, if appr opriate, taking the action required by § 15.2-2659 to obtain payment of any amounts in default. Proceedings to recover amounts due to the Fund may be instituted by the Authority in the name of the Fund in the appropriate circuit court. History History. 1999, c. 897. § 5.1-30.5. Loans to local governments. Text Except as otherwise provided in this chapter, money in the Fund shall be used solely to make loans to local governments to finance or refinance the cost of any project. The local governments to which loans are to be made, the purposes of the loan, and the amount of each such loan, shall be designated in writing by the Board to the Authority following consultation with the Authority. No loan from the Fund shall exceed t he total cost of the project to be financed or the outstanding principal amount of the indebtedness to be refinanced plus reasonable financing expenses. Except as otherwise provided in this chapter, the Authority shall determine the interest rate and terms and conditions of any loan from the Fund, which may vary between local governments. Each loan shall be evidenced by appropriate bonds or notes of the local government payable to the Fund. The bonds or notes shall have been duly authorized by the local government and executed by its authorized legal representatives. T he Authority is authorized to require in connection with any loan from the Fund such documents, instruments, certificates, legal opinions and other information as it may deem necessary or convenient. In addition to any other terms or conditions which the Authority may establish, the Authority may require, as a condition to making any loan from the Fund, that the local government receiving the loan covenant perform any of the following: 1. Estab lish and collect rents, rates, fees, and charges to produce revenue sufficient to pay all or a specified portion of (i) the costs of operation, maintenance, replacement, renewal, and repairs of the project; (ii) any outstanding indebtedness incurred for the purposes of the project, including the principal of, premium, if any, and interest on the loan from the Fund to the local government; and (iii) any amounts necessary to create and maintain any required reserve, including any rate stabilization fund d eemed necessary or appropriate by the Authority to offset the need, in whole or in part, for future increases in rents, rates, fees, or charges. 2. Create and maintain a special fund or funds for the payment of the principal of, premium, if any, and interest on the loan from the Fund to the local government and any other amounts b ecoming due under any agreement entered into in connection with the loan, or for the operation, maintenance, repair, or replacement of the project or any portions thereof or other property of the local government, and deposit into any fund or funds amoun ts sufficient to make any payments on the loan as they become due and payable. 3. Create and maintain other special funds as required by the Authority. 4. Perform other acts otherwise permitted by applicable law to secure payment of the principal of, premium, if any, and interest on the loan from the Fund to the local government and to p rovide for the remedies of the Fund in the event of any default by the local government in the payment of the loan, including, without limitation, any of the following: a. The procurement of insurance, guarantees, letters of credit and other forms of collateral, security, liquidity arrangements or credit s...</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-31"><akn:num>§ 5.1-31</akn:num><akn:heading>Authority to acquire, construct, maintain and operate; permission of Department required</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text All cities, incorporated towns and counties of the Commonwealth may acquire, by purchase, lease, gift, condemnation or otherwise, within or without the limits of any su ch city, town or county, whatever land may be reasonably necessary for the purpose of establishing, constructing, owning, controlling, leasing, equipping, improving, maintaining and operating airports for the use of airplanes; may acquire, establish, con struct, enlarge, improve, maintain, equip, operate and regulate the use of such airports or landing fields, structures, air navigation facilities and other property incident thereto; may make, prior to such acquisition, investigation, surveys and plans a nd enter upon any lands or waters for such purposes; may construct, install, maintain and operate facilities for the servicing of aircraft, and for the accommodation and comfort of air travelers; may purchase and sell equipment and supplies as an inciden t to the operation of its airport properties; provided, that in the case of any county, the exercise of such authority beyond its territorial boundaries shall be only with the consent of the governing body of the political subdivision in which the power is sought to be exercised; provided, however, that no such city, town or county shall establish or operate any airport without first obtaining the permission of the Board, as now or hereafter provided by law. The governing body of a county, city, or town may create an airport authority that shall be empowered on behalf of such county, city, or town to have and exercise the p owers and rights set out in this section. History History. Code 1950, §§ 5-20, 5-29; 1966, c. 576; 1979, c. 272; 1995, c. 453. Annotations Cross references. As to transparency and accountability for use of Department and Board funds, see § 5.1-2.2:4. Editors note. As to the creation of the Virginias Region 2000 Airport Authority Act, see Acts 2007, c. 812. CASE NOTES Court must defer to citys rational decision on airport requirements.  If the city has decided rationally that minimum space requirements for aviation fuel vendors serve its legitimate interest in maintaining the airport, the court m ust defer to that decision. Hillman Flying Serv., Inc. v. City of Roanoke, 652 F. Supp. 1142, 1987 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 4996 (W.D. Va. 1987), aff'd, 846 F.2d 71, 1988 U.S. App. LEXIS 5143 (4th Cir. 1988), aff'd, 846 F.2d 71 (4th Cir. 1988). The court was bound to accept the municipal defendants argument that the overbreadth of their aviation fuel standards was attributable to the high degree of d anger associated with air travel. It was rational for the city to err on the side of caution by promulgating broad minimum requirements for its airport contractors. Hillman Flying Serv., Inc. v. City of Roanoke, 652 F. Supp. 1142, 1987 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 4 996 (W.D. Va. 1987), aff'd, 846 F.2d 71, 1988 U.S. App. LEXIS 5143 (4th Cir. 1988), aff'd, 846 F.2d 71 (4th Cir. 1988). Under rational basis analysis.  Plaintiffs contention that citys aviation fuel standards were more restrictive than safety and efficiency require was insufficient to allow the court to s crutinize the airport regulations more strictly than under a rational basis analysis. Although it is true that legislation involving fundamental rights or suspect classifications must further its purpose in the least restrictive manner, economic legislat ion can accomplish its goal in broad strokes. Hillman Flying Serv., Inc. v. City of Roanoke, 652 F. Supp. 1142, 1987 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 4996 (W.D. Va. 1987), aff'd, 846 F.2d 71, 1988 U.S. App. LEXIS 5143 (4th Cir. 1988), aff'd, 846 F.2d 71 (4th Cir. 1988). Where municipal defendants sufficiently demonstrated that their standards for aviation fuel vendors at the airport were rationally related to the legitimate inter est to safely and efficiently provide public aviation services, plaintiffs complaint failed to demonstrate that the municipal defendants violated its right to equal protection under the Fourteenth Amendment. Hillman Flying Serv., Inc. v. City of Roan oke, 652 F. Supp. 1142, 1987 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 4996 (W.D. Va. 1987), aff'd, 846 F.2d 71, 1988 U.S. App. LEXIS 5143 (4th Cir. 1988), aff'd, 846 F.2d 71 (4th Cir. 1988). Free market for aviation businesses limited by legislature.  By granting cities the power to regulate airport facilities on such terms and subject to such conditions and regulations as may be provided, the Virginia legislature limited the free market for aviation businesses. Hillman Flying Serv., Inc. v. City of Roanoke, 652 F. Supp. 1142, 1987 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 4996 (W.D. Va. 1987), aff'd, 846 F.2d 71, 1988 U.S. App. LEXIS 5143 (4th Cir. 1988), aff'd, 846 F.2d 71 ( 4th Cir. 1988). Express endorsement of anticompetitive results not necessary.  Unlike the aviation laws of other states, the Virginia law does not expressly anticipate exclusive or anticompetitive arrangements. Nonetheless, a legislature s express endorsement of anticompetitive behavior is unnecessary for a municipalitys immunity under the antitrust laws. Indeed, the state action doctrine realistically anticipates that anticompetitive results are often foreseeable when a political su bdivision implements a state grant of general authority to act efficiently and in the best public interest. Hillman Flying Serv., Inc. v. City of Roanoke, 652 F. Supp. 1142, 1987 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 4996 (W.D. Va. 1987), aff'd, 846 F.2d 71, 1988 U.S. App. L EXIS 5143 (4th Cir. 1988), aff'd, 846 F.2d 71 (4th Cir. 1988). OPINIONS OF THE ATTORNEY GENERAL Authority to operate airport.  The Louisa Industrial Development Authority (IDA) presently lacks legal authority to operate an airport. Contracting out certain airport operations does not chang e the fact that the IDA is the airport operator, nor does the certification of the IDAs attorney that the IDA has authority to conduct certain airport activities create that authority where it does not exist under applicable law. The Board of Supervi sors may limit the number and type of projects undertaken by the IDA, but the Board may not limit the debt incurred by the IDA on a particular project. See opinion of Attorney General to Michael W. S. Lockaby, Esquire, County Attorney for Louisa County, No. 14-070 2015 Va. AG LEXIS 2 (1/30/15).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-32"><akn:num>§ 5.1-32</akn:num><akn:heading>Easements and privileges outside of airport or landing field boundaries</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Where necessary to provide unobstructed airspace for the landing and taking off of aircraft utilizing airports or landing fields acquired or operated by any county, cit y or town under the provisions of this article, any such county, city or town may acquire, in the same manner as is provided for the acquisition of land for airport purposes, easements through or other interests or privileges with respect to lands or wat ers outside the boundaries of such airports or landing fields which are necessary to insure safe approaches to such airports or landing fields and the safe and efficient operation thereof; and may also acquire in like manner, for a term of years or perpe tually, the right of easement to place and maintain suitable signs or markers or lights to adequately locate and mark objects or structures or uses of lands which are hazardous to aircraft using such airports or landing fields, including the right of ing ress and egress to and from such airport hazards for the purpose of maintaining and repairing such signs, markers and lights. History History. Code 1950, § 5-21; 1966, c. 576. Annotations OPINIONS OF THE ATTORNEY GENERAL An airport authority is authorized to exercise its power of eminent domain to condemn trees in a private cemetery to provide unobstructed airspace for purposes of air safety. See opi nion of Attorney General to Lucy E. Phillips, Esq., Washington County Attorney, 09-086, 2009 Va. AG LEXIS 53 (12/11/09).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-33"><akn:num>§ 5.1-33</akn:num><akn:heading>Public purpose declared</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Any lands, easements or privileges acquired, owned, controlled or occupied by any cities, incorporated towns and counties of the Commonwealth under the provisions of th is article are hereby declared to be acquired, owned, controlled or occupied for a public purpose, and as a matter of public necessity; and such lands, easements and privileges so acquired, owned, controlled or occupied are hereby declared to be acquired , owned, controlled or occupied for public, governmental and municipal purposes, and to be within the definition of property acquired for public uses as such term is used in Article I, Section 11 of the Constitution of Virginia. History History. Code 1950, §§ 5-22, 5-30; 1966, c. 576; 1971, Ex. Sess., c. 26. Annotations Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 7A M.J. Eminent Domain, § 28. CASE NOTES Court must defer to citys rational decision on airport requirements.  If the city has decided rationally that minimum space requirements for aviation fuel vendors serve its legitimate interest in maintaining the airport, the court m ust defer to that decision. Hillman Flying Serv., Inc. v. City of Roanoke, 652 F. Supp. 1142, 1987 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 4996 (W.D. Va. 1987), aff'd, 846 F.2d 71, 1988 U.S. App. LEXIS 5143 (4th Cir. 1988), aff'd, 846 F.2d 71 (4th Cir. 1988). The court was bound to accept the municipal defendants argument that the overbreadth of their aviation fuel standards was attributable to the high degree of d anger associated with air travel. It was rational for the city to err on the side of caution by promulgating broad minimum requirements for its airport contractors. Hillman Flying Serv., Inc. v. City of Roanoke, 652 F. Supp. 1142, 1987 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 4 996 (W.D. Va. 1987), aff'd, 846 F.2d 71, 1988 U.S. App. LEXIS 5143 (4th Cir. 1988), aff'd, 846 F.2d 71 (4th Cir. 1988). Under rational basis analysis.  Plaintiffs contention that citys aviation fuel standards were more restrictive than safety and efficiency require was insufficient to allow the court to s crutinize the airport regulations more strictly than under a rational basis analysis. Although it is true that legislation involving fundamental rights or suspect classifications must further its purpose in the least restrictive manner, economic legislat ion can accomplish its goal in broad strokes. Hillman Flying Serv., Inc. v. City of Roanoke, 652 F. Supp. 1142, 1987 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 4996 (W.D. Va. 1987), aff'd, 846 F.2d 71, 1988 U.S. App. LEXIS 5143 (4th Cir. 1988), aff'd, 846 F.2d 71 (4th Cir. 1988). Where municipal defendants sufficiently demonstrated that their standards for aviation fuel vendors at the airport were rationally related to the legitimate inter est to safely and efficiently provide public aviation services, plaintiffs complaint failed to demonstrate that the municipal defendants have violated its right to equal protection under the Fourteenth Amendment. Hillman Flying Serv., Inc. v. City of Roanoke, 652 F. Supp. 1142, 1987 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 4996 (W.D. Va. 1987), aff'd, 846 F.2d 71, 1988 U.S. App. LEXIS 5143 (4th Cir. 1988), aff'd, 846 F.2d 71 (4th Cir. 1988). Free market for aviation businesses limited by legislature.  By granting cities the power to regulate airport facilities on such terms and subject to such conditions and regulations as may be provided, the Virginia legislature limited the free market for aviation businesses. Hillman Flying Serv., Inc. v. City of Roanoke, 652 F. Supp. 1142, 1987 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 4996 (W.D. Va. 1987), aff'd, 846 F.2d 71, 1988 U.S. App. LEXIS 5143 (4th Cir. 1988), aff'd, 846 F.2d 71 ( 4th Cir. 1988). Express endorsement of anticompetitive results not necessary.  Unlike the aviation laws of other states, the Virginia law does not expressly anticipate exclusive or anticompetitive arrangements. Nonetheless, a legislature s express endorsement of anticompetitive behavior is unnecessary for a municipalitys immunity under the antitrust laws. Indeed, the state action doctrine realistically anticipates that anticompetitive results are often foreseeable when a political su bdivision implements a state grant of general authority to act efficiently and in the best public interest. Hillman Flying Serv., Inc. v. City of Roanoke, 652 F. Supp. 1142, 1987 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 4996 (W.D. Va. 1987), aff'd, 846 F.2d 71, 1988 U.S. App. L EXIS 5143 (4th Cir. 1988), aff'd, 846 F.2d 71 (4th Cir. 1988). Municipality operating and maintaining an airport acts in a proprietary capacity and may be liable for its negligence occurring in connection with such activities. Bowling v. City of Roanoke, 568 F. Supp. 446, 1983 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 15201 (W.D. Va. 1983).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-34"><akn:num>§ 5.1-34</akn:num><akn:heading>Acquisition of property; exercise of right of eminent domain</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Private property needed by any city, incorporated town or county for an airport or landing field shall be acquired by purchase, if the city, town or county is able to a gree with the owners on the terms thereof. The cities, incorporated towns or counties are hereby granted full power to exercise the right of eminent domain in the acquisition of any lands, easements and privileges that are necessary for airport and landi ng field purposes. Proceedings for the acquisition of such lands, easements and privileges by condemnation may be instituted and conducted in the name of such county, city or town, and the procedure shall be mutatis mutandis the same as in the acquisitio n of land by condemnation proceedings instituted by railroads and may acquire in like manner, for a term of years or perpetually, the right of easement to remove and control the growth of any tree or vegetation standing or growing in said land outside th e boundaries of any airport or landing field and the right of easement to place and maintain suitable signs or markers or lights to adequately locate and mark objects or structures that are hazardous to aircraft using such airports or landing fields, of ingress and egress to and from such airport hazards for the purpose of maintaining and repairing such signs, markers and lights and cutting of trees or other growing vegetation penetrating the approach and departure slope easement. The right of condemnat ion granted herein shall be subject to the same provisions as are provided in § 25.1-102 concerning the condemnation of property belonging to a corporation possessing the power of eminent domain by another public service corporation. History History. Code 1950, §§ 5-23, 5-31; 1966, c. 576; 2003, c. 940. Annotations The 2003 amendments. The 2003 amendment by c. 940 substituted that for which following privileges in the second sentence, substituted that for whic h following structures in the next-to-last sentence, and substituted § 25.1-102 for § 25-233 in the last sentence. Research References. Friends Virginia Pleading and Practice (Matthew Bender). Chapter 27. Property Actions. § 27.22. Condemnation and Eminent Domain. Friend. Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 7A M.J. Eminent Domain, § 28. CASE NOTES Court without power to approve airport commission agreement to relinquish power of eminent domain.  Circuit court ruling approving airport commissions agreement with landowners not to extend runway into landowners property as long as they or their childr en owned the property was void ab initio because the circuit court did not have the power to render a judgment which permitted a governmental entity to relinquish the power or right of eminent domain. Evans v. Smyth-Wythe Airport Comm'n, 255 Va. 69, 495 S.E.2d 825, 1998 Va. LEXIS 20 (1998). OPINIONS OF THE ATTORNEY GENERAL An airport authority is authorized to exercise its power of eminent domain to condemn trees in a private cemetery to provide unobstructed airspace for purposes of air safety. See opi nion of Attorney General to Lucy E. Phillips, Esq., Washington County Attorney, 09-086, 2009 Va. AG LEXIS 53 (12/11/09).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-35"><akn:num>§ 5.1-35</akn:num><akn:heading>Powers may be exercised jointly by two or more political subdivisions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text All powers, rights, and authority granted to counties, cities, and towns under this article may be exercised and enjoyed jointly by any two or more of such political su bdivisions within or without the territorial limits of either or any of them, or if one or more of such political subdivisions is a county, then within such county or one of such counties, and the political subdivisions so acting jointly may enter into s uch agreements with each other as may be necessary or proper for the exercise and enjoyment of the joint powers hereby granted, and for joint action in carrying out the general purposes of this article. The powers granted by this section shall include t he power to seek and obtain loans for the purpose of capital improvements to any airport or landing field established pursuant to this article. History History. Code 1950, § 5-24; 1966, c. 576; 1989, c. 234. Annotations OPINIONS OF THE ATTORNEY GENERAL An airport authority is authorized to exercise its power of eminent domain to condemn trees in a private cemetery to provide unobstructed airspace for purposes of air safety. See opi nion of Attorney General to Lucy E. Phillips, Esq., Washington County Attorney, 09-086, 2009 Va. AG LEXIS 53 (12/11/09).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-36"><akn:num>§ 5.1-36</akn:num><akn:heading>Agreement for joint exercise of powers; governing board, etc</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>, to act on behalf of political subdivisions; powers of board, etc. Text The agreement provided for in § 5.1-35 may provide for the creation of a governing board, commission, authority or body empowered to have and exercise, on behalf of the several political subdivisions which are parties to such agreement, the powers, rights and authority conferred on such political subdivisions by this article. Members of the governing bodies of the several political subdivisions may serve as a member of a board, commission, authority or body formed pursuant to § 5.1-35. Such agreement shall specify the name of the board, commission, authority or body and its composition and prescribe its powers and duties which may include powers to establish, co nstruct, manage, and operate an airport, acquire, hold and dispose of property but on behalf of the several political subdivisions, including the exercise on their behalf of the power of eminent domain. If any such board, commission, authority or body is created, all proceedings in connection with the establishment, construction, management and operation of the airport, including application for and issuance of any license required therefor, shall be in its name. The intent of § 5.1-35 and this secti on is that any such board, commission, authority or body established by two or more political subdivisions or through action of the General Assembly may have the same powers granted to a city, town and county but in no case will such powers be greater th an those granted to a city, town or county. Any joint airport authority created pursuant to this chapter and in existence on July 1, 1994, shall be continued in lawful existence under the terms and provisions of this chapter even though all the political subdivisions except one withdraw from the joint airport authority. History History. Code 1950, § 5-24.1; 1958, c. 523; 1966, c. 576; 1970, c. 717; 1993, c. 81; 1995, c. 453. Annotations Cross references. As to transparency and accountability for use of Department and Board funds, see § 5.1-2.2:4. OPINIONS OF THE ATTORNEY GENERAL An airport authority is authorized to exercise its power of eminent domain to condemn trees in a private cemetery to provide unobstructed airspace for purposes of air safety. See opi nion of Attorney General to Lucy E. Phillips, Esq., Washington County Attorney, 09-086, 2009 Va. AG LEXIS 53 (12/11/09). § 5.1-36.1. Contributions by counties to construction of certain airports. Text The governing body of any county is authorized to make appropriations of public funds to contribute to the initial construction of an airport by a city or town adjoinin g such county or by a city or town within a county adjoining such county. History History. Code 1950, § 5-24.2; 1966, c. 415. Annotations The number of this section was assigned by the Virginia Code Commission, the number in the 1966 act having been 5-24.2.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-37"><akn:num>§ 5.1-37</akn:num><akn:heading>Public waters and submerged lands</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The powers herein granted to counties, cities and towns include the power to establish, maintain and operate airports and landing areas and other air navigation facilit ies in, over and upon any public waters of this Commonwealth, or any submerged land under such public waters, within the limits or jurisdiction of or bordering on such counties, cities or towns. History History. Code 1950, § 5-26; 1966, c. 576.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-38"><akn:num>§ 5.1-38</akn:num><akn:heading>Right to zone property not limited</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The rights of any counties, cities or towns to zone property shall not be limited by the provisions of this article. History History. Code 1950, § 5-27; 1966, c. 576.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-39"><akn:num>§ 5.1-39</akn:num><akn:heading>Use, disposal and termination of rights acquired</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text No easements, rights or privileges acquired under the terms of this article by any county, city or town shall be employed or disposed of except to accomplish the purpos es for which they were originally acquired; except that when such easements, rights, or privileges have been transferred to the Virginia Aviation Board, they may be held, used, and disposed of in accordance with §§ 5.1-2.2 and 5.1-2.2:1. Upon the a bandonment of any airport or landing field acquired pursuant to this article all easements, rights and privileges which shall have been so acquired over or with respect to adjacent lands shall thereupon terminate and revert back to the person from whom t he easement, right or privilege was obtained or his successor in interest. History History. Code 1950, § 5-28; 1966, c. 576; 1980, c. 721. § 5.1-39.1. Use of airport property for industrial development purposes. Text Notwithstanding § 5.1-39, any county, city, town, or airport commission may use, lease or convey for any industrial development purposes any airport property describ ed in § 5.1-39 with the written approval of the Director of Aviation on such terms and conditions as the Director may require. When any easement, rights, or privileges have been pledged as a sponsors share to secure funds from the Federal Aviation Administration, written approval of the Federal Aviation Administration shall also be required. History History. 1980, c. 59.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-40"><akn:num>§ 5.1-40</akn:num><akn:heading>Lease of land acquired; approval by Department</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Any political subdivision or privately owned, licensed public use airport acquiring land under the provisions of this article may individually, or jointly where so oper ated, lease the same, or any part thereof, to any individual or corporation desiring to use the same for the purpose of operating an airport or landing field, or for the purpose of landing or starting airplanes therefrom or for other aviation purposes, a nd on such terms and subject to such conditions and regulations as may be provided; and any political subdivision or privately owned, licensed public use airport may enter into a contract in the form of a lease providing for the use of such land, or any part thereof, by the government of the United States for the use by the government of such land for aviation, mail delivery or other aviation purposes upon nominal or other rental or without consideration, provided the political subdivision or privately owned, licensed public use airport certifies that the lease meets the terms and provisions of any and all state and federal grants. History History. Code 1950, § 5-38; 1966, c. 576; 1979, c. 272; 2012, cc. 28, 8 05, 836. Annotations The 2012 amendments. The 2012 amendment by c. 28 substituted political subdivision or privately owned, licensed, public use airport for city, town or county twice. The 2012 amendments by cc. 805 and 836 are identical, and twice substituted political subdivision or privately owned, licensed public use airport for  city, town or county, and substituted the political subdivision or privately owned, licensed public use airport certifies that the lease meets the terms and provisions of any and all state and federal grants for that such lease to an indi vidual or a corporation or to the government of the United States shall not be of any force, effect or validity until the same shall be approved by the Department at the end. CASE NOTES Court must defer to citys rational decision on airport requirements.  If the city has decided rationally that minimum space requirements for aviation fuel vendors serve its legitimate interest in maintaining the airport, the court m ust defer to that decision. Hillman Flying Serv., Inc. v. City of Roanoke, 652 F. Supp. 1142, 1987 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 4996 (W.D. Va. 1987), aff'd, 846 F.2d 71, 1988 U.S. App. LEXIS 5143 (4th Cir. 1988), aff'd, 846 F.2d 71 (4th Cir. 1988). The court was bound to accept the municipal defendants argument that the overbreadth of their aviation fuel standards was attributable to the high degree of d anger associated with air travel. It was rational for the city to err on the side of caution by promulgating broad minimum requirements for its airport contractors. Hillman Flying Serv., Inc. v. City of Roanoke, 652 F. Supp. 1142, 1987 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 4 996 (W.D. Va. 1987), aff'd, 846 F.2d 71, 1988 U.S. App. LEXIS 5143 (4th Cir. 1988), aff'd, 846 F.2d 71 (4th Cir. 1988). Under rational basis analysis.  Plaintiffs contention that citys aviation fuel standards were more restrictive than safety and efficiency require was insufficient to allow the court to s crutinize the airport regulations more strictly than under a rational basis analysis. Although it is true that legislation involving fundamental rights or suspect classifications must further its purpose in the least restrictive manner, economic legislat ion can accomplish its goal in broad strokes. Hillman Flying Serv., Inc. v. City of Roanoke, 652 F. Supp. 1142, 1987 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 4996 (W.D. Va. 1987), aff'd, 846 F.2d 71, 1988 U.S. App. LEXIS 5143 (4th Cir. 1988), aff'd, 846 F.2d 71 (4th Cir. 1988). Free market for aviation businesses limited by legislature.  By granting cities the power to regulate airport facilities on such terms and subject to such conditions and regulations as may be provided, the Virginia legislature limited the free market for aviation businesses. Hillman Flying Serv., Inc. v. City of Roanoke, 652 F. Supp. 1142, 1987 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 4996 (W.D. Va. 1987), aff'd, 846 F.2d 71, 1988 U.S. App. LEXIS 5143 (4th Cir. 1988), aff'd, 846 F.2d 71 ( 4th Cir. 1988). Where municipal defendants sufficiently demonstrated that their standards for aviation fuel vendors at the airport were rationally related to the legitimate inter est to safely and efficiently provide public aviation services, plaintiffs complaint failed to demonstrate that the municipal defendants have violated its right to equal protection under the Fourteenth Amendment. Hillman Flying Serv., Inc. v. City of Roanoke, 652 F. Supp. 1142, 1987 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 4996 (W.D. Va. 1987), aff'd, 846 F.2d 71, 1988 U.S. App. LEXIS 5143 (4th Cir. 1988), aff'd, 846 F.2d 71 (4th Cir. 1988). Express endorsement of anticompetitive results not necessary.  Unlike the aviation laws of other states, the Virginia law does not expressly anticipate exclusive or anticompetitive arrangements. Nonetheless, a legislature s express endorsement of anticompetitive behavior is unnecessary for a municipalitys immunity under the antitrust laws. Indeed, the state action doctrine realistically anticipates that anticompetitive results are often foreseeable when a political su bdivision implements a state grant of general authority to act efficiently and in the best public interest. Hillman Flying Serv., Inc. v. City of Roanoke, 652 F. Supp. 1142, 1987 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 4996 (W.D. Va. 1987), aff'd, 846 F.2d 71, 1988 U.S. App. L EXIS 5143 (4th Cir. 1988), aff'd, 846 F.2d 71 (4th Cir. 1988).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-41"><akn:num>§ 5.1-41</akn:num><akn:heading>Operation by local governing body or special officer or board</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The governing body, or other proper authority, of a county, city, or town which has established an airport or landing field and acquired, leased, or set apart property for such purpose, may construct, improve, equip, maintain and operate the same, or may vest jurisdiction for the construction, improvement, equipment, maintenance and operation thereof in any suitable officer, board or body of such county, city, or town. A member of the governing body of any such county, city, or town may also serve as a member of any board or body established to manage an airport or landing field. No such city, town or county, however, shall operate an airport without first obtaining the permission of the Board as now or hereafter provided by law. In addition to other powers conferred by this section, any such governing body or other authority of a county, city, or town shall have the power to seek and obtain loans for the purpose of capital improvements to any airport or landing field established pursuant to this article. History History. Code 1950, § 5-34; 1966, c. 576; 1979, c. 272; 1989, c. 234; 1 993, c. 81. Annotations OPINIONS OF THE ATTORNEY GENERAL Authority to operate airport.  The Louisa Industrial Development Authority (IDA) presently lacks legal authority to operate an airport. Contracting out certain airport operations does not chang e the fact that the IDA is the airport operator, nor does the certification of the IDAs attorney that the IDA has authority to conduct certain airport activities create that authority where it does not exist under applicable law. The Board of Supervi sors may limit the number and type of projects undertaken by the IDA, but the Board may not limit the debt incurred by the IDA on a particular project. See opinion of Attorney General to Michael W. S. Lockaby, Esquire, County Attorney for Louisa County, No. 14-070 2015 Va. AG LEXIS 2 (1/30/15). § 5.1-41.1. Local governing bodies authorized to require boarding fee. Text The governing body of any county, city or town which operates an airport or an airport authority, after approval of its governing bodies, shall have the power by ordina nce or by bylaw to require a boarding fee on passengers boarding aircraft at local airports, where the trip of such passenger originates at such airport. Such fee shall be in such amount and on such terms as the governing body of the locality or airport authority may by ordinance or by bylaw prescribe, not to exceed two dollars per person. Nothing herein contained shall affect any authority heretofore granted to any local government or airport authority to require a boarding fee. History History. 1973, c. 536. Annotations The number of this section was assigned by the Virginia Code Commission, the number in the 1973 act having been 58-76.2. Article 2. Funds for Acquisition, Operation, etc. -360§ 5.1-42. Payment of purchase price or award for land acquired; issuance of bonds. -360§ 5.1-43. Expenses of construction, operation, etc., to be paid by political subdivision. -360§ 5.1-44. Rules and regulations; fees and charges. -360§ 5.1-45. Appropriations by local authorities. -360§ 5.1-46. Receipt and handling of federal and other funds.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-42"><akn:num>§ 5.1-42</akn:num><akn:heading>Payment of purchase price or award for land acquired; issuance of bonds</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The purchase price or award for real property acquired for an airport or landing field may be paid for by the appropriation of moneys available therefor or wholly or pa rtly paid from the proceeds of the sale of bonds of the city, town or county as the governing body of the city, town or county shall determine. Such city, town or county is hereby authorized to issue bonds for such purpose or purposes, subject, however, to the approval of such bond issue at a referendum thereon, if such approval is a prerequisite to the issuance of bonds by any such political subdivision of the Commonwealth for public purposes generally. History History. Code 1950, § 5-33; 1966, c. 576.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-43"><akn:num>§ 5.1-43</akn:num><akn:heading>Expenses of construction, operation, etc</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>, to be paid by political subdivision. Text The expenses of such construction, improvement, equipment, maintenance and operation shall be paid by such political subdivision, from available funds, subject to all a pplicable constitutional provisions. History History. Code 1950, § 5-35; 1966, c. 576.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-44"><akn:num>§ 5.1-44</akn:num><akn:heading>Rules and regulations; fees and charges</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The governing body of such city, town or county, or a board, commission, authority or body created under § 5.1-36, may adopt regulations not in conflict with the rul es and regulations adopted and promulgated by the Board from time to time and establish fees or other charges for the use of such airport or landing field or may authorize an officer representing such city, town, county, board, commission, authority or b ody to adopt such regulations and establish such fees and charges. History History. Code 1950, § 5-36; 1966, c. 576; 1970, c. 717; 1979, c. 272.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-45"><akn:num>§ 5.1-45</akn:num><akn:heading>Appropriations by local authorities</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The governing body of any city, town or county to which this chapter is applicable may appropriate or cause to be raised by taxation in such city, town or county a sum sufficient to carry out the provisions of this chapter. History History. Code 1950, § 5-39; 1966, c. 576.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-46"><akn:num>§ 5.1-46</akn:num><akn:heading>Receipt and handling of federal and other funds</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Any county, city or town in Virginia may accept, receive and receipt for federal moneys, and other moneys, either public or private, for the acquisition, construction, enlargement, improvement, maintenance and operation of airports and landing fields and other air navigation facilities, and is authorized and empowered to comply with the provisions of the laws of the United States and any rules and regulations made ther eunder for the expenditure of federal moneys in connection with such airports, landing fields and air navigation facilities. History History. Code 1950, § 5-25; 1966, c. 576; 1979, c. 272; 1988, c. 70. Article 3. Federal Airport Act. -360§ 5.1-47. Project and application to be approved by Department. -360§ 5.1-48. Repealed by Acts 1988, c. 70.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-47"><akn:num>§ 5.1-47</akn:num><akn:heading>Project and application to be approved by Department</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Notwithstanding any other provision of law, no county, city or town, whether acting alone or jointly with another county, city or town or with the Commonwealth, shall s ubmit to the Federal Aviation Administration of the United States any project application under the provisions of any act of Congress which provides airport construction, planning and development funds for the expansion and improvement of the airport sys tem insofar as such act shall pertain to the Commonwealth of Virginia, unless the project and the project application have been first approved by the Department. History History. Code 1950, § 5-39.1; 1966, c. 576; 1972, c. 374; 1979, c. 272.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-48"><akn:num>§ 5.1-48</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1988, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>70. Chapter 4. Commonwealth Transportation Board. -360§ 5.1-49. Roads to airports and landing fields; cooperation with Department as to aviation facilities. -360§ 5.1-50. Flight strips, airfields and roads requested by federal agency.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-49"><akn:num>§ 5.1-49</akn:num><akn:heading>Roads to airports and landing fields; cooperation with Department as to aviation facilities</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Department of Transportation is authorized to build roads to airports and landing fields open to public use, and may pay out of highway funds, which have been alloc ated by the Commonwealth Transportation Board, the cost of such roads. The Department of Transportation may, in cooperation with the Department of Aviation and either on an actual cost or contract basis, construct, maintain and improve airports, landing fields and other aviation facilities licensed for public use, the actual cost thereof to the Department of Transportation to be paid by the Department of Aviation. History History. Code 1950, § 5-40; 1966, c. 576; 1979, c. 272; 2013, cc. 585, 646. Annotations Cross references. As to the Commonwealth Transportation Board, see § 33.2-200 et seq. Editors note. Acts 2013, cc. 585 and 646, cl. 2 provides: That the provisions of this act shall not be construed to invalidate any action taken or approval rendered by the Commonwealth Transportation Board prior to July 1, 2013, and that any and all actions taken and all approvals rendered by the Board prior to July 1, 2013, shall remain valid and in effect unless modified, superseded, or repealed by subsequent action of t he Board. The 2013 amendments. The 2013 amendments by cc. 585 and 646 are identical, and substituted Department of Transportation for Commonwealth Transportation Board in the fi rst and last occurrence, inserted which have been allocated by the Commonwealth Transportation Board in the first sentence, substituted The Department of Transportation for Such Board at the beginning of the second sentence, and i nserted of Aviation following Department in two places.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-50"><akn:num>§ 5.1-50</akn:num><akn:heading>Flight strips, airfields and roads requested by federal agency</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text In order to further the interests of national security, the Commonwealth Transportation Board may, at the request of the Army and Navy Departments, Federal Highway Admi nistration or other agency of the United States, construct and maintain, or cooperate with any such federal agency in the construction and maintenance of flight strips, airfields, and roads leading thereto from public highways. To carry out this purpose the Department, acting through the Commissioner of Highways may acquire in the name of the Commonwealth by gift or purchase or by the exercise of the power of eminent domain such real property, or interest therein, including the rights in the air above r eal property, as may be needed for such flight strips, airfields and roads. The exercise of the power of eminent domain hereby conferred shall be in the same manner and pursuant to the same procedure that is now, or may hereafter be, provided by law for the acquisition of real property by the Commissioner of Highways for highway purposes, and in order that the construction work may proceed without delay, the Department may, in the same manner and under the same conditions and procedure as is provided in the case of real property needed for highway purposes, enter upon and take possession of such real property as may be needed for the purposes of this section, and proceed with the construction work prior to the acquisition of title to the property in co ndemnation proceedings. In carrying out the purposes of this section, the Department may expend only such funds as may be provided for such purposes by the federal government. If requested to do so by the federal agency which provided the funds with which the Department acquired the property for any such flight strips, airfields or roads, the Department may authorize and direct the Commissioner of Highways to convey, by deed executed in the name of the Commonwealth, such property to the United States to be used in the interests of national security. If title to such property is retained by t he Commonwealth, the Department may authorize any agency of the United States to use such property to further the interest of national security. Whenever the Department finds that property heretofore or hereafter acquired by it for any such flight strips , airfields or roads is no longer needed for the purpose for which it was acquired, it may sell the same for such consideration as it deems adequate to any private person, firm or corporation and may authorize and direct the Commissioner of Highways to e xecute a deed in the name of the Commonwealth conveying such property to the purchaser. The proceeds from any such sale shall be paid into the treasury of Virginia to the credit of the highway fund unless the terms of any grant to the Department or the C ommonwealth provide otherwise, in which case such proceeds shall be disposed of in accordance with the terms of such grant. History History. Code 1950, § 5-41; 1966, c. 576; 1979, c. 272. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2011, cc. 36 and 152, cl. 3 provides: That the Virginia Code Commission shall carry out such editorial changes to the Code of Virginia as may be required to reflect the provisions of this act changing the title Commonwealth Transportation Commissioner to Commissioner of Highways. Commissioner of Highways was substituted for Commonwealth Transportation Commissioner in t his section. Chapter 5. Special Fund for Administration of Aviation Laws. -360§ 5.1-51. Special fund accumulated from taxes, fees, etc. -360§ 5.1-52. Expenditure for planning, construction and maintenance of airports and landing fields. -360§ 5.1-53. Segregation and expenditure of amounts derived from taxes on motor fuel. -360§ 5.1-54. Repealed by Acts 1979, c. 272. -360§ 5.1-55. Recurring expenditures on airports and landing fields. Annotations Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 2C M.J. Aviation, §§ 1, 5, 7.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-51"><akn:num>§ 5.1-51</akn:num><akn:heading>Special fund accumulated from taxes, fees, etc</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text All funds accumulated from any special sales tax, excise tax or use tax, now or which may hereafter be imposed under the laws of this Commonwealth on aviation motor fue l purchased or used in this Commonwealth in the propulsion of aircraft, and all funds heretofore or hereafter accumulated from any fees for licensing or registering of airmen, aircraft and airports, now or hereafter imposed under the laws of this Commonw ealth, and all funds heretofore, and which may hereafter be, appropriated to the Department for the purpose of the promotion and development of aviation and airports, including the expense of the administration by the Department of the laws pertaining to aviation, as now or as may be hereafter enacted, and the jurisdiction for the administration thereof conferred on the Department, are hereby constituted a special fund within the Commonwealth Transportation Fund for the administration of the aviation la ws, heretofore or hereafter enacted, insofar as the administration has been, or shall be, imposed upon the Department, for the construction, maintenance and improvement of airports and landing fields and for the promotion of aviation in the interest of o perators and in the interest of the public. However, of the moneys expended for the construction, maintenance and improvement of airports at least thirty-five percent thereof computed over a period of three years shall be expended on carrier and reliever airports. Beginning July 1, 1998, any balances remaining in this fund at the end of the year shall be available for use in subsequent years for the purposes set forth in this chapter, and any interest income on such fund shall accrue to the fund. In considering or evaluating the application for or award of any grant of moneys under this section, the Board shall take into account the capacities of all airports wi thin the affected geographic region. History History. Code 1950, § 5-42; 1966, c. 576; 1970, c. 717; 1974, c. 388; 1 979, c. 272; 1997, c. 423; 1998, c. 480. Annotations Cross references. As to disposition of funds from Virginia Aircraft Sales and Use Tax, see § 58.1-1509. The 1998 amendment added the second paragraph.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-52"><akn:num>§ 5.1-52</akn:num><akn:heading>Expenditure for planning, construction and maintenance of airports and landing fields</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Such special fund shall be expended and disbursed by order of the Department, through the medium of warrants drawn by the Comptroller, for the reasonable and necessary costs of administration of the Department and for the planning, construction, maintenance and improvement of airports and landing fields, to which the public now has, or which it is proposed shall have, access, and for the promotion of aviation in the in terest of operators generally. Such expenditures and disbursements may be in the form of grants or loans to such person or persons as may be, in the discretion of the Board, entitled thereto in the interest of the public. Such grants or loans shall be ma de under such terms and conditions, as may be fixed by the Board and, in the case of loans, the rate of interest and the terms of repayment thereof as may be fixed by the Board. In considering or evaluating the application for or award of any grant of moneys under this section, the Board shall take into account the capacities of all airports wi thin the affected geographic region. History History. Code 1950, § 5-43; 1966, c. 576; 1970, c. 717; 1979, c. 272; 1 998, c. 480. Annotations The 1998 amendment added the second paragraph.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-53"><akn:num>§ 5.1-53</akn:num><akn:heading>Segregation and expenditure of amounts derived from taxes on motor fuel</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The special fund created and provided for in § 5.1-51 shall be so set up on the books of the Comptroller as to segregate the amounts paid into the fund as a direct t ax upon aviation motor fuel purchased by operators of airplanes and aircraft, and no portion of such fund, accumulated in the manner hereinbefore provided, shall ever be used for any other purpose than for the administration of the aviation laws and the construction, maintenance and improvement of airports and landing fields, and no portion of the same shall be covered into the general fund of the state treasury, such funds derived in the manner aforesaid being hereby irrevocably appropriated for promot ion of aviation in the interest of operators and of the public, as provided in this chapter, and to the extent necessary only, for the administration of this and other aviation laws. History History. Code 1950, § 5-44; 1966, c. 576; 1970, c. 717.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-54"><akn:num>§ 5.1-54</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 1979, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>272.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-55"><akn:num>§ 5.1-55</akn:num><akn:heading>Recurring expenditures on airports and landing fields</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text No part of such special fund shall be used for recurring expenditures on any airport or landing field under this chapter; except that recurring expenditures may be made where the Department deems such expenditure to be necessary for the preservation of the safety of the public. History History. Code 1950, § 5-46; 1966, c. 576; 1979, c. 272. Chapter 6. Virginia Airports Authority. -360§§ 5.1-56 through 5.1-76.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-56"><akn:num>§ 5.1-56</akn:num><akn:heading>5</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>1-56 through 5.1-76. Text Repealed by Acts 1980, c. 750. Annotations Cross references. For present sections covering the subject matter of the repealed sections, see §§ 5.1-2.5 through 5.1-2.24. As to the Virginia Aviation Board as successor to the Virginia Airports Authority, see § 5.1-2.23. Chapter 7. Emplaning Service Fee. -360§§ 5.1-77 through 5.1-82.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-77"><akn:num>§ 5.1-77</akn:num><akn:heading>5</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>1-77 through 5.1-82. Text Repealed by Acts 1980, c. 721. Chapter 8. Financial Responsibility. -360§§ 5.1-83 through 5.1-88.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-83"><akn:num>§ 5.1-83</akn:num><akn:heading>5</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>1-83 through 5.1-88. Text Repealed by Acts 1970, c. 707. Annotations Cross references. For present statute covering the subject matter of the repealed sections, see § 5.1-88.1 et seq. Chapter 8.1. Financial Responsibility. -360§ 5.1-88.1. Proof of financial responsibility to be furnished for each aircraft. -360§ 5.1-88.2. What constitutes proof of financial responsibility. -360§ 5.1-88.3. Certain sections of Code incorporated by reference; definitions. -360§ 5.1-88.4. Cancellation of insurance or corporate surety bond. -360§ 5.1-88.5. Repealed by Acts 1988, c. 588. -360§ 5.1-88.6. Parachute jump training schools; disclosure of liability insurance coverage; penalty. § 5.1-88.1. Proof of financial responsibility to be furnished for each aircraft. Text No aircraft, as defined in § 5.1-1 except a public aircraft or a balloon shall be registered by the Department unless and until the applicant thereof furnishes proof of financial responsibility in the amounts required by this chapter for each aircraft for which a registration is applied for. History History. Code 1950, § 5.1-83; 1968, c. 773; 1970, c. 707; 1979, c. 272; 1988, c. 588; 2017, c. 793. Annotations The 2017 amendments. The 2017 amendment by c. 793 substituted registered for licensed and registration for license. § 5.1-88.2. What constitutes proof of financial responsibility. Text A. The followi ng shall constitute proof of financial responsibility as required by § 5.1-88.1: 1. The i ssuance, by an insurance company licensed to write such insurance in this Commonwealth, of a policy or policies of bodily injury and property damage liability insurance, or a policy or policies written pursuant to Chapter 48 (§ 38.2-4805.1 et seq.) of Title 38.2 that provide coverage with respect to each such aircraft in the amount of $50,000 because of bodily injury to or death of one person in any one accident, including passenger liability, and $100,000 because of bodily injury to or death of two or more persons in any one accident, including passenger liability, and to a limit of $25,000 because of injury to or destruction of property of others in any one accident; or a single limit policy in the sum of $250,000, covering bodily injury and prope rty damage liability in any one accident, including passenger liability of $50,000 per passenger seat; or 2. The execution of a bond by the registrant and by a surety company authorized to transact business in this Commonwealth conditioned for payment in amounts and under the same circumstanc es as would be required in a policy of bodily injury liability and property damage liability insurance, as required by the provisions of subdivision A 1; or 3. The delivery to the Department of $250,000 in cash or an irrevocable letter of credit in the amount of $250,000 from a depository institution as defined in § 2.2-4701. Such money or securities so delivered to the Department shall be placed by it in the custody of the State Treasurer and shall be subject to execution to satisfy any judgment within the limits on amounts required by this chapter for personal injury and property damage liability insurance. B. Notwithstan ding the provisions of subsection A of this section, for an aircraft commonly known as an ultralight, as the same is now and may hereafter be defined by the Federal Aviation Administration, the proof of financial responsibility required by § 5 .1-88.1 may be satisfied by the issuance as to that aircraft of a single limit insurance policy in the sum of $100,000 covering bodily injury and property damage liability in any one accident, that is issued by an insurance company licensed to write such insurance in this Commonwealth or written pursuant to Chapter 48 (§ 38.2-4805.1 et seq.) of Title 38.2. History History. Code 1950, § 5.1-84; 1968, c. 773; 1970, c. 707; 1979, c. 272; 1984, c. 169; 1992, c. 810; 2005, c. 451; 2007, c. 207; 2017, c. 793. Annotations The 2005 amendments. The 2005 amendment by c. 451 substituted Title 38.2 that provide for Title 38.2, which provide in subdivision A 1; in subsection B, deleted by an insurance company licensed to write such insurance in this Commonwealth following aircraft and inserted that is issued by an insurance company licensed to write such insurance in this Commonwealth or written pursuant to Chapter 48 ( § 38.2-4800 et seq.) of Title 38.2. The 2007 amendments. The 2007 amendment by c. 207 rewrote the first sentence of subdivision A 3. The 2017 amendments. The 2017 amendment by c. 793, in subdivision A 2, substituted registrant for licensee and deleted of this section following provisions of subdivision A 1. § 5.1-88.3. Certain sections of Code incorporated by reference; definitions. Text The provisions of §§ 46.2-424, 46.2-447, 46.2-448, 46.2-449, 46.2-450, 46.2-451, 46.2-452, 46.2-456, 46.2-457, 46.2-458, 46.2-461, and 46.2-463 shall apply to all policies of insurance or other evidence of financial responsibility furnished hereunder except that whenever the word Commissioner appears in any of said sections it shall be taken to mean the Director of the Department of Aviation; and whenever the word Department or Department of Motor Vehicles appears, it shall be taken to mean as well the Department of Aviation. History History. Code 1950, § 5.1-86; 1968, c. 773; 1970, c. 707; 1979, c. 272. § 5.1-88.4. Cancellation of insurance or corporate surety bond. Text No policy of insurance or corporate surety bond issued pursuant to this chapter may be canceled or terminated, except for nonpayment of premiums, until at least thirty days after notice of cancellation or termination of said policy of insurance or corporate surety bond has been filed in the office of the Department, except that a subsequent policy or corporate surety bond procured and certified to the Department shall on the effective date thereof terminate the insurance or corporate surety bond previously in effect with respect to any aircraft designated in both policies or corporate surety bonds. History History. Code 1950, § 5.1-87; 1968, c. 773; 1970, c. 707; 1979, c. 272. § 5.1-88.5. Repealed by Acts 1988, c. 588. § 5.1-88.6. Parachute jump training schools; disclosure of liability insurance coverage; penalty. Text A. Every perso n operating a parachute jump training school in the Commonwealth shall disclose to his students whether he has obtained, and is maintaining, personal injury liability insurance, as defined in § 38.2-117, for the benefit and protection of such students during their training. B. The disclos ure required by this section shall be in writing and provided to every student prior to the commencement of any training. C. Any person failing to provide the disclosure required by this section shall be guilty of a Class 3 misdemeanor. History History. 1993, c. 46. Annotations The number of this section was assigned by the Virginia Code Commission, the number in the 1993 act having been 5.1-88.5. Cross references. As to punishment for Class 3 misdemeanors, see § 18.2-11. Chapter 8.2. Financial Responsibility of Owners of Airports and Landing Areas Required to be Licensed. -360§ 5.1-88.7. Proof of financial responsibility to be furnished for licensed airports or landing areas. -360§ 5.1-88.8. What constitutes proof of financial responsibility. -360§ 5.1-88.9. Certain sections of Code incorporated by reference; definitions. -360§ 5.1-88.10. Cancellation of insurance. § 5.1-88.7. Proof of financial responsibility to be furnished for licensed airports or landing areas. Text No airport or landing area shall be licensed by the Department unless and until the applicant thereof furnishes proof of financial responsibility at least in the amount s required by this chapter. Private-use airports required to be licensed by virtue of being located within five miles of a licensed public-use airport shall not be required to provide proof of financial responsibility. History History. 1995, cc. 682, 690; 2007, c. 206. Annotations The 2007 amendments. The 2007 amendment by c. 206 added the last sentence. § 5.1-88.8. What constitutes proof of financial responsibility. Text The following shall constitute proof of financial responsibility as required by § 5.1-88.7: 1. The i ssuance, by an insurance company licensed to write such insurance in the Commonwealth, of a policy of bodily injury and property damage liability insurance or a policy or policies written pursuant to Chapter 48 (§ 38.2-4805.1 et seq.) of Title 38.2, w hich provide coverage with respect to each airport or landing area in the amount of one million dollars covering bodily injury and property damage liability in any one accident; or 2. The delivery to the Department of one million dollars cash or in securities such as fiduciaries may invest in as provided by §§ 64.2-1502 through 64.2-1505. Such money or securit ies so delivered to the Department shall be placed by it in the custody of the State Treasurer and shall be subject to execution to satisfy any judgment within the limits on amounts required by this chapter for personal injury and property damage liabili ty insurance. History History. 1995, cc. 682, 690. Annotations Editors note. At the direction of the Virginia Code Commission, the reference to §§ 26-40.01 through 26-44 was changed to §§ 64.2-1502 through 64.2-1505  to conform to the recodification of Title 26 by Acts 2012, c. 614, effective October 1, 2012. § 5.1-88.9. Certain sections of Code incorporated by reference; definitions. Text The provisions of §§ 46.2-424, 46.2-447 through 46.2-452, 46.2-456 through 46.2-458, 46.2-461, and 46.2-463 shall apply to all policies of insurance or other evid ence of financial responsibility hereunder except that whenever the word Commissioner appears in any of said sections it shall be taken to mean the Director of the Department of Aviation; and whenever the word Department or Department of Motor Vehicles appears, it shall also be taken to mean the Department of Aviation and ...</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-89"><akn:num>§ 5.1-89</akn:num><akn:heading>Definitions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Whenever used in this chapter unless expressly stated otherwise: (a) The term person means any individual, firm, copartnership, corporation, company, association or joint-stock association, and includes any trustee, receiver, assignee, or personal representative thereof. (b) The term aircraft means any contrivance, except a contrivance operating twenty-four inches or less above ground or water level, now known or hereafter invented, used, or des igned for navigation of, or flight in, the airspace in the transportation of passengers, property or mail. (c) The term common carrier by aircraft means any person who undertakes, whether directly or by a lease or any other arrangement, to transport passengers, property for the gener al public, or mail by aircrafts for compensation (wholly within the airspace of the Commonwealth), whether over regular or irregular routes, including such aircraft operations of carriers by rail, water or motor vehicle and of express or forwarding compa nies. (d) The term restricted common carrier by aircraft means any person who undertakes, whether directly or by lease or other arrangement, to transport passengers or property of any restricted class or classes by aircraft for compensation whether over regular or irregular routes. (e) [Repealed.] (f) The term air carrier includes a common carrier by aircraft, a restricted common carrier by aircraft, and a contract carrier by aircraft. (g) The term broker means any person not included in the term air carrier and not a bona fide employee or agent of any such carrier, who, as principal or agent, sells or offers for sale any transportation subject to this chapter, or negotiates for, or holds himself out by solicitation, advertisement, or otherwise as one who sells, provides, furnishes, contracts, or arranges for such transportation. (h) The services and transportation to which this chapter applies include all aircraft operated by, for, or in the interest of, any air carrier irrespective of ownership or contract, express or implied, together with all facilities and property operated or controlled by any such carrier or carriers and used in the transportation of passengers, property or mail or in the performance of any service in connection therewith . (i) The term certificate means a certificate of public convenience and necessity issued by the State Corporation Commission to common carriers by aircraft and restricted common carriers by aircraft under this chapter. (j) [Repealed.] (k) The term airport means a landing area used regularly by aircraft for receiving or discharging passengers or cargo, and open to the public for use. (l) The term landing area means any locality, either of land or water, including airports and intermediate landing fields, which is used, or intended to be used, for the landing and takeoff of aircraft, whether or not facilities are provided for the shelter, servicing, or repair of aircraft, or for receiving or discharging passengers or cargo, and open to the public for such use. (m) The term airspace means all airspace above the lands and waters within the boundary of this Commonwealth. (n) For the purposes of this chapter, Commission means the State Corporation Commission. History History. Code 1950, § 56-142; 1952, c. 597; 1970, c. 708; 1979, c. 272; 1980, c. 721.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-90"><akn:num>§ 5.1-90</akn:num><akn:heading>Exempted aircraft</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text This chapter shall not be construed to cover or include aircraft used exclusively in transporting or handling United States mail, or aircraft while used exclusively in interstate commerce; provided, however, that any common carrier of passengers by airplane holding proper authority for and operating in interstate commerce on January 1, 1970, in the transportation of passengers between any licensed airport adjacent to o r within three miles of the Virginia State Line on the one hand and any other licensed airport in Virginia on the other, shall, without further proceedings, be issued a certificate by the Commission authorizing such operations as a common carrier of pass engers by aircraft in intrastate commerce if application is made to the Commission within 120 days after this section takes effect. Pending the determination of any such application, the continuance of such operation without a certificate shall be lawful . History History. Code 1950, § 56-143; 1952, c. 597; 1970, c. 708. § 5.1-90.1. Incidental transportation of certain passengers and property by motor vehicle. Text Nothing in this chapter shall be construed to prohibit the transportation of property or guards or other attendants of such property by motor vehicle when such transpor tation is incidental to transportation by aircraft, provided that such transportation shall not exceed twenty-five miles from airport to destination of such guards or other attendants or property. History History. 1972, c. 281. Annotations Editors note. At the direction of the Virginia Code Commission, deleted or in Chapter 12 (§ 56-273 et seq.) of Title 56 following Nothing in this chapter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-91"><akn:num>§ 5.1-91</akn:num><akn:heading>Air carriers to comply with chapter; subject to regulation by Commission</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text No air carrier shall operate any aircraft for the transportation of passengers or property for compensation in the airspace of this Commonwealth except in accordance wi th the provisions of this chapter, and every such air carrier is hereby declared to be subject to control, supervision and regulation by the Commission. History History. Code 1950, § 56-144; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-92"><akn:num>§ 5.1-92</akn:num><akn:heading>Regulation by Commission; reports; prevention of discrimination</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Commission shall supervise, regulate and control all air carriers, doing business in this Commonwealth, in all matters relating to the performance of their public d uties and their charges therefor, and shall correct abuses therein by such air carriers; and to that end the Commission shall, from time to time, prescribe reasonable rules, regulations, forms and reports for such air carriers in furtherance of the admin istration and operation of this chapter; and the Commission shall have the right at all times to require from such air carriers special reports and statements under oath, concerning their business. The Commission shall, from time to time, make and enforce such requirements, rules and regulations as may be necessary to prevent unjust and unreasonable discrimination s by any air carrier in favor of, or against, any person, locality, community or connecting carrier in the matter of service, schedule, efficiency of transportation or otherwise, in connection with the public duties of such air carriers; and the Commissi on shall administer and enforce all provisions of this chapter, and prescribe reasonable rules, regulations and procedure looking to that end. History History. Code 1950, § 56-145; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-93"><akn:num>§ 5.1-93</akn:num><akn:heading>Regulation of brokers</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Commission shall also regulate brokers and make and enforce reasonable requirements respecting their licenses, financial responsibility, accounts, records, reports, operations and practices. History History. Code 1950, § 56-146; 1970, c. 708. Article 2. Issuance of Certificates of Convenience and Rights Thereunder. -360§ 5.1-94. Required certificate of public convenience and necessity. -360§ 5.1-95. Application for certificate; notices, etc. -360§ 5.1-96. Fees in connection with certificates. -360§ 5.1-97. Hearing on application; action of Commission. -360§ 5.1-98. Factors to be considered by the Commission in granting certificates. -360§ 5.1-99. Occasional deviations from authorized routes; emergency landings. -360§ 5.1-100. Transportation of baggage, mail, etc., with passengers. -360§ 5.1-101. Chartered parties covered by common carriers. -360§ 5.1-102. Schedule changes require Commission approval.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-94"><akn:num>§ 5.1-94</akn:num><akn:heading>Required certificate of public convenience and necessity</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text No common carrier by aircraft or restricted common carrier by aircraft (not herein exempted) shall engage in intrastate operation in the airspace of this Commonwealth w ithout first having obtained from the Commission a certificate of public convenience and necessity authorizing such operation. History History. Code 1950, § 56-147; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-95"><akn:num>§ 5.1-95</akn:num><akn:heading>Application for certificate; notices, etc</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Commission shall prescribe the form of the application for a certificate of convenience and necessity, and such reasonable requirements as to notices, publication, proof of service and information as may in its judgment be necessary. History History. Code 1950, § 56-148; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-96"><akn:num>§ 5.1-96</akn:num><akn:heading>Fees in connection with certificates</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Every air carrier, upon filing with the Commission an application for a certificate, shall deposit with the Commission as a filing fee the sum of $100, and for the tran sfer of such certificate the sum of $100, and for the issuance of a duplicate certificate the sum of $5; provided, however, that an applicant for a certificate in lieu of an existing certificate, as provided by law, shall not be required to pay the fees prescribed in this section. History History. Code 1950, § 56-149; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-97"><akn:num>§ 5.1-97</akn:num><akn:heading>Hearing on application; action of Commission</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Upon the filing of an application for a certificate of public convenience and necessity, the Commission shall, within a reasonable time, fix a time and place of hearing on such application. If the Commission shall find that the proposed operation justified it, it shall issue a certificate to the applicant, subject to such terms, limitations and restrictions as the Commission may deem proper. If the Commission shall fin d the proposed operation not justified, the application shall be denied. History History. Code 1950, § 56-150; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-98"><akn:num>§ 5.1-98</akn:num><akn:heading>Factors to be considered by the Commission in granting certificates</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text In granting certificates of public convenience and necessity pursuant to § 5.1-94, the Commission shall take into consideration, among other things, the business exp erience of the particular passenger air carrier in the field of air operations, the financial stability of the carrier, the insurance coverage of the carrier, the type of aircraft which the carrier would employ, proposed routes and minimum schedules to b e established, whether the carrier could economically give adequate service to the communities involved, the need for the service, and any other factors which may affect the public interest. History History. Code 1950, § 56-152; 1970, c. 708. Annotations Law Review. For article on state constitutions and the environment, see 58 Va. L. Rev. 193 (1972).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-99"><akn:num>§ 5.1-99</akn:num><akn:heading>Occasional deviations from authorized routes; emergency landings</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A common carrier by aircraft, or a restricted common carrier by aircraft, operating under a certificate issued by the Commission may occasionally deviate from the route over which it is authorized to operate under the certificate, under such general or special rules and regulations as the Commission may prescribe. No air carrier shall be deemed to have violated any term, condition, or limitation of its certificate by landing or taking off during an emergency at a point not named in its certificate or by operating in an emergency, under regulations which may be prescribed by the Commission, between terminal and intermediate points other than those specified in its certificate. History History. Code 1950, § 56-153; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-100"><akn:num>§ 5.1-100</akn:num><akn:heading>Transportation of baggage, mail, etc</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>, with passengers. Text A certificate for the transportation of passengers may include, when so authorized by the Commission, authority to transport, in the same aircraft with passengers, the baggage of such passengers, newspapers, express parcels, or United States mail when the transportation thereof is authorized by the government of the United States of America; provided that the total weight of the aircraft and its contents shall not exce ed that weight authorized by the Operations Record of the individual aircraft. History History. Code 1950, § 56-154; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-101"><akn:num>§ 5.1-101</akn:num><akn:heading>Chartered parties covered by common carriers</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Any common carrier by aircraft transporting passengers under a certificate issued by the Commission may operate to any place special or chartered parties, under such re asonable rules and regulations as the Commission may prescribe. History History. Code 1950, § 56-155; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-102"><akn:num>§ 5.1-102</akn:num><akn:heading>Schedule changes require Commission approval</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A common carrier by aircraft or a restricted common carrier by aircraft operation under a certificate issued by the Commission shall not make any change in schedules or service without having first received the approval of the Commission for such change in schedules or service. History History. Code 1950, § 56-156; 1970, c. 708. Article 3. Contract Carriers and Limited For-Hire Service. -360§§ 5.1-103 through 5.1-106. Repealed by Acts 1980, c. 721.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-103"><akn:num>§ 5.1-103</akn:num><akn:heading>5</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>1-103 through 5.1-106. Repealed by Acts 1980, c. 721. Annotations Cross references. For present provisions as to contract carriers and limited for-hire service, see §§ 5.1-9.2 through 5.1-9.9. Article 4. Temporary Authority. -360§ 5.1-107. Issuance of temporary authority by Commission pending hearing on application for certificate.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-107"><akn:num>§ 5.1-107</akn:num><akn:heading>Issuance of temporary authority by Commission pending hearing on application for certificate</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text To enable the provision of service for which there is an immediate and urgent need to a point or between points in Virginia, the Commission, may, pending its determinat ion of an application for such permanent authority, in its discretion and without hearing or other proceeding, grant temporary authority for such service by common carrier by aircraft or restricted common carrier by aircraft, as the case may be. Such tem porary authority shall be valid for such time as the Commission shall specify but not for more than an aggregate of 180 days, and shall create no presumption that corresponding permanent authority will be granted thereafter. History History. 1970, c. 708. Annotations Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 8A M.J. Express Companies, § 2. Article 5. Regulation of Brokers. -360§ 5.1-108. When brokers license required. -360§ 5.1-109. Application for brokers license. -360§ 5.1-110. Hearing on such application and action thereon. -360§ 5.1-111. Authority over brokers; bond. -360§ 5.1-112. Brokers license not substitute for other certificates or permits required.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-108"><akn:num>§ 5.1-108</akn:num><akn:heading>When brokers license required</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text No person shall for compensation sell or offer for sale transportation subject to this chapter or shall make any contract, agreement, or arrangement to provide, procure , furnish, or arrange for such transportation or shall hold himself or itself out by advertisement, solicitation, or otherwise as one who sells, provides, procures, contracts, or arranges for such transportation, unless such person holds a brokers li cense issued by the Commission to engage in such transactions; provided that the provisions of this section shall not apply to any carrier holding a certificate or permit under the provisions of this chapter or to any bona fide employee or agent of such carrier so far as concerns transportation to be furnished wholly by such carrier or jointly with other air carriers holding like certificates or permits, or with a common carrier by railroad, motor vehicle, express or water; nor shall they apply to any a ir carrier not engaged in intrastate operations or to any bona fide employee of such carrier. History History. Code 1950, § 56-162; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-109"><akn:num>§ 5.1-109</akn:num><akn:heading>Application for brokers license</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Commission shall prescribe the form of application for a brokers license and such reasonable requirements and information as may in its judgment be necessary, a nd may assess a fee of ten dollars for filing. History History. Code 1950, § 56-163; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-110"><akn:num>§ 5.1-110</akn:num><akn:heading>Hearing on such application and action thereon</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Upon the filing of an application for a brokers license the Commission may fix a time and place for the hearing of the application and require such notices, publica tion, or other service as may, in its judgment, be necessary. If the Commission finds the application proper and in the public interest it shall issue a license, subject to such terms, limitations and restrictions as the Commission may deem proper. History History. Code 1950, § 56-164; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-111"><akn:num>§ 5.1-111</akn:num><akn:heading>Authority over brokers; bond</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Commission shall have the same authority over persons operating under and holding a brokerage license as it has over air carriers under this chapter and shall requi re a broker to furnish bond or other security approved by the Commission and sufficient for the protection of travelers or shippers by aircraft. History History. Code 1950, § 56-165; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-112"><akn:num>§ 5.1-112</akn:num><akn:heading>Brokers license not substitute for other certificates or permits required</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text No person who holds a brokers license under this chapter shall engage in transportation subject to this chapter unless he holds a certificate or permit as provided in this chapter. In the execution of any contract, agreement, or arrangement to sell, provide, procure, furnish, or arrange for such transportation, it shall be unlawful for such person to employ any aircraft which is not the lawful holder of an effectiv e certificate or permit issued as provided in this chapter. History History. Code 1950, § 56-166; 1970, c. 708. Article 6. Duration, Revocation, Transfer and Value of Certificates, etc.; Penalties. -360§ 5.1-113. Duration of certificates, registrations, etc.; suspension, revocation, or amendment; penalties. -360§ 5.1-114. Transfer or lease of certificate. -360§ 5.1-115. No value allowed for certificates.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-113"><akn:num>§ 5.1-113</akn:num><akn:heading>Duration of certificates, registrations, etc</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>; suspension, revocation, or amendment; penalties. Text Certificates, permits, registrations, and licenses issued under the provisions of this chapter shall be effective from the dates specified therein and shall remain in e ffect until terminated as herein provided. The Commission may at any time, by its order duly entered after hearing held after notice to the holder of any such certificate, permit, registration, or license and an opportunity to such holder to be heard at which it shall be proved that such holder has willfully made any misrepresentation of a material fact in obtaining such certificate, permit, registration, or license, or has willfully violated or refused to observe the laws of this Commonwealth touching such certificate, permit, registration, or license, or any of the terms of his certificate, permit, registration, or license, or any of the Commissions proper orders, rules, or regulations, impose a penalty not exceeding $1,000, which may be collecte d by the process of the Commission as provided by law; or the Commission may suspend, revoke, alter, or amend any such certificate, permit, registration, or license for any of the causes set forth above. But no such certificate, permit, registration, or license shall be revoked, altered, or amended (except upon application of the holder thereof) unless the holder thereof shall willfully fail to comply, within a reasonable time to be fixed by the Commission, with the lawful order of the Commission or wit h the lawful rule or regulation of the Commission, or with the term, condition, or limitation of such certificate, permit, registration, or license, found by the Commission to have been violated by such holder. Proceedings for the imposition of any penalty provided for in this section may be commenced upon the complaint of any person or upon the Commissions own initiative. From any order of the Commission suspending, revoking, altering or amending any certificate, permit, registration, or license, the holder thereof shall have the right o f appeal to the Supreme Court of Virginia, as a matter of right, as in other cases of appeals from the Commission. History History. Code 1950, § 56-167; 1970, c. 708; 2017, c. 793. Annotations The 2017 amendments. The 2017 amendment by c. 793 inserted registrations and registration throughout the section.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-114"><akn:num>§ 5.1-114</akn:num><akn:heading>Transfer or lease of certificate</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Any certificate issued under this chapter may be transferred or leased, subject to the approval of the Commission and under such reasonable rules and regulations as may be prescribed by the Commission. An application for such approval shall be made jointly by the transferor and transferee, or lessor and lessee. No certificate shall be transferred, leased or otherwise disposed of when any consideration is paid or promised which exceeds the then value of the tangible property so ld in connection with the transfer or lease of such certificate. History History. Code 1950, § 56-168; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-115"><akn:num>§ 5.1-115</akn:num><akn:heading>No value allowed for certificates</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text No value shall be allowed for any purpose for any certificate issued under this chapter. History History. Code 1950, § 56-169; 1970, c. 708. Article 7. Bonds or Insurance. -360§ 5.1-116. Bonds, insurance or certificate of insurance required prior to issuance of certificate or permit. -360§ 5.1-117. Bonds or insurance to be kept in force. -360§ 5.1-118. Policies, bonds or certificates to be filed with Commission; securities deposited in lieu thereof. -360§ 5.1-119. Condition of bond, etc. -360§ 5.1-120. Effect of failure to give security.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-116"><akn:num>§ 5.1-116</akn:num><akn:heading>Bonds, insurance or certificate of insurance required prior to issuance of certificate or permit</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text No certificate or permit shall be issued by the Commission to any air carrier until and after such air carrier shall have filed with, and the same has been approved by, the Commission, an insurance policy, bond or certificate of insurance in lieu thereof, certifying that such policy or bond covers the liability of such air carrier in accordance with the provisions of this article, issued by an insurance company or asso ciation or other insurer authorized to transact business in this Commonwealth, or bonds, to an amount approved by the Commission, of the Commonwealth of Virginia, of the United States of America, or of any municipality in this Commonwealth. Such state, f ederal, or municipal bonds shall be deposited with the State Treasurer, and such surety shall not be reduced during the life of such certificate or permit, except in accordance with an order of the Commission. History History. Code 1950, § 56-170; 1970, c. 708; 1975, c. 211.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-117"><akn:num>§ 5.1-117</akn:num><akn:heading>Bonds or insurance to be kept in force</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Each holder of a certificate or permit issued by the Commission shall also keep in force at all times insurance or a bond underwritten by an insurer approved or authori zed to do business in Virginia, or by one who is eligible as a surplus lines insurer in accordance with the provisions of Chapter 48 (§ 38.2-4805.1 et seq.) of Title 38.2 in amounts of not less than the following minimum limits: (a) liability for bodi ly injury to or death to any one person, passenger or other, aboard the aircraft, $75,000; and a limit for each occurrence in any one aircraft of at least an amount equal to the sum produced by multiplying $75,000 by seventy-five percent of the total num ber of passenger seats installed in the aircraft; and for the loss or damage to cargo owned by other than the insured, at least $10,000 for each occurrence; provided, however, that a holder of a permit issued by the Commission shall not be required to fi le any cargo insurance, bond or bonds for cargo liability for the hauling of property transported under contract. However, in no event shall the limits required herein for air common carriers be less than those prescribed for like carriers by the Civil A eronautics Board or the Federal Aviation Administration. History History. Code 1950, § 56-171; 1970, c. 708. Annotations Editors note. At the direction of the Virginia Code Commission, 38.2-4805.1 was substituted for 38.2-4800.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-118"><akn:num>§ 5.1-118</akn:num><akn:heading>Policies, bonds or certificates to be filed with Commission; securities deposited in lieu thereof</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Each holder of a certificate or permit issued by the Commission shall keep on file with the Commission an insurance policy, bond or certificate of insurance in lieu the reof, certifying that such policy or bond covers the liability of such air carrier in accordance with the provisions of this article, issued by an insurance company or association or other insurer authorized to transact business in this Commonwealth, and such insurance, bond or certificate of insurance filed with the Commission shall be kept in full force at all times. The policy, bond or certificate of insurance shall remain in the files of the Commission six months after the insurance or bond has expi red or has been cancelled for any cause. If federal, state or municipal bonds are deposited with the State Treasurer in lieu thereof, such bonds shall remain so deposited until six months after the authority for use of equipment insured has expired or is cancelled for any cause, unless otherwise ordered by the Commission. History History. Code 1950, § 56-172; 1970, c. 708; 1975, c. 211.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-119"><akn:num>§ 5.1-119</akn:num><akn:heading>Condition of bond, etc</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The insurance bond, or other security, shall obligate the insurer or surety to pay any final judgment for damages sustained by the passengers, shippers, or consignees f or injury to any passenger or passengers, or for loss or damage to property entrusted to such air carrier when a cargo policy is required, and for any and all injuries to persons and loss of, or damage to, property resulting from the negligent operation of any aircraft. History History. Code 1950, § 56-173; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-120"><akn:num>§ 5.1-120</akn:num><akn:heading>Effect of failure to give security</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Failure of any holder of a certificate or permit issued by and under the authority of the Commission to comply with any of the requirements of §§ 5.1-116, 5.1-117 or 5.1-118 shall be cause without further proceedings for the revocation or suspension of the certificate or permit, and upon further proceedings for the imposition of a fine not exceeding $1,000. History History. Code 1950, § 56-174; 1970, c. 708. Article 8. Through Routes, Service, Rates, etc. -360§ 5.1-121. Duties of carriers of passengers as to through routes, equipment, rates, regulations, etc. -360§ 5.1-122. Duties of carriers of property as to service, rates and regulations. -360§ 5.1-123. Through routes, joint rates, etc., not required may be established. -360§ 5.1-124. Undue preference not permitted. -360§ 5.1-125. Complaints; action of Commission thereon or on own initiative. -360§ 5.1-126. Establishment of through routes, etc., by Commission. -360§ 5.1-127. Prescribing divisions of joint rates. -360§ 5.1-128. New rate schedule; hearing; suspension; action thereon. -360§ 5.1-129. Goodwill, certificate, etc., not element of value in rate making. -360§ 5.1-130. Criteria for establishment of rates. -360§ 5.1-131. Other remedies not extinguished. -360§ 5.1-132. Tariffs showing rates, fares and charges, etc. -360§ 5.1-133. Unlawful to charge other than published tariff. -360§ 5.1-134. Changes in tariffs, etc. -360§ 5.1-135. No transportation except when rates have been filed and published. -360§ 5.1-136. Free passes or reduced rates. -360§ 5.1-137. Payment of rates and charges before delivery of freight. -360§ 5.1-138. Liability for additional charges. -360§ 5.1-139. Commission may enter judgment for refunds due public and collect and distribute same.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-121"><akn:num>§ 5.1-121</akn:num><akn:heading>Duties of carriers of passengers as to through routes, equipment, rates, regulations, etc</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Every common carrier or restricted common carrier of passengers by aircraft shall establish reasonable through routes with other such common carriers and provide safe a nd adequate service, equipment, and facilities for the transportation of passengers; shall establish, observe, and enforce just and reasonable individual and joint rates, fares and charges and just and reasonable regulations and practices relating theret o, and to the issuance, form, and substance of tickets, the carrying of personal, sample, and excess baggage, the facilities for transportation, and all other matters relating to or connected with the transportation of passengers; and in case of such joi nt rates, fares, and charges shall establish just, reasonable and equitable divisions thereof as between the carriers participating therein which shall not unduly prefer or prejudice any of such participating carriers. History History. Code 1950, § 56-176; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-122"><akn:num>§ 5.1-122</akn:num><akn:heading>Duties of carriers of property as to service, rates and regulations</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Every common carrier or restricted common carrier of property by aircraft shall provide safe and adequate service, equipment, and facilities for the transportation of p roperty; and shall establish, observe, and enforce just and reasonable rates, charges, and classifications, and just and reasonable regulations and practices relating thereto and to the manner and method of presenting, marking, packing, and delivering pr operty for transportation, the facilities for transportation, and all other matters relating to or connected with the transportation of property. History History. Code 1950, § 56-177; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-123"><akn:num>§ 5.1-123</akn:num><akn:heading>Through routes, joint rates, etc</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>, not required may be established. Text Common carriers or restricted common carriers of property by aircraft may establish reasonable routes and joint rates, charges, and classifications with other such carr iers or with common carriers by railroad, motor vehicle, express and/or water; and common carriers or restricted common carriers of passengers by aircraft may establish reasonable through routes and joint rates, fares, or charges with common carriers by railroad, motor vehicle, and/or water. In case of such joint rates, fares or charges it shall be the duty of the carriers parties thereto to establish just and reasonable regulations and practices in connection therewith, and just, reasonable and equitab le divisions thereof as between the carriers participating therein which shall not unduly prefer or prejudice any of such participating carriers. History History. Code 1950, § 56-178; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-124"><akn:num>§ 5.1-124</akn:num><akn:heading>Undue preference not permitted</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text It shall be unlawful for any common carrier or restricted common carrier by aircraft to make, give, or cause any undue or unreasonable preference or advantage to any pa rticular person, port, gateway, locality, or description of traffic in any respect whatsoever, or to subject any particular person, port, gateway, locality, or description of traffic to any unjust discrimination or any undue or unreasonable prejudice or disadvantage in any respect whatsoever; provided, however, that this section shall not be construed to apply to discriminations, prejudices or disadvantages to the traffic of any other carrier of whatever description. History History. Code 1950, § 56-179; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-125"><akn:num>§ 5.1-125</akn:num><akn:heading>Complaints; action of Commission thereon or on own initiative</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Any person, state board, organization, or body politic may make complaint in writing to the Commission that any rate, fare, charge, classification, rule, regulation, or practice of any common carrier or restricted common carrier by aircraft, in effect or proposed to be put into effect, is or will be in violation of §§ 5.1-121 to 5.1-124, or § 5.1-133. Whenever after hearing, upon complaint or in an investigati on on its own initiative, the Commission shall be of the opinion that any individual or joint rate, fare, or charge, demanded, charged, or collected by any common carrier or restricted common carrier by aircraft or by any common or restricted common carr ier by aircraft in conjunction with any common carrier by railroad, motor vehicle, express and/or water, or any classification, rule, regulation or practice whatsoever of such carrier affecting such rate, fare, or charge or the value of the service there under, is or will be unjust or unreasonable or unjustly discriminatory or unduly preferential or unduly prejudicial, it shall determine and prescribe the lawful rate, fare, or charge or the maximum or minimum rate, fare, or charge thereafter to be observ ed, or the lawful classification, rule, regulation, or practice thereafter to be made effective. History History. Code 1950, § 56-180; 1970, c. 708; 1971, Ex. Sess., c. 1.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-126"><akn:num>§ 5.1-126</akn:num><akn:heading>Establishment of through routes, etc</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>, by Commission. Text The Commission shall, whenever deemed by it to be necessary or desirable in the public interest, after hearing, upon complaint or upon its own initiative without a comp laint, establish through routes, and joint rates, fares, charges, regulations, or practices, applicable to the transportation of passengers by common or restricted common carriers by aircraft, or the maximum or minimum to be charged, and the terms and co nditions under which such through routes shall be operated. History History. Code 1950, § 56-181; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-127"><akn:num>§ 5.1-127</akn:num><akn:heading>Prescribing divisions of joint rates</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Whenever, after hearing, upon complaint or upon its own initiative, the Commission is of opinion that the divisions of joint rates, fares or charges, applicable to the transportation of passengers or property by common or restricted common carriers by aircraft or by such carriers in conjunction with common carriers by railroad, motor vehicle, express and/or water are or will be unjust, unreasonable, inequitable, or und uly preferential or prejudicial as between the carriers parties thereto (whether agreed upon by such carriers, or any of them, or otherwise established), the Commission shall by order prescribe the just, reasonable, and equitable divisions thereof to be received by the several carriers. In cases where the joint rate, fare, or charge was established pursuant to a finding or order of the Commission and the divisions thereof are found by it to have been unjust, unreasonable, or inequitable, or unduly prefe rential or prejudicial, the Commission may also by order determine what would have been the just, reasonable, and equitable divisions thereof to be received by the several carriers, and require adjustment to be made in accordance therewith. The order of the Commission may require the adjustment of divisions between the carriers, in accordance with the order, from the date of filing the complaint or entry of order of investigation or such other date subsequent as the Commission finds justified and, in th e case of joint rates prescribed by the Commission, the order as to divisions may be made effective as a part of the original order. History History. Code 1950, § 56-182; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-128"><akn:num>§ 5.1-128</akn:num><akn:heading>New rate schedule; hearing; suspension; action thereon</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Whenever there shall be filed with the Commission any schedule stating a new individual or joint rate, fare, charge, or classification for the transportation of passeng ers or property by a common or restricted common carrier by aircraft, or by any such carrier in conjunction with a common carrier by railroad, motor vehicle, express and/or water, or any rule, regulation, or practice affecting such rate, fare, or charge, or the value of the service thereunder, the Commission, upon complaint of any interested party or upon its own initiative, if it so orders, without answer or other formal pleading by the interested carrier or carriers, but upon reasonable notice, may en ter upon a hearing concerning the lawfulness of such rate, fare or charge, or such rule, regulations or practice. Pending such hearing and the decision thereon the Commission, by filing with such schedule and delivering to the carrier or carriers affected thereby a statement in wri ting of its reasons for such suspension, may suspend the operation of such schedule and defer the use of such rate, fare, or charge, or such rule, regulation, or practice, for a period of 90 days and if the proceeding has not been concluded and a final o rder made within such period the Commission may, from time to time, extend the period of suspension by order, but not for a longer period in the aggregate than 180 days beyond the time when such rate, fare, charge, rule, regulation or practice would othe rwise go into effect. After such hearing, whether completed before or after the rate, fare, charge, classification, rule, regulation, or practice goes into effect, the Commission may make su ch order with reference thereto as would be proper in a proceeding instituted after it had become effective. If the proceeding has not been concluded and an order made within the period of suspension, the proposed change of rate, fare or charge, or class ification, rule, regulation, or practice, shall go into effect at the end of such period. History History. Code 1950, § 56-183; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-129"><akn:num>§ 5.1-129</akn:num><akn:heading>Goodwill, certificate, etc</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>, not element of value in rate making. Text In any proceeding to determine the justness or reasonableness of any rate, fare, or charge of any common or restricted common carrier by aircraft there shall not be tak en into consideration or allowed as evidence or elements of value of the property of such carrier either goodwill, earning power, or the certificate under which such carrier is operating; and in applying for and receiving a certificate under this chapter any such carrier shall be deemed to have agreed to the provisions of this section, on its own behalf and on behalf of all transferees or lessees of such certificate. History History. Code 1950, § 56-184; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-130"><akn:num>§ 5.1-130</akn:num><akn:heading>Criteria for establishment of rates</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text In the exercise of its power to prescribe just and reasonable rates for the transportation of passengers or property by common or restricted common carriers by aircraft the Commission shall give due consideration, among other factors, to the inherent advantages of transportation by such carriers; to the effect of rates upon the movement of traffic by such carriers; to the need, in the public interest, of adequate and e fficient transportation service by such carriers at the lowest cost consistent with the furnishing of such service; and to the need of such carriers for revenues sufficient to enable them, under honest, economical, and efficient management, to provide su ch service. History History. Code 1950, § 56-185; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-131"><akn:num>§ 5.1-131</akn:num><akn:heading>Other remedies not extinguished</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Nothing in the preceding nine sections (§§ 5.1-122 through 5.1-130) shall be held to extinguish any remedy or right of action not inconsistent therewith. History History. Code 1950, § 56-186; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-132"><akn:num>§ 5.1-132</akn:num><akn:heading>Tariffs showing rates, fares and charges, etc</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Every common carrier and restricted common carrier by aircraft shall file with the Commission, and print, and keep open to public inspection, tariffs showing all the ra tes, fares and charges for transportation, and all services in connection therewith, of passengers or property between points on its own route and between points on its own route and points on the route of any other such carrier, or on the route of any c ommon carrier by railroad, motor vehicle, express and/or water, when a through route and joint rate shall have been established. Such rates, fares, and charges shall be stated in terms of lawful money of the United States. The tariffs required by this se ction shall be published, filed, and posted in such form and manner, and shall contain such information, as the Commission by regulations shall prescribe; and the Commission is authorized to reject any tariff filed with it which is not in consonance with this section and with such regulations. Any tariff so rejected by the Commission shall be void and its use shall be unlawful. History History. Code 1950, § 56-187; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-133"><akn:num>§ 5.1-133</akn:num><akn:heading>Unlawful to charge other than published tariff</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text No common carrier or restricted common carrier by aircraft shall charge or demand or collect or receive a greater or less or different compensation for transportation o r for any service in connection therewith between the points enumerated in such tariff than the rates, fares, and charges specified in the tariff in effect at the time; and no such carrier shall refund or remit in any manner or by any device, directly or indirectly, or through any agent or broker or otherwise, any portion of the rates, fares, or charges so specified, or extend to any person any privileges or facilities for transportation except such as specified in its tariffs. History History. Code 1950, § 56-188; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-134"><akn:num>§ 5.1-134</akn:num><akn:heading>Changes in tariffs, etc</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text No change shall be made in any rate, fare, charge, or classification, or any rule, regulation, or practice affecting such rate, fare, charge, or classification, or the value of the service thereunder, specified in any effective tariff of a common carrier or restricted common carrier by aircraft, except after thirty days notice of the proposed change, filed and posted in accordance with § 5.1-132. Such notice sha ll plainly state the change proposed to be made and the time when such change will take effect. The Commission may, in its discretion and for good cause shown, allow such change upon notice less than that herein specified or modify the requirements of th is section and § 5.1-132 with respect to posting and filing of tariffs either in particular instances or by general order applicable to special or peculiar circumstances or conditions. History History. Code 1950, § 56-189; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-135"><akn:num>§ 5.1-135</akn:num><akn:heading>No transportation except when rates have been filed and published</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text No common carrier or restricted common carrier by aircraft, unless otherwise provided by this chapter, shall engage in the transportation of passengers or property unle ss the rates, fares, and charges upon which the same are transported by such carrier have been filed and published in accordance with the provisions of this chapter. History History. Code 1950, § 56-190; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-136"><akn:num>§ 5.1-136</akn:num><akn:heading>Free passes or reduced rates</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text No air carrier subject to the provisions of this chapter shall, directly or indirectly, issue or give any free ticket, free pass or free transportation for passengers, but nothing in this section shall apply (1) to the carriage, storage or handling of property free or at reduced rates, when such rates have been authorized or prescribed by the Commission for the United States, state or municipal governments, or for char itable purposes or to or from fairs and expositions for exhibition thereat, or (2) to the free carriage of homeless and destitute persons and the necessary agents employed in such transportation, or (3) to mileage, excursion or commutation passenger tick ets. Nor shall anything in this section be construed to prohibit any air carrier from giving reduced rates or free passage to ministers of religion, or regular traveling sec retaries of the Young Mens Christian Association or Young Womens Christian Association, whose duties require regular travel in supervising and directing Young Mens Christian or Young Womens Christian Association work, secretaries of duly organized religious work, or to indigent persons, or to inmates of the Confederate homes or State homes for disabled soldiers and sailors, or to disabled soldiers and sailors, including those about to enter, and those returning home after discharge; nor from giving free carriage to its own officers, employees, and members of their families, representatives of the press and members of the Department of State Police or to any other person or persons to whom the giving of such free carriage is not otherwis e prohibited by the law; nor to prevent the principal officers of any air carrier from exchanging passes or tickets with other air carriers of any air, motor vehicle, steamship, or electric railway companies for their officers, employees and members of t heir families. History History. Code 1950, § 56-191; 1970, c. 708; 1971, Ex. Sess., c. 17.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-137"><akn:num>§ 5.1-137</akn:num><akn:heading>Payment of rates and charges before delivery of freight</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text No common carrier or restricted common carrier by aircraft shall deliver or relinquish possession at destination of any freight transported by it until all tariff rates and charges thereon have been paid, except under such rules and regulations as the Commission may from time to time prescribe to govern the settlement of all such rates and charges, including rules and regulations for weekly or monthly settlement, and t o prevent unjust discrimination or undue preference or prejudice; provided, that the provisions of this section shall not be construed to prohibit any such carrier from extending credit in connection with rates and charges on freight transported for the United States, for any department, bureau, or agency thereof, or for any state or territory or political subdivision thereof, or for the District of Columbia. History History. Code 1950, § 56-192; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-138"><akn:num>§ 5.1-138</akn:num><akn:heading>Liability for additional charges</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text When any common carrier by aircraft is instructed by a shipper or consignor to deliver property transported by such carrier to a consignee other than the shipper or con signor, such consignee shall not be legally liable for transportation charges in respect of the transportation of such property (beyond those billed against him at the time of delivery for which he is otherwise liable) which may be found to be due after the property has been delivered to him, if the consignee (a) is an agent only and had no beneficial title in the property, and (b) prior to delivery of the property has notified the delivering carrier in writing of the fact of such agency and absence of beneficial title, and, in the case of a shipment reconsigned or diverted to a point other than that specified in the original bill of lading, has also notified the delivering carrier in writing of the name and address of the beneficial owner of the prope rty. In such cases the shipper or consignor, or, in the case of a shipment so reconsigned or diverted, the beneficial owner shall be liable for such additional charges, irrespective of any provisions to the contrary in the bill of lading or in the contra ct under which the shipment was made. If the consignee has given to the carrier erroneous information as to who is the beneficial owner, such consignee shall himself be liable for such additional charges, notwithstanding the foregoing provisions of this section. On shipments reconsigned or diverted by any agent who has furnished the carrier with a notice of agency and the proper name and address of the beneficial owner, and when such shipments are refused or abandoned at ultimate destination, the benefi cial owner shall be liable for all legally applicable charges in connection therewith. History History. Code 1950, § 56-193; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-139"><akn:num>§ 5.1-139</akn:num><akn:heading>Commission may enter judgment for refunds due public and collect and distribute same</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text If any air carrier or broker, upon the final decision of an appeal from the action of the Commission prescribing rates, charges, or classification of traffic, confirmin g or modifying the action of the Commission, shall fail to refund in the manner and within the time prescribed in the notice of the Commission all amounts which the appealing air carrier or broker may have collected pending the appeal, in excess of that authorized by such final decision, upon notice to such air carrier or broker by the Commission of such final decision, then the Commission, after thirty days notice to any such air carrier or broker, may, unless the amount required by such order be p aid to the clerk of the Commission, render and enter judgment in the name of the Commonwealth, for the use of the persons, firms and corporations entitled to the same, against any such air carrier or broker for the aggregate amount of such collections an d for the costs, and may enforce the amount of such judgment and costs by process of execution, as hereinbefore provided as to the enforcement of the judgments of the Commission. The Commission shall, upon the collection of such judgment, forthwith distr ibute the amount thereof, through its clerk, among the parties entitled thereto, respectively, in such manner as it may by its rules or orders prescribe, and shall, upon the payment or collection of any such judgment enter the same satisfied upon its rec ords, and have the same satisfied on the judgment lien docket of the court of any city or county where the same may have been docketed, and the satisfaction of any such judgment shall be a bar to any further action or recovery against any such air carrie r or broker to the extent of such recovery. History History. Code 1950, § 56-194; 1970, c. 708. Article 9. Miscellaneous. -360§ 5.1-140. Unlawful to disclose certain information. -360§ 5.1-141. Repealed by Acts 2001, c. 137. -360§ 5.1-142. Reports, records, etc. -360§ 5.1-143. Reports of accidents. -360§ 5.1-144. Certificate or permit holder not relieved of liability for negligence. -360§ 5.1-145. Enforcement under Department of State Police or Commission; concurrent jurisdiction for investigations of accidents. -360§ 5.1-146. Violations and penalties. -360§ 5.1-147. Disposition of fees or sums collected. -360§ 5.1-148. Employees of Commission not to have interest in carriers. -360§ 5.1-149. No property rights in airspace conferred by chapter. -360§ 5.1-150. Licenses, registrations, taxes, etc., not affected. -360§ 5.1-151. Right to amend, revoke, etc., rights, certificates or franchises.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-140"><akn:num>§ 5.1-140</akn:num><akn:heading>Unlawful to disclose certain information</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text It shall be unlawful for any air carrier or broker or any officer, receiver, trustee, lessee, agent, or employee of such carrier, broker, or person, or for any other pe rson authorized by such carrier, broker, or person to receive information, knowingly to disclose to, or permit to be acquired by any person other than the shipper or consignee, without the consent of such shipper or consignee, any information concerning the nature, kind, quantity, destination, consignee, or routing of any property tendered or delivered to such air carrier or broker for such transportation, which information may be used to the detriment or prejudice of such shipper or consignee, or which may improperly disclose his business transactions to a competitor; and it shall also be unlawful for any person to solicit or receive knowingly any such information which may be so used. Nothing in this chapter shall be construed to prevent the giving of such information in response to any legal process issued under the authority of any court, or to any officer or agent of the government of the United States or of any state, territory, or district thereof, in the exercise of his power, or to any officer or other duly authorized person seeking such information for the prosecution of persons charged with or suspected of crimes or to another carrier or broker, or its duly authorized agent, for the purpose of adjusting mutual traffic accounts in the ordinary course of business of such carriers or brokers. History History. Code 1950, § 56-195; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-141"><akn:num>§ 5.1-141</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 2001, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>137.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-142"><akn:num>§ 5.1-142</akn:num><akn:heading>Reports, records, etc</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text (a) The Commis sion is hereby authorized to require annual, periodic, or special reports from all air carriers except such as are exempted from the operation of the provisions of this chapter, to prescribe the manner and form in which such reports shall be made, and to require from such carriers specific answers to all questions upon which the Commission may deem information to be necessary. Such reports shall be under oath whenever the Commission so requires. The Commission may also require any air carrier to file wi th it a true copy of any contract, agreement, or arrangement between such carrier and any other carrier or person in relation to any traffic affected by the provisions of this chapter. (b) The Commis sion may, in its discretion, prescribe the forms of any and all accounts, records, and memoranda to be kept by air carriers and the length of time such accounts, records and memoranda shall be preserved, including the accounts, records, and memoranda of the movement of traffic, as well as of the receipts and expenditures of money. The Commission or its employees shall at all times have access to all lands, buildings, and equipment of air carriers used in connection with their operation and also all acco unts, records, and memoranda, including all documents, papers, and correspondence now existing, and kept, or required to be kept, by air carriers. The Commission and its employees shall have authority to inspect and examine any and all such lands, buildi ngs, equipment, accounts, records, and memoranda, including all documents, papers, and correspondence now or hereafter existing and kept or required to be kept by such carriers. This provision shall apply to receivers of carriers and to operating trustee s and, to the extent deemed necessary by the Commission, to persons having control, direct or indirect, over or affiliated with any air carrier. (c) As used in this section the term air carriers includes brokers. History History. Code 1950, § 56-197; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-143"><akn:num>§ 5.1-143</akn:num><akn:heading>Reports of accidents</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text It shall be the duty of the manager, agent or other proper officer of every air carrier doing business or operating in this Commonwealth to make to the Commission such report or reports as may be required by it, under oath, of all accidents in this Commonwealth resulting in injury to persons, equipment, or property of any kind, under such rules and regulations as may be prescribed by the Commission. History History. Code 1950, § 56-198; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-144"><akn:num>§ 5.1-144</akn:num><akn:heading>Certificate or permit holder not relieved of liability for negligence</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Nothing in this chapter shall relieve any holder of a certificate or permit by and under the authority of the Commission from any liability resulting from his negligenc e, whether or not he has complied with the requirements of this chapter. History History. Code 1950, § 56-199; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-145"><akn:num>§ 5.1-145</akn:num><akn:heading>Enforcement under Department of State Police or Commission; concurrent jurisdiction for investigations of accidents</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The enforcement of any provision of this chapter requiring the use of police officers shall be under the Department of State Police or under the Commission; except the department of law enforcement of any city or county with an optional form of government shall have concurrent jurisdiction for the investigations of aircraft accidents occurring within such city or county. History History. Code 1950, § 56-200; 1964, c. 342; 1970, c. 708; 1979, c. 394; 1980, c. 721. Annotations Law Review. For article on the evolution of the State Corporation Commission, see 14 Wm. &amp; Mary L. Rev. 523 (1973).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-146"><akn:num>§ 5.1-146</akn:num><akn:heading>Violations and penalties</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text (a) Any person knowingly and willfully violating any provision of this chapter, or any rule, regulation, requirement, or order thereunder for which a penalty is not otherwise herein provided, shall, after proper proceeding before the Commission, and upon conviction th ereof, be fined not more than $100 for the first offense and not more than $500 for any subsequent offense. Each day of such violation shall constitute a separate offense. (b) Any person , whether carrier, shipper, consignee, or broker, or any officer, employee, agent, or representative thereof, who shall knowingly offer, grant, or give, or solicit, accept, or receive any rebate, concession, or discrimination in violation of any provisio n of this chapter, or who, by means of any false statement or representation, or by the use of any false or fictitious bill, bill of lading, receipt, voucher, roll, account, claim, certificate, affidavit, deposition, lease, or bill of sale or by any othe r means or device, shall knowingly and willfully assist, suffer or permit any person, natural or artificial, to obtain transportation of passengers or property subject to this chapter for less than the applicable rate, fare, or charge, or who shall knowi ngly and willfully by any such means or otherwise fraudulently seek to evade or defeat regulation as in this chapter provided for air carriers or brokers, shall be deemed guilty of a misdemeanor and upon conviction thereof be fined not more than $500 for the first offense and not more than $2,000 for any subsequent offense. (c) Any air ca rrier, or broker, or any officer, agent, employee, or representative thereof who shall willfully fail or refuse to make a report to the Commission as required by this chapter, or to keep accounts, records and memoranda in the form and manner approved or prescribed by the Commission, or shall knowingly and willfully falsify, destroy, mutilate, or alter any such report, account, record, or memorandum, or shall knowingly and willfully file any false report, account, record, or memorandum, shall, after prop er proceeding before the Commission and upon conviction thereof, be subject for each offense to a fine of not less than $100 and not more than $5,000. History History. Code 1950, § 56-201; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-147"><akn:num>§ 5.1-147</akn:num><akn:heading>Disposition of fees or sums collected</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text All fees or sums collected by the Commission under the provisions of this chapter shall be deposited with the State Treasurer, and shall be set aside by him for the use of the Commission for the administration and enforcement of this chapter. History History. Code 1950, § 56-202; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-148"><akn:num>§ 5.1-148</akn:num><akn:heading>Employees of Commission not to have interest in carriers</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text No employee of the Commission appointed or employed in the administration of this chapter shall in any manner have any pecuniary interest in, own any securities of, or hold any position with any air carrier, motor carrier, railroad, steamboat or canal company. History History. Code 1950, § 56-203; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-149"><akn:num>§ 5.1-149</akn:num><akn:heading>No property rights in airspace conferred by chapter</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Nothing in this chapter shall confer any proprietary or property rights in the use of the airspace of this Commonwealth. History History. Code 1950, § 56-204; 1970, c. 708.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-150"><akn:num>§ 5.1-150</akn:num><akn:heading>Licenses, registrations, taxes, etc</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>, not affected. Text Nothing in this chapter shall be construed to relieve any person from the payment of any licenses, registration fees, taxes, or levies now or hereafter imposed by law. History History. Code 1950, § 56-205; 1970, c. 708; 2017, c. 793. Annotations The 2017 amendments. The 2017 amendment by c. 793, inserted registration following licenses.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-151"><akn:num>§ 5.1-151</akn:num><akn:heading>Right to amend, revoke, etc</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>, rights, certificates or franchises. Text The right and power of the General Assembly to amend, alter, revoke or repeal any and all rights, certificates, or franchises granted pursuant to the provisions of this chapter is hereby reserved. History History. Code 1950, § 56-206; 1970, c. 708. Chapter 10. Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority. -360§ 5.1-152. Definitions. -360§ 5.1-153. Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority created. -360§ 5.1-154. Acquisition of airports; approval. -360§ 5.1-155. Membership; terms; officers. -360§ 5.1-156. Powers and duties of the Authority. -360§ 5.1-157. Authority rules and regulations; penalty. -360§ 5.1-158. Police. -360§ 5.1-159. Operation of foreign trade zone. -360§ 5.1-160. Acquisition of property; eminent domain. -360§ 5.1-161. Revenue bonds. -360§ 5.1-162. Refunding bonds. -360§ 5.1-163. Pledge of funds. -360§ 5.1-164. Marketability of bonds. -360§ 5.1-165. Bonds as legal investments and security for public deposits. -360§ 5.1-166. Credit of Commonwealth and political subdivisions not pledged. -360§ 5.1-167. Trust agreement. -360§ 5.1-168. Revenues. -360§ 5.1-169. Trust funds. -360§ 5.1-170. Annual audit. -360§ 5.1-171. Remedies. -360§ 5.1-172. Exemption from taxation. -360§ 5.1-173. Jurisdiction of courts; liability for contracts and torts. -360§ 5.1-174. Procurement Act exemption. -360§ 5.1-175. Act liberally construed. -360§ 5.1-176. Repealed by Acts 2015, c. 709, cl. 2. -360§ 5.1-177. Inconsistent laws inapplicable. -360§ 5.1-178. Repealed by Acts 2021, Sp. Sess. I, c. 377, cl. 1, effective July 1, 2021.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-152"><akn:num>§ 5.1-152</akn:num><akn:heading>Definitions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text For the purposes of this act, the following terms and phrases shall mean: Authority shall mean the Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority created by this ac t and by similar enactment by the District of Columbia or, if the Authority shall be abolished, the board, body, or commission or agency succeeding to the principal functions thereof or upon whom the powers given by this act to the Authority shall be con ferred by law; Authority Facilities shall mean any or all airport facilities now existing or hereafte r acquired or constructed or caused to be constructed by the Authority under this act, and together with any or all buildings, improvements, additions, extensions, replacements, appurtenances, lands, rights in land, water rights, air rights, franchises, machinery, equipment, furnishings, landscaping, easements, utilities, approaches, roadways and other facilities necessary or desirable in connection therewith or incidental thereto, including the existing Dulles Airport Access Road and its right-of-way, acquired or constructed by the Authority; Bonds or revenue bonds shall mean bonds and notes or refunding bonds and notes or bond anticipation notes or other obligations of the Authority issued under the provisions of this act. Cost shall mean, as applied to Authority Facilities, the cost of acquisition of all la nds, structures, rights-of-way, franchises, easements and other property rights and interests, the cost of lease payments, the cost of construction, the cost of demolishing, removing or relocating any buildings or structures on lands acquired, including the cost of acquiring any lands to which such buildings or structures may be moved or relocated, the cost of any extensions, enlargements, additions and improvements, the cost of all labor, materials, machinery and equipment, financing charges, interest on all bonds prior to and during construction and, if deemed advisable by the Authority, for a period not exceeding one year after completion of such construction, the cost of engineering, financial and legal services, plans, specifications, studies, sur veys, estimates of cost and of revenues, other expenses necessary or incident to determining the feasibility or practicability of constructing the Authority Facilities, administrative expenses, provisions for working capital, reserves for interest and fo r extensions, enlargements, additions and improvements, the cost of bond issuance and other devices designed to enhance the creditworthiness of the bonds, and such other expenses as may be necessary or incidental to the construction of the Authority Faci lities, the financing of such construction and the placing of the Authority Facilities in operation. Any obligation or expenses incurred by the Commonwealth or any agency thereof, with the approval of the Authority, for studies, surveys, borings, prepara tion of plans and specifications or other work or materials in connection with the construction of the Authority Facilities may be regarded as part of the cost of the Authority Facilities and may be reimbursed to the Commonwealth or such agency out of an y funds available therefor or the proceeds of the revenue bonds issued for such Authority Facilities as hereinafter authorized. History History. 2001, c. 342. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2001, c. 342, cl. 2, provides: That Chapter 598 of the Acts of Assembly of 1985, Chapter 665 of the Acts of Assembly of 1987, Chapter 180 and 610 of the Acts of Assembly of 1991, Chapter 402 of the Acts of Assembly of 1992, Chapters 647 and 661 of the Acts of Assembly of 1997, and Chapter 824 of the Acts of Assembly of 1998 are repealed. Acts 2001, c. 342, cl. 3, provides: That it is the intent of the General Assembly, through the passage of this act, to codify the provisions of Chapter 598 of the Acts of Assembly of 1985, Chapter 665 of the Acts of Assembly of 1987, Chapters 180 and 610 of the Acts of Assembly of 1991, Chapter 402 of the Acts of Assembly of 1992, Chapters 647 and 661 of the Acts of Assembly of 1997, and Chapter 824 of the Ac ts of Assembly of 1998, relating to the Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority, and the provisions of this act shall not be deemed to impair or otherwise affect any regulation promulgated, any contract entered into, any appointment made, or any other action lawfully taken under the provisions of the Acts of Assembly repealed by this act. Accordingly, the provisions of this act are declarative of existing law. Acts 2003, c. 1012, cl. 1, provides: § 1. Limited waiver of sovereign immunity by Commonwealth of Virginia. Notwithstanding any contrary provision of Chapter 10 (§ 5.1-152 et seq.) of Title 5.1 of the Code of Virginia, the Commonwealth of Virginia agrees to a lim ited waiver of its sovereign immunity, not to exceed $5 million, so as to indemnify the Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority against claims, damages, losses, and expenses arising out of, resulting from, or attributable to the Commonwealths use of Authority property, in or near the Dulles Corridor, on which transportation facilities are constructed, to the extent required in any agreement between the Virginia Department of Transportation and the Authority. For purposes of this act and all provi sions of law, Dulles Corridor means the transportation corridor with an eastern terminus of the East Falls Church Metrorail station and a western terminus of Route 772 in Loudoun County. Acts 2013, c. 766, cl. 6 provides: That $100 million of the increased revenues provided to the Highway Maintenance and Operating Fund pursuant to this act in fiscal years 2014, 2015, and 2016 shall be dedicated to Phase 2 of the Dulles Corridor Metrorail Extension Project, provided, however, that the Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority (MWAA) Board of Directors first address all recommendations cited i n the Office of the Inspector General of the U.S. Department of Transportations Report on MWAA Governance and the accountability officer appointed by the U.S. Secretary of Transportation determines that such recommendations have been addressed. Notwi thstanding the foregoing provisions of this enactment, in the event that all conditions for dedication of funds are satisfied, the Commonwealth Transportation Board may provide funding from other available revenue sources to satisfy the requirements of t his provision in order to maximize the use of increased revenues provided under this act. CASE NOTES Dulles Toll Road.  Tolls charged for passage on the Dulles Toll Road were user fees, not taxes, under Virginia law and their collection by the Metropolitan Washington Airports Autho rity did not run afoul of Va. Const. art. I, § 6 and did not violate the due process rights of the motorists. Corr v. Metro. Wash. Airports Auth., 740 F.3d 295, 2014 U.S. App. LEXIS 1099 (4th Cir. 2014), cert. denied, 577 U.S. 815, 136 S. Ct. 29, 193 L. Ed. 2d 23, 2015 U.S. LEXIS 5503 (2015). CIRCUIT COURT OPINIONS Authority facilities.  Because a road was part of the Dulles Airport Access Highway, it was recognized as part of the Airport Authority Facilities and an officer had the authority to ma ke a warrantless arrest of the defendant because the road was part of Authority Facilities. Commonwealth v. Selby, 2002 Va. Cir. LEXIS 285 (Fairfax County Oct. 25, 2002). OPINIONS OF THE ATTORNEY GENERAL Whether a particular transportation facility construc ted on the Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority property is in or near the Dulles Corridor is a factual determination to be resolved by the Commonwealth Transportation Board. See opinion of Attorney General to The Honorable Whittington W. Clement, Secr etary of Transportation, 03-121, 2004 Va. AG LEXIS 10 (2/17/04). Dulles Toll Road.  Although the issue has not been conclusively resolved, under the only available precedent, the Governor was authorized to divest the Commonwealth of its interest in the Dulles Toll Road as part of the overall project to extend Metrorail. See opinion of Attorney General to The Honorable Robert G. Marshall, Member, Virginia House of Delegates, 11-004, 2012 Va. AG LEXIS 20 (5/25/12). All the parties to the Compact governing Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority (MWAA) would not be required to approve the Authoritys takeover of the Dul les Toll Road. Instead, the approval of MWAAs Board would be sufficient to confer upon MWAA the authority and responsibility to operate and maintain the Dulles Toll Road. See opinion of Attorney General to The Honorable Robert G. Marshall, Member, Vi rginia House of Delegates, 11-004, 2012 Va. AG LEXIS 20 (5/25/12).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-153"><akn:num>§ 5.1-153</akn:num><akn:heading>Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority created</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text There is hereby created the Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority, hereafter referred to as the Authority, a public body corporate and politic and independent of a ll other bodies, having the powers and jurisdiction hereinafter enumerated, and such other and additional powers as shall be conferred upon it by the legislative authorities of both the Commonwealth of Virginia and the District of Columbia. History History. 2001, c. 342. Annotations Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 2C M.J. Aviation, §§ 1, 8. CIRCUIT COURT OPINIONS Sovereign immunity barred claims.  In an action filed by a group of residents against various state entities and an airport authority seeking both declaratory and injunctive relief, and alleging th at the transfer of a toll road and toll revenue derived therefrom from the Commonwealth defendants to the airport authority was an unlawful delegation or assignment, and an unlawful transfer of state assets and the legislative ability to tax, demurrers a nd pleas in bar filed against said complaint were granted, and the case was dismissed, as the doctrine of sovereign immunity barred consideration of said claims. Gray v. Va. Secy. of Transp., 74 Va. Cir. 30, 2007 Va. Cir. LEXIS 150 (Richmond Mar. 19, 200 7), aff'd in part and rev'd in part, 276 Va. 93, 662 S.E.2d 66, 2008 Va. LEXIS 73 (2008). OPINIONS OF THE ATTORNEY GENERAL Procurement procedures.  State agency can negotiate to include in its grant agreement a provision that makes Metropolitan Washington Airports Authoritys receipt of Virginia funds cond itional upon Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority conducting the procurement in a manner that does not give a preference to offerors who will have a project labor agreement. Such a condition would be enforceable in accordance with general contract laws, but it could not be enforced through the special remedial provisions contained in subsection C of § 2.2-4321.2, because Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority is not subject to that statute. See opinion of Attorney General to The Honorable M ark D. Sickles, Member, House of Delegates, 12-025, 2012 Va. AG LEXIS 29 (7/6/2012).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-154"><akn:num>§ 5.1-154</akn:num><akn:heading>Acquisition of airports; approval</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority created by this act is hereby authorized, when similarly authorized by the District of Columbia, to acquire from the Unit ed States of America, by lease or otherwise, the two airports known as Ronald Reagan Washington National Airport and Washington Dulles International Airport and all related properties now administered by the Metropolitan Washington Airports, an agency of the Federal Aviation Administration of the United States Department of Transportation, but only with the approval of the Governor of Virginia. Subject to such gubernatorial approval, general consent is hereby given to conditions imposed by the Congress of the United States on such acquisitions that are not inconsistent with this act. History History. 2001, c. 342.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-155"><akn:num>§ 5.1-155</akn:num><akn:heading>Membership; terms; officers</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. The Authori ty shall consist of 17 members: seven appointed by the Governor of the Commonwealth of Virginia, four appointed by the Mayor of the District of Columbia, three appointed by the Governor of the State of Maryland, and three appointed by the President of th e United States. Members representing the Commonwealth of Virginia shall be subject to confirmation by the Virginia General Assembly. For the purposes of doing business, nine members shall constitute a quorum. The failure of a single appointing official to appoint one or more members, as herein provided, shall not impair the Authoritys creation when the other conditions thereof have been met. B. Members sha ll (i) not hold elective or appointive public office, (ii) serve without compensation, and (iii) reside within the Washington Standard Metropolitan Statistical Area, except that the members appointed by the President of the United States shall be registe red voters of states other than Maryland, Virginia, or the District of Columbia. The members of the Authority shall be entitled to reimbursement for their expenses incurred in attendance upon the meetings of the Authority or while otherwise engaged in th e discharge of their duties. C. Appointment s to the Authority shall be for a period of six years. However, initial appointments shall be made as follows: each jurisdiction shall appoint one member for a full six-year term, a second member for a four-year term, and, in the case of the Commonwealth and the District of Columbia, a third member for a two-year term. The Governor of Virginia shall make the final two Virginia initial appointments for one two-year and one four-year term. The President shall make subsequent appointments for six-year term s. The President shall make one of the initial appointments pursuant to the Metropolitan Washington Airports Amendments Act of 1996 for a four-year term. D. Ten affirma tive votes shall be required to approve bond issues and the annual budget of the Authority. E. Each member may be removed or suspended from office only for cause, and in accordance with the laws of the jurisdiction from which he is appointed. F. The Authori ty shall annually elect one of its members as chairman and another as vice-chairman and shall also elect annually a secretary and a treasurer, or a secretary-treasurer, who may or may not be members of the Authority, and prescribe their powers and duties . The Authority may also appoint from its staff an assistant secretary and an assistant treasurer, or an assistant secretary-treasurer, who shall, in addition to other duties, discharge such functions of the secretary and the treasurer. G. Any person appointed to fill a vacancy shall serve for the unexpired term. Any member of the Authority shall be eligible for reappointment for one term. A member shall not serve after the expiration of the members term or terms. H. The members of the Authority, including any nonvoting members, shall not be personally liable for any act done or action taken in their capacities as members of the Authority, nor shall they be personally liable for any bond, note or other evidence of indebtedness issued by the Authority. History History. 2001, c. 342; 2012, cc. 549, 712. Annotations The 2012 amendments. The 2012 amendments by cc. 549 and 712 are identical, and in subsection A, substituted shall consist of 17 members: seven appointed by the Governor of the Com monwealth of Virginia, three appointed by the Mayor of the District of Columbia, three appointed by for shall consist of thirteen members: five appointed by the Governor of the Commonwealth of Virginia, four appointed by the Mayor of the District of Columbia, two appointed by in the first sentence and business, nine members for business, seven members in the third sentence; substituted Ten affirmative votes for Eight affirmative votes at the beginning of subse ction D; and in subsection G, deleted the former first sentence, which read: The members of the Authority shall continue to serve until their successors shall be duly appointed. and added the second sentence.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-156"><akn:num>§ 5.1-156</akn:num><akn:heading>Powers and duties of the Authority</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. For the pur pose of acquiring, operating, maintaining, developing, promoting and protecting Ronald Reagan Washington National Airport and Washington Dulles International Airport together as primary airports for public purposes serving the metropolitan Washington are a, the Authority shall have all necessary or convenient powers including, but not limited to, the power: 1. To ad opt and amend bylaws for the regulation of its affairs and the conduct of its business; 2. To plan, establish, operate, develop, construct, enlarge, maintain, equip and protect the airports; 3. To adopt and amend regulations to carry out the powers granted by this section; 4. To adopt an official seal and alter the same at its pleasure; 5. To appoint one or more advisory committees; 6. To issue revenue bonds of the Authority for any of its purposes, payable solely from the fees and revenues pledged for their payment, and to refund its bonds, all as provided in this a ct; 7. To borrow money on a short-term basis and issue from time to time its notes therefor payable on such terms, conditions or provisions as it may deem advisable; 8. To fix, revise, charge, and collect rates, fees, rentals and other charges for the use of the airports; 9. To acquire, hold and dispose of real and personal property in the exercise of its powers and the performance of its duties under this act; 10. To employ, in its discretion, consulting engineers, attorneys, accountants, construction and financial experts, superintendents, managers, and such other employees and agents as may be necessary, and to fix their compensation and benefits. Employees of the Authority shall not participate in any strike or assert any right to strike against the Authority, and any employment agreement entered into by the Authority shall contain an exp licit prohibition against strikes by the employee or employees covered by such agreement. The Authority shall comply with any act of Congress concerning former employees of the Federal Aviation Administration and Metropolitan Washington Airports; 11. To sue and be sued in its own name, plead and be impleaded; 12. To construct or permit the construction of commercial and other facilities consistent with the purposes of this act upon the airport property on terms established by the Authority; 13. To make and enter into all contracts and agreements necessary or desirable to the performance of its duties, the proper operation of the airports and the furnishing of services to t he travelling public and airport users, including contracts for normal governmental services on a reimbursable basis with local political subdivisions where the Authority Facilities are situated and with the District of Columbia government; and any such contracts shall be exclusive or limited when it is necessary to further the public safety, improve the quality of service, avoid duplication of services, or conserve airport property and the airport environment; 14. To apply for, receive and accept such payments, appropriations, grants, gifts, loans, advances, and other funds, properties, and services as may be transferred or made available to it by the United States government or any other public or private entity or individual; 15. To make payments to reimburse the local political subdivisions where the Authority Facilities are situated for extraordinary law-enforcement costs incurred by such localities; and 16. To do all acts and things necessary or convenient to carry out the powers expressly granted in this act. B. Pursuant to Section 6007 (b) of the Metropolitan Washington Airports Act of 1986, the Authority is established solely to operate and improve both metropolitan Washington airports as primary airports serving the metropolitan Washington area and shall be independent of the Commonwealth and its local political subdivisions, the District of Columbia and the federal government in the performance and exercise of the airport-related duties and powers enumerated in subdivisions 1 through 16 of subsection A of this section . Any conflict between the exercise of these enumerated powers by the Authority and the powers of any local political subdivision within which Authority Facilities are situated shall be resolved in favor of the Authority. History History. 2001, c. 342. Annotations Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 2C M.J. Aviation, §§ 1, 8. CIRCUIT COURT OPINIONS Illustrative cases.  Maintenance of airport runways was a proprietary function under Virginia law, and the Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority was not immune from suit by an ai rline which claimed that its plane was damaged when it hit debris that was on a runway. Alpine Air, Inc. v. Metro. Wash. Airports Auth., 62 Va. Cir. 215, 2003 Va. Cir. LEXIS 106 (Fairfax County June 30, 2003). Sovereign immunity barred claims.  In an action filed by a group of residents against various state entities and an airport authority seeking both declaratory and injunctive relief, and alleging th at the transfer of a toll road and toll revenue derived therefrom from the Commonwealth defendants to the airport authority was an unlawful delegation or assignment, and an unlawful transfer of state assets and the legislative ability to tax, demurrers a nd pleas in bar filed against said complaint were granted, and the case was dismissed, as the doctrine of sovereign immunity barred consideration of said claims. Gray v. Va. Secy. of Transp., 74 Va. Cir. 30, 2007 Va. Cir. LEXIS 150 (Richmond Mar. 19, 200 7), aff'd in part and rev'd in part, 276 Va. 93, 662 S.E.2d 66, 2008 Va. LEXIS 73 (2008). OPINIONS OF THE ATTORNEY GENERAL Procurement procedures.  State agency can negotiate to include in its grant agreement a provision that makes Metropolitan Washington Airports Authoritys receipt of Virginia funds cond itional upon Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority conducting the procurement in a manner that does not give a preference to offerors who will have a project labor agreement. Such a condition would be enforceable in accordance with general contract laws, but it could not be enforced through the special remedial provisions contained in subsection C of § 2.2-4321.2, because Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority is not subject to that statute. See opinion of Attorney General to The Honorable M ark D. Sickles, Member, House of Delegates, 12-025, 2012 Va. AG LEXIS 29 (7/6/2012).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-157"><akn:num>§ 5.1-157</akn:num><akn:heading>Authority rules and regulations; penalty</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. The Authori ty shall have the power to adopt, amend, and repeal rules and regulations pertaining to use, maintenance and operation of its facilities and governing the conduct of persons and organizations using its facilities. B. Unless the Authority shall by unanimous vote of all members present determine that an emergency exists, the Authority shall, prior to the adoption of any rule or regulation or alteration, amendment or modification thereof: 1. Make such rule, regulation, alteration, amendment, or modification in convenient form available for public inspection in the office of the Authority for at least ten days; 2. Publish a notice in a newspaper or newspapers of general circulation in the District of Columbia and in the local political subdivisions of the Commonwealth where the Authority Facilit ies are located declaring the Authoritys intention to consider adopting such rule, regulation, alteration, amendment, or modification and informing the public that the Authority will hold a public hearing at which any person may appear and be heard f or or against the adoption of such rule or regulation or such alteration, amendment, or modification, on a day and at a time to be specified in the notice, after the expiration of at least ten days from the day of the publication thereof; and 3. Hold the public hearing on the day and at the time specified in such notice or any adjournment thereof, and hear persons appearing for or against such rule, regulation, alteration, ame ndment or modification. C. The Authori tys rules and regulations shall be available for public inspection in the Authoritys principal office. D. The Authori tys rules and regulations relating to: (i) Air operations and motor vehicle traffic, including but not limited to, motor vehicle speed limits and the location of and payment for public parking; (ii) Access to and use of Authority Facilities, including but not limited to, solicitation, handbilling, picketing and the conduct of commercial activities; and (iii) Aircraft operation and maintenance; shall have the force and effect of law, as shall any other rule or regulation of the Authority which shall contain a determination by the Authori ty that it is necessary to accord the same force and effect of law in the public interest; provided, however, that with respect to motor vehicle traffic rules and regulations, the Authority shall obtain the approval of the traffic engineer or comparable official of the local political subdivision in which such rules or regulations are to be enforced. E. The violati on of any rule or regulation of the Authority establishing a noise limitation on aircraft that operate at the Authority Facilities shall subject the violator, in the discretion of the circuit court of any political subdivision where the facility is locat ed, to a civil penalty not to exceed $5,000 for each violation. Such penalty shall be paid to the Authority. With the consent of the violator or the accused violator of a rule establishing aircraft noise limits, the Authority may provide, in an order iss ued against the violator or accused violator, for the payment of civil charges in specific sums not to exceed the limit that could be imposed by the court. Such civil charge when paid shall be in lieu of any civil penalty which could be imposed by the co urt. Any court proceeding shall be within the exclusive jurisdiction of the circuit court and shall be a civil proceeding at law brought by the Authority. F. The violati on of any Authority rule or regulation, having the force and effect of law, shall be a Class 1 misdemeanor unless otherwise specified by this chapter or unless a lesser penalty is set by the Authority in the rule or regulation. The rules of criminal proc edure and evidence that apply throughout the Commonwealth shall apply to the adjudication of any case involving the violation of any Authority rule or regulation having the force and effect of law. G. The courts of this Commonwealth shall take judicial notice of the Authoritys regularly adopted rules and regulations. For the convenience of the courts which may regularly hear cases arising under the Authoritys rules and regulations, the Authority may cert ify to the clerk of such court a copy of its rules and regulations. Any such certification, when signed by the chairman of the Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority, shall be accepted as evidence of the facts therein stated. H. With respec t to the violation of any statute of the Commonwealth, local ordinance or Authority rule or regulation having the force and effect of law occurring at the Authority Facilities: 1. The m atter shall be within the jurisdiction of the state courts of the political subdivision where the violation occurred; violations occurring at Ronald Reagan Washington National Airport shall be within the jurisdiction of the courts for Arlington County; 2. The attorney for the Commonwealth shall have authority to prosecute those offenses in the name of the Commonwealth or local government as appropriate; and the county or city attorney, if otherwise authorized to prosecute offenses in the name of the county or city, shall have authority to prosecute those offenses in the name of the county or city; and 3. Sheriffs and clerks of the court shall provide those same services and exercise those same powers with respect to the Authority Facilities within their jurisdiction as for their politi cal subdivisions. History History. 2001, c. 342. Annotations Cross references. As to punishment for Class 1 misdemeanor, see § 18.2-11.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-158"><akn:num>§ 5.1-158</akn:num><akn:heading>Police</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. The Commonw ealth hereby grants, accepts and agrees to concurrent police power authority over the Metropolitan Washington Airports as provided in Section 6009 (c) of the Metropolitan Washington Airports Act of 1986. B. The Authori ty is authorized to establish and maintain a regular police force and to confer police powers to be exercised with respect to offenses occurring on the Authority Facilities upon its employees meeting the minimum requirements of the Department of Criminal Justice Services.Such police officers shall have all powers vested in police officers under Chapter 17 of Title 15.2, Chapter 11 of Title 16.1, Title 18.2, Title 19.2, and Title 46.2 of the Code of Virginia as those titles may be amended from time to ti me and shall be responsible upon the Authority Facilities and within 300 yards of the Facilities for enforcing the laws of the Commonwealth, the Authoritys rules and regulations and all other applicable ordinances, rules, and regulations.Such police officers may issue summons to appear, or arrest on view or on information without warrant as permitted by law, and conduct before any judicial officer of competent jurisdiction any person violating, upon Authority Facilities, any rule or regulation of th e Authority, any ordinance or regulation of any local political subdivision, or any other law of the Commonwealth. C. The Departm ent of State Police shall exercise the same powers upon Authority Facilities as elsewhere in the Commonwealth. D. The Authori ty may enter into reciprocal or mutual aid agreements with the local political subdivisions in the National Capital Region as defined in § 2674(f)(2) of title 10 of the United States Code, those counties with a border abutting that area, and any munic ipalities therein; any agency of the Commonwealth, the District of Columbia, the State of Maryland; the federal government; or any combination of the foregoing for cooperation in the furnishing of services during a public service event, an emergency, or planned training, including law-enforcement, fire, rescue, emergency health, and medical services, transportation, communications, public works and engineering, mass care, and resource support. When responding to a request under such an agreement, Author ity employees may go outside Authority facilities, and the Authority and its employees shall enjoy the same immunities from liability as localities and their employees do in responding under similar circumstances. E. The police force of Arlington County shall have concurrent jurisdiction with the police force established herein at Ronald Reagan Washington National Airport. The Authority shall enter into an agreement with Arlington County regarding the exercise of police authori ty. F. The sheriff s and police forces of Loudoun and Fairfax Counties shall continue to exercise concurrent jurisdiction with the police force established herein over the Authority Facilities situated within their respective counties. History History. 2001, c. 342; 2007, cc. 729, 742. Annotations Cross references. As to assault and battery of police officer, see § 18.2-57. As to background checks of applicants of the Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority, see § 19.2-389.2. The 2007 amendments. The 2007 amendments by cc. 729 and 742 are nearly identical, and rewrote subsection D, which formerly read: The Authority may enter into reciprocal or mutual aid agreements with the local political subdivisions in which the Authority Facilities are situated, any agency of the Commonwealth or the federal government, or any combination of the foregoing, for cooperation in the furnishing of police services. CASE NOTES Sovereign immunity.  Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority was entitled to dismissal of plaintiffs claim for malicious prosecution because plaintiffs arrest by a Metropol itan Washington Airports Authority police officer clearly occurred in the performance of a governmental function. Mukuna v. Gibson, No. 1:11cv493, 2011 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 95408 (E.D. Va. Aug. 25, 2011).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-159"><akn:num>§ 5.1-159</akn:num><akn:heading>Operation of foreign trade zone</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Authority is authorized and empowered to establish, operate and maintain a foreign trade zone and otherwise to expedite and encourage foreign commerce. History History. 2001, c. 342.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-160"><akn:num>§ 5.1-160</akn:num><akn:heading>Acquisition of property; eminent domain</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. The Authori ty is hereby authorized to acquire by purchase, lease or grant such additional lands, structures, property, rights, rights-of-way, franchises, easements and other interests in lands as it may deem necessary or convenient for construction and operation of the airports, upon such terms and at such prices as may be considered by it to be reasonable and can be agreed upon between it and the owner thereof. B. Any politic al subdivision of the Commonwealth, all or a part of which is located within 60 miles of Authority Facilities, is authorized to provide services, to donate real or personal property and to make appropriations to the Authority for the acquisition, constru ction, maintenance, and operation of the Authority Facilities. Any such political subdivision is hereby authorized to issue its bonds in the manner provided in the Public Finance Act or in any applicable municipal charter for the purpose of providing fun ds to be appropriated to the Authority. The Authority may agree to assume, or reimburse such a political subdivision for, any indebtedness incurred by such political subdivision with respect to facilities conveyed by it to the Authority. With the consent of the governing body of the political subdivision, any such agreement may be made subordinate to the Authoritys indebtedness to others. C. The Authori ty established hereunder is hereby granted full power to exercise the right of eminent domain in the acquisition of any lands, easements, privileges or other property interests that are necessary for airport and landing field purposes, including the righ t to acquire, by eminent domain, aviation easements over lands or water outside the boundaries of its airports or landing fields where necessary in the interests of safety for aircraft to provide unobstructed air space for the landing and taking off of a ircraft utilizing its airports and landing fields even though such aviation easement be inconsistent with the continued use of such land, or inconsistent with the maintenance, preservation and renewal of any structure or any tree or other vegetation stan ding or growing on the land at the time of such acquisition. Proceedings for the acquisition of such lands, easements and privileges by condemnation may be instituted and conducted in the name of the Authority in accordance with Chapter 2 (§ 25.1-200 et seq.) of Title 25.1. History History. 2001, c. 342; 2003, c. 940. Annotations The 2003 amendments. The 2003 amendment by c. 940 substituted 60 for sixty in subsection B; and in subsection C, substituted that for which in the firs t sentence and substituted Chapter 2 (§ 25.1-200 et seq.) of Title 25.1 for Title 25 of the Code of Virginia in the last sentence.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-161"><akn:num>§ 5.1-161</akn:num><akn:heading>Revenue bonds</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Authority is hereby authorized to provide by resolution for the issuance, at one time or from time to time, of revenue bonds of the Authority for the purpose of pay ing all or any part of the cost of Authority Facilities, including the refunding of federal appropriations not reimbursed to the United States Treasury by the Metropolitan Washington Airports. The principal of and the interest on such bonds shall be paya ble solely from the funds herein provided for such payment. The bonds of each issue shall be dated, shall mature at such time or times not exceeding forty years from their date or dates, as may be determined by the Authority, and may be subject to redemp tion or repurchase before maturity, at the option of the Authority, at such price or prices and under such terms and conditions as may be fixed by the Authority prior to the issuance of the bonds. The bonds may bear interest payable at such time or times and at such rate or rates as determined by the Authority or as determined in such manner as the Authority may provide, including the determination by agents designated by the Authority under guidelines established by it. The Authority shall determine th e form and the manner of execution of the bonds, including any interest coupons to be attached thereto, and shall fix the denomination or denominations of the bonds and the place or places of payment of principal and interest, which may be at any bank or trust company within or without the Commonwealth of Virginia. In case any officer whose signature or a facsimile of whose signature shall appear on any bonds or coupons shall cease to be such officer before the delivery of such bonds, such signature or such facsimile shall nevertheless be valid and sufficient for all purposes the same as if he had remained in office until such delivery. Notwithstanding any other provision of this act or any recitals in any bonds issued under the provisions of this sect ion, all such bonds shall be deemed to be negotiable instruments under the laws of the Commonwealth of Virginia. The bonds may be issued in coupon or in registered form, or both, as the Authority may determine, and provision may be made for the registrat ion of any coupon bonds as to principal alone and also as to both principal and interest, for the reconversion into coupon bonds of any bonds registered as to both principal and interest, and for the interchange of registered and coupon bonds. The Author ity may sell such bonds in such manner, either at public or negotiated sale, and for such price, as it may determine will best effect the purposes of this section. The proceeds of the bonds shall be used solely for the payment of the cost of Authority Facilities, including improvements, and shall be disbursed in such manner and un der such restrictions, if any, as the Authority may provide in the resolution authorizing the issuance of such bonds or in the trust agreement hereinafter mentioned securing the same. If the proceeds of the bonds of any issue, by error of estimates or ot herwise, shall be less than such cost, additional bonds may in like manner be issued to provide the amount of such deficit, and, unless otherwise provided in the resolution authorizing the issuance of such bonds or in the trust agreement securing the sam e, shall be deemed to be of the same issue and shall be entitled to payment from the same fund without preference or priority of the bonds first issued. If the proceeds of the bonds of any issue shall exceed such cost, the surplus shall be deposited to t he credit of the sinking fund for such bonds. Prior to the preparation of definitive bonds, the Authority may, under like restrictions, issue interim receipts or temporary bonds, with or without coupons, exchangeab le for definitive bonds when such bonds shall have been executed and are available for delivery. The Authority may also provide for the replacement of any bonds which shall become mutilated or shall be destroyed or lost. Bonds may be issued under the pro visions of this section without obtaining the consent of any agency of the Commonwealth of Virginia, and without any other proceedings, conditions or things not specifically required by this section. History History. 2001, c. 342.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-162"><akn:num>§ 5.1-162</akn:num><akn:heading>Refunding bonds</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Authority is hereby authorized to provide by resolution for the issuance of its revenue refunding bonds for the purpose of refunding any bonds then outstanding whic h shall have been issued under the provisions of this act, including the payment of any redemption premium thereon and any interest accrued or to accrue to the date of redemption of such bonds, and if deemed advisable by the Authority, for either or both of the following additional purposes: constructing improvements, extensions or enlargement of the Authority Facilities in connection with which the bonds to be refunded shall have been issued, and paying all or any part of the cost of any additional Aut hority Facilities. The issuance of such bonds, the maturities and other details thereof, the rights of the holders thereof, and the rights, duties and obligations of the Authority in respect to the same, shall be governed by the provisions of this act in sofar as the same may be applicable. Revenue refunding bonds issued under this section may be sold or exchanged for outstanding bonds issued under this act and, if sold, the proceeds thereof may be applied to the purchase, redemption or payment of such o utstanding bonds. History History. 2001, c. 342.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-163"><akn:num>§ 5.1-163</akn:num><akn:heading>Pledge of funds</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text All moneys received pursuant to the provisions of this act, whether as proceeds from the sale of bonds, as revenues, or as grants, appropriations or other funds provide d by federal, state or local governments, may be pledged to the payment of bonds issued by the Authority and, if so pledged, shall be deemed to be trust funds to be held and applied solely as provided in this act. History History. 2001, c. 342.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-164"><akn:num>§ 5.1-164</akn:num><akn:heading>Marketability of bonds</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Authority is authorized and empowered to exercise all or any part or combination of the powers herein granted; to make covenants other than and in addition to the c ovenants herein expressly authorized, of like or different character; and to make such covenants and to do any and all such acts and things as may be necessary or convenient or desirable in order to secure its bonds or, in the absolute discretion of the Authority, as will tend to make the bonds more marketable, notwithstanding that such covenants, acts or things may not be enumerated herein. History History. 2001, c. 342.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-165"><akn:num>§ 5.1-165</akn:num><akn:heading>Bonds as legal investments and security for public deposits</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Bonds issued by the Authority under the provisions of this act are hereby made securities in which all public officers and public bodies of the Commonwealth and its pol itical subdivisions, all insurance companies, trust companies, banking associations, investment companies, executors, administrators, trustees and other fiduciaries may properly and legally invest funds, including capital in their control or belonging to them. Such bonds are hereby made securities which may properly and legally be deposited with and received by any state or municipal officer or any agency or political subdivision of the Commonwealth for any purpose for which the deposit of bonds or obli gations is now or may hereafter be authorized by law. History History. 2001, c. 342.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-166"><akn:num>§ 5.1-166</akn:num><akn:heading>Credit of Commonwealth and political subdivisions not pledged</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Revenue bonds issued under the provisions of this act shall not constitute a debt of the Commonwealth of Virginia or of any other political subdivision thereof nor a pl edge of the faith and credit of the Commonwealth or of any political subdivision thereof. Such bonds shall be payable solely from funds provided therefor from revenues. The issuance of revenue bonds under the provisions of this act shall not directly, in directly, or contingently obligate the Commonwealth or any political subdivision thereof to the payment thereof or to the levy or pledge of any form of taxation whatever therefor. All such revenue bonds shall contain a statement on their face substantial ly to this effect. History History. 2001, c. 342.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-167"><akn:num>§ 5.1-167</akn:num><akn:heading>Trust agreement</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text In the discretion of the Authority, any bonds issued under the provisions of this act may be secured by a trust agreement by and between the Authority and a corporate t rustee, which may be any trust company or bank having the power of a trust company within or without the Commonwealth of Virginia. Such trust agreement or the resolution providing for the issuance of such bonds may pledge or assign the fees and other rev enues to be received, but shall not convey or mortgage the airports or any part thereof. Such trust agreement or resolution providing for the issuance of such bonds may contain such provisions for protecting and enforcing the rights and remedies of the b ondholders as may be reasonable and proper and not in violation of law, including covenants setting forth the duties of the Authority in relation to the acquisition of property and the construction, improvement, maintenance, repair, operation and insuran ce of the airports, the rates or fees or other charges to be charged, and the custody, safeguarding and application of all moneys. It shall be lawful for any bank or trust company incorporated under the laws of the Commonwealth of Virginia which may act as depositary of the proceeds of bonds or of revenues to furnish such indemnifying bonds or to pledge such securities as may be required by the Authority. Any such trust agreement may set forth the rights and remedies of the bondholders. In addition to t he foregoing, any such trust agreement or resolution may contain such other provisions as the Authority may deem reasonable and proper for the security of the bondholders. All expenses incurred in carrying out the provisions of such trust agreement or re solution may be treated as a part of the cost of the operation of the airports. History History. 2001, c. 342.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-168"><akn:num>§ 5.1-168</akn:num><akn:heading>Revenues</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Authority is hereby authorized to fix, revise, charge and collect fees or other charges for the use of the airports and to contract with any person, partnership, as sociation or corporation desiring the use of any part thereof, including the right-of-way adjoining the airports for placing thereon telephone, telegraph, electric light or power lines, and to fix the terms, conditions, rents and fees or other charges fo r such use. Such fees or other charges shall be so fixed and adjusted in respect of the aggregate of fees or other charges from the airports as to provide a fund sufficient with other revenues, if any, (i) to pay the cost of maintaining, repairing and op erating the airports, (ii) to pay the principal of and interest on such bonds as the same shall become due and payable, and (iii) to create reserves for such purposes. The fees and other charges and all other revenues derived from the airports, except su ch part thereof as may be necessary to pay such cost of maintenance, repair and operation and provide such reserves as may be provided for in the resolution authorizing the issuance of such bonds or in the trust agreement securing the same, shall be set aside at such regular intervals as may be provided in such resolution or such trust agreement in a sinking fund which is hereby pledged to, and charged with, the payment of the principal of and the interest on such bonds as the same shall become due, and the redemption price or the purchase price of bonds retired by call or purchase as therein provided. Such pledge shall be valid and binding from the time when the pledge is made. The fees and other charges and other revenues or other moneys so pledged a nd thereafter received by the Authority shall immediately be subject to the lien of such pledge without any physical delivery thereof or further act, and the lien of any such pledge shall be valid and binding as against all parties having claims of any k ind in tort, contract or otherwise against the Authority, irrespective of whether such parties have notice thereof. Neither the resolution nor any trust agreement by which a pledge is created need be filed or recorded except in the records of the Authori ty. The use and disposition of moneys to the credit of such sinking fund shall be subject to the provisions of the resolution authorizing the issuance of such bonds or of such trust agreement. Except as may otherwise be provided in such resolution or suc h trust agreement, such sinking fund shall be a fund for all such bonds without distinction or priority of one over another. History History. 2001, c. 342.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-169"><akn:num>§ 5.1-169</akn:num><akn:heading>Trust funds</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text All proceeds from the sale of bonds and revenues derived therefrom received pursuant to the provisions of this act shall be deemed to be trust funds to be held and appl ied solely as provided in this act. The Authority may, in the resolution authorizing the bonds or in the trust agreement securing such bonds, provide for the payment of the proceeds of the sale of the bonds and the revenues of the Authority to a trustee, which may be any trust company or bank having the powers of a trust company within or without the Commonwealth of Virginia, which shall act as trustee of the funds, and hold and apply the same to the purposes of this act, subject to such regulations as this act and such resolution or trust agreement may provide. The trustee may invest and reinvest such funds in such securities as may be provided in the resolution authorizing the bonds or in the trust agreement securing such bonds. History History. 2001, c. 342.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-170"><akn:num>§ 5.1-170</akn:num><akn:heading>Annual audit</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Authority shall keep suitable records of all its financial transactions and shall have the same audited annually. Copies of such audit shall be furnished to the Gov ernor of the Commonwealth of Virginia and to the Mayor of the District of Columbia and shall be open to public inspection. History History. 2001, c. 342.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-171"><akn:num>§ 5.1-171</akn:num><akn:heading>Remedies</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Any holder of bonds issued under the provisions of this act or of any of the coupons appertaining thereto, and the trustee under any trust agreement, except to the exte nt the rights herein given may be restricted by such trust agreement, may either at law or in equity, by suit, action, injunction, mandamus or other proceedings, protect and enforce any and all rights under the laws of the Commonwealth of Virginia, or gr anted by this act or under such trust agreement or the resolution authorizing the issuance of such bonds and may enforce and compel the performance of all duties required by this act or by such agreement or resolution to be performed by the Authority or by any officer or agent thereof including the fixing, charging and collection of fees or other charges. History History. 2001, c. 342.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-172"><akn:num>§ 5.1-172</akn:num><akn:heading>Exemption from taxation</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The exercise of the powers granted by this act shall be in all respects for the benefit of the inhabitants of the Commonwealth of Virginia, for the increase of their co mmerce, and for the promotion of their safety, health, welfare, convenience and prosperity, and as the operation and maintenance of the airports by the Authority will constitute the performance of essential governmental functions, the Authority shall not be required to pay any taxes or assessments upon the airports or any property acquired or used by the Authority under the provisions of this act or upon the income therefrom; and the bonds issued under the provisions of this act, their transfer and the income therefrom, including any profit made on the sale thereof, shall at all times be free and exempt from taxation by the Commonwealth of Virginia and by any municipality, county or other political subdivision thereof. History History. 2001, c. 342.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-173"><akn:num>§ 5.1-173</akn:num><akn:heading>Jurisdiction of courts; liability for contracts and torts</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. The courts of the Commonwealth of Virginia shall have original jurisdiction of all actions brought by or against the Authority, which courts shall in all cases apply the law of the Commonwealth of Virginia. B. The Authori ty shall be liable for its contracts and for its torts and those of its members, officers, employees, and agents committed in the conduct of any proprietary function, in accordance with the law of the Commonwealth of Virginia but shall not be liable for any torts occurring in the performance of a governmental function. The exclusive remedy for such breach of contracts and torts for which the Authority shall be liable, as herein provided, shall be by suit against the Authority. Nothing in this act shall be construed as a waiver by the Commonwealth of Virginia or the District of Columbia or of their political subdivisions of any immunity from suit. C. The Authori ty shall be responsible for all executory contracts entered into by the United States with respect to the former Metropolitan Washington Airports before the date of acquisition of those airports, except that the procedure for disputes resolution containe d in any such contract shall continue to govern the performance of the contract unless otherwise agreed to by the parties to the contract. D. The Authori ty shall not be responsible for any tort claims arising before the date of transfer. History History. 2001, c. 342. Annotations Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 2C M.J. Aviation, § 6. CASE NOTES Sovereign immunity barred claims.  Pursuant to subsection B of § 5.1-173, the Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority was entitled to dismissal of plaintiffs claim for malicious prosecuti on because a police officer had probable cause to execute an arrest warrant after a complainant contacted the officer and told the officer that plaintiff had stolen the complainants income tax refund. Mukuna v. Gibson, No. 1:11cv493, 2011 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 95408 (E.D. Va. Aug. 25, 2011). CIRCUIT COURT OPINIONS Sovereign immunity barred claims.  In an action filed by a group of residents against various state entities and an airport authority seeking both declaratory and injunctive relief, and alleging th at the transfer of a toll road and toll revenue derived therefrom from the Commonwealth defendants to the airport authority was an unlawful delegation or assignment, and an unlawful transfer of state assets and the legislative ability to tax, demurrers a nd pleas in bar filed against said complaint were granted, and the case was dismissed, as the doctrine of sovereign immunity barred consideration of said claims. Gray v. Va. Secy. of Transp., 74 Va. Cir. 30, 2007 Va. Cir. LEXIS 150 (Richmond Mar. 19, 200 7), aff'd in part and rev'd in part, 276 Va. 93, 662 S.E.2d 66, 2008 Va. LEXIS 73 (2008). Illustrative cases.  Maintenance of airport runways was a proprietary function under Virginia law, and the Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority was not immune from suit by an ai rline which claimed that its plane was damaged when it hit debris that was on a runway. Alpine Air, Inc. v. Metro. Wash. Airports Auth., 62 Va. Cir. 215, 2003 Va. Cir. LEXIS 106 (Fairfax County June 30, 2003).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-174"><akn:num>§ 5.1-174</akn:num><akn:heading>Procurement Act exemption</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text In light of the multijurisdictional nature of the Authority, an exemption is hereby provided to the Authority from the provisions of the Virginia Public Procurement Act . History History. 2001, c. 342. Annotations Cross references. As to the Virginia Public Procurement Act, see § 2.2-4300 et seq. OPINIONS OF THE ATTORNEY GENERAL Procurement procedures.  State agency can negotiate to include in its grant agreement a provision that makes Metropolitan Washington Airports Authoritys receipt of Virginia funds cond itional upon Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority conducting the procurement in a manner that does not give a preference to offerors who will have a project labor agreement. Such a condition would be enforceable in accordance with general contract laws, but it could not be enforced through the special remedial provisions contained in subsection C of § 2.2-4321.2, because Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority is not subject to that statute. See opinion of Attorney General to The Honorable M ark D. Sickles, Member, House of Delegates, 12-025, 2012 Va. AG LEXIS 29 (7/6/2012).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-175"><akn:num>§ 5.1-175</akn:num><akn:heading>Act liberally construed</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text This act, being necessary for the welfare of the Commonwealth of Virginia and its inhabitants, shall be liberally construed to effect the purposes thereof. History History. 2001, c. 342.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-176"><akn:num>§ 5.1-176</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 2015, c</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>709, cl. 2. Annotations Editors note. Former § 5.1-176, pertaining to severability, derived from 2001, c. 342.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-177"><akn:num>§ 5.1-177</akn:num><akn:heading>Inconsistent laws inapplicable</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text All other general or special laws inconsistent with any provision of this act are hereby declared to be inapplicable to the provisions of this act. History History. 2001, c. 342.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_5.1-178"><akn:num>§ 5.1-178</akn:num><akn:heading>Repealed by Acts 2021, Sp</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Sess. I, c. 377, cl. 1, effective July 1, 2021. Annotations Editors note. Former § 5.1-178, which contained the effective date provision for this chapter was enacted by Acts 2001, c. 342. The section was formerly not set out in conformance with Virginia Code Commission policy.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section></akn:body></akn:act></akn:akomaNtoso>