<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akn:akomaNtoso xmlns:akn="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><akn:act><akn:meta><akn:identification source="#cosilico"><akn:FRBRWork><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-01" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-01" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2023-03-01" name="release" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#virginia-general-assembly" /><akn:FRBRcountry value="us-va" /><akn:FRBRnumber value="title-01" /><akn:FRBRname value="act" /></akn:FRBRWork><akn:FRBRExpression><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-01/eng@2023-03-01" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-01/eng@2023-03-01" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2023-03-01" name="publication" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#lexisnexis" /><akn:FRBRlanguage language="eng" /></akn:FRBRExpression><akn:FRBRManifestation><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-01/eng@2023-03-01/main.xml" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-va/act/code/title-01/eng@2023-03-01/main.xml" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="conversion" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#cosilico" /></akn:FRBRManifestation></akn:identification><akn:references source="#cosilico"><akn:TLCOrganization eId="virginia-general-assembly" href="/ontology/organization/us-va/general-assembly" showAs="Virginia General Assembly" /><akn:TLCOrganization eId="lexisnexis" href="/ontology/organization/lexisnexis" showAs="LexisNexis" /><akn:TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="/ontology/organization/cosilico" showAs="Cosilico" /></akn:references></akn:meta><akn:preface><akn:docTitle>Title 01. </akn:docTitle></akn:preface><akn:body><akn:section eId="sec_1-1"><akn:num>§ 1-1</akn:num><akn:heading>Contents and designation of Code</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The laws embraced in this and the following titles, chapters, articles and sections of this act shall constitute, and be designated and cited as the Code of Virgini a, hereinafter referred to as the Code or this Code. History History. Code 1919, § 1; R. P. 1948, § 1-1. Annotations Cross references. As to rules of construction, see §§ 1-200 through 1-257 and notes thereto. History of Code of 1 950 and cumulative supplement. The proposed Code of Virginia, submitted by the then Commission on Code Recodification to the 1948 session of the General Assembly, with certain amendments fully explained in the preface and known as the Reorganization Provisions of the Code of Virginia, was adopted as the Code of Virginia, to be effective as provided in §§ 1-2 and 1-2.1, by an act approved April 6, 1948. Under authority and direction of chapter 262 of the Acts of 1948, codified as former §§ 9-66 through 9-77 (see now § 30-152 et seq.), the Commission, now styled the Virginia Code Commission, prepared and had published an annotated edition, in ten volumes including the index, of the Code so adopted, with the reorganization provisions and the general acts of the 1948 session incorporated therein. This edition was submitted to the General Assembly for approval at its 1950 session and was adopted by an act approved January 27, 1950. The final paragraph of that act, which has not been codified, read in part: . . . the body of the statute law contained in the foregoing ten volumes is to tak e effect February one, nineteen hundred fifty as the official Code of Virginia, sometimes for brevity called the Code of 1950. The general acts of the 1950 through 2014 sessions have been codified and published, under authority of § 30-152 et seq., in the supplements and in the added a nd replacement volumes. CASE NOTES The 1948 enactment of the Code submitted to that session of the General Assembly was a valid enactment and did not violate Va. Const., Art. IV, § 11, or § 12, which provides that no law shall embrace more than one object, which shall be expressed in its title. Article IV, § 12, was not intended to apply to a general code revisio n, and adoption of a code by general title is broad enough to cover any lawful enactment. McClain v. Commonwealth, 189 Va. 847, 55 S.E.2d 49, 1949 Va. LEXIS 223 (1949) (see notes to Va. Const., Art. IV, §§ 11 and 12).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-2"><akn:num>§ 1-2</akn:num><akn:heading>Effective date of Code</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text All the provisions of this Code shall be in force on and after February 1, 1950, except as provided in § 1-2.1. History History. Code 1919, § 6567; R. P. 1948, § 1-2. Annotations Cross references. As to rules of construction, see §§ 1-200 through 1-257 and notes thereto. § 1-2.1. Effective date of certain provisions. Text The following provisions of this Code shall become effective July 1, 1948, namely: Chapter 1 of Title 1; Chapters 1, 8, 9, 12, 14, 15, and 16 of Title 2; Chapter 13 of Title 3; Chapter 11 of Title 6; Chapters 2 and 5 of Title 9; all of Title 10; Artic le 7 of Chapter 1 of Title 14; Article 3 of Chapter 6 of Title 18; Chapter 2 of Title 19; Chapter 3 of Title 24; Chapter 3 of Title 27; Chapters 15 and 19 of Title 32; all of Title 41; Article 4 of Chapter 6 of Title 42; Articles 2 and 12 of Chapter 1 of Title 44 and all of Chapter 2 of Title 44; Chapter 3 of Title 51; Chapter 1 of Title 52; Chapters 1 through 14, inclusive, of Title 53; Chapter 24 of Title 54; Chapters 12 and 13 of Title 59; Chapter 7 of Title 62; all of Title 63 except Chapter 13. History History. R. P. 1948, § 1-2.1. Annotations Cross references. As to rules of construction, see §§ 1-200 through 1-257 and notes thereto. Editors note. Title 2, referred to above, was repealed by Acts 1966, c. 677. Title 3, referred to above, was repealed by Acts 1966, c. 702. Title 6, referred to above, was repe aled by Acts 1966, c. 584. Chapter 2 of Title 9, referred to above, was repealed by Acts 1970, c. 463; Acts 1978, c. 580. Chapter 5 of Title 9, referred to above, was repealed by Acts 2001, c. 844. Title 10, referred to above, was repealed by Acts 1988, c. 891. Title 14, referred to above, was repealed by Acts 1964, c. 386. Title 18, referred to above, was repealed by Acts 1960, c. 358. Title 19, referred to above, was repealed by Acts 1960, c. 366. Title 24, referred to above, was repealed by Acts 1970 , c. 462. Chapter 15 of Title 32, referred to above, was repealed by Acts 1968, c. 578. Chapter 19 of Title 32, referred to above, was repealed by Acts 1979, c. 711. Title 41, referred to above, was repealed by Acts 1970, c. 291. Title 42, referred to ab ove, was repealed by Acts 1970, c. 606. Chapter 3 of Title 51, referred to above, was repealed by Acts 1952, c. 1. Chapter 1 of Title 53, referred to above, was repealed by Acts 1956, c. 386; Acts 1970, c. 648; Acts 1972, c. 175; Acts 1974, cc. 44, 45. C hapters 2 through 14 of Title 53, referred to above, were repealed by Acts 1982, c. 636. Chapter 24 of Title 54, referred to above, was repealed by Acts 1974, c. 534; Acts 1976, c. 651; Acts 1977, c. 640; Acts 1979, c. 408. Title 59, referred to above, w as repealed by Acts 1968, c. 439. Title 62, referred to above, was repealed by Acts 1968, c. 659. Title 63, referred to above, was repealed by Acts 1968, c. 578.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-3"><akn:num>§ 1-3</akn:num><akn:heading>Repeal of acts of a general nature</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text All acts and parts of acts of a general nature, in force at the time of the adoption of this Code, shall be repealed from and after February 1, 1950, with such limitati ons and exceptions as are hereinafter expressed; and all acts and parts of acts of a general nature in force at the time of the adoption of this Code, and in conflict with any of the provisions of this Code which by virtue of § 1-2.1 become effective on July 1, 1948, shall be repealed from and after July 1, 1948, with such limitations and exceptions as are hereinafter expressed. History History. Code 1919, § 6567; R. P. 1948, § 1-3. Annotations CASE NOTES Special act not repealed.  The Code of 1919 was a revision of the general statutes of the Commonwealth, and it did not repeal a special act of 1910 establishing a road law for Augusta Count y. Hamilton v. Commonwealth, 143 Va. 572, 130 S.E. 383, 1925 Va. LEXIS 291 (1925). Omission of acts of a general nature.  An act providing a different rule of ejectment procedure in three named counties, being a general law, was held repealed by being omitted from the Code of 1887. C arter's Heirs v. Edwards, 88 Va. 205, 13 S.E. 352, 1891 Va. LEXIS 18 (1891). An act authorizing the voluntary incorporation of building fund associations, being an act of a general nature, was repealed by being omitted from the Code of 188 7. Crabtree v. Old Dominion Bldg. &amp; Loan Ass'n, 95 Va. 670, 29 S.E. 741, 1898 Va. LEXIS 34 (1898).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-4"><akn:num>§ 1-4</akn:num><akn:heading>Effect of such repeal generally; effect of revision or amendment of state Constitution</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text No such repeal nor any amendment or revision of the Constitution of Virginia shall affect any offense or act committed or done, or any penalty or forfeiture incurred, o r any right established, accrued, or accruing before the day upon which such repeal, amendment or revision takes effect, or any prosecution, suit, or proceeding pending on that day, except that the proceedings thereafter had shall conform, so far as prac ticable, to the provisions of this Code; and where any penalty, forfeiture, or punishment is mitigated by those provisions, such provisions may, with the consent of the party affected, be applied to any judgment to be pronounced after that day; and such repeal, amendment or revision as to any statute of limitations, under which the bar of a right of action or remedy is complete at the time the repeal, amendment or revision takes effect, shall not be deemed a removal of such bar, but the bar shall contin ue, notwithstanding such repeal, amendment or revision. History History. Code 1919, § 6569; R. P. 1948, § 1-4; 1971, Ex. Sess., c. 1 4. Annotations CASE NOTES Acts done under a statute while in force remain valid, though the statute may afterwards be repealed, but the rule goes no farther than to render valid things actually done. Crawford v. Halsted &amp; Putnam, 61 Va. (20 Gratt.) 211, 1871 Va. LEXIS 2 (1871). An election held under an act subsequently repealed by being omitted from the Code of 18 87 was not invalidated by such repeal. Thomas v. Commonwealth, 90 Va. 92, 17 S.E. 788, 1893 Va. LEXIS 17 (1893). Section not controlling in action arising under federal act.  This section is not expressly controlling or directly in point on a legal question presented in an action arising under the Federal Housing and Rent Act of 1947 t o recover damages and attorneys fees for rentals charged in excess of the maximum rent that could be charged, where such act is later repealed, because the alleged right of action asserted arose under a federal act. Levinson v. Bott, 193 Va. 47, 67 S .E.2d 923, 1951 Va. LEXIS 239 (1951). As to change of mode of procedure in a pending case to conform to the then new Code of 1 887, see Edmunds' Ex'r v. Bruce, 88 Va. 1007, 14 S.E. 840, 1892 Va. LEXIS 63 (1892).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-5"><akn:num>§ 1-5</akn:num><akn:heading>Effect of such repeal as to persons in office</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text All persons who, at the time when such repeal takes effect, shall hold any office under any of the acts hereby repealed, shall continue to hold the same according to th e tenure thereof, except those offices which may have been abolished, and those as to which a different provision is made by this Code. History History. Code 1919, § 6571; R. P. 1948, § 1-5.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-6"><akn:num>§ 1-6</akn:num><akn:heading>Effect of repeal of validating statutes</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The repeal by any provisions of this Code of a statute validating previous acts, contracts or transactions shall not affect the validity of such acts, contracts or tran sactions, but the same shall remain as valid as if there had been no such repeal, but no further. History History. Code 1919, § 8; R. P. 1948, § 1-6.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-7"><akn:num>§ 1-7</akn:num><akn:heading>Acts passed between certain dates not affected</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The enactment of this Code shall not affect any act passed by the General Assembly, which shall have become a law after January 14, 1948, and before February 1, 1950; b ut every such act shall have full effect, and so far as the same varies from or conflicts with any provision contained in this Code it shall have effect as a subsequent act, and as repealing any part of this Code inconsistent therewith; provided, however , that any such act which becomes a law between said dates and which amends and reenacts, or reenacts any previously existing provisions of law conferring any power or imposing any duty upon any department, board, commission, agency or officer of the sta te government whose functions, powers and duties are affected by any of the provisions of this Code becoming effective July 1, 1948, shall be construed as conferring the powers and imposing the duties specified therein upon the department, board, commiss ion, agency or officer of the state government to which or to whom the duties and powers imposed or conferred by such previously existing provisions of law were transferred by the provisions of this Code becoming effective July 1, 1948. History History. Code 1919, § 6568; R. P. 1948, § 1-7. Annotations CASE NOTES Under former Codes.  As to application of similar provisions of the Codes of 1887 and 1919, see Virginia Dev. Co. v. Crozer Iron Co., 90 Va. 126, 17 S.E. 806, 1893 Va. LEXIS 21 (1893) ; Somers v. Commonwealth, 97 Va. 759, 33 S.E. 381, 1899 Va. LEXIS 90 (1899); Southern Ry. v. Russell, 133 Va. 292, 112 S.E. 700, 1922 Va. LEXIS 98 (1922); Campbell v. City of Danville, 138 Va. 817, 122 S.E. 120, 1924 Va. LEXIS 71 (1924).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-8"><akn:num>§ 1-8</akn:num><akn:heading>Notice, recognizance or process given, taken or issued before Code in force</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Although a notice, recognizance or process shall have been given, taken or issued before the day prescribed for the commencement of this Code, or of any provisions of t his Code, it may, nevertheless, be given, taken or returnable to a day after such commencement, or to a court established by this Code or the clerks office of such court, in like manner as if this Code had commenced before the same was given, taken, or issued. History History. Code 1919, § 6570; R. P. 1948, § 1-8.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-9"><akn:num>§ 1-9</akn:num><akn:heading>Pending cases; parties; where books, records and papers to remain</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Nothing in this Code shall operate to discontinue any cause or matter, civil or criminal, which shall be pending and undetermined in any court on the day before this Co de, or any provision of this Code, takes effect; but every such cause and matter shall be proceeded in, tried and determined in such court, or in the court which succeeds to or has its jurisdiction, and in the names of the same parties, or in the names o f any officers, boards, commission, or other persons or bodies who may have succeeded under the provisions of this Code to the rights or obligations of such parties, or any of them. The papers and records of such causes and matters, and all books, record s and papers whatever which on such day may be in the custody of any clerk of a court shall remain in custody of the clerk of the same, or of such court as succeeds to or has its jurisdiction. History History. Code 1919, § 6570; R. P. 1948, § 1-9. Annotations CIRCUIT COURT OPINIONS Operability of statute.  Section 1-219.1 did not prohibit the housing authority from acquiring the owners property because § 1-239 and case precedent made clear that Acts 2007, c. 926, cl. 3, allowed proceedings instituted by redevelopment and housing authorities before July 1, 2010, to continue until resolution. Norfolk Redevelopment &amp; Hous. Auth. v. Cent. Radio, Inc., 82 Va. Cir. 240, 2011 Va. Cir. LEXIS 85 (Norfolk Feb. 17, 201 1). Condemnation proceeding.  Section 1-219.1 did not apply to a condemnation proceeding because, although the proceeding was not finalized before the July 1, 2010, effective date of the statu te, the proceeding was instituted under the former law and before the new law took effect; to hold otherwise would have improperly discontinued a pending matter in violation of § 1-9. Norfolk Redevelopment &amp; Hous. Auth. v. Pryer, 2011 Va. Cir. LEXIS 8 4 (Norfolk May 16, 2011). Chapter 2. Common Law, Statutes and Rules of Construction. -360§§ 1-10 through 1-17.2.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-10"><akn:num>§ 1-10</akn:num><akn:heading>1-10 through 1-17</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>2. Text Repealed by Acts 2005, c. 839, cl. 10, effective October 1, 2005. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2005, c. 839, recodified Chapters 2 and 3 of Title 1, and all of Title 7.1, as Chapters 2.1 through 5 of Title 1, effective October 1, 2005. In addition to r evision by Acts 2005, c. 839, Titles 1 and 7.1 were also amended by other acts passed at the 2005 Session. As required by § 30-152, the Code Commission has incorporated the majority of these amendments into the new sections. Where appropriate, the his torical citations to former sections have been added to corresponding new sections. For tables of corresponding former and new sections, see the tables in Volume 10. Former § 1-13.4 was repealed by Acts 1986, c. 155. Former § 1-13.11 was repealed by Acts 1981, c. 228. Former § 1-13.39 was repealed by Acts 1983, c. 260 . Former § 1-14 was repealed by Acts 1975, c. 547. Chapter 2.1. Common Law and Rules of Construction. -360Article 1. Common Law and Acts of Parliament. -360Article 2. Rules of Construction and Definitions. Article 1. Common Law and Acts of Parliament. -360§ 1-200. The common law. -360§ 1-201. Acts of Parliament.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-18"><akn:num>§ 1-18</akn:num><akn:heading>1-18 through 1-21</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Repealed by Acts 2005, c. 839, cl. 10, effective October 1, 2005. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2005, c. 839, recodified Chapters 2 and 3 of Title 1, and all of Title 7.1 as Chapters 2.1 through 5 of Title 1, effective October 1, 2005. In addition to re vision by Acts 2005, c. 839, Titles 1 and 7.1 were also amended by other acts passed at the 2005 Session. As required by § 30-152, the Code Commission has incorporated the majority of these amendments into the new sections. Where appropriate, the hist orical citations to former sections have been added to corresponding new sections. For tables of corresponding former and new sections, see the tables in Volume 10. Chapter 3.1. Boundaries of the Commonwealth. -360§ 1-300. Boundaries. -360§ 1-301. Extent of territory of the Commonwealth after the Constitution of 1776. -360§ 1-302. Jurisdiction and ownership of Commonwealth over offshore waters and submerged lands. -360§ 1-303. Cession of territory northwest of Ohio River. -360§ 1-304. Boundary with North Carolina. -360§ 1-305. Boundary with North Carolina eastward from low-water mark of Atlantic Ocean. -360§ 1-306. Boundary with Tennessee. -360§ 1-307. Compact and boundary with Kentucky. -360§ 1-308. Boundary with Maryland. -360§ 1-309. Boundary with Maryland eastward from Assateague Island. -360§ 1-310. Boundary with Maryland in upper reaches of Pocomoke sound and lower reaches of Pocomoke River. -360§ 1-311. Recession of portion of District of Columbia. -360§ 1-312. Boundary with District of Columbia. -360§ 1-313. Boundary line between Loudoun County, Virginia, and Jefferson County, West Virginia.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-200"><akn:num>§ 1-200</akn:num><akn:heading>The common law</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The common law of England, insofar as it is not repugnant to the principles of the Bill of Rights and Constitution of this Commonwealth, shall continue in full force wi thin the same, and be the rule of decision, except as altered by the General Assembly. History History. Code 1919, § 2, § 1-10; 2005, c. 839. Annotations Transition provisions. Chapters 2 and 3 of Title 1 and Title 7 have been rewritten, primarily as new Chapters 2.1 through 5 of Title 1, by Acts 2005, c. 839, effective October 1, 2005. In addition to revision by Acts 2005, c. 839, §§ 1-13.23:1 [see now § 1-237] and 7.1-40.7:1 [see now § 1-510] were also amended by other acts passed a t the 2005 Session. As required by § 30-152, the Code Commission has incorporated these amendments into the new sections. Where appropriate, the historical citations to former sections have been added to corresponding new sections. The case notes appearing under new sections were decided under corresponding former sections or under prior law. For tables of corresponding former and new sections, see the tables in Volume 10. Acts 2005, c. 839, cl. 2, provides: That whenever any of the conditions, requirements, provisions or contents of any section or chapter of Titles 1 and 7.1 or any other title of the Code of Virginia as such titles existed prior to October 1, 2005, are transferred in the same or modified form to a new section or chapter of Title 1 or any other title of the Code and whenever any such former section or chapter i s given a new number in Title 1 or any other title, all references to any such former section or chapter of Title 1 or other title appearing in this Code shall be construed to apply to the new or renumbered section or chapter containing such conditions, requirements, provisions, contents or portions thereof. Acts 2005, c. 839, cl. 3, provides: That the regulations of any department or agency affected by the revision of Titles 1 or 7.1 or such other titles in effec t on the effective date of this act shall continue in effect to the extent that they are not in conflict with this act and shall be deemed to be regulations adopted under this act. Acts 2005, c. 839, cl. 4, provides: That the title revisions of Titles 1 and 7.1 as Chapters 2.1, 3.1, 4, and 5 of Title 1 shall not be construed to require t he reappointment of any officer or any member of a board, council, committee or other appointed body referred to in Titles 1 and 7.1 and each such officer and member shall continue to serve for the term for which appointed pursuant to the provisions of C hapter 2 and Chapter 3 of Title 1 and Title 7.1. Acts 2005, c. 839, cl. 5, provides: That the provisions of § 30-152 of the Code of Virginia shall apply to the revision of Titles 1 and 7.1 so as to give e ffect to other laws enacted by the 2005 session of the General Assembly notwithstanding the delay in the effective date of this act. Acts 2005, c. 839, cl. 6, provides: That the repeal of Chapters 2 and 3 of Title 1 and Title 7.1, effective as of October 1, 2005, shall not affect any act or offense done or committed, or any penalty incurred, or any right established, accrued or accruing on or before such date, or any proceeding, prosecution, suit or action pending on that day. Except as otherwise provided in this act, neither the repeal of Chapters 2 and 3 of Title 1 and Title 7.1 nor the enactment of Chapters 2.1, 3.1, 4 and 5 of Title 1 shall apply to offenses committed prior to October 1, 2005, and prosecution for such offenses shall be governed by the prior law, which is continued in effect for that purpose. For the purpose of this enactment, an offense was committed prior to October 1, 2005, if any of the essential elements of the offense occurred prior thereto. Acts 2005, c. 839, cl. 7, provides: That any notice given, recognizance taken, or process or writ issued before October 1, 2005, shall be valid although given , taken or to be returned to a day after such date, in like manner as if Chapters 2.1, 3.1, 4 and 5 of Title 1 had been effective before the same was given, taken or issued. Acts 2005, c. 839, cl. 8, provides: That if any clause, sentence, paragraph, subdivision or section of Chapters 2.1, 3.1, 4 and 5 of Title 1 shall be adjudged in any court of competent jurisdiction to be invalid, the judgment shall not affect, impair or invalidate the remainder thereof, but shall be confined in its operation to the clause, sentence, paragraph, subdivision or section thereof directly involved in the controversy in which the judgment shall have been rendered, and to this end the provisions of Title 1 are declared severable. Acts 2005, c. 839, cl. 9, provides: All actions of any county, city or town or political subdivision of the Commonwealth or any combination thereof identified by population classification under an act of the Assembly enacted prior to July 1, 1960, and of the officers thereof and of the clerks of courts thereof in the operation of their respective offices either on a fee or salary basis for the calendar year o f 1961, and until March 30, 1962, are hereby ratified, validated and confirmed. Effective date. This chapter became effective October 1, 2005. Law Review. For article, A Century of Tort Immunities in Virginia, see 4 U. Rich. L. Rev. 238 (1970). For survey of Virginia law on torts for the year 1970-71, see 57 Va. L. Rev. 1501 (1971). For note on law revision and reform in the common-law countries, see 13 Wm. &amp; Mary L. Rev. 253 (1971). For survey of Virginia law on taxation for the year 1972-73, see 59 Va. L. Rev. 1584 (1973). For survey of Virginia criminal procedure for the year 1977-1978, see 64 Va. L. Rev. 1419 (1978). For a re-examination of sovereign tort immunity in Virginia, see 15 U. Rich. L. Rev. 247 (1981). For article on discovery penalties, see 15 U. Rich. L. Rev. 283 (1981). For comment, Picking Up the Tab For Your Competitors: Innovator Liability After PLIVA, Inc. v. Mensing, see 19 Geo. Mason L. Rev. 1257 (2012). For comment, see Commonwealth and Constitution, 48 U. Rich. L. Rev. 415 (2013). For article, The Legitimacy of (Some) Federal Common Law, see 101 Va. L. Rev. 1 (2015). For article Making the Case to Avoid Entering the eBay Marketplace: A Recommended Analytical Framework for Evaluating Requests for Permanent Injunctions in Vi rginia, see 32 Regent U.L. Rev. 1 (2019). Research References. Bryson on Virginia Civil Procedure (Matthew Bender). Chapter 2. Potential Jurisdiction. § 2.02 Subject matter jurisdiction, etc. Bryson. Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 17 M.J. Statutes, § 48. CASE NOTES Editors note. Some of the cases annotated below were decided under former law. The common law of England is in force in Virginia in conformity to the terms of this sec tion. Wiseman v. Commonwealth, 143 Va. 631, 130 S.E. 249, 1925 Va. LEXIS 295 (1925); Elliott v. Commonwealth, 172 Va. 595, 1 S.E.2d 273, 1939 Va. LEXIS 264 (1939); Brown v. Brown, 183 Va. 353, 32 S.E.2d 79, 1944 Va. LEXIS 160 (1944); Needam v. Needam, 18 3 Va. 681, 33 S.E.2d 288, 1945 Va. LEXIS 214 (1945); Rosenberger v. Rosenberger, 184 Va. 1024, 37 S.E.2d 55, 1946 Va. LEXIS 166 (1946); Carter v. Hinkle, 189 Va. 1, 52 S.E.2d 135, 1949 Va. LEXIS 143 (1949). Insofar as applicable to our circumstances.  Such of the doctrines and principles of the common law as are repugnant to the nature and character of our political system, or which the different and varied cir cumstances of our country render inapplicable to us, are either not in force here or must be so modified in their application as to adapt them to our condition. It is a reasonable and substantial compliance with the common law, rather than a literal one, which is exacted by its adoption. Foster v. Commonwealth, 96 Va. 306, 31 S.E. 503, 1898 Va. LEXIS 92 (1898) (see Baring v. Reeder, 11 Va. (1 Hen. &amp; M.) 154 (1806); Coleman v. Moody, 14 Va. (4 Hen. &amp; M.) 1 (1809); Findlay v. Smith, 20 Va. (6 Munf.) 134 ( 1818); Stout v. Jackson, 23 Va. (2 Rand.) 132 (1823); Stokes &amp; Smith v. Upper Appomattox Co., 30 Va. (3 Leigh) 318 (1831)). Such of English common-law doctrines and principles as are repugnant to the nature and character of the political system, or which the different and varied circum stances of the country render inapplicable to the State, are either not in force here, or must be so modified in their application as to adapt them to the condition. Weishaupt v. Commonwealth, 227 Va. 389, 315 S.E.2d 847, 1984 Va. LEXIS 258 (1984). Except where modified by statute.  Virginia is a common-law State, except where modified by statute. Carey v. Foster, 221 F. Supp. 185, 1963 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 6685 (E.D. Va. 1963), aff'd, 345 F.2d 7 72, 1965 U.S. App. LEXIS 5571 (4th Cir. 1965). Although the General Assembly can abrogate the common law, its intent to do so must be p lainly manifested. Wackwitz v. Roy, 244 Va. 60, 418 S.E.2d 861, 8 Va. Law Rep. 3230, 1992 Va. LEXIS 58 (1992). Legislative intent to change the common law must be clear or plainly manifested. Chandle r v. National R.R. Passenger Corp., 882 F. Supp. 533, 1995 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 4344 (E.D. Va. 1995). This section does not mean that common-law rules are forever chiseled in stone, never changing. The common law is dynamic, evolves to meet developing societal problems, and is adaptable to societys requirements at the time of its application by the court. Williamson v. Old Brogue, Inc., 232 Va. 350, 350 S.E.2d 621, 3 Va. Law Rep. 1325, 1986 Va. LEXIS 264 (1986). But the common law cannot be enlarged by judicial decision in the absence of authority.  Virginia law, including the common law of England incorporated into the Virginia Code by § 1-10 [now § 1-200], does not provide a basis for recognizing a co mmon law right to use force to resist an illegal detention; in the absence of authority requiring such a right, there was no reason for enlarging, by judicial decision, the scope of the common law on the subject. Commonwealth v. Hill, 264 Va....</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-201"><akn:num>§ 1-201</akn:num><akn:heading>Acts of Parliament</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The right and benefit of all writs, remedial and judicial, given by any statute or act of Parliament, made in aid of the common law prior to the fourth year of the reig n of James the First, of a general nature, not local to England, shall still be saved, insofar as the same are consistent with the Bill of Rights and Constitution of this Commonwealth and the Acts of Assembly. History History. Code 1919, § 3, § 1-11; 2005, c. 839. Annotations Law Review. For note on law revision and reform in the common-law countries, see 13 Wm. &amp; Mary L. Rev. 253 (1971). Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 17 M.J. Statutes, § 36. CASE NOTES Scire facias.  As to preservation by this section of scire facias in personal actions, see Dykes &amp; Co. v. Woodhouse's Adm'r, 24 Va. (3 Rand.) 287, 1825 Va. LEXIS 20 (1825) (deci ded under prior law). Article 2. Rules of Construction and Definitions. -360§ 1-202. General rule of construction. -360§ 1-203. Adult. -360§ 1-204. Age of majority. -360§ 1-205. Bond with surety. -360§ 1-206. Certified mail equivalent to registered mail; certain subsequent mail or notice may be sent by regular mail. -360§ 1-207. Child; juvenile; minor; infant. -360§ 1-208. City. -360§ 1-208.1. Carbon-free energy; clean energy. -360§ 1-209. Collegial body. -360§ 1-210. Computation of time. -360§ 1-211. Constitutional references. -360§ 1-211.1. (Effective until July 1, 2024) Courthouse; posting of notices. -360§ 1-211.1. (Effective July 1, 2024) Courthouse; posting of notices. -360§ 1-212. Courts of record. -360§ 1-213. Delegation of duties assigned to political subdivision. -360§ 1-214. Effective dates. -360§ 1-215. Ex officio. -360§ 1-216. Gender. -360§ 1-217. Headlines of sections. -360§ 1-218. Includes. -360§ 1-219. Land; real estate. -360§ 1-219.1. Limitations on eminent domain. -360§ 1-220. Local ordinances incorporating state law by reference. -360§ 1-221. Locality. -360§ 1-222. Majority authority. -360§ 1-222.1. Manufacturer. -360§ 1-223. Month; year. -360§ 1-224. Municipality; incorporated communities; municipal corporation. -360§ 1-225. Nonlegislative citizen member. -360§ 1-226. Notary. -360§ 1-227. Number. -360§ 1-228. Oath. -360§ 1-229. Optional form of county government; effect of change in form. -360§ 1-230. Person. -360§ 1-231. When person includes business trust and limited liability company. -360§ 1-232. Person under disability. -360§ 1-233. Personal estate. -360§ 1-234. Personal representative. -360§ 1-235. Population; inhabitants. -360§ 1-236. Population classifications. -360§ 1-237. Process. -360§ 1-238. Reenacted. -360§ 1-239. Repeal not to affect liabilities; mitigation of punishment. -360§ 1-240. Repeal not to revive former act. -360§ 1-240.1. Rights of parents. -360§ 1-241. Seal. -360§ 1-242. Senate Committee on Privileges and Elections. -360§ 1-243. Severability. -360§ 1-244. Short title citations. -360§ 1-245. State. -360§ 1-246. Stricken language or italics. -360§ 1-247. Summaries of legislation. -360§ 1-248. Supremacy of federal and state law. -360§ 1-249. Supreme Court. -360§ 1-250. Swear; sworn. -360§ 1-251. Systems of state highways. -360§ 1-252. Tier-city. -360§ 1-253. Time zone. -360§ 1-254. Town. -360§ 1-255. United States. -360§ 1-256. Weights and measurements; metric equivalents. -360§ 1-257. Written; writing; in writing.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-202"><akn:num>§ 1-202</akn:num><akn:heading>General rule of construction</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The rules and definitions set forth in this chapter shall be used in the construction of this Code and the acts of the General Assembly, unless the construction would b e inconsistent with the manifest intention of the General Assembly. History History. Code 1919, § 5; Code 1950, § 1-13; 1950, p. 20; 2005, c. 83 9. Annotations Effective date. This chapter became effective October 1, 2005. Law Review. For article, Legislative History and the Interpretation of Statutes: Toward a Fact-Finding Model of Statutory Interpretation, see 76 Va. L. Rev. 1295 (199 0). Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 17 M.J. Statutes, § 80; 18 M.J. Taxation, § 10. CASE NOTES Editors note. The cases annotated below were decided under prior law. Section appl ies to statutes, not to deeds, wills, etc.  This section applies only in the construction of this Code and of all statutes. It says nothing about deeds, contracts, wills, or other documents, but is restricted to statutes, and in reference to the latter, it applies to all statutes. Kelly v. Trehy, 133 Va. 160, 112 S.E. 757, 1922 Va. LEXIS 90 (1922). Code is one act and construed as a who le.  The Code of 1887 was held to be one act, which must be construed as a whole. Gaines' Adm'r v. Marye, 94 Va. 225, 26 S.E. 511, 1897 Va. LEXIS 65 (1897); First Nat' l Bank v. Holland, 99 Va. 495, 39 S.E. 126, 1901 Va. LEXIS 70 (1901); South &amp; W. Ry. v. Commonwealth, 104 Va. 314, 51 S.E. 824, 1905 Va. LEXIS 101 (1905); Bertram v. Commonwealth, 108 Va. 902, 62 S.E. 969, 1908 Va. LEXIS 113 (1908). The Code of 1919 was held a single act, and its different sections were regarded, not as prior and subsequent acts, but as simultaneous expressions of the legisla tive will. It was further held that all provisions therein dealing with the same subject should be construed together and reconciled whenever possible. Shepherd v. Kress Box Co., 154 Va. 421, 153 S.E. 649, 1930 Va. LEXIS 225 (1930) (citing Piedmont Fin. Corp. v. Commonwealth, 146 Va. 287, 135 S.E. 673 (1926)). Resort to original statutes.  Notwithstanding the fact that the Codes of 1887 and 1919 were revisions of the statute law, if the various sections of one of the Codes were harmonious and their meaning plain, resort could not be had in construing them to the original statutes to see if any error was committed in the revision. If, however, there was a substantial doubt as to the meaning of the sections, the law which was the subject of the revis ion could be looked to in ascertaining their meaning. If they were inconsistent and could not stand together, the original statutes, and the respective dates of their enactment, could be examined to see what was the last expression of the will of the leg islature on the subject. Gaines' Adm'r v. Marye, 94 Va. 225, 26 S.E. 511, 1897 Va. LEXIS 65 (1897); W.S. Forbes &amp; Co. v. Southern Cotton Oil Co., 130 Va. 245, 108 S.E. 15, 1921 Va. LEXIS 152 (1921); Xippas v. Commonwealth, 141 Va. 497, 126 S.E. 207, 1925 Va. LEXIS 427 (1925). And see Shepherd v. Kress Box Co., 154 Va. 421, 153 S.E. 649, 1930 Va. LEXIS 225 (1930). Inte ntion to alter old law by revision must plainly appear.  The settled rule in construing the Code is that the old law was not intended to be altered, unless such intention plainly appears. Durrett v. Davis, 65 Va. (24 Gr att.) 302, 1874 Va. LEXIS 13 (1874); Hamilton v. Commonwealth, 143 Va. 572, 130 S.E. 383, 1925 Va. LEXIS 291 (1925) (see Parramore v. Taylor, 52 Va. (11 Gratt.) 220 (1854); Davis v. Commonwealth, 58 Va. (17 Gratt.) 617 (1867); Owners of Steamboat Wenonah v. Bragdon, 62 Va. (21 Gratt.) 685 (1872); Vaughan v. Jones, 64 Va. (23 Gratt.) 444 (1873); Thomas Admr v. Lewis, 89 Va. 1, 15 S.E. 389 (1892); Harrison v. Wissler, 98 Va. 597, 36 S.E. 982 (1900); Puckett v. Mullins Admr, 106 Va. 248, 55 S.E. 676 (1906); Wright v. Collins Admr, 111 Va. 806, 69 S.E. 942 (1911); Chapman v. Richardson, 123 Va. 388, 96 S.E. 776 (1918)). Change in phraseology is not important. Code revisors often make such changes and shorte n statutes with no intention to change their substance, and no change in substance will be construed as intended unless it plainly appears. Keister's Adm'r v. Keister's Ex'rs, 123 Va. 157, 96 S.E. 315, 1918 Va. LEXIS 13 (1918); Norfolk &amp; Portsmouth Bar A ss'n v. Drewry, 161 Va. 833, 172 S.E. 282, 1934 Va. LEXIS 307 (1934). Revised or substituted statute omitting provisions in original.  It is a general rule that when a revised statute, or one reenacted for another, omits provisions contained in original act, the omitted part cannot be supplied by construction. Richmond-Ashland Ry. v. Commonwealth ex rel. City of Richmond, 162 Va. 296, 173 S.E. 892, 1934 Va. LEXIS 246 (1934). When a statute is revised, or when one act is framed from another, and portions of the former are omitted, the missing part will not be revived by statutory const ruction but will be considered as annulled and revoked. Godlewski v. Gray, 221 Va. 1092, 277 S.E.2d 213, 1981 Va. LEXIS 253 (1981). Construction of one section considered in construing similar sections.  The construction placed upon language used in one section of the Code may be considered in determining the meaning of similar or the same language used in other s ections. First Nat'l Bank v. Holland, 99 Va. 495, 39 S.E. 126, 1901 Va. LEXIS 70 (1901). That the section of a Code last adopted in sequence will prevail where the difference in language is irreconcilable, see Building Supplies Corp. v. Willcox, 284 F. 113, 1922 U.S. App. LEXIS 2348 (4th Cir. 1922). If there is conflict between the body of a statute and a proviso, then the proviso must prevail, as the later expression of the legislative intent. Loyd Corp. v. Commonwealth, 126 Va. 39, 100 S.E. 833, 1919 Va. LEXIS 72 (1919). When a statute has been construed by the courts and is then reenacted by the legislature , the construction given to it is presumed to be sanctioned by the legislature and therefore becomes obligatory upon the courts. Kelly v. Trehy, 133 Va. 160, 112 S.E. 757, 1922 Va. LEXIS 90 (1922). When the General Assembly enacts a statute in language with a long history of definition by the Supreme Court, it intends that the words carry their historical co nstruction. Quintana v. Commonwealth, 224 Va. 127, 295 S.E.2d 643, 1982 Va. LEXIS 276 (1982), cert. denied, 460 U.S. 1029, 103 S. Ct. 1280, 75 L. Ed. 2d 501, 1983 U.S. LEXIS 4118 (1983). Subsequent legislation is enacted in the light of and with knowledge of an interpretative statute, such as this section, and hence the latter controls unless there be a clear legislative intent to substitute a different interpretation. Alphonse Custodis Chimney Constr. Co. v. Molina, 183 Va. 512, 32 S.E.2d 726, 1945 Va. LEXIS 197 (1945) (see Kelly v. Trehy, 133 Va. 160, 112 S.E. 757 (1922)). The rule that taxing statutes must be construed liberally in favor of the taxpayer when they are doubtful or ambiguous remains unaffected by this section. Williams v. City of Richmond, 177 Va. 477, 14 S.E.2d 287, 1941 Va. LEXIS 235 (1941). CIRCUIT COURT OPINIONS Illustrative cases.  In holding that the crime of conspiracy to commit a misdemeanor existed in Virginia, the court noted that, under the common law of England, a conspiracy to commit a misdemeanor was an offense. Commonwealth v. Howlett, 61 Va. Cir. 509, 2003 Va. Cir. LEXIS 136 (Norfolk May 8, 2003).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-203"><akn:num>§ 1-203</akn:num><akn:heading>Adult</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Adult means a person 18 years of age or more. History History. 1972, cc. 824, 825, § 1-13.42; 2005, c. 839.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-204"><akn:num>§ 1-204</akn:num><akn:heading>Age of majority</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text For the purposes of all laws of the Commonwealth including common law, case law, and the acts of the General Assembly, unless an exception is specifically provided in t his Code, a person shall be an adult, shall be of full age, and shall reach the age of majority when he becomes 18 years of age. History History. 1972, cc. 824, 825, § 1-13.42; 2005, c. 839. Annotations CASE NOTES Editors note. Most of the cases annotated below were decided under prior law. Minority is a legal status subject to change by the legislature rather than a vested right. For cases under prior law, see Mack v. Mack, 217 Va. 534, 229 S.E.2d 895, 1976 Va. LEXIS 317 (1976); Hurdle v. Prinz, 218 Va. 134, 235 S.E.2d 354, 1977 Va. LEXIS 174 (1977). Application to plaintiffs under age 21 when causes of action accrued prior to enactment of section.  There was no retroactive application of this section where the statute was applied to plaintiffs, both of whom were under the age of 21 at the time their causes o f action accrued prior to the enactment of the statute, causing the statute of limitations to run from the time plaintiffs reached 18 rather than from the age of 21 as at common law. Hurdle v. Prinz, 218 Va. 134, 235 S.E.2d 354, 1977 Va. LEXIS 174 (1977) . Application of the age of majority statute to the plaintiff s, both of whom were under the age of 21 at the time their causes of action accrued prior to the e nactment of the statute, causing the statute of limitations to run from the time plaintiff s reached the age of 18 rather than from the age of 21 as at common law, was not error. Hurdle v. Prinz, 218 Va. 134, 235 S.E.2d 354, 1977 Va. LEXIS 174 (1977) . Former § 8-30 in no event could properly be read to delay until age 21 the running of the statute of limitations in cases where causes of action for personal i njury accrued while plaintiffs were under 21 years of age, but where this section, changing the age of majority and therefore changing the status of plaintiffs, was enacted before plaintiffs reached 21. Hurdle v. Prinz, 218 Va. 134, 235 S.E.2d 354, 1977 Va. LEXIS 174 (1977). Child support payments.  When contract provisions as to child support entered into prior to the change in the age of majority were supplanted by a later court order in a divorce suit ente red after the change in majority, the court order controls and support payments were not owing for children over 18 despite contracts provision for payments until age 21. Eaton v. Eaton, 215 Va. 824, 213 S.E.2d 789, 1975 Va. LEXIS 233 (1975). Where a divorce decree incorporated the terms of a property settlement contract, by which the husband agreed to make child support payments until his child reache d the age of 21, where the chancellor subsequently ordered a consent decree awarding the husband custody of the child and reduced child support payments until further order of the court, and where custody of the child was subsequently restored to the wif e by court order and monthly payment required for the childs support was reinstated for the same period fixed in the property settlement contract, the consent decree did not supplant the child support provisions of the contract and did not deprive th e court of jurisdiction to order support beyond 18, despite the statutory reduction of the age of majority from 21 to 18 enacted subsequently. Gazale v. Gazale, 219 Va. 775, 250 S.E.2d 365, 1979 Va. LEXIS 169 (1979). Where no specific age for termination was set forth, but support payments were required until the child reached his majority, the parties intended not to extend the duty of child support beyond the period within which, in the absence of an agreement, the father would have been liable under Virginia law for such support. Meredith v. Meredith , 216 Va. 636, 222 S.E.2d 511, 1976 Va. LEXIS 178 (1976). The parties intended that the fathers duty to support his minor children terminated on the day when, in the absence of any agreement, his legal liabil ity for such support under Virginia law ended and that was his childs eighteenth birthday. Mack v. Mack, 217 Va. 534, 229 S.E.2d 895, 1976 Va. LEXIS 317 (1976). Attorney s claim for fees barred by clients infancy.  Trial court properly determined that an attorneys claim for legal services was barred by the clients infancy; the attorneys services to the client con cerning his potential inheritance were not actually necessary to the clients position and condition, as any distribution from the estate of the clients grandfather would not have come until several years after the client turned 18. Zelnick v. Ada ms, 269 Va. 117, 606 S.E.2d 843, 2005 Va. LEXIS 4 (2005).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-205"><akn:num>§ 1-205</akn:num><akn:heading>Bond with surety</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Bond with surety includes the payment in cash of the full amount of the required bond and, in such case, no surety shall be required. History History. 1977, c. 156, § 1-13.1:1; 2005, c. 839. Annotations Research References. Friends Virginia Pleading and Practice (Matthew Bender). Chapter 31 Proceedings in General District Courts. § 31.12 Pleadings. Friend. Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 1B M.J. Appeal and Error, § 154.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-206"><akn:num>§ 1-206</akn:num><akn:heading>Certified mail equivalent to registered mail; certain subsequent mail or notice may be sent by regular mail</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. If any mail or notice is required to be sent by registered mail, it shall constitute compliance with this requirement if such mail or notice is sent by certified mail. B. Notwithstan ding any provision of law to the contrary, whenever a state agency is required to send any mail or notice by certified mail and such mail or notice is sent certified mail, return receipt requested, then any subsequent, identical mail or notice that is se nt by such state agency may be sent by regular mail. C. As used in this section, state agency means the same as that term is defined in § 2.2-4347. History History. 1956, c. 647, § 1-15.1; 2005, c. 839; 2011, c. 566. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2011, c. 566, cl. 2 provides: That whenever in the Code of Virginia a state agency is required to send any mail or notice by certified mail and such mail or notice is sent certified mail, return receipt requested, then any subsequent, identical mail or notice that is sent by such state agency may be sent by regular mail. State agency means the same as that term is defined in § 2.2-4347 of the Code of Virginia. The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendment by c. 566 designated the existing provisions of the section as subsection A; and added subsections B and C.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-207"><akn:num>§ 1-207</akn:num><akn:heading>Child; juvenile; minor; infant</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Child, juvenile, minor, infant, or any combination thereof mea ns a person less than 18 years of age. History History. 1972, cc. 824, 825, § 1-13.42; 2005, c. 839. Annotations Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 9B M.J. Infants and Juveniles, § 2. CASE NOTES Minority is a legal status subject to change by the legislature rather than a vested right. For cases under prior law, see Mack v. Mack, 217 Va. 534, 229 S.E.2d 895, 1976 Va. LEXIS 317 (1976); Hurdle v. Prinz, 218 Va. 134, 235 S.E.2d 354, 1977 Va. LEXIS 174 (1977). Attorney s claim for fees barred by clients infancy.  Trial court properly determined that an attorneys claim for legal services was barred by the clients infancy; the attorneys services to the client con cerning his potential inheritance were not actually necessary to the clients position and condition, as any distribution from the estate of the clients grandfather would not have come until several years after the client turned 18. Zelnick v. Ada ms, 269 Va. 117, 606 S.E.2d 843, 2005 Va. LEXIS 4 (2005) (decided under prior law). Sodomy statute constitutional as applied where defendant is adult and victim is minor.  As defendants victims, 16 and 17, were minors as defined by § 1-207, his as-applied constitutional challenge to the sodomy statute, § 18.2-361, failed because nothing in Lawrence v. Texas, 539 U.S. 558 (2003), or Martin v. Ziherl, 607 S.E.2d 367 (2005), prohibited the application of the sodomy statute to conduct between adults and minors. McDona ld v. Commonwealth, 274 Va. 249, 645 S.E.2d 918, 2007 Va. LEXIS 87 (2007).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-208"><akn:num>§ 1-208</akn:num><akn:heading>City</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text City means an independent incorporated community which became a city as provided by la w before noon on July 1, 1971, or which has within defined boundaries a population of 5,000 or more and which has become a city as provided by law. History History. Code 1919, § 5; Code 1950, § 1-13; 1950, p. 21; 1971, Ex. S ess., c. 49, § 1-13.2; 1995, c. 155; 2005, c. 839. Annotations Cross references. As to local government, see Va. Const., Art. VII and § 15.2-100 et seq. Law Review. For note, Securing a Valid Annexation in Virginia, see 10 U. Rich. L. Rev. 557 (1976). § 1-208.1. Carbon-free energy; clean energy. Text Carbon-free energy or clean energy includes electric energy generated from a source that does not emit carbon dioxide into the atmosphere during the pro cess of generating the electric energy, including electric energy generated by the conversion of sunlight, wind, falling water, wave motion, tides, geothermal or nuclear energy. History History. 2020, c. 811.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-209"><akn:num>§ 1-209</akn:num><akn:heading>Collegial body</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Collegial body means a governmental entity whose power or authority is vested within i ts membership. History History. 2004, c. 651, § 1-13.4:1; 2005, c. 839.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-210"><akn:num>§ 1-210</akn:num><akn:heading>Computation of time</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. When an act of the General Assembly or rule of court requires that an act be performed a prescribed amount of time before a motion or proceeding, the day of such motion or proceeding shall not be counted against the time allowed, but the day on which such act is pe rformed may be counted as part of the time. When an act of the General Assembly or rule of court requires that an act be performed within a prescribed amount of time after any event or judgment, the day on which the event or judgment occurred shall not b e counted against the time allowed. B. When the la st day for performing an act during the course of a judicial proceeding falls on a Saturday, Sunday, legal holiday, or any day or part of a day on which the clerks office is closed as authorized by an act of the General Assembly, the act may be perfo rmed on the next day that is not a Saturday, Sunday, legal holiday, or day or part of a day on which the clerks office is closed as authorized by an act of the General Assembly. C. When an act of the General Assembly specifies a maximum period of time in which a legal action may be brought and the last day of that period falls on a Saturday, Sunday, legal holiday, or day or part of a day on which the clerks office is closed as authorized by an act of the General Assembly, the action may be brought on the next day that is not a Saturday, Sunday, legal holiday, or day or part of a day on which the clerks office is closed as authorized by an act of the General Assembly. D. Any court o r proceeding authorized to be adjourned from day to day shall not be required to meet on a Sunday or legal holiday. E. When an act of the General Assembly or local governing body, order of the court, or administrative regulation or order requires, either by specification of a date or by a prescribed period of time, that an act be performed or an action be filed on a Saturday, Sunda y, or legal holiday or on any day or part of a day on which the state or local government office where the act to be performed or the action to be filed is closed, the act may be performed or the action may be filed on the next business day that is not a Saturday, Sunday, legal holiday, or day on which the state or local government office is closed. F. For the pur poses of this section, any day on which the Governor authorizes the closing of the state government shall be considered a legal holiday. History History. Code 1919, § 5; 1932, p. 24; Code 1950, § 1-13; 1950, pp. 2 1, 23, §§ 1-13.3, 1-13.27; 1962, cc. 104, 284, § 1-13.3:1; 1977, c. 93; 1986, c. 166; 1987, c. 92; 2005, c. 839; 2008, c. 816; 2010, c. 96; 2014, c. 596. Annotations The 2008 amendments. The 2008 amendment by c. 816 added subsection C and redesignated former subsection C as subsection D. The 2010 amendments. The 2010 amendment by c. 96 added subsection E. The 2014 amendments. The 2014 amendment by c. 596 added subsection F. Law Review. For article, Civil Practice and Procedure, see 45 U. Rich. L. Rev. 183 (2010). Research References. Bryson on Virginia Civil Procedure (Matthew Bender). Chapter 6. Pleading. § 6.01 Filing of Pleadings, et seq. Bryson. Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 1B M.J. Appeal and Error, § 127; 12A M.J. Limitation of A ctions, § 2; 13A M.J. Motions for Judgment, § 18; 18 M.J. Sundays and Holidays, § 3; 18 M.J. Time, § 5. CASE NOTES Editors note. Most of the cases annotated below were decided under prior law. In general.  Acts 1932, p. 24, added the latter part of the section [now subsection A of this section], relating to notice or act required by statute within a certain time aft er an event or judgment. With this exception, this rule of construction as to computation of time has been on the statute books of the State, with a brief intermission, for over a century. Acts 1916, ch. 290, p. 508, made radical changes in the language of this provision, and extended the rule of construction to contracts, but the language of the old section was restored by the Code of 1919, which went into effect January 8, 1920. Kelly v. Trehy, 133 Va. 160, 112 S.E. 757, 1922 Va. LEXIS 90 (1922) (see School Bd. v. Alexander, 126 Va. 407, 101 S.E. 349 (1919)). Excluding day on w hich event or judgment occurred.  Hence, where a final decree, from which an appeal was obtained, was entered on April 24, the period for executing the appeal bond did not begin to run until April 25. Hurley v. Bennett, 163 Va. 241, 176 S.E. 171, 1934 Va. LEXIS 181 (1934). Prior to 1932, a different holding prevailed. See Kelly v. Trehy, 133 Va. 160, 112 S.E. 757, 1922 Va. LEXIS 90 (1922) (time for filing bill of exceptions); Swift &amp; Co. v. Wood, 103 Va. 494, 49 S.E. 643, 1905 Va. LEXIS 16 (1905) (time for return of notice of motion for judgment); Jennings v. Pocahontas Consol. Collieries Co., 114 Va. 213, 76 S.E. 298, 1912 Va. LEXIS 129 (1912) (time for filing declaration). Under this section, when a statute or rule of court requires a notice to be given or any other act to be done within a certain time after any event or judgment, t hat time shall be in addition to the day on which the event or judgment took place; thus here, the five month speedy trial time allowance under § 19.2-243 did not begin to run until the day after defendants probable cause hearing. Randolph v. Comm onwealth, 22 Va. App. 334, 470 S.E.2d 132, 1996 Va. App. LEXIS 324 (1996). In matters of private contract, such as the notice of sale required by a deed of trust, this section does not now apply; but it is the rule in Virginia that if a contract is to be performed or some act is to be done within a certain number of days from a specified date, the first or specified day is not to be counted. Dickerson v. McNulty, 142 Va. 559, 129 S.E. 242, 1925 Va. LEXIS 359 (1925). Saving provision applicable.  The court erred in holding that no judgment could be entered in favor of appellants because Rule 3:3 [see now § 8.01-275.1] effectively fixes the 365th day after commencement of the action as the last day for the motion for judgment to be served [or] delivered, thereby subjecting the one-year period of Rule 3:3 to the saving provision in former § 1-13.3:1 [now § 1-210]; therefore, since the 365th day was a Saturday, former § 1-13.3:1 extended the date for service to be completed until the next day that was not a Saturday, Sunday, or legal holiday. Frey v. Jefferson Homebuilders, Inc., 251 Va. 375, 467 S.E.2d 788, 1996 Va. LEXI S 26 (1996). Court overruled appellee corporations motion to dismiss because the argument that former § 1-13.3:1 [now § 1-210] is inapplicable because former Rule 3: 3 [see now § 8.01-275.1] neither establishes a last day to serve process on a defendant, nor invalidates the service of process in this case, but merely prohibits the court from entering judgment for a plaintiff who fails to serve process with in a year after his action is commenced, results in the absurd construction validating a delayed service but effectively nullifying that service. Frey v. Jefferson Homebuilders, Inc., 251 Va. 375, 467 S.E.2d 788, 1996 Va. LEXIS 26 (1996). Occupational disease portion of an employees workers compensation claim was not time-barred because the employee timely filed the claim within the five-ye ar limitations period as the limitations period ended on a Sunday and the employee filed the claim on the following Monday. Iglesias v. QVC Suffolk, Inc., 2019 Va. App. LEXIS 86 (Va. Ct. App. Apr. 16, 2019). Sections govern how time period in § 34-17 should be calculated.  This section and former § 1-13.3:1 [now subsections A and B of this section], and not the Federal Rules of Bankruptcy Procedure, govern how the five-day period provided for in § 34-17 should be calculated to determine whether debtors failed to file their homestead deed in a timely fashion. In re Haynesworth, 145 Bankr. 222, 1992 Bankr. LEXIS 1512 (Bankr. E.D. Va. 1992). Trustees objection to debtors claim of exemptions, under 11 U.S.C.S. § 522(b)(2)(A), was overruled as debtors timely filed their amended homestead deed s on November 16, 2005, pursuant to § 34-17, because: (1) a legal proceeding was not in ordinary parlance considered to have been held until it was over; (2) a meeting of creditors had not occurred, pursuant to subsection A of § 1-2 10, until it actually concluded; and (3) the original meeting of creditors was not concluded on October 17, 2005, but was continued to November 23, 2005, at which time the meeting was concluded according to trustee. In re Shelton, 343 Bankr. 545, 2006 Ba nkr. LEXIS 1401 (Bankr. W.D. Va. 2006). Chapter 7 debtor was not entitled to claim the homestead exemption under § 34-4 because the debtor did not record a homestead deed in the proper jurisdiction w ithin five days after the 11 U.S.C.S. § 341 meeting of creditors, as required by § 34-17. The debtor recorded the deed two days after the end of the five-day period as calculated under § 1-210. In re Conner, 408 Bankr. 88, 2009 Bankr. LEXIS 2409 (Bankr. W.D. Va. 2009). Sunday being dies non juridicus, it is not one of the days of the term of a court. Michi e v. Michie's Adm'rs, 58 Va. (17 Gratt.) 109, 1866 Va. LEXIS 10 (1866); Read v. Commonwealth, 63 Va. (22 Gratt.) 924, 1872 Va. LEXIS 71 (1872); Bowles v. Brauer, 89 Va. 466, 16 S.E. 356, 1892 Va. LEXIS 123 (1892). An entry of a vacation decree on Sunday was held void. Lee v. Willis, 99 Va. 16, 37 S.E. 826, 1900 Va. LEXIS 118 (1900). Computation of time.  When a statute prescribes a certain number of days within which an act is to be done, and says nothing about Sunday, it is to be included, unless the last day fal ls on Sunday, in which case the act may generally be on the succeeding day. But, if the act may be lawfully done on Sunday, and the last day falls on Sunday, then Sunday is not to be excluded. Bowles v. Brauer, 89 Va. 466, 16 S.E. 356, 1892 Va. LEXIS 123 (1892) (see Harris v. Sparrow, 146 Va. 747, 132 S.E. 694 (1926), with reference to computation of ti...</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-211"><akn:num>§ 1-211</akn:num><akn:heading>Constitutional references</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Whenever any act of the General Assembly in effect at noon on July 1, 1971, refers to any section, article, or provision of the prior Constitution of Virginia, such ref erence shall apply to any comparable section, article, or provision of the Constitution of Virginia then in effect unless the construction would be contrary to the legislative intent of the act. History History. 1971, Ex. Sess., c. 49, § 1-13.41; 2005, c. 839. § 1-211.1. (Effective until July 1, 2024) Courthouse; posting of notices. Text If any notice, summons, order, or other official document of any type is required to be posted on or at the front door of a courthouse or on a public bulletin board at a courthouse, it shall constitute compliance with this requirement if the notice, summons, order, or other official document is posted with other such documents where such notice, summons, order or other official document is posted or at or near the prin cipal public entrance to the courthouse in a location that is conspicuous to the public and approved by the chief judge of the circuit in which the courthouse is situated, or both. The requirement to post any notice, summons, order, or other official doc ument of any type is satisfied if such notice, summons, order, or other official document is posted on the public government website of the locality served by the court or the website of the circuit court clerk. History History. 2007, c. 734; 2014, c. 269; 2015, c. 631; 2022, c. 683. Annotations The 2014 amendments. The 2014 amendment by c. 269, inserted either on the public government website of the locality served by the court where such notice, summons, order or other official document is posted or and added or both at the end. The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendment by c. 631 deleted either on the public government website of the locality served by the court following other such documents in the first sentence and added the second sentence. The 2022 amendments. The 2022 amendment by c. 683, effective July 1, 2024, added the clause (i) and (ii) designations; deleted the former last sentence, which read: The requiremen t to post any notice, summons, order, or other official document of any type is satisfied if such notice, summons, order, or other official document is posted on the public government website of the locality served by the court or the website of the circ uit court clerk.; and made stylistic changes. § 1-211.1. (Effective July 1, 2024) Courthouse; posting of notices. Text If any notice, summons, order, or other official document of any type is required to be posted on or at the front door of a courthouse or on a public bulletin board at a courthouse, it shall constitute compliance with this requirement if the notice, summons, order, or other official document is (i) posted with other such documents where such notice, summons, order or other official document is posted or at or near the principal public entrance to the courthouse in a location that is conspicuous to the public and approved by the chief judge of the circuit in which the courthouse is situated, or both, and (ii) posted on the public government website of the locality serv ed by the court or the website of the circuit court clerk. History History. 2007, c. 734; 2014, c. 269; 2015, c. 631; 2022, c. 683.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-212"><akn:num>§ 1-212</akn:num><akn:heading>Courts of record</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Courts of record means the Supreme Court of Virginia, the Court of Appeals of Virginia , and the circuit courts. History History. 1971, Ex. Sess., c. 49, § 1-13.5:1; 2005, c. 839. Annotations Law Review. For survey of Virginia law on practice and pleading for the year 1970-71, see 57 Va. L. Rev. 1561 (1971).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-213"><akn:num>§ 1-213</akn:num><akn:heading>Delegation of duties assigned to political subdivision</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The governing body of a political subdivision shall be responsible for any duty or responsibility imposed upon its political subdivision. History History. 1986, c. 239, § 1-17.2; 1987, c. 471; 1988, c. 273; 2005, c. 8 39.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-214"><akn:num>§ 1-214</akn:num><akn:heading>Effective dates</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. All laws en acted at a regular session of the General Assembly, including laws which are enacted by reason of actions taken during the reconvened session following a regular session, but excluding general appropriation acts, decennial reapportionment acts, and emerg ency acts, shall take effect on the first day of July following the adjournment of the regular session at which they were enacted, unless a subsequent date is specified. B. All laws en acted at a special session of the General Assembly, including laws which are enacted by reason of actions taken during the reconvened session following a special session, but excluding general appropriations acts, decennial reapportionment acts, and emer gency acts, shall take effect on the first day of the fourth month following the month of adjournment of the special session at which they were enacted, unless a subsequent date is specified. C. A general a ppropriation act shall take effect from its passage, unless another effective date is specified in the act. D. An emergenc y act shall take effect from its passage, or on a subsequent date if specified in the act, provided that the emergency shall be expressed in the body of the act and that the emergency shall be approved by a four-fifths vote of the members voting in each house of the General Assembly. The name of each member voting and how he voted shall be recorded in the journal. E. A decennial reapportionment act to reapportion the Commonwealth into electoral districts shall take effect immediately. History History. Code 1919, § 4; 1971, Ex. Sess., c. 49, § 1-12; 1981, c. 32 9; 2005, c. 839. Annotations Cross references. For implementation of changes to Title 24.2, see § 24.2-101.1. See Va. Const., Art. IV, § 13. CASE NOTES As to what constitutes a case of emergency referred to in this section, see Couk v. Skee n, 109 Va. 6, 63 S.E. 11, 1908 Va. LEXIS 115 (1908) (decided under prior law). Act without emergency cl ause under former law.  An act which contained no emergency clause did not take effect until the lapse of 90 days after the adjournment of the General Assembly, but became effective imme diately upon the expiration of the suspension period. Burks v. Commonwealth, 126 Va. 763, 101 S.E. 230, 1919 Va. LEXIS 111 (1919) (decided under § 53 of the Constitution of 1902 and a prior version of this section as it stood before the 1971 amendment ). Computation of effecti ve date under former law.  An event which took place June 1, 1914, occurred seventeen days before  an act approved March 20, 1914, took effect,  the session of the General A ssembly having adjourned sine die March 20, 1914. Burks v. Commonwealth, 126 Va. 763, 101 S.E. 230, 1919 Va. LEXIS 111 (1919) (decided under § 53 of the Constitution of 1902 and a prior version of this section as it stood before the 1971 amendment). An act approved March 3, 1932, the 1932 session of the Assembly having adjourned sine die March 22, 1932, became law on June 21, 1932. Allen v. Mottley Constr. Co ., 160 Va. 875, 170 S.E. 412, 1933 Va. LEXIS 264 (1933) (decided under § 53 of the Constitution of 1902 and a prior version of this section as it stood before the 1971 amendment).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-215"><akn:num>§ 1-215</akn:num><akn:heading>Ex officio</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Ex officio means service by virtue of ones office and includes voting privileges f or ex officio members unless otherwise provided. History History. 2005, c. 839.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-216"><akn:num>§ 1-216</akn:num><akn:heading>Gender</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A word used in the masculine includes the feminine and neuter. History History. Code 1919, § 5; Code 1950, § 1-13; 1950, p. 21, § 1-13.7 ; 1997, c. 406; 2005, c. 839.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-217"><akn:num>§ 1-217</akn:num><akn:heading>Headlines of sections</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The headlines of the sections printed in black-face type are intended as mere catchwords to indicate the contents of the sections and do not constitute part of the act of the General Assembly. History History. Code 1919, § 5; Code 1950, § 1-13; 1950, p. 21, § 1-13.9 ; 2005, c. 839. Annotations Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 17 M.J. Statutes, § 109. CASE NOTES Editors note. Some of the cases annotated below were decided under prior law. Statute heading just i nformative convenience.  It is well-settled that the words of the statute, not its heading, carry the force of law. The heading of the statute is purely a matter of informative convenienc e. The court must construe the body of the statute. Jones v. Division of Child Support Enforcement ex rel. Owens, 19 Va. App. 184, 450 S.E.2d 172, 1994 Va. App. LEXIS 653 (1994); Foster v. Commonwealth, 271 Va. 235, 623 S.E.2d 902, 2006 Va. LEXIS 6 (2006 ). Related to titles of acts.  In the construction of an act, its title is entitled to its due share of consideration, and while a headline is not strictly a title, it occupies a closely relate d position. It contains catchwords which are intended to indicate the contents of a section. Jordan v. Town of South Boston, 138 Va. 838, 122 S.E. 265, 1924 Va. LEXIS 76 (1924) (see Chambers v. Higgins, 169 Va. 345, 193 S.E. 531 (1937)). Retaining a heading after an amendment similar to that which appeared prior to the amendment does not control the classification of the section or take precedence over the language adopted by the legislature. Shaw v. Commonwealth, 9 Va. App. 331, 387 S.E.2d 792, 6 Va. Law Rep. 1200, 1990 Va. App. LEXIS 12 (1990). Not applicable to federal law.  Parental rights of a mother were properly terminated where the mother was convicted in federal court of abusive sexual contact, a felony, as felony sexual assault in Virginia included all felonies proscribed by the article within the Virginia Code captioned Criminal Sexual Assault; unlike the contents of § 1-13.9 [now § 1-217] regarding the headlines of Virginia Code sections, the fe deral law contained no provision stating that captions of subtitles, chapters, or articles were intended as mere catchwords, and it expressly provided that a subtitle, chapter, or article could be cited by its caption where no section or provision establ ished or authorized a short title citation for such subtitle, chapter, or article. M. G. v. Albemarle County Dep't of Soc. Servs., 41 Va. App. 170, 583 S.E.2d 761, 2003 Va. App. LEXIS 406 (2003).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-218"><akn:num>§ 1-218</akn:num><akn:heading>Includes</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Includes means includes, but not limited to. History History. 2005, c. 839.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-219"><akn:num>§ 1-219</akn:num><akn:heading>Land; real estate</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Land, lands, or real estate includes lands, tenements and hereditaments, and all rights and appurtenances thereto and interests therein, other than a chattel interest. History History. Code 1919, § 5; Code 1950, § 1-13; 1950, p. 22, § 1-13.1 2; 2005, c. 839. Annotations CASE NOTES Editors note. Some of the cases annnotated below were decided under prior law. Leasehold is not real property.  At common law, an estate for years was considered personalty. Absent statutory modification, this remains the law in Virginia. There is no statutory modification of this common-law rule. Therefore, leasehold interests are not considered to be real estate. CSB, Inc. v. Cradle of Democracy Broadcasting Co., 547 F. Supp. 106, 1982 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 14592 (E.D. Va. 1982). A chattel real or leasehold is intangible personal property and not real property. CSB, Inc. v. Cradle of Democracy Broadcasting Co., 547 F. Supp. 106, 1982 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 14592 (E.D. Va. 1982). Real estat e does not include unattached building.  The words used in this section to define real estate plainly do not encompass a building that is unattached to land. Pardoe &amp; Graham Real Estate, Inc. v. Schulz Homes Corp., 259 Va. 398, 525 S.E.2d 284, 2000 Va. LEXIS 44 (2000). Land embraces underlying miner als.  Land sold without reservation of any kind embraces the underlying minerals. Steinman v. Vicars, 99 Va. 595, 39 S.E. 227, 1901 Va. LEXIS 84 (1901). And includes ground rents.  The word land as defined in this section is sufficient to include ground rents. Willis's Ex'r v. Commonwealth, 97 Va. 667, 34 S.E. 460, 1899 Va. LEXIS 83 (1899). Transferrable development rights.  Transferrable development rights are entirely creatures of statute and they are governed by a specific statutory regime. Two things must occur for transferrable d evelopment rights to come into being. First, the county must approve an application from an eligible sending site, and, second, the county must approve a receiving site. The dedication of density or other rights, i.e., the creation of transferrable devel opment rights, occurs under § 15.2-750 when both conditions have been fulfilled. The transferrable development rights have potential value before that, but until the county approves a sending site and a receiving site, in the eyes of the law, the tran sferrable development rights remain an inchoate interest or right. Once the transferrable development rights are created by the countys approval of a sending and a receiving site, they become a right or interest in real estate under the broad definit ion found in § 1-219 and they may be taxed under § 58.1-3201. Johnson v. Arlington Cnty., 292 Va. 843, 794 S.E.2d 389, 2016 Va. LEXIS 200 (2016). Water mains, gates, hydrants and pipes of a city water system were to be regarded as fix tures and taxable as land under § 183 (g) of the Constitution of 1902, notwithstanding the statutory definition of land contained herein. City of Newport News v. Warwick County, 159 Va. 571, 166 S.E. 570, 1932 Va. LEXIS 219 (1932). § 1-219.1. Limitations on eminent domain. Text A. The right t o private property being a fundamental right, the General Assembly shall not pass any law whereby private property shall be taken or damaged for public uses without just compensation. The term public uses mentioned in Article I, Section 11 of the Constitution of Virginia is hereby defined as to embrace only the acquisition of property where: (i) the property is taken for the possession, ownership, occupation, and enjoyment of property by the public or a public corporation; (ii) the property is t aken for construction, maintenance, or operation of public facilities by public corporations or by private entities provided that there is a written agreement with a public corporation providing for use of the facility by the public; (iii) the property i s taken for the creation or functioning of any public service corporation, public service company, or railroad; (iv) the property is taken for the provision of any authorized utility service by a government utility corporation; (v) the property is taken for the elimination of blight provided that the property itself is a blighted property; or (vi) the property taken is in a redevelopment or conservation area and is abandoned or the acquisition is needed to clear title where one of the owners agrees to s uch acquisition or the acquisition is by agreement of all the owners. B. For purpose s of this section:Blighted property means any property that endangers the public health or safety in its condition at the time of the filing of the petition for condemnation and is (i) a public nuisance or (ii) an individual commercial, industrial, or residential structure or improvement that is beyond repair or unfit for human occupancy or use. Government utility corporation means any county or municipality, or entity or agency thereof, which provides or operates one or more of the following authorized utility services: gas, pipeline, electric light, heat, power, water supply, sewer, telephone, or telegraph.Public corporation means the Commonwealth of Virginia or any political subdivision thereof or any incorporated municipality therein or any public agency of the Commonwealth or of any political subdivision thereof or of any municipality therein.Public facilities means (i) airport s, landing fields, and air navigation facilities; (ii) educational facilities; (iii) flood control, bank and shore protection, watershed protection, and dams; (iv) hospital facilities; (v) judicial and court facilities; (vi) correctional facilities, incl uding jails and penitentiaries; (vii) library facilities; (viii) military installations; (ix) parks so designated by the Commonwealth or by the locality in its comprehensive plan; (x) properties of historical significance so designated by the Commonwealt h; (xi) law enforcement, fire, emergency medical, and rescue facilities; (xii) sanitary sewer, water or stormwater facilities; (xiii) transportation facilities including highways, roads, streets, and bridges, traffic signals, related easements and rights -of-way, mass transit, ports, and any components of federal, state, or local transportation facilities; (xiv) waste management facilities for hazardous, radioactive, or other waste; (xv) office facilities occupied by a public corporation; and (xvi) such other facilities that are necessary to the construction, maintenance, or operation of a public facility as listed in clauses (i) through (xv) and directly related thereto. C. No more pri vate property may be taken than that which is necessary to achieve the stated public use. D. Except wher e property is taken (i) for the creation or functioning of a public service corporation, public service company, or railroad; (ii) for the provision of any authorized utility service by a government utility corporation; or (iii) for sanitary sewer, water or stormwater facilities, or transportation facilities, including highways, roads, streets, and bridges, traffic signals, related easements and rights-of-way, mass transit, ports, and any components of federal, state, or local transportation facilities, by a public corporation, property can only be taken where: (a) the public interest dominates the private gain and (b) the primary purpose is not private financial gain, private benefit, an increase in tax base or tax revenues, an increase in employment, or economic development. E. During cond emnation proceedings, the property owner may challenge whether the taking or damaging is for a public use, the stated public use is a pretext for an unauthorized use, or the taking or damaging of property is a violation of subsection D. Nothing in this s ection shall be construed as abrogating any defenses or rights otherwise available to the property owner independently of this section. F. Subject to the provisions of subsection D, the limitations contained in this section shall not abrogate any other provision of law that authorizes a condemnor to dispose of property taken for a public use as surplus property, as otherwise provided by law. G. If the acqu isition of only part of a property would leave its owner with an uneconomic remnant, the condemnor shall offer to acquire the entire property for its fair market value as otherwise provided by law, but the condemnor shall not acquire an uneconomic remnan t if the owner objects and desires to maintain ownership of the excess property. H. The provisi ons of this section shall control to the extent there are any inconsistencies between this section and any other general or special law; otherwise, nothing herein shall be construed as abrogating the power of eminent domain delegated independently of thi s section. I. The provisi ons of this section shall not apply to the forfeiture of property under Chapters 22.1 (§ 19.2-386.1 et seq.) and 22.2 (§ 19.2-386.15 et seq.) of Title 19.2. J. The provisi ons of this section shall not apply to real property that is subject to a certificate of take or a certificate of deposit recorded prior to July 1, 2007, in the circuit court clerks office for the circuit where the real property is located or real pr operty that is the subject of a petition for condemnation filed prior to July 1, 2007. K. For the pur poses of any taking of private property in accordance with Article I, Section 11 of the Constitution of Virginia, a government utility corporation shall be considered to be acting as a public service corporation or public service company where the proper ty is taken for the provision of an authorized utility service only; provided, however, that nothing in this subsection shall modify or affect the jurisdiction of the State Corporation Commission. History History. 2007, cc. 882, 901, 926; 2012, cc. 283, 626, 756. Annotations The number of this section was assigned by the Virginia Code Commission, the number in the 2007 acts having been § 1-237.1. Editors note. Acts 2...</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-220"><akn:num>§ 1-220</akn:num><akn:heading>Local ordinances incorporating state law by reference</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text When counties, cities and towns are empowered to incorporate by reference provisions of the Code, acts of the General Assembly, or state regulations into a local ordina nce, any ordinance incorporating by reference provisions of the Code, acts of the General Assembly or state regulations may include future amendments to the provisions of the Code, acts of the General Assembly or state regulations provided such intent is specifically stated in such ordinance. History History. 1993, c. 710, § 1-13.39:2; 2001, c. 771; 2005, c. 839.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-221"><akn:num>§ 1-221</akn:num><akn:heading>Locality</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Locality means a county, city, or town as the context may require. History History. 2005, c. 839. Annotations OPINIONS OF THE ATTORNEY GENERAL A regional planning district commi ssion is not a locality, authority, or sanitation district for purposes of competitive negotiation as defined in § 2.2-4301 of the Virginia Public Procurement Act. See opinion of Attorney General to The Honorable Robert D. Bobby Orrock, Member, House of Delegates, 10-020, (4/27/10).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-222"><akn:num>§ 1-222</akn:num><akn:heading>Majority authority</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Whenever authority is conferred by law to three or more persons, a majority of such persons shall have the power to exercise such authority, unless otherwise provided. History History. Code 1919, § 5; Code 1950, § 1-13; 1950, p. 21, § 1-13.1 ; 2005, c. 839. Annotations CASE NOTES This section is a rule of construction which only confers power on a majority of a valid commission when acting pursuant to their authority. Dillon v. Davis, 201 Va. 514, 112 S.E.2d 137, 1960 Va. LEXIS 123 (1960) (decided under prior law). Persons deriving authority from statutory source.  This subsection refers only to the construction of statutes and to public officers or other persons deriving their authority from a statutory source. It has no ap plication to arbitrators acting under a private agreement of submission. Fraley v. Nickels, 121 Va. 377, 93 S.E. 636, 1917 Va. LEXIS 42 (1917) (decided under prior law). Bank directors.  If a majority of a board of bank directors be present and qualified to vote and do vote, an election may be made by a majority of the votes given, although they b e not a majority of the whole board; and this although others of the directors be present, but do not vote. Booker v. Young, 53 Va. (12 Gratt.) 303, 1855 Va. LEXIS 21 (1855) (decided under prior law). § 1-222.1. Manufacturer. Text Manufacturer shall not include any farm or aggregation of farms that owns and operates facilities within the Commonwealth for the generation of electric energy from waste-to-energy technology. As used in this definition, (i) farm means any person that obtains at least 51 percent of its annual gross income from agricultural operations and produces the agricultural waste used as feedstock for the waste-to -energy technology, (ii) agricultural waste means biomass waste materials capable of decomposition that are produced from the raising of plants and animals during agricultural operations, including animal manures, bedding, plant stalks, hulls, an d vegetable matter, and (iii) waste-to-energy technology means any technology, including but not limited to a methane digester, that converts agricultural waste into gas, steam, or heat that is used to generate electricity on-site. History History. 2009, c. 746. Annotations Law Review. For annual survey article, see Environmental Law, see 44 U. Rich. L. Rev. 423 (2009).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-223"><akn:num>§ 1-223</akn:num><akn:heading>Month; year</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Month means a calendar month and year means a calendar year. History History. Code 1919, § 5; Code 1950, § 1-13; 1950, pp. 22, 24, § § 1-13.13, 1-13.33; 2005, c. 839. Annotations Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 18 M.J. Time, § 2. CASE NOTES The word month in a statute means a month as designated in the calendar without regard to the number of days it may contain, and is to be computed not by counting the days but by looking at the calendar. It runs from a given day in one month to a corresponding number in the next month, except where the last month has not so many day s, in which event it expires on the last day of that month. Cousins v. Commonwealth, 187 Va. 506, 47 S.E.2d 391, 1948 Va. LEXIS 241 (1948) (decided under prior law). And not 30 days.  Where the minimum punishment for an offense is confinement in jail for not less than one month, it is error for the jury, in view of this section, to fix the puni shment at 30 days in jail when the calendar month consists of 31 days. But as the error is in the accuseds favor it is harmless. Barrack v. Commonwealth, 142 Va. 596, 128 S.E. 638, 1925 Va. LEXIS 362 (1925) (decided under prior law). Courts are required to employ calendar years and not 365-day periods when comput ing whether a statute of limitations has expired. Ward v. Insurance Co. of N. Am., 253 Va. 232, 482 S.E.2d 795, 1997 Va. LEXIS 33 (1997) (decided under prior law).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-224"><akn:num>§ 1-224</akn:num><akn:heading>Municipality; incorporated communities; municipal corporation</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Municipality, incorporated communities, municipal corporation, and wor ds or terms of similar import mean cities and towns. History History. 2005, c. 839.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-225"><akn:num>§ 1-225</akn:num><akn:heading>Nonlegislative citizen member</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Nonlegislative citizen member means any natural person who is not a member of the Gene ral Assembly of Virginia. History History. 2004, c. 709, § 1-13.13:1; 2005, c. 839.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-226"><akn:num>§ 1-226</akn:num><akn:heading>Notary</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Notary means notary public. History History. Code 1919, § 5; Code 1950, § 1-13; 1950, p. 22, § 1-13.1 4; 2005, c. 839.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-227"><akn:num>§ 1-227</akn:num><akn:heading>Number</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A word used in the singular includes the plural and a word used in the plural includes the singular. History History. Code 1919, § 5; Code 1950, § 1-13; 1950, p. 22, § 1-13.1 5; 2005, c. 839. Annotations CASE NOTES The article a does not necessarily denote the singular. Wolfe v. Commonwealth, 16 7 Va. 486, 189 S.E. 320, 1937 Va. LEXIS 292 (1937) (decided under prior law). Regulatory interpretation.  Trial court wrongly interpreted 18 Va. Admin. Code § 150-20-140 to require multiple acts of a veterinarians unprofessional conduct because Va. Code Ann. § 1-227 said a word used in the plural included the singular. Va. Bd. of Veterinary Med. v. Leonard, 2014 Va. App. LEXIS 370 (Va. Ct. App. Nov. 12, 2014), aff'd, No. 141764, 2015 Va. Unpub. LEXIS 11 (Va. Oct. 8, 2015).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-228"><akn:num>§ 1-228</akn:num><akn:heading>Oath</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Oath includes affirmation. History History. Code 1919, § 5; Code 1950, § 1-13; 1950, p. 22, § 1-13.1 6; 2005, c. 839. Annotations Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 14A M.J. Oath, § 2.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-229"><akn:num>§ 1-229</akn:num><akn:heading>Optional form of county government; effect of change in form</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Whenever any county, city, town, political subdivision, or combination thereof is identified in an act of the General Assembly by reference to its proximity to a county that has adopted an optional form of government provided in Title 15.2, and that county changes its form of government, the act shall continue to apply to such county, city, town, political subdivision, or combination thereof and shall cease to apply on ly upon the subsequent enactment by the General Assembly of a measure in which such intent clearly is stated. History History. 1990, c. 253, § 1-13.35:1; 2005, c. 839.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-230"><akn:num>§ 1-230</akn:num><akn:heading>Person</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Person includes any individual, corporation, partnership, association, cooperative, li mited liability company, trust, joint venture, government, political subdivision, or any other legal or commercial entity and any successor, representative, agent, agency, or instrumentality thereof. History History. Code 1919, § 5; Code 1950, § 1-13; 1950, p. 22, § 1-13.1 9; 1988, c. 36; 2005, c. 839. Annotations Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 4B M.J. Corporations, § 6; 17 M.J. Statutes, § 60. CASE NOTES Editors note. The cases annotated below were decided under prior law. Corporations.  Corporations are included under the term persons as used in a statute, unless they are exempted by its terms or by the nature of the subject to which the statute relates. Miller's Ex'r v. Commonwealth, 68 Va. (27 Gratt.) 110, 1876 Va. LEXIS 9 (1876) (see Portsmouth Gas Co. v. Sanford, 97 Va. 124, 33 S.E. 516 (1899)). When the word person is used in a statute, corporations as well as natural persons are included for civil purposes. B &amp; O R.R. v. Gallahue's Adm'rs, 53 Va . (12 Gratt.) 655, 1855 Va. LEXIS 51 (1855) (see Sun Life Assurance Co. v. Bailey, 101 Va. 443, 44 S.E. 692 (1903)). The word person in a former statute relating to persons paying taxes on real estate was held to include corporations. Crafford v. Board of Supvrs. , 87 Va. 110, 12 S.E. 147, 1890 Va. LEXIS 99 (1890). In support of the rule that corporations are to be deemed and taken as persons when the circumstances in which they are placed are identical with those of natural persons, see Stribling v. Bank of Valley, 26 Va. (5 Rand.) 132, 1827 Va. LEXIS 9 (1827); Bank of United States, Inc. v. Merchants Bank, 40 Va. (1 Rob.) 573, 1843 Va. LEXIS 8 (1843); B &amp; O R.R. v. Gallahue's Adm'rs, 53 Va. (12 Gratt.) 655, 1855 Va. LEXIS 51 (1855). But it has been held that a city charter giving authority to impose a license tax upon persons engaged in certain enumerated callings, and upon any other pers on or employment, did not empower the city to impose such tax upon a railroad corporation, which is neither a person nor employment within the ordinary acceptation of these words. City of Lynchburg v. Norfolk &amp; W.R.R., 80 Va. 237, 1885 Va. LEXIS 61 ( 1885). Counties and cities may be included in the word person. Commonwealth v. Schmelz, 116 Va. 62, 81 S.E. 45, 1914 Va. LEXIS 8 (1914) (see Portsmouth Gas Co. v. Sanford, 97 Va. 124, 33 S.E. 516 (1899)). A city is a person whose rights may be prejudiced by a forgery. Hanbury v. Commonwealth, 203 Va. 182, 122 S.E.2d 911, 1961 Va. LEXIS 238 (1961). Municipal corporations have a dual identity, existing both as a body politic and a body corporate; in the latter identity, a municipal corporation may be a pe rson just as any corporation or other legal entity is a person. City of Va. Beach v. Flippen, 251 Va. 358, 467 S.E.2d 471, 1996 Va. LEXIS 25 (1996). Board of public welfare (now board of social services) held person aggrieved for appeal purposes.  See Board of Pub. Welfare v. Blackburn, 214 Va. 425, 201 S.E.2d 777, 1974 Va. LEXIS 152 (1974). Sanctions error where issue as to whether city was person undetermined.  Where district judge awarded sanctions to city since plaintiffs should have known that the city was incapable of forming the criminal intent necessary for liabili ty under the Virginia Conspiracy Act, where the Virginia Conspiracy Act itself does not clearly state whether cities can be subjected to liability, where the Virginia Supreme Court has not been confronted directly with whether a city is a person within t he meaning of the Virginia Conspiracy Act, and where a recent pronouncement of the Supreme Court in a Virginia Conspiracy Act case seemed to have left open the possibility that a city could be sued under that act, the district court abused its discretion in sanctioning plaintiffs since the court of appeals was unable to say that plaintiffs had absolutely no chance of success in bringing a Virginia Conspiracy Act claim against the city. Brubaker v. City of Richmond, 943 F.2d 1363, 1991 U.S. App. LEXIS 17931 (4th Cir. 1991). OPINIONS OF THE ATTORNEY GENERAL Registered limited liability partnership.  A registered limited liability partnership organized under the laws of the Commonwealth may serve as a trustee under a deed of trust covered by § 55-58.1. See opinion of Attorney General to The Honorable Gregory D. Habeeb, Member, House of Delegates, 11-131, (3/23/12).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-231"><akn:num>§ 1-231</akn:num><akn:heading>When person includes business trust and limited liability company</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Whenever the term person is defined to include both corporation and partnership, such term shall also include business trust and limited lia bility company. History History. 2002, c. 621, § 1-13.19:1; 2005, c. 839. Annotations Cross references. For the Virginia Business Trust Act, see § 13.1-1200 et seq. Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 12A M.J. Limited Liability Companies, § 3.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-232"><akn:num>§ 1-232</akn:num><akn:heading>Person under disability</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Person under disability includes a person less than 18 years of age. History History. 1972, cc. 824, 825, § 1-13.42; 2005, c. 839.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-233"><akn:num>§ 1-233</akn:num><akn:heading>Personal estate</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Personal estate includes chattels real and such other estate as, upon the death of the owner intestate, would devolve upon his personal representative. History History. Code 1919, § 5; Code 1950, § 1-13; 1950, p. 22, § 1-13.2 0; 2005, c. 839. Annotations CASE NOTES Bank stock is personal property. West v. City of Newport News, 104 Va. 21, 51 S.E. 206, 1905 Va. LEXIS 64 (1905) (decided under prior law).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-234"><akn:num>§ 1-234</akn:num><akn:heading>Personal representative</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Personal representative includes the executor of a will or the administrator of the es tate of a decedent, the administrator of such estate with the will annexed, the administrator of such estate unadministered by a former representative, whether there is a will or not, any person who is under the order of a circuit court to take into his possession the estate of a decedent for administration, and every other curator of a decedents estate, for or against whom suits may be brought for causes of action that accrued to or against the decedent. History History. Code 1919, § 5; Code 1950, § 1-13; 1950, p. 22, § 1-13.2 1; 1971, Ex. Sess., c. 49; 2005, c. 839. Annotations Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 8A M.J. Executors and Administrators, § 13. CASE NOTES The primary sense of the word representatives, when used in a bequest of persona l property, is the same as that of legal representatives or personal representatives. Each of them is equivalent to executors or administrators. But this primary sense of the word representatives may be controlled, where an intent ion is clearly indicated to employ it in a different sense. Brent v. Washington's Adm'rs, 59 Va. (18 Gratt.) 526, 1868 Va. LEXIS 24 (1868) (decided under prior law). An administrator with the will annexed  that is, an ancillary administratrix  is among those who can be a personal representative under this section. Higgins v. Washington Metro. Area Transit Auth., 507 F. Supp. 984, 1981 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 11943 (D.D.C. 1981) (decided under prior law). Standing.  Testators daughters did not have standing to bring the claims asserted because the testators son remained the personal representative of the testators estate, and he was the only party entitled to bring suit on behalf of the estate; the daughters claims relating to the rescission of inter vivos transfers were inherently on behalf of the estate as they would have belonged to the testator during his lifetime. Platt v. Griffith, 299 Va. 690, 858 S.E.2d 413, 2021 Va. LEXIS 59 (2021). Any claim for the rescission of a transaction between the decedent and a trustee belonged to the decedents estate as it would have belonged to the decedent, a nd, upon the decedents death, any viable claim relating to the sale of the decedents minority interest in a limited liability company passed to the decedents estate and only may have been pursued by the estates personal representative. Th us, the remainder beneficiaries, neither of whom was the personal representative of the decedents estate, lacked standing to bring such a claim. Kittrell v. Fowler, 301 Va. 25, 870 S.E.2d 210, 2022 Va. LEXIS 18 (2022). CIRCUIT COURT OPINIONS Administrator as personal re presentative.  Consultants claim that a wrongful death suit was improperly filed by an administratrix rather than a personal representative as required by § 8.01-50 was r ejected as the definition of personal representative in § 1-234 included an administrator. Rodriguez v. N. Va. Elec. Coop., 79 Va. Cir. 266, 2009 Va. Cir. LEXIS 236 (Loudoun County Sept. 14, 2009).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-235"><akn:num>§ 1-235</akn:num><akn:heading>Population; inhabitants</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Population or inhabitants means with reference to any county, city, town, political subdivision of the Commonwealth or any combination thereof, the natural persons in such c ounty, city, town, political subdivision or combination as shown by the unadjusted United States decennial census last preceding the time at which any provision dependent upon population is being applied or the time as of which it is being construed. Whe re two or more political subdivisions are consolidated, the population of the consolidated county or city or other political subdivision shall be the combined population of the consolidating subdivisions, under the last preceding unadjusted United States decennial census. History History. 1942, p. 668; Michie Code 1942, § 5a; Code 1950, § 1-13; 19 50, p. 23, § 1-13.22; 1954, c. 295, § 1-13.10:1; 1958, c. 330; 1966, c. 78; 2005, c. 839. Annotations Cross references. For effect of population changes on statutes containing population classifications, see § 1-236. See Va. Const., Art. VII, § 1. CIRCUIT COURT OPINIONS Relevant evidence.  A census report was properly admitted, pursuant to §§ 1-13.22 and 1-13.35 [now § 1-236], as evidence to establish that a city was large enough to use las er speed devices. Commonwealth v. Fagin, 61 Va. Cir. 428, 2003 Va. Cir. LEXIS 225 (Charlottesville Apr. 4, 2003) (decided under prior law). OPINIONS OF THE ATTORNEY GENERAL Inmate population.  The General Assembly has not authorized local governing bodies to exclude out-of-state prisoners housed in a state adult correctional facility from the locality s population for the purposes of the decennial reapportionment if the total population of inmates housed at the facility does not exceed twelve percent of the localitys population pursuant to subsection C of § 24.2-304.1. See opinion of Attorn ey General to J. Vaden Hunt, Esquire, County Attorney, Pittsylvania County, 11-011, 2011 Va. AG LEXIS 15 (3/1/11).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-236"><akn:num>§ 1-236</akn:num><akn:heading>Population classifications</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Any act of the General Assembly with a population classification applicable to any county, city, town, or subdivision of the Commonwealth or any combination thereof sha ll continue to apply to any such body notwithstanding any subsequent change in population and shall apply to any county, city, town, or political subdivision of the Commonwealth or any combination thereof subsequently falling within such population class ification. The provisions of this section shall not apply to, or limit, the distribution of any state funds, grants-in-aid, or other allocation from the state treasury, to any county, city, town, or other political subdivision of the Commonwealth. History History. 1950, pp. 464, 465, §§ 1-13.35, 1-13.36; 1960, cc. 251, 307 ; 1962, c. 315; 1964, c. 404; 1966, c. 78; 2005, c. 839. Annotations CIRCUIT COURT OPINIONS Relevant evidence.  A census report was properly admitted, pursuant to §§ 1-13.22 and 1-13.35 [now §§ 1-235 and 1-236], as evidence to establish that a city was large eno ugh to use laser speed devices. Commonwealth v. Fagin, 61 Va. Cir. 428, 2003 Va. Cir. LEXIS 225 (Charlottesville Apr. 4, 2003) (decided under prior law).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-237"><akn:num>§ 1-237</akn:num><akn:heading>Process</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Process includes subpoenas, the summons and complaint in a civil action, and process i n statutory actions. History History. 1954, c. 543, § 1-13.23:1; 1986, c. 155; 2005, cc. 681, 839. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2005, c. 681, effective January 1, 2006, amended former § 1-13.23:1, from which this section is derived. Pursuant to § 30-152 and Acts 2005, c. 839, c l. 5, the 2005 amendment by c. 681 has been given effect in this section as set out above. The phrase the summons and complaint in a civil action was substituted for in chancery, notices to commence actions at law.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-238"><akn:num>§ 1-238</akn:num><akn:heading>Reenacted</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Reenacted, when used in the title or enactment of a bill or act of the General Assembl y, means that the changes enacted to a section of the Code of Virginia or an act of the General Assembly are in addition to the existing substantive provisions in that section or act, and are effective prospectively unless the bill expressly provides tha t such changes are effective retroactively on a specified date. The provisions of this section are declaratory of existing public policy and law. History History. 2001, c. 720, § 1-13.39:3; 2005, c. 839. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2001, c. 720, cl. 2 provides: That the provisions of this act are intended to reverse the ruling in Rubio v. Rubio, 33 Va. App. 74, 531 S.E. 2nd 612 (2000). CASE NOTES Declaratory of existing law.  Amendments to the law surrounding the Virginia Birth-Related Neurological Injury Compensation Act were effective prospectively, as the phrase declaratory of e xisting law did not state retroactive intent and the language of the amended laws did not support retroactivity. Berner v. Mills, 265 Va. 408, 579 S.E.2d 159, 2003 Va. LEXIS 52 (2003) (decided under prior law). Retrospective applicatio n of reenacted laws.  Trial court properly denied defendants motion to be sentenced under a version of § 18.2-308.4 that became effective after the crime was committed; the lang uage of the statute did not clearly allow for retroactive application of the amendment, and the statute also could not be applied retroactively pursuant to this section. Taylor v. Commonwealth, 44 Va. App. 179, 604 S.E.2d 103, 2004 Va. App. LEXIS 512 (20 04) (decided under prior law). CIRCUIT COURT OPINIONS Applicability of amendments.  Although defendants alleged offense took place before statutory amendment went into effect, and defendant was not arrested or charged until the indictment aft er the enactment of the amended statute, the amended version of the statute applied in defendants case because the proceedings were governed by the procedural laws in effect at the time of the proceeding and the amendments to the statute were procedu ral and not substantive. Commonwealth v. Weatherholtz, 106 Va. Cir. 106, 2020 Va. Cir. LEXIS 202 (Frederick County Oct. 2, 2020). No retroactive application.  Subsection P of § 46.2-1052 does not apply retroactively also because § 1-239 states that the proceedings shall conform to laws in force at the time of suc h proceedings and that such new provision may, with the consent of the party affected, be applied; to require compliance with a provision not yet law defies common sense, plus the Commonwealth did not consent in this case. Commonwealth v. Tarpley, 108 Va . Cir. 348, 2021 Va. Cir. LEXIS 172 (Newport News Aug. 10, 2021). Regardless of whether a statutory prohibition against stopping vehicles for defective exhaust was substantive, procedural, or a mixture of both for purposes of a retroactivity analysis, drug evidence from a stop of defendants vehicle for defective exhaust was admissible because the stop occurred before the effective date of the prohibition and thus did not violate it. Commonwealth v. Southerly, 2021 Va. Cir. LEXIS 528 (Page County Oct. 12, 2021). Procedural changes.  Section 1-238 lays out the general principles against retroactive application of statutes, which do not apply when changes are procedural, as § 1-239 allows fo r their retroactive application; statutory change that forbid police officers from stopping vehicles solely for violation of certain statutes did not alter § 46.2-1014.1 Bs punishment and instead created an evidentiary rule. Court excluded evidenc e obtained during traffic stop due to the statutory change that became effective after the stop occurred. Commonwealth v. Hardy, 2021 Va. Cir. LEXIS 149 (Roanoke County July 1, 2021).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-239"><akn:num>§ 1-239</akn:num><akn:heading>Repeal not to affect liabilities; mitigation of punishment</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text No new act of the General Assembly shall be construed to repeal a former law, as to any offense committed against the former law, or as to any act done, any penalty, fo rfeiture, or punishment incurred, or any right accrued, or claim arising under the former law, or in any way whatever to affect any such offense or act so committed or done, or any penalty, forfeiture, or punishment so incurred, or any right accrued, or claim arising before the new act of the General Assembly takes effect; except that the proceedings thereafter held shall conform, so far as practicable, to the laws in force at the time of such proceedings; and if any penalty, forfeiture, or punishment b e mitigated by any provision of the new act of the General Assembly, such provision may, with the consent of the party affected, be applied to any judgment pronounced after the new act of the General Assembly takes effect. History History. Code 1919, § 6, § 1-16; 2005, c. 839. Annotations Cross references. As to proceedings pending when Code takes effect, see §§ 1-4, 8.01-1. Law Review. For survey of Virginia law on criminal law and procedure for the year 2007-2008, see 43 U. Rich. L. Rev. 149 (2008). Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 5B M.J. Criminal Procedure, §§ 4, 84; 9B M.J. Housing, § 1; 17 M.J. Statutes, §§ 73, 91, 96, 105; 18 M.J. Taxation, § 12. CASE NOTES Editors note. Some of the cases annotated below were decided under prior law. General comment.  This section or a predecessor has been the law of Virginia for more than 100 years and has long been held to apply to civil as well as criminal cases. Pursuant to it, both substantive and vested rights are protected from retroactive application of statutes. Garraghty v. Virginia, Dep't of Cors., 52 F.3d 1274, 1995 U.S. App. LEXIS 10478 (4th Cir. 1995). Under the former law the rule was different in Virginia. See Scutt v. Commonwealth, 4 Va . (2 Va. Cas.) 54 (1817); Commonwealth v. Leftwich, 26 Va. (5 Rand.) 657, 1827 Va. LEXIS 27 (1827); Pitman v. Commonwealth, 41 Va. (2 Rob.) 800, 1843 Va. LEXIS 59 (1843). When rights and claims are subject to protection of due process.  It is only when a right has accrued or a claim has arisen that it is subject to the protection of the due process clause. Hess v. Snyder Hunt Corp., 240 Va. 49, 3 92 S.E.2d 817, 6 Va. Law Rep. 2565, 1990 Va. LEXIS 104 (1990). Application to both crimin al and civil cases.  A former statute corresponding to this section was held to apply to forfeitures in civil as well as criminal cases. White's Adm'x v. Freeman, 79 Va. 597, 1884 Va. LEXIS 118 (1884) (citing Mosby v. St. Louis Mut. Ins. Co., 72 Va. (31 Gratt.) 629 (1879)). Substantive rights and vested rights protected from retroactive application of statutes.  Substantive rights, as well as vested rights, are included within those interests protected from retroactive application of statutes. City of Norf olk v. Kohler, 234 Va. 341, 362 S.E.2d 894, 4 Va. Law Rep. 1165, 1987 Va. LEXIS 263 (1987); Brushy Ridge Coal Co. v. Blevins, 6 Va. App. 73, 367 S.E.2d 204, 4 Va. Law Rep. 2325, 1988 Va. App. LEXIS 28 (1988). After obtaining a judgment relieving appellant of quarterly reregistration requirements under former § 19.2-298.4 for sex offenders, appellant was not entitled to enjoin the reposting of his information on a sex offender internet registry after the 2006 amendment to § 9.1-909 as appellant did not have an accrued right under § 1-239 affected by the statutes retroactive application as the removal remed y under § 9.1-909 was self-executing and could be altered at will by the legislature. Morency v. Commonwealth, 274 Va. 569, 649 S.E.2d 682, 2007 Va. LEXIS 114 (2007), cert. denied, 552 U.S. 1286, 128 S. Ct. 1717, 170 L. Ed. 2d 524, 2008 U.S. L EXIS 2757 (2008). When § 1-219.1 prevented a housing and redevelopment authority from acquiring unblighted property within a blighted redevelopment area by eminent domain, the s tatute did not impair the authoritys rights to the property in violation of § 1-239 because the authority held no rights to the property when § 1-219.1 terminated the authoritys ability to acquire the unblighted property by eminent domain, so the statute affected no claim arising before the statute took effect. PKO Ventures, LLC v. Norfolk Redevelopment &amp; Hous. Auth., 286 Va. 174, 747 S.E.2d 826, 2013 Va. LEXIS 100 (2013). Prospective constructi on approved by section.  The general principle that statutes should be given a prospective rather than a retrospective construction has been given statutory approval by this section. Ferg uson v. Ferguson, 169 Va. 77, 192 S.E. 774, 1937 Va. LEXIS 158 (1937). New laws g enerally presumed prospective in operation.  New laws, except as to matters of remedy which may be applied retrospectively, are usually presumed to be prospective and not retrospective in their operation. Pa ul v. Paul, 214 Va. 651, 203 S.E.2d 123, 1974 Va. LEXIS 193 (1974). Consistent with § 64.1-62, requiring that wills be construed as if the testator died immediately before death, unless the will showed a contrary intent, inter vivos trusts were to be construed according to the law in effect at the time the trust was executed, absent language showing a contrary intent, as such a rule recognized that the interests of trust beneficiaries accrued when the trust was executed and pr otected those interests, and such a rule was compelled by § 1-16 [a former version of this section], mandating that no new law should be construed in any way whatever to affect any right accrued, or claim arising before the new law took effect. McGehe e v. Edwards, 268 Va. 15, 268 Va. 23, 597 S.E.2d 99, 2004 Va. LEXIS 96 (2004). Trial court did not err in convicting and sentencing defendant under former Va. Code Ann. § 18.2-104 for petit larceny, third offense, committed on July 5, 202 0, and indicted on March 2, 2021, because the General Assemblys repeal of § 18.2-104 was a new act of the General Assembly that became effective July 1, 2021, and the repeal contained no language stating that it would apply retroactively to all pr osecutions still pending under § 18.2-104. Compton v. Commonwealth, 2023 Va. App. LEXIS 14 (Va. Ct. App. Jan. 10, 2023). Retroactive application of law did not breach plea agreement.  As § 9.1-902s reclassification of carnal knowledge of a minor as a sexually violent offense, which retroactively subjected a convicted sex offender to heightened registration requirements, was an exercise of the states regulatory police power, the Commonwealths retroactive enforcement of those requirements did not breach its plea agreement with the offender or violate Va. Const. art. I, § 11 and § 1-239. Smith v. Commonwealth, 286 Va. 52, 743 S.E.2d 146, 2013 Va. LEXIS 76 (2013). What procedural provisions control.  The procedural provisions of the statute in effect on the date of trial control the conduct of trial insofar as practicable. Smith v. Commonwealth, 219 Va. 455, 2 48 S.E.2d 135, 1978 Va. LEXIS 203 (1978), cert. denied, 441 U.S. 967, 99 S. Ct. 2419, 60 L. Ed. 2d 1074 (1979). The procedural provisions of the statute in effect on the date of trial control the conduct of trial insofar as practicable. Riley v. Commonwealth, 21 Va. App. 33 0, 464 S.E.2d 508, 1995 Va. App. LEXIS 896 (1995). Sentencing discretion with trial c ourt.  Where statute changed the status of the offense charged from a felony to a misdemeanor after entry of the defendants guilty plea but prior to his sentencing a nd the Commonwealth agreed to pursue misdemeanor sentencing, it was discretionary with the trial court, and not with the Commonwealth, whether misdemeanor or felony punishment should be imposed. Awkard v. Commonwealth, 21 Va. App. 40, 461 S.E.2d 419, 12 Va. Law Rep. 140, 1995 Va. App. LEXIS 676 (1995). Instances of prospective operation.  A deposition of a party, to be read in a pending cause at law, commenced before the passage of the statute which required that parties should testify, ore tenus, but which was not completed until that law went into effect, is inadmissible as evidence. Crawford v. Halsted &amp; Putnam, 61 Va. (20 Gratt.) 211, 1871 Va. LEXIS 2 (1871). A statute which amended the former law as to payment of decedents debts by inserting in the third class debts of trustee for persons under disabilities,  was only prospective in its operation and did not authorize the placing of a debt as trustee in the third class, though the estate was not distributed until the act went into operation. Price's Ex'r v. Harrison's Ex'r, 72 Va. (31 Gratt.) 114, 1878 V a. LEXIS 32 (1878). Where a provision of a curative act amending a former law with reference to the assessment of land for taxes, if construed retrospectively, would deprive a citize n of the opportunity to be heard as to the correctness and justice of an assessment made under the original act, which opportunity was afforded by the original act, such provision will, if possible, be construed prospectively only, and the remedy given u nder the original act as to acts done prior to the passage of the curative act will be preserved. Whitlock v. Hawkins, 105 Va. 242, 53 S.E. 401, 1906 Va. LEXIS 31 (1906). Whether procedural or substantive, a new code section making inadmissible any evidence found pursuant to a search based solely on the odor of marijuana could not be applied retroactively; there was no need to determine whether this was a procedural remedy because its application to a search that was not a violation at the time of the search would not meet the requirement that proceedings conform, so far as practi cable, to the laws in force at the time. Loeper v. Commonwealth, 2023 Va. App. LEXIS 44 (Va. Ct. App. Jan. 24, 2023). Subdivisio n ordinance without grandfather clause.  Local government body could not, after amending subdivision ordinance without making any provision to grandfather pending applications, lawfully invoke un written practice of applying prior la...</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-240"><akn:num>§ 1-240</akn:num><akn:heading>Repeal not to revive former act</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text When an act of the General Assembly that has repealed another act shall itself be repealed, the previous act shall not be revived without express words to that effect, unless the act repealing it be passed during the same session. History History. Code 1919, § 7, § 1-17; 2005, c. 839. Annotations CASE NOTES This section applies to statutes and not to the common law. For cases under prior law, s ee Booth v. Commonwealth, 57 Va. (16 Gratt.) 519, 1861 Va. LEXIS 10 (1861); Insurance Co. v. Barley's Adm'r, 57 Va. (16 Gratt.) 363, 1863 Va. LEXIS 2 (1863). Omitted portions annulled.  When a statute is revised, or one act framed from another, and some parts are omitted, the omitted parts are not revived by construction, but are annulled. Combin ed Saw &amp; Planer Co. v. Flournoy, 88 Va. 1029, 14 S.E. 976, 1892 Va. LEXIS 68 (1892) (decided under prior law). § 1-240.1. Rights of parents. Text A parent has a fundamental right to make decisions concerning the upbringing, education, and care of the parents child. History History. 2013, cc. 668, 678. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2013, cc. 668 and 678, cl. 2 provides: That it is the expressed intent of the General Assembly that this act codify the opinion of the Supreme Court of V irginia in L.F. v. Breit, issued on January 10, 2013, as it relates to parental rights. CASE NOTES Right to litigate paternity issue.  Trial court erred in dismissing a petition to determine parentage filed by the childs biological father, as subdivision A 3 of § 20-158 and subsection D of § 32.1-257 did bar an unmarried, biological father from establishing legal parentage of his child conceived through assisted conception, pursuant to a voluntary written agreement as authorized by subdivision B 2 of § 20-49.1.L.F. v. Breit, 285 Va. 163, 736 S.E.2d 711, 2013 Va. LEXIS 4 (2013).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-241"><akn:num>§ 1-241</akn:num><akn:heading>Seal</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Seal, when required to be affixed by any court or public office to any paper, includes an impression or print of such official seal made upon the paper. When th e seal of any natural person is required, it shall be sufficient for the person to place a mark intended as a seal. History History. Code 1919, § 5; Code 1950, § 1-13; 1950, p. 23, § 1-13.2 5; 1975, c. 500; 2005, c. 839. Annotations Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 16 M.J. Seals and Sealed Instruments, § 1.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-242"><akn:num>§ 1-242</akn:num><akn:heading>Senate Committee on Privileges and Elections</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Senate Committee on Privileges and Elections, whenever the Committee is referred to as an appointing authority, means the Senate Committee designated under the Rules of the Senate to make Senate appointments to study committees and commissions. History History. 2004, c. 709, § 1-13.25:1; 2005, c. 839.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-243"><akn:num>§ 1-243</akn:num><akn:heading>Severability</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The provisions of acts of the General Assembly or the application thereof to any person or circumstances that are held invalid shall not affect the validity of other ac ts, provisions, or applications that can be given effect without the invalid provisions or applications. The provisions of all acts, except for the title of the act, are severable unless (i) the act specifically provides that its provisions are not sever able; or (ii) it is apparent that two or more acts or provisions must operate in accord with one another. History History. 1986, c. 239, § 1-17.1; 1987, c. 56; 2005, c. 839. Annotations Law Review. For 2003/2004 survey of criminal law and procedure, see 39 U. Rich. L. Rev. 133 (2004). Editors note. Acts 2015, c. 709, cl. 3 provides: That the General Assembly has determined that all severability clauses removed from the Code of Virginia pursuant to this a ct are removed because the Code sections that they purport to make severable are already severable pursuant to § 1-243 of the Code of Virginia and shall continue to be severable after the passage of this act. CASE NOTES The test of severability in the commonwealth of Virginia is whether the legislature woul d be satisfied with what remains after the invalid part has been eliminated. Sons of Confederate Veterans, Inc. v. Holcomb, 129 F. Supp. 2d 941, 2001 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 538 (W.D. Va. 2001), aff'd, 288 F.3d 610, 2002 U.S. App. LEXIS 7864 (4th Cir. 2002), va cated, No. 7:99-cv-00530, 2015 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 103603 (W.D. Va. Aug. 6, 2015) (decided under prior law). Provision is not inextricably intertwined with the rest of the statute.  The fact that the prima facie evidence provision is not inextricably intertwined with the rest of the statute is illustrated by the fact that the cross burning st atute, now codified at § 18.2-423, existed for 16 years, from 1952 to 1968, without the prima facie evidence provision. Elliott v. Commonwealth, 267 Va. 464, 593 S.E.2d 263, 2004 Va. LEXIS 41 (2004) (decided under prior law). The General Assembly impermissibly delegated taxing power to the local area transportation authority through enactment of Acts 2007, c. 896, because it did not ha ve the constitutional power to delegate taxing authority to an unelected political subdivision, pursuant to Va. Const., Art. I, § 6. However, the parts of the enactment that were unconstitutional could be severed from the rest of the enactment because the enactments provisions did not have to operate with regard to each other and enactment did not state that its provisions could not be severed. Marshall v. N. Va. Transp. Auth., 275 Va. 419, 657 S.E.2d 71, 2008 Va. LEXIS 25 (2008). Ordinance held not severable.  Where ordinances restrictions on commercial and noncommercial speech were inextricably intertwined, severability provision within the ordinance could not save any part, section, or clause of the ordinance as it applied to billboards where its restrictions on noncommercial speech were found unconstitutional. Adams Outdoor Adv. v. City of Newport News, 236 Va. 370, 373 S.E.2d 917, 5 Va. Law Rep. 981, 1988 Va. L EXIS 137 (1988) (decided under prior law). Severa bility of allegedly unconstitutional provision.  Even if a provision of subdivision A 6 of § 56-585.1 were found to violate the dormant Commerce Clause, U.S. Const., Art. I, § 8, cl. 3, severance of the al legedly impermissible language, utilizes Virginia coal, would save subdivision A 6 from invalidation. Appalachian Voices v. State Corp. Comm'n, 277 Va. 509, 675 S.E.2d 458, 2009 Va. LEXIS 61 (2009).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-244"><akn:num>§ 1-244</akn:num><akn:heading>Short title citations</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Whenever a subtitle, chapter, or article does not have a section or provision establishing or authorizing a short title citation for such subtitle, chapter or article, such subtitle, chapter or article may be cited by its caption. The caption is that word or group of words appearing directly below the numerical designation given the subtitle, chapter or article. Captions are intended as mere catchwords to indicate the contents of the subtitles, chapters, and articles and do not constitute part of the act of the General Assembly. History History. 1993, c. 308, § 1-13.9:1; 2005, c. 839.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-245"><akn:num>§ 1-245</akn:num><akn:heading>State</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text State, when applied to a part of the United States, includes any of the 50 states, the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, Guam, the Northern Mariana Islands, and the United States Virgin Islands. History History. Code 1919, § 5; Code 1950, § 1-13; 1950, p. 23, § 1-13.2 6; 1971, Ex. Sess., c. 49; 2005, c. 839.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-246"><akn:num>§ 1-246</akn:num><akn:heading>Stricken language or italics</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Stricken language for deletions and italics for additions or changes may be used in legislative drafts, printed bills, enrolled bills, and printed Acts of Assembly, in an attempt to call attention to amendments to existing acts of the General Assembly. The stricken language and italics shall not be construed as evidence of amendments to acts of the General Assembly. History History. 1950, p. 24, § 1-13.34; 1986, c. 155; 2005, c. 839.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-247"><akn:num>§ 1-247</akn:num><akn:heading>Summaries of legislation</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Any legislative summary associated with a bill, joint resolution or resolution, including any summary appearing on the face of such legislation, shall not constitute a part of the legislation considered, agreed to, or enacted, and shall not be used to indicate or infer legislative intent. History History. 1997, c. 375, § 30-19.03:2; 2005, c. 839.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-248"><akn:num>§ 1-248</akn:num><akn:heading>Supremacy of federal and state law</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Constitution and laws of the United States and of the Commonwealth shall be supreme. Any ordinance, resolution, bylaw, rule, regulation, or order of any governing b ody or any corporation, board, or number of persons shall not be inconsistent with the Constitution and laws of the United States or of the Commonwealth. History History. Code 1919, § 5; Code 1950, § 1-13; 1950, p. 22, § 1-13.1 7; 2005, c. 839. Annotations Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 13B M.J. Municipal Corporations, §§ 60, 61. CASE NOTES Editors note. Some of the cases annotated below were decided under prior law. An ordinance may not conflict with state law. Board of Supvrs. v. Pumphrey, 221 Va. 205, 269 S.E.2d 361, 1980 Va. LEXIS 236 (1980). It is, of course, fundamental that local ordinances must conform to and not be in conflict with the public policy of the state as embodied in its statutes. Blanto n v. Amelia County, 261 Va. 55, 540 S.E.2d 869, 2001 Va. LEXIS 16 (2001). Municipal ordinances must be consistent with the general law and policy of the State. Na tional Linen Serv. Corp. v. City of Norfolk, 196 Va. 277, 83 S.E.2d 401, 1954 Va. LEXIS 221 (1954) (see Allen v. City of Norfolk, 196 Va. 177, 83 S.E.2d 397 (1954)). The provision of the Norfolk City Code making possession of certain indicia of a lottery prima facie evidence of guilt was contrary to state policy and void becau se inconsistent with former § 18.1-340, in that it prescribed a different method of proof, imposing on accused a burden not contemplated by the legislature. Allen v. City of Norfolk, 196 Va. 177, 83 S.E.2d 397, 1954 Va. LEXIS 211 (1954) (see Allen v. City of Norfolk, 195 Va. 844, 80 S.E.2d 605, modified, 196 Va. 177, 83 S.E.2d 397 (1954)). Under § 15.2-1429, no punishment for violation of an ordinance may exceed the penalties prescribed by general law for like offenses; Virginia Beach, Va., Code § 23-38, which punished destruction of property by fine of up to $2,500 and up to 12 months in jail, manifested a conflict with state law because the penalty that attached exceeded the penalty under the state code destruction of property statute, § 18.2-137, a violation of which was punishable only by a fine not exceeding $500, and defendants convictions for violations of Virginia Beach, Va., Code § 23-38 were reversed. Strout v. City of Va. Beach, 43 Va. App. 99, 596 S.E.2d 529, 2004 Va. A pp. LEXIS 240 (2004). But may enlarge thereon.  The fact that an ordinance enlarges upon statutory provisions does not necessarily create an inconsistency therewith, since some state statutes are not sufficient ly comprehensive to cover local exigencies. Allen v. City of Norfolk, 196 Va. 177, 83 S.E.2d 397, 1954 Va. LEXIS 211 (1954). The mere fact that the State, in the exercise of the police power, has made certain regulations does not prohibit a municipality from exacting additional requirem ents, so long as there is no conflict. King v. County of Arlington, 195 Va. 1084, 81 S.E.2d 587, 1954 Va. LEXIS 187 (1954). The fact that an ordinance enlarges upon the provisions of a statute by requiring more than the statute requires creates no conflict therewith, unless the statute limits the requirement for all cases to its own prescription. Blanton v. Amelia County, 261 Va. 55, 540 S.E.2d 869, 2001 Va. LEXIS 16 (2001). Where both an ordinance and a statute are prohibitory and the only difference between them is that the ordinance goes further in its prohibition, but not counter to the prohibition under the statute, and the municipality does not attempt to authorize by the ordinance what the legislature has forbidden or forbid what the legislature has expressly licensed, authorized, or required, there is nothing contradictory be tween the provisions of the statute and the ordinance because of which they cannot coexist and be effective. Blanton v. Amelia County, 261 Va. 55, 540 S.E.2d 869, 2001 Va. LEXIS 16 (2001). And provide greater penalty than statute.  The fact that the penalty for the violation of an ordinance prohibiting the use of common towels is greater than that provided for in the statute on the subject d oes not invalidate the ordinance. National Linen Serv. Corp. v. City of Norfolk, 196 Va. 277, 83 S.E.2d 401, 1954 Va. LEXIS 221 (1954). Ordinance held not invalid because it enlarged on the statute by prescribing a heavier penalty for the second offense. Allen v. City of Norfolk, 196 Va. 177, 83 S .E.2d 397, 1954 Va. LEXIS 211 (1954). If both the statute and ordinance can stand together, courts are obliged to harmonize them, rather than nullifying the ordinance. Board of Supvrs. v. Pumphrey, 221 Va. 205, 269 S.E.2d 361, 1980 Va. LEXIS 236 (1980); Granny's Cottage Inc. v. Town of Occoquan, 3 Va. App. 577, 352 S.E.2d 10, 3 Va. Law Rep. 1583, 1987 Va. App. LEXIS 1 42 (1987). There can be no conflict between a statute and an ordinance where there is no statute de aling with the same subject matter. Kisley v. City of Falls Church, 212 Va. 693, 187 S.E.2d 168, 1972 Va. LEXIS 242 (1972). An ord inance may forbid an act not prohibited by state law.  A local legislative body, in the exercise of its police powers, may forbid the doing of an act where state legislation is silent on the subject. Kisley v. City of Falls Church, 212 Va. 693, 187 S.E.2d 168, 1972 Va. LEXIS 242 (1972). An ordinance may prohibit an act upon which state law is silent or proscribe conduct already proscribed by state law where the ordinance is not inconsistent with state law. Board of Supvrs. v. Pumphrey, 221 Va. 205, 269 S.E.2d 361, 1980 Va. LEXIS 236 (1980); Granny's Cottage Inc. v. Town of Occoquan, 3 Va. App. 577, 352 S.E.2d 10, 3 Va. Law Rep. 1583, 1987 Va. App. LEXIS 142 (1987). Powers of condominium owners limited.  While the Condominium Act, § 55-79.39 et seq., is designed to and does permit the exercise of wide powers by an association of unit owners, these powers are li mited by general law and the Act itself. Unit Owners Ass'n of Buildamerica-1 v. Gillman, 223 Va. 752, 292 S.E.2d 378, 1982 Va. LEXIS 263 (1982). Public nudity ordinances.  State laws do not prevent a local governing body, under its police power, from enacting public nudity ordinances not inconsistent with the state law prohibiting c onduct which the local governing body reasonably deems to be contrary to the morals, health, safety and general welfare of the community. Wayside Restaurant, Inc. v. City of Virginia Beach, 215 Va. 231, 208 S.E.2d 51, 1974 Va. LEXIS 264 (1974). County ordinance prohibiting the keeping of a dog addicted to attacking human beings was held valid and not in conflict with the state law which prohibits the keeping of a dog addicted to attacking livestock and poultry. King v. County of Arlington, 195 Va. 1084, 81 S.E.2d 587, 1954 Va. LEXIS 187 (1954). Statute governing use of biosolids.  The general assembly, by its enactment former § 32.1-164.5 [see now § 62.1-44.19:3 et seq.], has expressly authorized the land application of biosolids cond itioned upon the issuance of a permit and a countys ordinances were inconsistent with that section and invalid because the ordinances forbid certain plaintiffs from using biosolids on their farmland even though those plaintiffs had obtained licenses to use biosolids pursuant to the statutory and regulatory scheme established by the general assembly. Blanton v. Amelia County, 261 Va. 55, 540 S.E.2d 869, 2001 Va. LEXIS 16 (2001). An ordinance punishing forgery of city cigarette tax stamp was a nullity. This was not a case where a specific statute takes precedence over a general statute relating to the same offense, but a case where a general state statute (former § 18.1-96) controlled as against a later city ordinance in conflict with it. Hanbury v. Commonwealth, 203 Va. 182, 122 S.E.2d 911, 1961 Va. LEXIS 238 (1961). CIRCUIT COURT OPINIONS Public expenditure of funds.  Trial court found that the taxpayers had standing to bring their claims against the town and county, as the taxpayers claimed that the town and county were violat ing state, federal, and local laws by creating and operating with public funds a site for temporary day workers involving some people who entered and were in the United States illegally. Karunakarum v. Town of Herndon, 70 Va. Cir. 208, 2006 Va. Cir. LEXI S 33 (Fairfax County Feb. 10, 2006). State health commissioners issuance of certificate did not depr ive county of ability to make land use decisions.  That the Virginia State Heath Commissioner issued a hospital owner a certificate of public need to build an acute care hospital did not prevent a county board of supervisors from denying the owners application to build it in a specific location. Pursuant to former § 1-13.17, the board could exercise its authority to make land use decisions without undermining the Commissioners authority to evaluate hea lth needs and to authorize the construction of health care facilities where needed. N. Va. Cmty. Hosp., L.L.C. v. Loudoun County Bd. of Supervisors, 70 Va. Cir. 283, 2006 Va. Cir. LEXIS 168 (Loudoun County Mar. 9, 2006). Tattooing ban.  City ordinances total ban on tattooing violated § 1-248, as it conflicted with Virginias policy of restricting but not banning tattooing, as expressed in §§ 15.2-912 and 18.2-371.3. Thus, the citys demurrer to petitioners claim that the ordinance was inconsistent with state law was denied. Blue Horseshoe Tattoo, V, Ltd. v. City of Norfolk, 72 Va. Cir. 388, 2007 Va. Cir. LEXIS 151 (Norfolk Jan. 17, 2007). City code not preempted by statute.  Chesapeake, Va., City Code § 62-88(7)(b) was not preempted by subsection C because, when read in context, subsection C was, in essence, a savings provision and did not preempt the city from regulating a power companys electric power plant on the basis that it was permitted; the General Assembly has not expressly preempted the field of waste management. Va. Elec. &amp; Power Co. v. City of Chesapeake, 95 Va. Ci r. 106, 2017 Va. Cir. LEXIS 7 (Chesa...</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-249"><akn:num>§ 1-249</akn:num><akn:heading>Supreme Court</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Supreme Court means the Supreme Court of Virginia. History History. 1975, c. 36, § 1-13.27:2; 2005, c. 839.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-250"><akn:num>§ 1-250</akn:num><akn:heading>Swear; sworn</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Swear or sworn means affirm or affirmed. History History. Code 1919, § 5; Code 1950, § 1-13; 1950, p. 23, § 1-13.2 8; 2005, c. 839.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-251"><akn:num>§ 1-251</akn:num><akn:heading>Systems of state highways</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Systems of state highways means all systems of highways within the Commonwealth over w hich the Commonwealth Transportation Board exercises jurisdiction and control. In context, such words shall apply to the extent, but only to the extent, that the Commonwealth Transportation Board exercises such jurisdiction and control. History History. 1970, c. 136, § 1-13.40; 2005, c. 839.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-252"><akn:num>§ 1-252</akn:num><akn:heading>Tier-city</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Tier-city means an incorporated community within a consolidated county that (i) has wi thin defined boundaries a population of 5,000 or more, (ii) has been designated as a tier-city by the General Assembly, and (iii) has both the powers of a town and such additional powers as may be granted tier-cities by the General Assembly. All referenc es in this Code and the acts of the General Assembly to towns shall be deemed references to tier-cities, except to the extent tier-cities may be specifically excluded or where the context requires otherwise. History History. 1984, c. 695, §§ 1-13.28:1, 1-13.28:2; 1989, c. 493; 2005, c. 839.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-253"><akn:num>§ 1-253</akn:num><akn:heading>Time zone</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The United States Eastern Standard Time shall be in effect in all parts of the Commonwealth except during the period when the United States Eastern Daylight Time shall be in effect as provided by federal law. This section shall not be construed to be in contravention of federal law, or duly authorized orders of the United States Secretary of Transportation with respect to the time zones of the United States and the app lication of standard time to interstate commerce and other matters within such zones. In all laws, statutes, orders, decrees, rules and regulations relating to the time of performance of any act by any officer or agency of the Commonwealth, or any politi cal subdivision thereof, or relating to the time in which any rights shall accrue or determine, or within which any act shall or shall not be performed by any person subject to the jurisdiction of the Commonwealth, and in all public schools, institutions of the Commonwealth or its political subdivisions, and contracts or choses in action made or to be performed in the Commonwealth, it shall be understood and intended that the time applicable thereto or referred to or implied therein shall be the United States Eastern Standard Time, or the United States Eastern Daylight Time, when and during such is in effect. History History. 1946, p. 103; Michie Suppl. 1946, § 5b; 1952, c. 637, § 1-1 5; 1962, c. 617; 1964, c. 646; 1966, c. 581; 1988, c. 177; 2005, c. 839. Annotations Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 18 M.J. Time, § 2.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-254"><akn:num>§ 1-254</akn:num><akn:heading>Town</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Town means any existing town or an incorporated community within one or more counties which became a town before noon, July 1, 1971, as provided by law or which has within defined boundaries a population of 1,000 or more and which has become a town as provided by law. History History. Code 1919, § 5; Code 1950, § 1-13; 1950, p. 24, § 1-13.2 9; 1971, Ex. Sess., c. 49; 1995, c. 155; 2005, c. 839. Annotations Cross references. For definition of town under article relating to local government, see Va. Const., Art. VII, § 1. Law Review. For note, Securing a Valid Annexation in Virginia, see 10 U. Rich. L. Rev. 557 (1976).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-255"><akn:num>§ 1-255</akn:num><akn:heading>United States</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text United States includes the 50 states, the District of Columbia the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, Guam, the Northern Mariana Islands and the United States Virgin Islands. History History. Code 1919, § 5; Code 1950, § 1-13; 1950, p. 24, § 1-13.3 1; 2005, c. 839. Annotations CASE NOTES Applies to all statutes.  The definition of United States herein applies to all statutes. Alphonse Custodis Chimney Constr. Co. v. Molina, 183 Va. 512, 32 S.E.2d 726, 1945 Va. LEXI S 197 (1945) (decided under prior law). Puerto Rico was one of the territories referred to as a part of the United S tates and its citizens and residents were citizens and residents of the United States within former § 65-62. Alphonse Custodis Chimney Constr. Co. v. Molina, 183 Va. 512, 32 S.E.2d 726, 1945 Va. LEXIS 197 (1945) (decided under prior law). So-called means commonly named. For case construing the several terr itories so-called under former law, see Alphonse Custodis Chimney Constr. Co. v. Molina, 183 Va. 512, 32 S.E.2d 726, 1945 Va. LEXIS 197 (1945) (decided under prior law).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-256"><akn:num>§ 1-256</akn:num><akn:heading>Weights and measurements; metric equivalents</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Words or terms relating to the customary system of weights and measurements include their International System (SI) metric equivalents, but shall not require the postin g or publishing of the equivalents along with the customary system of weights and measurements. History History. 1980, c. 465. § 1-15.2; 2005, c. 839.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-257"><akn:num>§ 1-257</akn:num><akn:heading>Written; writing; in writing</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Written, writing, and in writing include any representation of words, letters, symbols, numbers, or figures, whether (i) printed or inscribed on a tangible medium or (ii) stored in an electronic or other medium and retrievable in a perceivable form and whether an electronic signature authorized by Chapter 42.1 (§ 59.1-479 et seq.) of Title 59.1 is or is not affixed. History History. Code 1919, § 5; Code 1950, § 1-13; 1950, p. 24, § 1-13.3 2; 1999, c. 145; 2000, c. 995; 2005, c. 839. Annotations CASE NOTES Videotape evidence.  Trial court did not err by admitting the testimony of a police officer regarding what he observed on a surveillance video on the ground that the testimony violate d the best evidence rule because the best evidence rule applied only to writings. Since a videotape was not a writing as understood in common law and as defined by § 1-257, the best evidence rule was inapplicable to the videotape evidence in question. Brown v. Commonwealth, 54 Va. App. 107, 676 S.E.2d 326, 2009 Va. App. LEXIS 226 (2009). Text messages.  Text messages were writings, because they consisted of letters, words, or numbers. Cobb v. Commonwealth, 2013 Va. App. LEXIS 301 (Va. Ct. App. Oct. 22, 20 13). Chapter 3. Citizenship. -360§§ 1-18 through 1-21.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-300"><akn:num>§ 1-300</akn:num><akn:heading>Boundaries</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The territory and boundaries of the Commonwealth shall be and remain the same as they were after the Constitution of Virginia was adopted on June 29, 1776, except for t he territory that constitutes West Virginia and its boundaries, and other boundary adjustments as provided in this chapter. History History. Code 1950, § 7-1; 1966, c. 102, § 7.1-1; 2005, c. 839. Annotations Effective date. This chapter became effective October 1, 2005. CASE NOTES The Code asserts jurisdiction over the Virginia shores and strands of the Potomac, in ac cordance with the claim in the Virginia Constitution; and it is admitted that these terms include the lands between high and low water mark. Washington Airport, Inc. v. Smoot Sand &amp; Gravel Corp., 44 F.2d 342 (4th Cir. 1930), revd, 283 U.S. 348, 51 S. Ct. 474, 75 L. Ed. 1109 (1931) (decided under prior law). The majority opinion in the reversing case, which actually dealt with the boundary line between Virginia and the District of Columbia, declared that the original boundary of Maryland was the high -water mark on the southern bank of the Potomac, and that the compact of 1785 between Maryland and Virginia and the case of Maryland v. West Virginia , 217 U.S. 577, 30 S. Ct. 630, 54 L. Ed. 888 (1910), settling a controversy between those states, could not affect the rights of the District of Columbia. The decision was in effect a holding that the boundary between Virginia and the District of Columbia was the high-water mark on the southern bank of the Potomac. But see dissenting opinion. And see provisions of § 1-312 establishing present boundary between Virginia and the District.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-301"><akn:num>§ 1-301</akn:num><akn:heading>Extent of territory of the Commonwealth after the Constitution of 1776</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The authorities in determining the extent of the territory of the Commonwealth after the adoption of the Constitution of 1776 shall consist of: 1. The c harter of April 10, 1606, granted by James the First, in the fourth year of his reign, that authorized the first plantation at any place upon the coast of the Commonwealth between the thirty-fourth and forty-first degrees of north latitude; and granted t he territory from the seat of the plantation (which under this charter was begun at Jamestown), for 50 miles along the coast towards the west and southwest, as the coast lay, and for 50 miles along the coast, towards the east and northeast, or towards th e north, as the coast lay, together with all the islands within 100 miles directly over against the seacoast, and all the territory from the same 50 miles every way on the seacoast, directly into the mainland for the space of 100 miles. 2. The second charter of James, dated May 23, 1609, in the seventh year of his reign, that granted all the territory from the point of land called Cape or Point Comfort, all along the sea coast to the northward 200 miles, and from the point of Cape Comfort all along the seacoast to the southward 200 miles, and all that space and circuit of land lying from the seacoast of the precinct, up into the land, throughout from sea to sea, west and northwest, and also all the islands lying within 100 miles along the coast of both seas of the precinct aforesaid. 3. The third charter of James, dated March 12, 1611-12, in the ninth year of his reign, that granted all the islands in any part of the seas within 300 leagues of any territory granted in the former patents. 4. The 1763 treaty of peace between Great Britain and France that established a line along the middle of the river Mississippi and became the Commonwealths western boundary. 5. Section 21 of the Constitution of Virginia adopted June 29, 1776, that ceded, released, and confirmed to the people of Maryland, Pennsylvania, North and South Carolina, such parts of t he territory of the Commonwealth as were contained within the charters erecting those colonies, with all the rights in those parts that might have been claimed by the Commonwealth, except the free navigation of the Rivers Potomac and Pocomoke, with the p roperty of the Commonwealth shore or strands bordering on either of the rivers, and all improvements thereon; and that at the same time laid down in the section that the western and northern extent of the Commonwealth should in all other respects stand a s fixed by the charter of James the First, granted in 1609, and by the treaty of peace between Great Britain and France in 1763, unless by act of the legislature one or more territories should thereafter be laid off, and governments established, westward of the Alleghany mountains. History History. Code 1950, § 7-1; 1966, c. 102, § 7.1-1; 2005, c. 839. Annotations CASE NOTES The Code asserts jurisdiction over the Virginia shores and strands of the Potomac, in ac cordance with the claim in the Virginia Constitution; and it is admitted that these terms include the lands between high and low water mark. Washington Airport, Inc. v. Smoot Sand &amp; Gravel Corp., 44 F.2d 342 (4th Cir. 1930), revd, 283 U.S. 348, 51 S. Ct. 474, 75 L. Ed. 1109 (1931) (decided under prior law). The majority opinion in the reversing case, which actually dealt with the boundary line between Virginia and the District of Columbia, declared that the original boundary of Maryland was the high -water mark on the southern bank of the Potomac, and that the compact of 1785 between Maryland and Virginia and the case of Maryland v. West Virginia , 217 U.S. 577, 30 S. Ct. 630, 54 L. Ed. 888 (1910), settling a controversy between those states, could not affect the rights of the District of Columbia. The decision was in effect a holding that the boundary between Virginia and the District of Columbia was the high-water mark on the southern bank of the Potomac. But see dissenting opinion. And see provisions of § 1-312 establishing present boundary between Virginia and the District.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-302"><akn:num>§ 1-302</akn:num><akn:heading>Jurisdiction and ownership of Commonwealth over offshore waters and submerged lands</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. The jurisdi ction of the Commonwealth shall extend to and over, and be exercisable with respect to: 1. Water s offshore from the coasts of the Commonwealth for a distance of three geographical miles as determined by appropriate metes and bounds surveys approved by the Virginia Institute of Marine Science and the Virginia Marine Resources Commission in consultat ion with the Bureau of Ocean Energy Management pursuant to a decree of the United States Supreme Court in U.S. v. Maine , 423 U.S. 1 (1975), and the Submerged Lands Act, 42 U.S.C. § 1301 et seq. 2. All submerged lands, including the subsurface thereof, lying under the waters listed in subdivision 1. B. The ownersh ip of the waters and submerged lands enumerated or described in subsection A shall be in the Commonwealth unless it shall be, with respect to any given parcel or area, in any other person or entity by virtue of a valid and effective instrument of conveya nce or by operation of law. C. Nothing con tained herein shall be construed to limit or restrict in any way: 1. The j urisdiction of the Commonwealth over any person or with respect to any subject within or without the Commonwealth which jurisdiction is exercisable by reason of citizenship, residence, or for any other reason recognized by law. 2. The jurisdiction or ownership of or over any other waters or submerged lands, within or forming part of the boundaries of the Commonwealth. Nor shall anything in this section be constr ued to impair the exercise of legislative jurisdiction by the United States over any area to which such jurisdiction has been validly ceded by the Commonwealth and that remains in the ownership of the United States. D. Nothing in this section shall alter the geographic area to which any act of the General Assembly applies if the act specifies the area precisely in miles or by some other numerical designation of distance or position. However, nothing in the act or in this section shall be construed as a waiver or relinquishment of jurisdiction or ownership by the Commonwealth over or in any area to which such jurisdiction or ownership extends by virtue of this section or any other provision or rule of law. History History. Code 1950, § 7-1.1; 1960, c. 518; 1966, c. 102, § 7.1-2; 19 72, c. 689; 2005, c. 839; 2016, c. 371. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2016, c. 371, cl. 2 provides: That the Secretary of Natural Resources shall execute the metes and bounds surveys described in subsection A of § 1-302 of the Code of Virginia and request the filing of appropriate motions by the Attorney General in the Supreme Court of the United States to fix the three-mile boundary, which shall thereafter constitute the seaward boundary of the Commonwealth and the ext ent of its territorial sea. The 2016 amendments. The 2016 amendment by c. 371, in subsection A, inserted the subdivision 1 designation and substituted for a distance of three geographical miles as determined by appropriate metes and bounds surveys approved by the Virginia Institute of Marine Science and the Virginia Marine Resources Commission in consultation with the Bureau of Ocean Energy Management pursuant to a decree of the United States Supreme Court in U.S. v. Maine, 423 U.S. 1 (1975), and the Submerged Lands Act, 42 U.S.C. § 1301 et seq. for as follows: 1. The marginal sea and the high seas to the extent claimed in the Virginia Constitution of 1776 and not thereafter ceded by action of t he General Assembly; and made minor stylistic changes. OPINIONS OF THE ATTORNEY GENERAL Authority of localities to regulate state-owned submerged lands.  Virginia localities do not have the authority to extend the application of their land use ordinances to state-owned submerged lands, therefore, for small renewabl e energy projects located on or in the waters above state-owned bottomland, there are no applicable land use ordinances for purposes of the certification requirement of subdivision B 2 of § 10.1-1197.6. See opinion of Attorney General to Mr. D avid K. Paylor, Director, Virginia Department of Environmental Quality, 10-091, 2010 Va. AG LEXIS 88 (12/30/10).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-303"><akn:num>§ 1-303</akn:num><akn:heading>Cession of territory northwest of Ohio River</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. The territo ry northwest of the Ohio River ceded by the Commonwealth shall be and remain the same as provided by: 1. An ac t of the General Assembly passed on January 2, 1781, that resolved that this Commonwealth would on certain conditions yield for the benefit of the United States all her right to the territory northwest of the Ohio River. 2. An act of the General Assembly passed on December 20, 1783, that authorized the transfer to the United States, subject to the terms and conditions contained in the act of the United St ates Congress passed on September 13, 1783 and the deed of cession that was made accordingly. 3. An act of the General Assembly passed on December 30, 1788, whereby, after referring to an ordinance for the government of the territory, passed by the United States Congress on July 1 3, 1787, and reciting a particular article declared in the ordinance to be part of the compact between the original states and the people and states in the territory, the article of compact was ratified and confirmed. B. Such cessio n shall be deemed and taken according to the true intent and meaning of the acts and deed, and subject to all the terms and conditions therein expressed. History History. Code 1950, § 7-2; 1966, c. 102, § 7.1-3; 2005, c. 839. Annotations Editors note. For historical purposes, the text of the original acts have been set out in the Compacts volume.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-304"><akn:num>§ 1-304</akn:num><akn:heading>Boundary with North Carolina</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The boundary line between the Commonwealth and North Carolina shall be and remain the same as the line run by Fry and Jefferson, and afterwards extended by Walker and S mith and approved on December 7, 1791, by an act of the General Assembly. History History. Code 1950, § 7-3; 1966, c. 102, § 7.1-4; 2005, c. 839.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-305"><akn:num>§ 1-305</akn:num><akn:heading>Boundary with North Carolina eastward from low-water mark of Atlantic Ocean</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The boundary line between the Commonwealth and North Carolina eastward from the low-water mark of the Atlantic Ocean shall be and remains the line beginning at the inte rsection with the low-water mark of the Atlantic Ocean and the existing North Carolina-Virginia boundary line; thence due east to the seaward jurisdictional limit of Virginia; such boundary line to be extended on the true 90 degree bearing as far as a ne ed for further delimitation may arise. History History. 1970, c. 343, § 7.1-4.1; 2005, c. 839.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-306"><akn:num>§ 1-306</akn:num><akn:heading>Boundary with Tennessee</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The boundary line between the Commonwealth and Tennessee shall be and remain the same as established by the Supreme Court of the United States in the case of Tennessee v. Virginia, 190 U.S. 64 (1903), and the compact between the Commonwealth and Tennessee approved on February 9, 1901, by an act of the General Assembly. History History. Code 1950, § 7-4; 1966, c. 102, § 7.1-5; 2005, c. 839.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-307"><akn:num>§ 1-307</akn:num><akn:heading>Compact and boundary with Kentucky</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. Except such part as may constitute the boundary line between West Virginia and the Commonwealth of Kentucky, the boundary between this Commonwealth and the Commonwealth of Kentucky, shall be and remain as the line approved on January 13, 1800, by an act of the Gene ral Assembly. B. The article s set forth in the act of separation of the Commonwealth of Kentucky from this Commonwealth adopted by the General Assembly on December 18, 1789, shall be and remain a solemn compact mutually binding on the Commonwealths of Virginia and Kentucky, and una lterable by either without the consent of the other. History History. Code 1950, § 7-5; 1966, c. 102, § 7.1-6; 2005, c. 839. Annotations Editors note. The text of the original acts have been set out in the Compacts volume for historical purposes.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-308"><akn:num>§ 1-308</akn:num><akn:heading>Boundary with Maryland</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Black-Jenkins Award, which established the boundary line between the Commonwealth and Maryland and was ratified on March 14, 1878, by an act of the General Assembly shall be and remain obligatory on this Commonwealth and the citizens thereof, and shall be forever observed and kept by the Commonwealth and all of its citizens according to the true intent and meaning of the same, and to that end the faith of the Commo nwealth stands pledged. History History. Code 1950, § 7-6; 1966, c. 102, § 7.1-7; 2005, c. 839. Annotations Editors note. The text of the original act has been set out in the Compacts volume for historical purposes. CASE NOTES Editors note. The cases annotated below were decided under the original acts or prior law, and set out below for reference. For cases construing the Maryland-Virginia Compact of 1785, see Hendricks v. Commonwealth, 75 Va. 934 (1882); Wharton v. Wise, 153 U.S. 155, 14 S. Ct. 783, 38 L. Ed. 669 (1894); Evans v. United States, 31 App. D.C. 544 (1908). For text of the 1785 Compact, see the Appendix at the end of the Compacts volume. The Maryland-Virginia Compact of 1785, and the description of boundary lines and rights in the Potomac river contained therein, does not apply to the District of Columbia; when Maryland and Virginia ceded land to the District, they relinquished any joint interest in, and control over, that part of the river located within the District. Consequently, a Virginia resident, fishing from the Virginia shore, was subje ct to the laws of the District of Columbia when fishing with a dip net in that part of the Potomac river controlled by the District of Columbia. Evans v. United States, 1908 U.S. App. LEXIS 5666 (D.C. Cir. June 9, 1908). Maryland has a uniform southern boundary along Virginia and West Virginia at low-water m ark on the south bank of the Potomac River to the intersection of the north and south line between Maryland and West Virginia. Maryland v. West Virginia, 217 U.S. 577, 30 S. Ct. 630, 54 L. Ed. 888, 1910 U.S. LEXIS 426 (1910). But see Smoot Sand &amp; Gravel Corp. v. Washington Airport, Inc., 283 U.S. 348, 51 S. Ct. 474, 75 L. Ed. 1109, 1931 U.S. LEXIS 837 (1931). Article 4 of the Award precluded regulation by Maryland of Virginias sovereign riparian rights.  Portion of a binding arbitration award set out at § 7.1-7 [now § 1-308], Fourth, clearly established Virginias dominion over the soil to the low-water m ark on the Virginia shore of the Potomac River by prescription, and clearly established Virginias sovereign riparian right to use the river beyond the low water mark without regulation by Maryland. Virginia v. Maryland, 540 U.S. 56, 124 S. Ct. 598, 1 57 L. Ed. 2d 461, 2003 U.S. LEXIS 9192 (2003). Rights granted under Article 7 of the Compact are not subject to regulation by Maryland.  Plain language of § 7.1-7 [now § 1-308], Seventh, grants to the citizens of Maryland and Virginia full property rights in the shores of the Potomac River an d the privilege of building improvements from the shore and, especially since the scope of Marylands sovereignty over the river was vigorously disputed both before and after ratification of the interstate compact, there was no grant or recognition of sovereign authority to permit Maryland to regulate the exercise of this privilege by Virginia citizens. Virginia v. Maryland, 540 U.S. 56, 124 S. Ct. 598, 157 L. Ed. 2d 461, 2003 U.S. LEXIS 9192 (2003). Article 8 of the compact gives Virginia concurrent jurisdiction with Maryland, over the Potomac River from shore to shore, and over that part of the Pocomoke River which is within the limits of Virginia, to enact such laws, with the consent and approval of Maryland, as may be deemed necessary and proper for the preservation of fish in said waters. Hendricks v. Commonwealth, 75 Va. 934, 1882 Va. LEXIS 4 (1882). Article 10 of the compact refers only to offenses against the citizen or individual. Whe n the offense is against the state, and not against an individual or citizen, there is no declaration as to the court of which state shall take cognizance of it. Hendricks v. Commonwealth, 75 Va. 934, 1882 Va. LEXIS 4 (1882). And see Wharton v. Wise, 153 U.S. 155, 14 S. Ct. 783, 38 L. Ed. 669, 1894 U.S. LEXIS 2172 (1894) (holding that such article of the compact does not forbid the State of Virginia from trying and convicting citizens of Maryland for offenses committed in Virginia against its laws regul ating oyster fisheries.). Mutual rights of fishery.  The provisions of articles 7 and 8 of the compact, which give mutual rights of fishery to the citizens of the two states, refer only to the Potomac River, and do not operate to give such rights in the Pocomoke river and sound. Wharton v. Wise, 153 U.S. 155, 14 S. Ct. 783, 38 L. Ed. 669, 1894 U.S. LEXIS 2172 (1894) (criticizing Hendricks v. Commonwealth, 1882 Va. LEXIS 4, 75 Va. 934 (1882)). Determination of location of murder victims body.  The exact physical location of a murder victims body within river constituted a factual question which the jury could appropriately decide. However, the exact location of the boundary between Virginia and Maryland involves an interpretation of this section and represents a legal question outside the jurys province. If it were impossible for the jurors to interpret the evidence concerning the bodys exa ct placement so as to conclude under this section that the body lay in Virginia, the trial court should not have submitted the issue of venue to the jury. Traverso v. Commonwealth, 6 Va. App. 172, 366 S.E.2d 719, 4 Va. Law Rep. 2318, 1988 Va. App. LEXIS 21 (1988). Where body of murder victim was found six to seven and one-half feet from Virginia shoreline, and the only evidence introduced concerning the low water mark showed that, on the day the body was found, the river level was at the actual low water mark, unless a line could be drawn between two headlands in order to form a new low water mark, the bodys placement would have been six to seven and one-half feet beyond the Virginia border. Since victims body lay six to seven and one-half feet from the Commonwealth of Virginia, venue did not lie in Loudoun County and the appellant s conviction would be reversed. Traverso v. Commonwealth, 6 Va. App. 172, 366 S.E.2d 719, 4 Va. Law Rep. 2318, 1988 Va. App. LEXIS 21 (1988).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-309"><akn:num>§ 1-309</akn:num><akn:heading>Boundary with Maryland eastward from Assateague Island</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The boundary line between the Commonwealth and Maryland eastward from Assateague Island shall be and remain as follows: Beginning at a point on the Maryland-Virginia li ne located on Assateague Island designated as station Pope Island Life Saving Station (1907) defined by latitude 38°01´36.93" and longitude 75°14´47.105"; thence running N 84°05´43.5" E (true) - 1,100.00 feet to station Atla ntic; thence due east (true) to the Maryland-Virginia jurisdictional limit. History History. 1970, c. 342, § 7.1-7.1; 2005, c. 839.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-310"><akn:num>§ 1-310</akn:num><akn:heading>Boundary with Maryland in upper reaches of Pocomoke sound and lower reaches of Pocomoke River</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. The boundar y line between the Commonwealth and Maryland in the previously undescribed portion of the Maryland-Virginia line in the upper reaches of the Pocomoke sound and lower reaches of the Pocomoke River shall be and remain as follows:Beginning at a point which is corner D defined by latitude 37°56´28.00" and longitude 75°45´43.56"; which is the last point on the Maryland-Virginia line that was defined by the joint report of engineers on relocating and remarking Maryland-Virginia boundary line a cross Tangier and Pocomoke sounds December 1916; thence running N 73°34´31.9" E about 17,125.11 feet to corner H a point defined by latitude 37°57´115.82" and longitude 75°42´18.48"; thence running N 85°39´33.9" E about 3,785. 82 feet to corner J a point defined by latitude 37°57´18.65" and longitude 75°41´31.25"; thence running S 74°16´00.8" E about 7,278.41 feet to corner K a point defined by latitude 37°56´59.13" and longitude 75°40´03.89"; the nce running S 61°57´55.7" E about 3,664.73 feet to corner L a point defined by latitude 37°56´42.10" and longitude 75°39´23.51"; thence running N 76°15´24.5" E about 2,263.49 feet to corner M a point defined by latitude 37°56 ´47.65" and longitude 75°38´54.85"; thence running N 00°49´51.5" W about 7,178.56 feet to corner N a point defined by latitude 37°57´58.61" and longitude 75°38´56.15"; thence northeasterly about 3 1/2 miles following the middle thread of the meandering Pocomoke river to corner P a point defined by latitude 37°59´39.37" and longitude 75°37´26.52", which is at or near the point of intersection with the Scarborough and Calvert boundary line of May 28, 1668; corners N and P are connected by a line running N 35°08´33.5" E about 12,465.32 feet; thence N 83°45´59.9" E about 24,156.95 feet to the boundary monument near triangulation station Davis on the Scarborough and Calvert boundary line of May 28, 1668. Ge ographic positions are based on 1927 datum. B. No vested r ight of any individual, partnership or corporation within the area affected by this section shall in any wise be impaired, restricted or affected thereby. This section shall not be retrospective in its operation nor shall it in any way affect the rights of any individual, partnership or corporation in any suit now pending in any of the courts of this Commonwealth or of the United States wherein such cause of action arose over, or is in any way based upon, the area affected. This section shall in no wise preclude the Commonwealth from prosecuting any individual, partnership or corporation for violation of any of the criminal laws of this Commonwealth within such area until this section shall become effective. History History. 1970, c. 315, § 7.1-7.2; 2005, c. 839.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-311"><akn:num>§ 1-311</akn:num><akn:heading>Recession of portion of District of Columbia</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text That portion of the District of Columbia which, by an act of the General Assembly, passed December 3, 1789, was ceded to the United States and receded and forever relin quished to this Commonwealth by an act of Congress approved July 9, 1846, and accepted by the Commonwealth by an act of the General Assembly adopted on February 3, 1846, shall be and remain reannexed to this Commonwealth and constitutes a portion thereof , subject to such reservation and provisions respecting the public property of the United States, as the United States Congress has enacted in its act of recession. History History. Code 1950, § 7-8; 1966, c. 102, § 7.1-9; 2005, c. 839. Annotations Editors note. The text of the original act has been set out in the Compacts volume for historical purposes. CASE NOTES Act making cession of territory.  See Suckley v. Rotchford, 53 Va. (12 Gratt.) 60, 1855 Va. LEXIS 6 (1855) (decided under prior law).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-312"><akn:num>§ 1-312</akn:num><akn:heading>Boundary with District of Columbia</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The boundary line between the Commonwealth and the District of Columbia shall be and remain as described by the United States Public Law 208, Seventy-Ninth Congress, ap proved October 31, 1945, and amended by Chapter 772 of the 1968 Acts of Assembly and Chapter 94 of the 2002 Acts of Assembly. History History. Code 1950, § 7-9; 1966, c. 102, § 7.1-10; 1968, c. 772; 200 2, c. 94; 2005, c. 839. Annotations CASE NOTES Virginia has ceded to the United States exclusive jurisdiction over the territory embraced within the Washington National Airport, reserving, however, the power to levy a tax on the sale of oil and gasoline sold on the airport for use in vehicles. This reservation does not include the power to levy taxes for the privilege of doing busin ess on the airport. Hence one whose business is the sale of oil and gasoline there is not properly assessed under Arlington Countys business privilege tax ordinance or the states merchants license tax, since they are not taxes on the sale of the products. Floyd v. Fischer, 199 Va. 363, 99 S.E.2d 612, 1957 Va. LEXIS 198 (1957) (decided under prior law). Under the grant from Virginia to the United States in § 107 of the act of Congress set out in this section, the Commonwealth is presumed to have specifically r eserved all taxing rights which it intended to reserve, and the Virginia retail merchants license tax and the countys business privilege license tax, not having been reserved, are necessarily excluded. Floyd v. Fischer, 199 Va. 363, 99 S.E.2d 612 , 1957 Va. LEXIS 198 (1957) (decided under prior law). Grant of exclusive jurisdiction over Washington National Airport to the federal government does not exclude all state jurisdiction relating to the federal area. Bartsch v. Washington Metro. Area Transit Comm'n, 357 F.2d 923, 1966 U.S. App. LEXIS 6967 (4th Cir. 1966) (decided under prior law). Virginia law governs employment relationships.  At Washington National Airport, Virginia law governs employment relationships between private employers and their employees. Singleton v. International Ass'n of M achinists, Dist. 141, Local Lodge No. 1747, 240 Va. 403, 397 S.E.2d 856, 7 Va. Law Rep. 828, 1990 Va. LEXIS 134 (1990) (decided under prior law).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-313"><akn:num>§ 1-313</akn:num><akn:heading>Boundary line between Loudoun County, Virginia, and Jefferson County, West Virginia</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. The boundar y line between Loudoun County, Virginia, and Jefferson County, West Virginia shall be the watershed line of the top of the ridge of the Blue Ridge Mountains as established by the survey approved by the Commission on April 29, 1997, and recorded in the la nd books in the courthouses of Loudoun County, Virginia, and Jefferson County, West Virginia. B. No vested r ight of any individual, partnership, or corporation within the territory affected by this act shall in any wise be impaired, restricted, or affected by this act. This act shall not be retrospective in its operation nor shall it in any way affect the righ ts of any individual, partnership, or corporation in any suit now pending in any of the courts of this Commonwealth or of the United States wherein the cause of action arose over, or is in any way based upon, the territory affected. History History. 1993, c. 141, § 7.1-10.1; 1998, c. 123; 2005, c. 839. Chapter 4. Jurisdiction Over Lands Acquired by the United States. -360§ 1-400. Conditional consent given to acquisition of lands by United States; concurrent jurisdiction ceded. -360§ 1-401. Ceding additional jurisdiction to United States. -360§ 1-402. Shenandoah National Park. -360§ 1-403. Conveyances of certain waste and unappropriated lands and marshlands to the United States. -360§ 1-404. Licensing sale of mixed alcoholic beverages on lands ceded to or owned by United States. -360§ 1-405. Reversion to Commonwealth; recorded title prerequisite to vesting jurisdiction. -360§ 1-406. Conveyances to political subdivisions of lands ceded to and no longer used by United States. -360§ 1-407. Concurrent jurisdiction of Commonwealth and United States over certain lands leased to political subdivisions. -360§ 1-408. Relinquishment by United States of jurisdiction over lands in the Commonwealth.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-400"><akn:num>§ 1-400</akn:num><akn:heading>Conditional consent given to acquisition of lands by United States; concurrent jurisdiction ceded</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. On and afte r July 1, 1981, the conditional consent of the Commonwealth is hereby given in accordance with clause 17, § 8, Article 1 of the United States Constitution to the acquisition by the United States, or under its authority, by purchase, lease, condemnatio n, or otherwise, of any lands in the Commonwealth, whether under water or not, required for customhouses, post offices, arsenals, forts, magazines, dockyards, military reserves, or for needful public buildings. B. The acquisi tion by condemnation of any property within the Commonwealth, not expressly consented to in subsection A of this section, shall require the prior approval of the General Assembly. C. Over all la nds hereafter acquired by the United States, the Commonwealth hereby cedes to the United States concurrent governmental, judicial, executive and legislative power and jurisdiction. D. There is he reby expressly reserved in the Commonwealth, over all lands so acquired by the United States the following: 1. Tax o n motor vehicle fuels and lubricants.  The Commonwealth shall have the jurisdiction and power to levy a tax on oil, gasoline and all other motor fuels and lubricants thereon owned by others than the United States and a tax on the sale thereof, on suc h lands, except sales to the United States for use in the exercise of essentially governmental functions. 2. Service of civil and criminal process.  The Commonwealth shall have the jurisdiction and power to serve criminal and civil process on such lands. 3. Sale of intoxicating liquors.  The Commonwealth shall have the jurisdiction and power to license and regulate, or to prohibit, the sale of intoxicating liquors on any such lands. 4. Tax on property and businesses.  The Commonwealth shall have the jurisdiction and power to tax all property, including buildings erected thereon, not belonging to the United States , and to require licenses and impose license taxes upon any business or businesses conducted thereon. E. For all pur poses of taxation and of the jurisdiction of the courts of the Commonwealth over persons, transactions, matters and property on such lands, the lands shall be deemed to be a part of the county or city in which they are situated. F. Any such ac quisition by or conveyance or lease to the United States, as provided in this section, shall be deemed to have been secured or made upon the express condition that the reservations of power and limitations provided in this section are recognized as valid by the United States and, in the event the United States shall deny the validity of the reservations, as to all or any part of such lands, then and in that event, the title and possession of all or any such part of such lands, conveyed to the United Sta tes by the Commonwealth, shall immediately revert to the Commonwealth. G. Nothing con tained in this section shall affect any special act adopted ceding jurisdiction to the United States, nor any deeds executed pursuant to § 1-401. History History. 1976, c. 211, § 7.1-18.1; 1981, c. 533; 2005, c. 839. Annotations Effective date. This chapter became effective October 1, 2005. Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 5B M.J. Criminal Procedure, § 9; 19 M.J. United States, § 5. CASE NOTES Editors note. The cases annotated below were decided under prior law. The question whether a federal area within a state is subject to exclusive jurisdiction of the United States is complicated and often difficult to decide. A determination depends upon many factors, jurisdiction being subject to the terms, conditions, restrictions, limitations and provisions of the acquisition by the United States, includi ng the consent of the State and acceptance by the United States. Western Union Tel. Co. v. Commonwealth ex rel. SCC, 204 Va. 421, 132 S.E.2d 407, 1963 Va. LEXIS 167 (1963). The presumption prevails that the State has jurisdiction over land which is owned by Uni ted States unless a defendant shows that the United States was deeded the land and accepted jurisdiction over it. Smith v. Commonwealth, 219 Va. 455, 248 S.E.2d 135, 1978 Va. LEXIS 203 (1978), cert. denied, 441 U.S. 967, 99 S. Ct. 2419, 60 L. Ed. 2d 1074 (1979). Jurisdiction may be transferred to the general government by cession. The terms of cessi on, to the extent that they may lawfully be prescribed, determine the extent of the federal jurisdiction. United States v. Schuster, 220 F. Supp. 61, 1963 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 7359 (E.D. Va. 1963). The argument that a state is powerless to surrender its jurisdiction to the United States over privately owned lands is without merit. United States v. Schuster, 220 F. Supp. 61, 1963 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 7359 (E.D. Va. 1963). The reservation in an act of cession of concurrent jurisdiction with the United States o ver land, so that the courts and officers of the State may take such cognizance, execute such process and discharge such legal functions within the same as may not be incompatible with the consent given, is subject to the provisions of Article 1, § 8 of the federal Constitution, that is, as may not be incompatible with the exclusive jurisdiction of the United States, and may operate to authorize the service by the officers of the State of the civil and criminal process of its courts, with reference t o acts done within the acknowledged territory of the State outside of the ceded lands. This reservation is valid and is intended to prevent such places from becoming harbors of refuge for debtors and criminals. Foley v. Shriver, 81 Va. 568, 1886 Va. LEXI S 124 (1886). Retention of right to serve process does not prevent cession of jurisdiction.  The mere fact that the State has retained the right to serve criminal and civil process on land described in this section is not effective to prevent cession of e xclusive or concurrent criminal jurisdiction to the federal government. The purpose of this reservation is to prevent the land involved from becoming an asylum for fugitives from justice. United States v. Schuster, 220 F. Supp. 61, 1963 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 7359 (E.D. Va. 1963). And practice is to permit federal government to prosecute.  The practice which exists in this area with respect to crimes committed on lands acquired in any manner by the United States is to permit  indeed, to require  the federal government to prosecute. The State adopts a hands off policy. United States v. Schuster, 220 F. Supp. 61, 1963 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 7359 (E.D. Va. 1963). Reservation of right to execute pr ocess.  See Western Union Tel. Co. v. Chiles, 214 U.S. 274, 29 S. Ct. 613, 53 L. Ed. 994, 1909 U.S. LEXIS 1916 (1909) (Norfolk Navy Yard); Norfolk &amp; P. Belt Line R.R. v. Parker, 152 Va. 484, 147 S.E. 461, 1929 Va. LEXIS 185 (1929). Does not affect personal sta tus of resident.  The right of the State to serve process in territory ceded to the United States does not affect the personal status of a resident in such territory. Such person d oes not thereby acquire a residence in this State so as to defeat the right of a creditor to attach his property in this State on the ground that he is a nonresident. Bank of Phoebus v. Byrum, 110 Va. 708, 67 S.E. 349, 1910 Va. LEXIS 113 (1910). State ceded concurrent jurisdiction to prosecute crimes committed on lands transferred to the federal government.  Virginia consented to cede only concurrent jurisdiction to the United States to prosecute crimes committed on lands transferred to the federal government; the presumption in favor of concurrent jurisdiction was rebuttable, but only by a clear manifestation of a specific intent to do so. Campbell v. Commonwealth, 39 Va. App. 180, 571 S.E.2d 906, 2002 Va. App. LEXIS 681 (2002). State has ceded concurrent jurisdiction of crimes committed on private property leased for naval base.  Virginia has ceded concurrent jurisdiction to the federal government for crimes committed on private property leased by the United States for purposes of the oper ation of a naval base. United States v. Schuster, 220 F. Supp. 61, 1963 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 7359 (E.D. Va. 1963). Virginia laws in force at Old Point Comfort.  The general laws of Virginia, other than criminal, which are not in conflict with those of the United States relating to forts, and which do not interfere with th e military control, discipline, and use by the United States of Fortress Monroe as a military post, are in force at Old Point Comfort, and are especially in force in those parts and places at Old Point Comfort which have been appropriated to other than t he military purposes of the United States. Crook, Horner &amp; Co. v. Old Point Comfort Hotel Co., 54 F. 604, 1893 U.S. App. LEXIS 1481 (C.C.D. Va. 1893). OPINIONS OF THE ATTORNEY GENERAL Jurisdiction over military base.  In the absence of a notice of acceptance filed with the Governor whereby the United States has accepted concurrent jurisdiction over the land on which certain fac ilities are located, the United States does not hold concurrent legislative jurisdiction over the land on which the facilities are located. See opinion of Attorney General to Cynthia E. Hudson, Esquire, City Attorney for the City of Hampton and John F. H augh, Esquire, Acting Commonwealths Attorney, 12-053, 2013 Va. AG LEXIS 7 (1/17/13).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-401"><akn:num>§ 1-401</akn:num><akn:heading>Ceding additional jurisdiction to United States</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. Whenever th e head or other authorized officer of any department or independent establishment or agency of the United States shall deem it desirable that additional jurisdiction or powers be ceded over any lands in the Commonwealth acquired or proposed to be acquire d by the United States under his immediate jurisdiction, custody or control, and whenever the Governor and Attorney General of the Commonwealth shall agree to the same, the Governor and Attorney General shall execute and acknowledge a deed in the name of and under the lesser seal of the Commonwealth ceding such additional jurisdiction. The deed shall accurately and specifically describe the area and location of the land over which the additional jurisdiction and powers are ceded and shall set out specif ically what additional jurisdiction and powers are ceded, and may set out any reservations in the Commonwealth of jurisdiction which may be deemed proper in addition to those referred to in subsection D. B. No such dee d shall become effective or operative until the jurisdiction therein provided for is accepted on behalf of the United States as required by 40 U.S.C. § 255. The head or other authorized officer of a department or independent establishment or agency of the United States shall indicate such acceptance by executing and acknowledging such deed and admitting it to record in the office of the clerk of the court in which deeds conveying the lands affected would properly be recorded. C. When such d eed has been executed and acknowledged on behalf of the Commonwealth and the United States, and admitted to record as provided in subsection B, it shall have the effect of ceding to and vesting in the United States the jurisdiction and powers therein pro vided for and none other. D. Every such deed as is provided for in this section shall reserve in the Commonwealth over all lands therein referred to the jurisdiction and power to serve civil and criminal process on such lands and in the event that the lands or any part thereof shall be sold or leased to any person, under the terms of which sale or lease the vendee or lessee shall have the right to conduct thereon any private industry or business, then the jurisdiction ceded to the United States over any such lands so sold or leased shall ceas e and determine, and thereafter the Commonwealth shall have all jurisdiction and power she would have had if no jurisdiction or power had been ceded to the United States. This provision, however, shall not apply to post exchanges, officers clubs and similar activities on lands acquired by the United States for purposes of national defense. It is further provided that the reservations provided for in this subsection shall remain effective even though they should be omitted from any deed executed purs uant to this section. E. Nothing con tained in this section shall be construed as repealing any special acts ceding jurisdiction to the United States to acquire any specific tract of land. History History. Code 1950, § 7-24; 1966, c. 102, § 7.1-21; 1972, c. 597; 19 76, c. 211; 2005, c. 839. Annotations CASE NOTES The presumption prevails that the State has jurisdiction over land which is owned by Uni ted States unless a defendant shows that the United States was deeded the land and accepted jurisdiction over it. Smith v. Commonwealth, 219 Va. 455, 248 S.E.2d 135, 1978 Va. LEXIS 203 (1978), cert. denied, 441 U.S. 967, 99 S. Ct. 2419, 60 L. Ed. 2d 1074 (1979) (decided under prior law). OPINIONS OF THE ATTORNEY GENERAL Jurisdiction over naval base.  Although the United States government exercises exclusive jurisdiction over a naval base, such jurisdiction does not prohibit a locality from assessing a business professional and occupation license tax on activities carried out by a private company on that land. See opinion of Attorney General to Ronald S. Hallman, Esquire, City Attorney for the City of Chesapeake, 11-029, 2012 Va. AG LEXIS 9 (2/24/12). Jurisdiction over military base.  In the absence of a notice of acceptance filed with the Governor whereby the United States has accepted concurrent jurisdiction over the land on which certain fac ilities are located, the United States does not hold concurrent legislative jurisdiction over the land on which the facilities are located. See opinion of Attorney General to Cynthia E. Hudson, Esquire, City Attorney for the City of Hampton and John F. H augh, Esquire, Acting Commonwealths Attorney, 12-053, 2013 Va. AG LEXIS 7 (1/17/13).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-402"><akn:num>§ 1-402</akn:num><akn:heading>Shenandoah National Park</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The respective jurisdiction and powers of the Commonwealth and the United States over all lands within the Shenandoah National Park, as it is now constituted or may her eafter be extended, shall be as follows: 1. Crimi nal and police jurisdiction.  The United States shall have exclusive jurisdiction, legislative, executive and judicial, with respect to the commission of crimes, and the arrest, trial and punishment therefor, and exclusive general police jurisdiction thereover. 2. Sale of alcoholic beverages.  The United States shall have the power to regulate or prohibit the sale of alcoholic beverages on such lands; provided, that, if the sale of alcoholic beverages is prohibited by general law in the Commonwealth outside of such lands, no such alcoholic beverages shall be sold on the lands contained in the Park area; and provided further, that if the general laws of the Commonwealth permit the sale of al coholic beverages, then the regulations of the United States relating to such sales on such lands shall conform as nearly as possible to the regulatory provisions in accordance with which such sales are permitted in the Commonwealth outside of such Park lands. Nothing in this subsection shall be construed as reserving in the Commonwealth power to require licenses of persons engaged in the sale of intoxicating beverages on such lands, nor the power to require that any sales be made through official liquo r stores. 3. Service of civil and criminal process.  The Commonwealth shall have jurisdiction to serve civil process within the limits of the Park in any suits properly instituted in any of the courts of the Commonwealth and to serve criminal process within such limits in any suits or prosecutions for or on account of crimes committed in the Commonwealth but outside of the Park. 4. Tax on alcoholic beverages.  The Commonwealth shall have jurisdiction and power to levy a nondiscriminatory tax on all alcoholic beverages possessed or sold on such lands. 5. Tax on motor vehicle fuels and lubricants.  The Commonwealth shall have jurisdiction and power to tax the sales of oil and gasoline, and other motor vehicle fuels and lubricants fo r use in motor vehicles. This subsection shall not be construed as a consent by the United States to the taxation by the Commonwealth of such sales for the exclusive use of the United States. 6. Tax on businesses.  The Commonwealth shall have jurisdiction and power to levy nondiscriminatory taxes on private individuals, associations and corporations, their franchises and p roperties, on such lands, and on their businesses conducted thereon. 7. Jurisdiction of courts.  The courts of the Commonwealth shall have concurrent jurisdiction with the courts of the United States of all civil causes of action arising on such lands to the same extent as if the cause of action had arisen in the county or city in which the land lies outside the Park area, and the state officers shall have jurisdiction to enforce on such lands the judgments of the state courts and the collection of ta xes by appropriate process. 8. Voting residence.  Persons residing in or on any of the lands embraced in the Park shall have the right to establish a voting residence in the Commonwealth by reason thereof, and t he consequent right to vote at all elections within the county or city in which the land or lands upon which they reside are located upon like terms and conditions, and to the same extent as they would be entitled to vote in such county or city if the la nds on which they reside had not been deeded or conveyed to the United States. 9. Fugitives.  All fugitives from justice taking refuge in the Park shall be subject to the same laws as refugees from justice found in the Commonwealth. History History. Code 1950, § 7-22; 1966, c. 102, § 7.1-19; 2005, c. 839. Annotations Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 14A M.J. Parks, Public Squares and Playgrounds, § 2. CASE NOTES Section merely preserves traditional jurisdiction of State.  Having no power to confer jurisdiction on federal courts, Virginia, in enacting this section, intended only to preserve its traditional jurisdiction, and Congress , in adopting the very language of subdivision (g) of this section in a subsequent statute, intended no more. Fowler v. Dodson, 159 F. Supp. 101, 1958 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 2605 (D. Pa. 1958) (decided under prior law). Jurisdiction of action arising from automobile collision in Park.  Absent diversity of citizenship, a federal district court had no jurisdiction of an action arising from an automobile collision occurring in Shenandoah National P ark. Fowler v. Dodson, 159 F. Supp. 101, 1958 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 2605 (D. Pa. 1958) (decided under prior law). Jurisdiction to serve process within the limits of the Park was not reserved by the Comm onwealth in Chapter 371 of the Acts of 1928, under which lands in the Park were conveyed to the United States; and the jurisdiction was denied in Buttery v. Robbins, 177 Va. 368, 14 S.E.2d 544 (1941) (decided under prior law).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-403"><akn:num>§ 1-403</akn:num><akn:heading>Conveyances of certain waste and unappropriated lands and marshlands to the United States</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. The Governo r is authorized to execute in the name of the Commonwealth deeds conveying, subject to the jurisdictional and other limitations and reservations contained in §§ 1-400 and 1-405, to the United States such title as the Commonwealth may have in waste and unappropriated lands entirely surrounded by lands owned by the United States, when the same are certified as being vacant and unappropriated by a duly authorized agent of the United States and are described by metes and bounds descriptions filed with the Secretary of the Commonwealth and with the clerk of the court in the county wherein such unappropriated land is situated. B. The Governo r is authorized to execute, in the name and on behalf of the Commonwealth, a deed or other appropriate instrument conveying to the United States, without any consideration but subject to the jurisdictional limitations and reservations contained in § § 1-400 and 1-405, such right, title and interest in or easement over and across the marshes lying along the seaside of the Counties of Accomack and Northampton as may be necessary and proper for the construction, operation and maintenance of a canal or channel for small boats over and through such marshlands. History History. Code 1950, § 7-23; 1966, c. 102, § 7.1-20; 1976, c. 211; 20 05, c. 839.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-404"><akn:num>§ 1-404</akn:num><akn:heading>Licensing sale of mixed alcoholic beverages on lands ceded to or owned by United States</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Virginia Alcoholic Beverage Control Authority may license the sale of mixed alcoholic beverages as defined in Chapter 1 (§ 4.1-100 et seq.) of Title 4.1 at place s primarily engaged in the sale of meals on lands ceded by the Commonwealth to the United States or owned by the government of the United States or any agency thereof provided that such lands are used as ports of entry or egress to and from the United St ates, and provided that such lands lie within or partly within the boundaries of any county in this Commonwealth which permits the lawful dispensing of mixed alcoholic beverages. The Board of Directors of the Authority may adopt rules and regulations gov erning the sale of such spirits, and to fix the fees for such licenses, within the limits fixed by general law. History History. 1968, c. 511, § 7.1-21.1; 1993, c. 866; 2005, c. 839; 2015, cc . 38, 730. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2015, cc. 38 and 730, cl. 4, as amended by Acts 2017, cc. 698 and 707, cl. 2, provides: That the provisions of this act shall become effective on January 15, 2018, except that the provisions of the (i) thirteenth, fourteenth, and fifteenth enactments of this act shall become effective on July 1, 2015; (ii) third enactment of this act shall become effective on July 1, 2018; and (iii) eleventh enactment of this act shall become effective on January 1, 2019. The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendments by cc. 38 and 730, effective January 15, 2018, substituted Authority for Board in the first sentence and of Directors of t he Authority may for is hereby authorized to in the last sentence.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-405"><akn:num>§ 1-405</akn:num><akn:heading>Reversion to Commonwealth; recorded title prerequisite to vesting jurisdiction</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. As used in this section, unless the context requires otherwise:Corrective action means the response and reme diation to environmental contamination to the extent required by any applicable environmental law or regulation applicable to the property.Environmental contamination means any hazardous waste, substance or toxic material, or its discharge or release, that is regulated under any environmental law or regulation applicable to the property, and shall i nclude petroleum (including crude oil), natural gas, liquefied natural gas, ordnance, unexploded munitions, and asbestos. B. If the Unit ed States shall cease to be the owner of any lands, or any part thereof, granted or conveyed to it by the Commonwealth; if the purposes of any such grant or conveyance to the United States shall cease; or if the United States shall for five consecutive y ears fail to use any such land for the purposes of the grant or conveyance, then, and in that event, the right and title to such land, or such part thereof, shall immediately revert to the Commonwealth unless such land, or part thereof, contains environm ental contamination. No land containing environmental contamination shall be transferred or revert to the Commonwealth, unless and until all corrective action necessary to protect human health and the environment with respect to any environmental contami nation on the lands, or portion thereof, has been completed to the satisfaction of the Commonwealth and approved by the Governor pursuant to § 2.2-1149, and the United States has executed and delivered a transfer instrument including covenants warrant ing that (i) all corrective action necessary to protect human health and the environment with respect to any environmental contamination on the land or any portion thereof has been taken, and (ii) any corrective action for environmental contamination occ urring before the date of transfer found to be necessary after the date of the transfer of the title of the land or any portion thereof shall be conducted by the United States.In cases where the Defense Base Closure and Realignment Commission (BRAC Commi ssion) established pursuant to P.L. 101-510 (1990), as amended, identifies United States military bases located in the Commonwealth for closure, the Commonwealth shall have, in addition to the foregoing, the right to enter upon such lands so identified f or the purpose of inspection for environmental contamination. Upon completion of such inspection, the Commonwealth shall report its findings to the Governor and the appropriate federal agencies. C. All deeds, conveyances or title papers for the transfer of title of lands to the United States shall be recorded in the county or city wherein the land or the greater part thereof lies, but no tax shall be required on any such instrument made to the United States b y which they acquire lands for public purposes. D. The jurisdi ction ceded by § 1-400 shall not vest until the United States shall have acquired the title of record to such lands, or rights or interest therein, by purchase, condemnation, lease or otherwise. So long as the lands, or any rights or interest therein, are held in fee simple by the United States, and no longer, such lands, rights or interest, as the case may be, shall continue exempt and exonerated, from all state and local taxes which may be levied or imposed under the authority of the Commonwealth. History History. Code 1950, § 7-25; 1966, c. 102, § 7.1-22; 1975, c. 449; 19 76, c. 211; 1994, c. 23; 2005, c. 839. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2007, c. 490, provides: § 1. Notwithstanding the limitation on the transfer or reversion of lands to the Commonwealth contained in subsection B of § 1-405 of the Code of Virginia, lands located within the Northern Virginia Planning District that contain environmental contamination may revert or transfer to the Commonwealth if the United States enters into a written agreement with the Commonwealt h pursuant to § 2.2-1149 to indemnify the Commonwealth against all costs and liabilities associated with such environmental contamination and related corrective action or otherwise provides satisfactory assurances that all corrective action necessary to protect human health and the environment will be taken at the sole expense of the United States. The written agreement shall be in a form approved by the Attorney General of Virginia. § 2. In addition to the requirements set forth in § 1, such transfer or reversion shall not occur unless and until the United States has agreed, and pro vides assurances satisfactory to the Commonwealth, to provide all transportation infrastructure improvements required to accommodate the development of any property owned by the United States and contiguous or adjacent to the property subject to the tran sfer or reversion. § 3. Except as provided in § 1, the provisions of § 1-405 of the Code of Virginia shall apply mutatis mutandis to this act. § 4. As used in this act, corrective action and environmental contamination shall mean the same as those terms are defined in § 1-405 of the Code of Virginia.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-406"><akn:num>§ 1-406</akn:num><akn:heading>Conveyances to political subdivisions of lands ceded to and no longer used by United States</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Whenever any land in the Commonwealth has been or is conveyed to the United States with a provision in the deed that upon abandonment or use for any purpose other than that stated in the deed such land shall revert to the Commonwealth, and if any such land is abandoned or is no longer used for the purpose for which conveyed, the Governor is hereby authorized to convey to the political subdivision in which such land is situated, all right, title and interest of the Commonwealth in and to such land. This section shall not affect any lease made under Chapter 321 of the Acts of 1952. History History. Code 1950, § 7-25.1; 1954, c. 170; 1966, c. 102, § 7.1-23; 2005, c. 839.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-407"><akn:num>§ 1-407</akn:num><akn:heading>Concurrent jurisdiction of Commonwealth and United States over certain lands leased to political subdivisions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Whenever the United States government has exclusive jurisdiction over property located in the Commonwealth of Virginia, and leases the property, or part thereof, to any political subdivision to be used by it for a public purpose, the exclusive jurisdiction shall cease as to the property so leased and the Commonwealth and the United States government shall have concurrent jurisdiction over the property so long as the le ase continues. At the termination of the lease the jurisdiction of the Commonwealth shall cease and the United States shall have exclusive jurisdiction thereof. History History. Code 1950, § 7-25.2; 1964, c. 362; 1966, c. 102, § 7.1-24; 2005, c. 839.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-408"><akn:num>§ 1-408</akn:num><akn:heading>Relinquishment by United States of jurisdiction over lands in the Commonwealth</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Whenever a duly authorized official or agent of the United States, acting pursuant to authority conferred by the United States Congress, notifies the Governor that the United States desires or is willing to relinquish to the Commonwealth the jurisdiction, or a portion thereof, held by the United States over lands located in the Commonwealth, as designated in such notice, the Governor may, in his discretion, accept such relinquishment. Such acceptance shall be made by sending a notice of acceptance to the official or agent designated by the United States to receive such notice of acceptance. The Governor shall send a signed copy of the notice of acceptance, together wi th the notice of relinquishment received from the United States, to the Secretary of the Commonwealth, who shall maintain a permanent file of said notices. Upon the sending of the notice of acceptance to the designated official or agent of the United States, the Commonwealth shall immediately have such jurisdiction over th e lands designated in the notice of relinquishment as the notice shall specify. Upon receipt of a copy of the notice of relinquishment and a copy of the notice of acceptance, the Secretary of the Commonwealth shall immediately give written notice o f such change in jurisdiction to the Attorney General and the attorney for the Commonwealth of the city or county in which such lands are located. The Secretary of the Commonwealth shall also certify a copy of each of the notices to the clerk of court in which deeds are admitted to record for the city or county in which such lands are located. The clerk shall record the notices in his deed book and index them in the name of the United States and the Commonwealth. History History. 1975, c. 411, § 7.1-25.1; 2005, c. 839. Chapter 5. Emblems. -360Article 1. Symbols of Sovereignty. -360Article 2. Emblems, Designations, and Honors. Article 1. Symbols of Sovereignty. -360§ 1-500. The great seal. -360§ 1-501. The lesser seal. -360§ 1-502. Custody; impressions displayed in The Library of Virginia. -360§ 1-503. Uses and tax on great seal. -360§ 1-504. Uses and tax on lesser seal. -360§ 1-505. Seals deemed property of Commonwealth; unauthorized use; penalty. -360§ 1-506. Flag of the Commonwealth. -360§ 1-507. Governor to prescribe size of flag. -360§ 1-508. Director of General Services to have available flags of the Commonwealth for sale. -360§ 1-509. When flag to be suspended over Capitol.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-500"><akn:num>§ 1-500</akn:num><akn:heading>The great seal</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The great seal of the Commonwealth shall consist of two metallic discs, two and one-fourth inches in diameter, with an ornamental border one fourth of an inch wide, wit h such words and figures engraved as follows: On the obverse, Virtus, the genius of the Commonwealth, dressed as an Amazon, resting on a spear in her right hand, point downward, touching the earth; and holding in her left hand, a sheathed sword, or paraz onium, pointing upward; her head erect and face upturned; her left foot on the form of Tyranny represented by the prostrate body of a man, with his head to her left, his fallen crown nearby, a broken chain in his left hand, and a scourge in his right. Ab ove the group and within the border conforming therewith, shall be the word Virginia, and, in the space below, on a curved line, shall be the motto, Sic Semper Tyrannis. On the reverse, shall be placed a group consisting of Libertas, hold ing a wand and pileus in her right hand; on her right, Aeternitas, with a globe and phoenix in her right hand; on the left of Libertas, Ceres, with a cornucopia in her left hand, and an ear of wheat in her right; over this device, in a curved line, the w ord Perseverando. History History. Code 1950, § 7-26; 1966, c. 102, § 7.1-26; 2005, c. 839. Annotations Effective date. This chapter became effective October 1, 2005.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-501"><akn:num>§ 1-501</akn:num><akn:heading>The lesser seal</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The lesser seal of the Commonwealth shall be one and nine sixteenths inches in diameter, and be engraved with the device and inscriptions contained in the obverse of th e great seal. History History. Code 1950, § 7-27; 1966, c. 102, § 7.1-27; 2005, c. 839.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-502"><akn:num>§ 1-502</akn:num><akn:heading>Custody; impressions displayed in The Library of Virginia</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The seals of the Commonwealth described in §§ 1-500 and 1-501 shall be kept by the Secretary of the Commonwealth and used as provided by law, and at least three c lear impressions of the seals shall be kept and displayed by the Librarian of Virginia in some suitable place in The Library of Virginia, for public inspection. History History. Code 1950, § 7-28; 1966, c. 102, § 7.1-28; 1994, c. 64; 199 8, c. 427; 2005, c. 839.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-503"><akn:num>§ 1-503</akn:num><akn:heading>Uses and tax on great seal</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The great seal shall be affixed to documents, signed by the Governor, which are to be used before tribunals, or for purposes outside of the jurisdiction of the Commonwe alth; and in every such case, except where the Commonwealth is a party concerned in the use to be made of the document, the tax imposed by § 58.1-1725 on the seal of the Commonwealth shall be collected and accounted for by the Secretary of the Commonw ealth. History History. Code 1950, § 7-30; 1966, c. 102, § 7.1-30; 2005, c. 839.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-504"><akn:num>§ 1-504</akn:num><akn:heading>Uses and tax on lesser seal</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The lesser seal shall be affixed to all grants for lands and writs of election issued by the Governor; to all letters of pardon and reprieve; to all commissions, civil and military, signed by the Governor, and to all other papers, requiring a seal, authorized to be issued by the Governor for the purpose of carrying the laws into effect within the Commonwealth; and also, when deemed necessary by the Secretary of the Com monwealth, may be used by him as an authentication of his official signature. No tax shall be imposed on the use of such lesser seal, except upon commissions appointing notaries, and commissioners in other states for taking acknowledgments, and upon cert ificates of the Secretary of the Commonwealth, when, at the request of the parties desiring such certificates, the seal is attached. In all such cases the tax shall be the same as upon the great seal, and shall be collected and accounted for in the same manner. History History. Code 1950, § 7-31; 1966, c. 102, § 7.1-31; 2005, c. 839.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-505"><akn:num>§ 1-505</akn:num><akn:heading>Seals deemed property of Commonwealth; unauthorized use; penalty</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The seals of the Commonwealth shall be deemed the property of the Commonwealth; and no persons shall exhibit, display, or in any manner utilize the seals or any facsimi le or representation of the seals of the Commonwealth for nongovernmental purposes unless such use is specifically authorized by law. Except for the authorized commercial use of the seal as provided in § 2.2-122, any person violating the provisions of this section shall be punished by a fine of not more than $100, or by imprisonment for not more than 30 days or both. History History. 1966, c. 102, § 7.1-31.1; 1995, c. 295; 2005, c. 839.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-506"><akn:num>§ 1-506</akn:num><akn:heading>Flag of the Commonwealth</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The flag of the Commonwealth shall be a deep blue field, with a circular white centre of the same material. Upon this circle shall be painted or embroidered, to show on both sides alike, the coat of arms of the Commonwealth, as described in § 1-500 for the obverse of the great seal of the Commonwealth; and there may be a white fringe on the outer edge, furthest from the flagstaff. This shall be known and respected a s the flag of the Commonwealth. History History. Code 1950, § 7-32; 1966, c. 102, § 7.1-32; 2005, c. 839.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-507"><akn:num>§ 1-507</akn:num><akn:heading>Governor to prescribe size of flag</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Governor shall regulate the size and dimensions of the flag proper for forts, arsenals and public buildings, for ships-of-war and merchant marine, for troops in the field, respectively, and for any other purpose, according to his discretion by proclamation. History History. Code 1950, § 7-33; 1966, c. 102, § 7.1-33; 2005, c. 839.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-508"><akn:num>§ 1-508</akn:num><akn:heading>Director of General Services to have available flags of the Commonwealth for sale</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The Director of the Department of General Services shall have available at all times flags of the Commonwealth, to be offered for sale to the public in such manner as t he Director may determine. Such flags shall be of good quality, shall conform to the specifications prescribed in § 1-506, shall be offered in the various sizes prescribed by the Governor purs uant to § 1-507, and shall be purchased in compliance with the provisions of § 2.2-4323.1. The prices to be charged for such flags shall be at cost as determined by the Director. History History. Code 1950, § 7-33.1; 1958, c. 553; 1960, c. 347; 1966, c. 102, § 7.1-34; 2005, c. 839; 2016, cc. 289, 297. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2016, cc. 289 and 297, cl. 2 provides: That the provisions of this act shall become effective on July 1, 2017. The 2016 amendments. The 2016 amendments by cc. 289 and 297 are identical, effective July 1, 2017, and inserted and shall be purchased in compliance with the provisions of § 2. 2-4323.1 and made a related change in the second paragraph.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-509"><akn:num>§ 1-509</akn:num><akn:heading>When flag to be suspended over Capitol</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text During the sessions of either house of the General Assembly the flag of the Commonwealth shall be kept raised over the respective chambers of the Capitol, or other plac e of session, if practicable, as directed by the Director of the Department of General Services and the Chief of the Virginia Capitol Police in consultation with the Clerk of the House of Delegates and the Clerk of the Senate. History History. Code 1950, § 7-34; 1966, c. 102, § 7.1-35; 1970, c. 561; 20 05, c. 839. Annotations Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 8B M.J. Flags and Emblems, § 1; 1A M.J. Administrative La w, § 10. Article 2. Emblems, Designations, and Honors. -360§ 1-510. Official emblems and designations. -360§ 1-511. English designated the official language of the Commonwealth. -360§ 1-512. Poet laureate.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-510"><akn:num>§ 1-510</akn:num><akn:heading>Official emblems and designations</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The following are hereby designated official emblems and designations of the Commonwealth: Artisan Center  Virginia Artisans Center, located in the City of Waynesboro. Bat  Virginia Big-eared bat (Corynorhinos townsendii virginianus). Beverage  Milk. Bird  Northern Cardinal (Cardinalis cardinalis). Blue Ridge Folklore State Center  Blue Ridge Institute located in the village of Ferrum. Boat  Chesapeake Bay Deadrise. Cabin Capital of Virginia  Page County. Coal Miners Memorial  The Richlands Coal Miners Memorial located in Tazewell County. Covered Bridge Capital of the Commonwealth  Patrick County. Covered Bridge Festival  Virginia Covered Bridge Festival held in Patrick County. Dog  American Foxhound. Fish (Freshwater)  Brook Trout. Fish (Saltwater)  Striped Bass. Flag of Remembrance of September 11, 2001  Freedom Flag, designed by a Virginian, as the flag of remembrance of September 11, 2001. Fleet  Replicas of the three ships, Susan Constant, Godspeed, and Discovery, which comprised the Commonwealths founding fleet that brought the first permanent E nglish settlers to Jamestown in 1607, and which are exhibited at the Jamestown Settlement in Williamsburg. Flower  American Dogwood (Cornus florida). Folk dance  Square dancing, the American folk dance that traces its ancestry to the English Country Dance and the French Ballroom Dance, and is called, cued, or pro mpted to the dancers, and includes squares, rounds, clogging, contra, line, the Virginia Reel, and heritage dances. Fossil  Chesapecten jeffersonius. Gold mining interpretive center  Monroe Park, located in the County of Fauquier. Insect  Tiger Swallowtail Butterfly (Papilio glaucus Linne). Maple Festival  The Highland County Maple Festival. Motor sports museum  Wood Brothers Racing Museum and Virginia Motor Sports Hall of Fame, located in Patrick County. Opry  The Virginia Opry. Outdoor drama  The Trail of the Lonesome Pine Outdoor Drama, adapted for the stage by Clara Lou Kelly and performed in the Town of Big Stone Gap. Outdoor drama, historical  The Long Way Home based on the life of Mary Draper Ingles, adapted for the stage by Earl Hobson Smith, and performed in the City of Radford. Rock  Nelsonite. Salamander  Red Salamander (Pseudotriton ruber). Shakespeare festival  The Virginia Shakespeare Festival held in the City of Williamsburg. Shell  Oyster shell (Crassostrea virginica). Snake  Eastern Garter Snake (Thamnophis sirtalis sirtalis). Song emeritus  Carry Me Back to Old Virginny, by James A. Bland, as set out in the House Joint Resolution 10, adopted by the General Assembly of Virginia at the Session of 1940. Song (Popular)  Sweet Virginia Breeze, by Robbin Thompson and Steve Bassett. Song (Traditional)  Our Great Virginia, lyrics by Mike Greenly and arranged by Jim Papoulis with music from the original American folk song Oh Shenandoa h. Spirit  George Washingtons rye whiskey produced at Mount Vernon, Virginia. Sports hall of fame  Virginia Sports Hall of Fame, located in the City of Portsmouth. Television series  Song of the Mountains. Tree  American Dogwood (Cornus florida). War memorial museum  Virginia War Museum, (formerly known as the War Memorial Museum of Virginia), located in the City of Newport News. History History. Code 1950, §§ 7-35, 7-36, 7-37; 1966, cc. 102, 547, § § 7.1-37, 7.1-38, 7.1-39; 1974, c. 24, § 7.1-40; 1982, c. 191, § 7.1-40.1; 1986, c. 138, § 7.1-40.2; 1988, c. 317, § 7.1-40.3; 1991, cc. 71, 575, §§ 7.1-40.4, 7.1-40.5; 1993, cc. 251, 509, § 7.1-40.6; 1994, cc. 33, 134, 220, 464, §§ 7.1-40.2:1, 7.1-40.8; 1995, cc. 12, 180, § 7.1-40.2:2; 1996, c. 52, § 7.1-40.9; 1997, cc. 66, 576, § 7.1-40.10; 1999, cc. 69, 336, § 7.1-40.11; 2001, cc. 97, 134, § 7.1-40.12; 2001, c. 228, § 7.1-40.13; 2005, cc. 557, 839; 2006 , c. 128; 2007, cc. 391, 685; 2008, c. 262; 2009, cc. 145, 227; 2011, c. 671; 2013, c. 702; 2014, c. 553; 2015, cc. 586, 587; 2016, cc. 278, 675; 2017, cc. 15, 576, 577; 2018, cc. 284, 684; 2020, c. 583. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2005, c. 557, enacted former § 7.1-40.7:1 designating the Virginia big-eared bat as the official bat of the Commonwealth. The substance of the provisions were included in § 1-510 as enacted by Acts 2005, c. 839. The 2006 amendments. The 2006 amendment by c. 128 substituted Corynorhinus for Corynorhinos in the paragraph of Bat; and inserted the paragraph Fish  Brook Tro ut. The 2007 amendments. The 2007 amendments by cc. 391 and 685 are identical, and inserted Covered Bridge Festival  Virginia Covered Bridge Festival held in Patrick County. The 2008 amendments. The 2008 amendment by c. 262 inserted Covered Bridge Festival  Virginia Covered Bridge Festival held in Patrick County. The 2009 amendments. The 2009 amendment by c. 145 inserted Coal Miners Memorial  The Richlands Coal Miners Memorial located in Tazewell County. The 2009 amendment by c. 227 inserted Cabin Capital of Virginia  Page County. The 2011 amendments. The 2011 amendment by c. 671 inserted (Freshwater) following Fish and added Fish (Saltwater)  Striped Bass. The 2013 amendments. The 2013 amendment by c. 702 inserted Shakespeare festival  The Virginia Shakespeare Festival held in the City of Williamsburg. The 2014 amendments. The 2014 amendment by c. 553 added the designation of Maple Festival. The 2015 amendments. The 2015 amendments by cc. 586 and 587 are identical, and substituted Virginny for Virginia following Old in the designation for Song emeritus; and added the designations for Song (Popular) and Song (Traditional). The 2016 amendments. The 2016 amendment by c. 278 inserted Bird  Northern Cardinal (Cardinalis cardinalis), Snake  Eastern Garter Snake (Thamnophis sirtalis sirtal is), and Tree  American Dogwood (Cornus florida). The 2016 amendment by c. 675, added Bird  Northern Cardinal (Cardinalis cardinalis),deleted Emergency medical services museum  To The Res cue, located in the City of Roanoke, and added Rock  Nelsoniteand Tree  American Dogwood (Cornus florida). The 2017 amendments. The 2017 amendments by cc. 15 and 577 are identical, and inserted Television series  Song of the Mountains. The 2017 amendment by c. 576 inserted Spirit  George Washingtons rye whiskey produced at Mount Vernon, Virginia. The 2018 amendments. The 2018 amendment by c. 284 inserted Salamander  Red Salamander (Pseudotriton ruber). The 2018 amendment by c. 684 inserted the entry for Flag of Remembrance of September 11, 2001. The 2020 amendments. The 2020 amendment by c. 583 added Opry  The Virginia Opry to the list of the official emblems and designations of the Commonwealth.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-511"><akn:num>§ 1-511</akn:num><akn:heading>English designated the official language of the Commonwealth</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text English shall be designated as the official language of the Commonwealth. Except as provided by law, no state agency or local government shall be required to provide an d no state agency or local government shall be prohibited from providing any documents, information, literature or other written materials in any language other than English. History History. 1996, c. 829, § 7.1-42; 2005, c. 839. Annotations Law Review. For comment, The Fiber of the Common Bond, see 13 Geo. Mason L. Rev. 367 (2005).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-512"><akn:num>§ 1-512</akn:num><akn:heading>Poet laureate</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The honorary position of Poet Laureate of Virginia is hereby created. The Governor may appoint a poet laureate from a list of nominees submitted by the Poetry Society o f Virginia. Each poet laureate shall serve a term of two years with no restrictions on reappointment. History History. 1997, c. 299, § 7.1-43; 2005, c. 839. Chapter 6. Virginia Coordinate Systems. -360§ 1-600. Virginia coordinate systems designated. -360§ 1-601. North and South Zones. -360§ 1-602. Designation of systems in land description. -360§ 1-603. Plane coordinates used in systems. -360§ 1-604. Tract of land lying in both coordinate zones. -360§ 1-605. Definition of systems by National Ocean Service/National Geodetic Survey; adopted. -360§ 1-606. Position of systems. -360§ 1-607. Limitation on use of systems. -360§ 1-608. Limitation on use of name of systems. -360§ 1-609. Use of system not compulsory. -360§ 1-610. Old Dominion University designated as administrative agency.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-600"><akn:num>§ 1-600</akn:num><akn:heading>Virginia coordinate systems designated</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The systems of plane coordinates that have been established by the National Ocean Service/National Geodetic Survey or its successors for defining and stating the positi ons or locations of points on the surface of the earth within the Commonwealth are to be known and designated as the Virginia Coordinate System of 1927 and the Virginia Coordinate System of 1983. History History. 1946, p. 166; Michie Suppl. 1946, § 2849(1); Code 1950, § 5 5-287; 1984, c. 726; 2019, c. 712. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2019, c. 712, recodified Title 55 as Title 55.1, effective October 1, 2019. As part of the recodification, former Chapter 17 (§ 55-287 et seq.) of Title 55 was recodified as Chapter 6 (§ 1-600 et seq.) of this title. Where appropriate, the historical citations to former sections have been added to corresponding new sections. For transition provisions, see § 55.1-100. For tables of corresponding fo rmer and new sections, see the tables in Volume 10. Acts 2019, c. 712, cl. 13 provides: That the provisions of this act shall become effective on October 1, 2019. Michies Jurisprudence. For related discussion, see 18 M.J. Surveys and Surveyors, § 1.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-601"><akn:num>§ 1-601</akn:num><akn:heading>North and South Zones</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text For the purpose of the use of the Virginia Coordinate System of 1927 and the Virginia Coordinate System of 1983, the Commonwealth is divided into a North Zone a nd a South Zone. The area now included in the following counties and cities shall constitute the North Zone: Arlington, Augusta, Bath, Caroline, Clarke, Culpeper, Fairfax, Fauquier, Fre derick, Greene, Highland, King George, Loudoun, Madison, Orange, Page, Prince William, Rappahannock, Rockingham, Shenandoah, Spotsylvania, Stafford, Warren, and Westmoreland Counties and the Cities of Alexandria, Fairfax, Falls Church, Fredericksburg, Ha rrisonburg, Manassas, Manassas Park, Staunton, Waynesboro, and Winchester. The area now included in the following counties and cities shall constitute the South Zone: Accomack, Albemarle, Alleghany, Amelia, Amherst, Appomattox, Bedford, Bland, Botetourt, Brunswick, Buchanan, Buckingham, Campbell, Carroll, Charles City, Charlotte, Chesterfield, Craig, Cumberland, Dickenson, Dinwiddie, Essex, Floyd, Fluvanna, Franklin, Giles, Gloucester, Goochland, Grayson, Greensville, Halifax, Hanover, Henric o, Henry, Isle of Wight, James City, King and Queen, King William, Lancaster, Lee, Louisa, Lunenburg, Mathews, Mecklenburg, Middlesex, Montgomery, Nelson, New Kent, Northampton, Northumberland, Nottoway, Patrick, Pittsylvania, Powhatan, Prince Edward, Pr ince George, Pulaski, Richmond, Roanoke, Rockbridge, Russell, Scott, Smyth, Southampton, Surry, Sussex, Tazewell, Washington, Wise, Wythe, and York Counties and the Cities of Bristol, Buena Vista, Charlottesville, Chesapeake, Colonial Heights, Covington, Danville, Emporia, Franklin, Galax, Hampton, Hopewell, Lexington, Lynchburg, Martinsville, Newport News, Norfolk, Norton, Petersburg, Poquoson, Portsmouth, Radford, Richmond, Roanoke, Salem, Suffolk, Virginia Beach, and Williamsburg. History History. Code 1950, § 55-288.1; 1984, c. 726; 2006, c. 861; 2016, cc. 1 64, 312; 2019, c. 712. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2019, c. 712, cl. 13 provides: That the provisions of this act shall become effective on October 1, 2019.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-602"><akn:num>§ 1-602</akn:num><akn:heading>Designation of systems in land description</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. As establis hed for use in the North Zone, the Virginia Coordinate System of 1927 or the Virginia Coordinate System of 1983 shall be named, and in any land description in which it is used, it shall be designated the Virginia Coordinate System of 1927, North Zone  or Virginia Coordinate System of 1983, North Zone. B. As establis hed for use in the South Zone, the Virginia Coordinate System of 1927 or the Virginia Coordinate System of 1983 shall be named, and in any land description in which it is used, it shall be designated the Virginia Coordinate System of 1927, South Zone  or Virginia Coordinate System of 1983, South Zone. History History. 1946, p. 167; Michie Suppl. 1946, § 2849(2); Code 1950, § 5 5-289; 1984, c. 726; 2019, c. 712. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2019, c. 712, cl. 13 provides: That the provisions of this act shall become effective on October 1, 2019.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-603"><akn:num>§ 1-603</akn:num><akn:heading>Plane coordinates used in systems</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The plane coordinates of a point on the earths surface, to be used in expressing the position or location of such point in the appropriate zone of these systems, sh all be expressed in U.S. survey feet and decimals of a foot. One of these distances, to be known as the x-coordinate, shall give the position in an east-and-west direction; the other, to be known as the y-coordinate, shall give the positi on in a north-and-south direction. These coordinates shall be made to depend upon and conform to the coordinate values for the monumented points of the North American Horizontal Geodetic Control Network as published by the National Ocean Service/National Geodetic Survey, or its successors, and whose plane coordinates have been computed on the systems defined in this chapter. Any such station may be used for establishing a survey connection to either Virginia coordinate system. When converting coordinates in the Virginia Coordinate System of 1983 from meters and decimals of a meter to feet and decimals of a foot, the U.S. survey foot conversio n factor (one foot equals 1200/3937 meters) shall be used. This requirement does not preclude the continued use of the International foot conversion factor (one foot equals 0.3048 meters) in those counties and cities where this factor was in use prior to July 1, 1992. The plat or plan shall contain a statement of the conversion factor used and the coordinate values of a minimum of two project points in feet. History History. 1946, p. 167; Michie Suppl. 1946, § 2849(3); Code 1950, § 5 5-290; 1984, c. 726; 1992, c. 1; 2019, c. 712. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2019, c. 712, cl. 13 provides: That the provisions of this act shall become effective on October 1, 2019.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-604"><akn:num>§ 1-604</akn:num><akn:heading>Tract of land lying in both coordinate zones</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text When any tract of land to be defined by a single description extends from one into the other of the two coordinate zones established in this chapter, the positions of a ll points on its boundaries may be referred to either of the two zones, with the zone that is used being specifically named in the description. History History. 1946, p. 167; Michie Suppl. 1946, § 2849(4); Code 1950, § 5 5-291; 2019, c. 712. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2019, c. 712, cl. 13 provides: That the provisions of this act shall become effective on October 1, 2019.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-605"><akn:num>§ 1-605</akn:num><akn:heading>Definition of systems by National Ocean Service/National Geodetic Survey; adopted</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text A. For purpose s of more precisely defining the Virginia Coordinate System of 1927, the following definition by the National Ocean Service/National Geodetic Survey is adopted:The Virginia Coordinate System of 1927, North Zone, is a Lambert conformal projection of the C larke spheroid of 1896, having standard parallels at north latitudes 38° 02´ and 39° 12´, along which parallels the scale shall be exact. The origin of coordinates is at the intersection of the meridian 78° 30´ west of Greenwich with th e parallel 37° 40´ north latitude, such origin being given the coordinates: x = 2,000,000/, and y = 0´.The Virginia Coordinate System of 1927, South Zone, is a Lambert conformal projection of the Clarke spheroid of 1896, having standard para llels at north latitudes 36° 46´ and 37° 58´, along which parallels the scale shall be exact. The origin of coordinates is at the intersection of the meridian 78° 30´ west of Greenwich with the parallel 36° 20´ north latitude, suc h origin being given the coordinates: x = 2,000,000´, and y = 0´. B. For purpose s of more precisely defining the Virginia Coordinate System of 1983, the following definition by the National Ocean Service/National Geodetic Survey is adopted:The Virginia Coordinate System of 1983, North Zone, is a Lambert conformal conic projection ba sed on the North American Datum of 1983, having standard parallels at north latitudes 38° 02´ and 39° 12´, along which parallels the scale shall be exact. The origin of coordinates is at the intersection of the meridian 78° 30´ west of Greenwich and the parallel 37° 40´ north latitude, such origin being given the coordinates: x = 3,500,000 meters and y = 2,000,000 meters.The Virginia Coordinate System of 1983, South Zone, is a Lambert conformal conic projection based on the North American Datum of 1983, having standard parallels at north latitudes 36° 46´ and 37° 58´, along which parallels the scale shall be exact. The origin of coordinates is at the intersection of the meridian 78° 30´ west of Greenwich and th e parallel 36° 20´ north latitude, such origin being given the coordinates: x = 3,500,000 meters and y = 1,000,000 meters. History History. 1946, p. 167; Michie Suppl. 1946, § 2849(5); Code 1950, § 5 5-292; 1984, c. 726; 2019, c. 712. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2019, c. 712, cl. 13 provides: That the provisions of this act shall become effective on October 1, 2019.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-606"><akn:num>§ 1-606</akn:num><akn:heading>Position of systems</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The position of the Virginia coordinate systems shall be as marked on the ground by triangulation or traverse stations established in conformity with the standards of a ccuracy and specifications for first-order and second-order geodetic surveying as prepared and published by the Federal Geodetic Control Subcommittee of the Federal Geographic Data Committee of the U.S. Department of Commerce. The geodetic position of st ations defining the position of the Virginia Coordinate System of 1927 shall have been rigidly adjusted on the North American Datum of 1927, and the plane coordinates shall have been computed on the Virginia Coordinate System of 1927. The geodetic positi on of stations defining the position of the Virginia Coordinate System of 1983 shall have been rigidly adjusted on the North American Datum of 1983, and the plane coordinates shall have been computed on the Virginia Coordinate System of 1983. Any such st ation may be used for establishing a survey connection with the Virginia coordinate systems. History History. 1946, p. 168; Michie Suppl. 1946, § 2849(5); Code 1950, § 5 5-293; 1984, c. 726; 2019, c. 712. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2019, c. 712, cl. 13 provides: That the provisions of this act shall become effective on October 1, 2019.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-607"><akn:num>§ 1-607</akn:num><akn:heading>Limitation on use of systems</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text No coordinates based on the Virginia coordinate systems, purporting to define the position of a point on a land boundary, shall be presented to be recorded in any publi c land records or deed records unless such point is within two kilometers of a public or private monumented horizontal control station established in conformity with the standards of accuracy and specifications for second-order, class II or better geodet ic surveying as prepared and published by the Federal Geodetic Control Subcommittee of the Federal Geographic Data Committee of the U.S. Department of Commerce. Standards and specifications of the Federal Geodetic Control Subcommittee or its successor in force on the date of such survey shall apply. The publishing of the existing control stations, or the acceptance with intent to publish the new established control stations, by the National Ocean Service/National Geodetic Survey constitutes evidence of adherence to the Federal Geodetic Control Subcommittee specifications. The two kilometers limitation may be modified by a duly authorized state agency to meet local conditions. Nothing contained in this chapter shall be interpreted as preventing the use of the Virginia coordinate systems in any unrecorded deeds, maps, or computations. History History. 1946, p. 168; Michie Suppl. 1946, § 2849(6); Code 1950, § 5 5-294; 1984, c. 726; 2019, c. 712. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2019, c. 712, cl. 13 provides: That the provisions of this act shall become effective on October 1, 2019.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-608"><akn:num>§ 1-608</akn:num><akn:heading>Limitation on use of name of systems</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text The use of the terms Virginia Coordinate System of 1927 or Virginia Coordinate System of 1983 on any map, report of survey, or other document shall be l imited to coordinates based on the Virginia coordinate systems as defined in this chapter. History History. 1946, p. 168; Michie Suppl. 1946, § 2849(7); Code 1950, § 5 5-295; 1984, c. 726; 2019, c. 712. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2019, c. 712, cl. 13 provides: That the provisions of this act shall become effective on October 1, 2019.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-609"><akn:num>§ 1-609</akn:num><akn:heading>Use of system not compulsory</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text For purposes of describing the location of any survey station or land boundary corner in the Commonwealth, it shall be considered a complete, legal, and satisfactory de scription of such location to give the position of such survey station or land boundary corner on the system of plane coordinates defined in this chapter. Nothing contained in this chapter shall require any purchaser or mortgagee to rely on a description any part of which depends exclusively upon either Virginia coordinate system. History History. 1946, p. 168; Michie Suppl. 1946, § 2849(8); Code 1950, § 5 5-296; 1984, c. 726; 2019, c. 712. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2019, c. 712, cl. 13 provides: That the provisions of this act shall become effective on October 1, 2019.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="sec_1-610"><akn:num>§ 1-610</akn:num><akn:heading>Old Dominion University designated as administrative agency</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Text Old Dominion University is designated as the authorized state agency to collect and distribute information, to authorize such modifications as are referred to in § 1 -607, and generally to advise with and assist appropriate state and federal agencies and individuals interested in the development of the provisions of this chapter. History History. 1946, p. 168; Michie Suppl. 1946, § 2849(10); Code 1950, § 55-297; 1966, c. 55; 1968, c. 223; 1977, c. 114; 2019, c. 712. Annotations Editors note. Acts 2020, c. 1289, as amended by Acts 2021, Sp. Sess. I, c. 552, Item 187 C, and Acts 2022, Sp. Sess. I, c. 2, Item 179 C, effective for the biennium ending Jun e 30, 2023, provides: Notwithstanding § 1-610, Code of Virginia, Old Dominion University is hereby designated as the administrative agency for the Virginia Coordinate System. Acts 2019, c. 712, cl. 13 provides: That the provisions of this act shall become effective on October 1, 2019.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section></akn:body></akn:act></akn:akomaNtoso>